<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-07T08:13:15+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Strat Packer’s blog</title><subtitle>Creative and intellectual output beyond the realm of my day job</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Pathless Path: A call to action to escape your desk job</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/07/the-pathless-path-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Pathless Path&amp;#58; A call to action to escape your desk job" /><published>2025-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/07/the-pathless-path-review</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="business" /><category term="career" /><summary type="html">In The Pathless Path, Paul Millerd makes the case that life should be about more than work, and that people should invest more time and effort in finding their true calling - one that is more engaging and fulfilling than the daily grind. A rough representation of the daydream The Pathless Path inspired for me When Millerd’s own corporate consulting career was disrupted by health issues, he gained a new outlook on life. He left New York and spent time in Asia, first working freelance consulting gigs before developing online training courses and writing more. He found himself in a far happier place as a result. He argues that too many people unquestioningly follow a default path, where regular raises and promotions make it easy to continue in an unfulfilling career and switch off the voice questioning your happiness. With sufficient coping strategies, Millerd says people can tolerate consistent misery almost indefinitely. But if not that, then what else? The Pathless Path prompts readers to discover what they would be if they weren’t simply workers. By identifying what you enjoy doing, you can work backwards to build a life around that - ideally one that leaves you happier and better serves the people and communities around you. It’s inspiring stuff. I often daydream about a future where I manage to make a living from a software as a service project, this blog, or some other creative endeavour. I have no doubt that I’d wake up with greater motivation each day if granted that kind of agency and freedom to focus on what interests me. Millerd would argue that freedom is already there, but few actually recognise or take advantage of it. However, The Pathless Path almost overlooks the biggest factor that chains most people to their desks for 40 hours per week - money. When the author left his corporate job, he managed to find income through freelance consulting and moved to Taiwan, where the cost of living is lower. He does mention that those on the pathless path must learn to view money differently, but his biggest obstacle through the book seems to be a fear of making a fool of himself, rather than dread of ending up completely broke. I have a family to support and a mortgage to pay, and if I left my traditional career, I’m not confident I’d be able to find enough customers to avoid whittling my savings down to nothing and being forced to return to the rat race. Of course, I might be surprised if I ever did try it, but it feels as though holding a tolerable nine-to-five job is a necessary sacrifice to ensure long-term stability. Therefore, The Pathless Path was more of an escapist read - something philosophically interesting that I’d be keen to try if the mortgage was paid off, I somehow came across a large sum of money, or a side project gained some momentum, but that didn’t provide a practical path from A to B for me. 3/5</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/the-pathless-path_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/the-pathless-path_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy new year! Changes coming to Strat Packer’s blog in 2025</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/05/blog-changes-2025" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy new year! Changes coming to Strat Packer's blog in 2025" /><published>2025-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/05/blog-changes-2025</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">Happy new year to anybody who stumbles across this site and this article. I genuinely wish you and the people you love a pleasant 2025. Happy new year to all my online acquaintances! For more than three years now, this blog has existed in an ambiguous state. Is it a gaming news and reviews site? A place for retrospectives covering old games? A collection of thoughts on general geeky interests? An intermittent travel blog? This probably also raised some questions for the few people who gave my identity any thought. “Who is this Strat Packer guy?” you might have asked. At various points you’d have been forgiven for categorising me as a wannabe video games journalist, an indie gaming connoisseur, a pseudo-intellectual rambling about social science, a semi-serious runner, or some sort of wealthy globetrotter.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/happy-new-year_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/happy-new-year_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Long Drive: A surreal road trip that’s too weird to put down</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/12/29/the-long-drive-preview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Long Drive&amp;#58; A surreal road trip that's too weird to put down" /><published>2024-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/12/29/the-long-drive-preview</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="the-long-drive" /><category term="indie" /><summary type="html">It’s 2am, and I’m driving down an empty road in the middle of the desert. The pitch black night stretches out to the horizon, my car’s headlights and the stars providing the only illumination over the barren landscape. Suddenly, my engine dies and the lights cut out, plunging the scene into blackness. An ominous hum approaches from behind, before my dashboard is lit up in bright green by the UFO flying overhead. Panic takes hold. What’s going to happen to me? Out here in the wilderness, nobody would know if I was abducted - or worse.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/the-long-drive_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/the-long-drive_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Precinct: 80s police simulation with a retrowave kick</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/12/16/the-precinct-preview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Precinct&amp;#58; 80s police simulation with a retrowave kick" /><published>2024-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/12/16/the-precinct-preview</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="the-precinct" /><category term="indie" /><summary type="html">The Precinct threatens to scratch an itch I didn’t realise I had. Playing Falling Tree Games’ upcoming title, I realised I’d always thought that the action-packed parts of Grand Theft Auto roleplay cops’ jobs looked quite fun, but that the amount of grinding and bureaucracy to navigate to get there put me off. Averno City looks slick and is densely populated The Nottingham-based developer’s new game does the opposite, putting the paperwork aside and focusing on action inspired by 80s and 90s cop movies. It leans heavy into stereotypes - the main character is a fresh academy graduate and the son of a legendary officer, and even in the short demo encounters all the skeptical colleagues, jaded veterans, and hints of corruption you’d expect. It would all feel a bit derivative if it didn’t come in a package so polished that it reassures you the designers know what they’re doing. While The Precinct is a fully 3D game, its angles and zoom levels are reminiscent of 2D GTA. Averno City, while small, is densely populated and atmospheric, and the whole thing is set to convincing voice actors and a pulsing retrowave soundtrack. Gameplay sees your cop head out on his beat to fight crime in all its forms, from ticketing illegally parked cars to pursuing bank robbers. The Precinct’s longevity could depend heavily on the variety here. Thankfully there’s a long list of potential crimes in the police handbook - I just hope there are plenty of substories and unique dialogue to avoid low-level crimes feeling like a grind over time. Drive or pilot well enough and you're granted the option to call in support However, that may not matter if action feels solid enough. Combat is mostly a one-button affair, and in my opinion much of the fun lies in the vehicles. The driving model supports the retro cop show vibe, enabling long sideways slides when arriving on the scene, and the demo even includes a helicopter chase. What sets The Precinct apart are its police mechanics. The handbook tells you how much force you can use in any particular situation, and what the penalty should be for the culprit. You need to abide by these or face the repercussions. Pursuits also present some interesting options, as you’ll need to augment your own driving with tactical calls for backup from the rest of the force. I’ll certainly be keeping an eye on The Precinct ahead of its to-be-announced 2025 release date. The strength of the story and variety in the scenarios remain to be seen, but if the full game is as polished and engaging as the short slice of action Fallen Tree Games offered in the demo, it could be an indie gem.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/the-precinct_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/the-precinct_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Half-Life 2: 20th Anniversary Documentary</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/11/18/half-life-2-20th-anniversary-documentary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Half-Life 2&amp;#58; 20th Anniversary Documentary" /><published>2024-11-18T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-18T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/11/18/half-life-2-20th-anniversary-documentary</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="half-life" /><category term="retro" /><summary type="html">☢️ Can you believe that Half-Life 2 is 20 years old already? Rather than cobbling together a typical anniversary edition to rake in the cash, Valve made an updated version of the game free on Steam to mark the occasion. They also released a two-hour YouTube documentary documenting its development, which is fascinating and nostalgic in equal measure.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Spy Drops attempts to revive PlayStation-era stealth action</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/10/26/spy-drops-preview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spy Drops attempts to revive PlayStation-era stealth action" /><published>2024-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/10/26/spy-drops-preview</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="spy-drops" /><category term="indie" /><summary type="html">Spy Drops wears its inspiration on its sleeve. In the words of its creator, Rainy Night Creations, the upcoming indie title promises “PlayStation generation, low-polygon 3D stealth action”, and its visual language so closely matches its muse that any screenshot could be mistaken for the original Metal Gear Solid. The inspiration for Spy Drops is instantly recognisable Playing the recently released demo, it’s clear this is also true of the overall mood. In the opening cut scene, a gravelly-voiced colonel briefs Ripley on her mission in a monologue peppered with acronyms, namechecking artificial intelligence and other common themes of Hideo Kojima’s iconic series. We’re yet to see enough to know whether this is just lip service, or if it amounts to a compelling plot. Gameplay closely mirrors the MGS formula, tasking the player with sneaking through levels using cover and darkness. I’m not sure the mechanic was at play during the demo, but the game’s website says stages will have randomly generated layouts, which should drastically increase replayability. Engaging with the enemy As you’d expect, Ripley encounters enemy guards on her missions. While hand-to-hand combat is an option, sneaking up and grabbing them presents the option to either neutralise or kill them. Before doing so, you can also interrogate them to gain what are essentially gameplay hints, which is a nice addition. I wouldn’t say I was ever challenged during the demo - even when approaching a guard directly from the front it was easy enough to subdue them before they did much damage, and my only death came via a mishap with a proximity mine (whose description claimed it couldn’t deal damage to the player character). Squint a little and you'd be forgiven for thinking it's 1998 Items in general are an area that could be improved for the full release. New items in MGS were sparse, and each had a specific purpose that was explained via Codec dialogue. Conversely, Spy Drops throws new equipment at you from all angles with little information on what each gadget does, and it’s not helped by a clunky interface that can make it a bit of a hassle to assign and equip gear. Promising signs The only misfire when it comes to atmopshere is some of the audio choices - guards sometimes sound as though they’re wearing stiletto heels, and have little to say beyond: “Where are you?” The music, while fitting the bill in terms of mood, is a short and imperfect loop that sometimes distracts from the action. I also encountered a few performance issues that I wouldn’t have expected from a low-poly game, with stutters between certainly scene changes and animations - although hopefully that’s something that can be optimised out before release. I remain optimistic for Spy Drops - I’ve always daydreamed about what it might be like if somebody tried to emulate the Metal Gear Solid glory days, and this is already an amazing achievement for a one-man studio - but it remains to be seen how well the pieces will all fit together, and if it will successfully capture the tone and thematic elements that made the series so special.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/spy-drops_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/spy-drops_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Dark Knight Rises review - a warning to edgy teen communists</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/10/10/the-dark-knight-rises-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Dark Knight Rises review &amp;#45; a warning to edgy teen communists" /><published>2024-10-10T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/10/10/the-dark-knight-rises-review</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="films" /><category term="reviews" /><category term="batman" /><summary type="html">The Dark Knight’s War on Terror analogy ended with Harvey Dent, representing the US, being effectively absolved of his crimes to preserve his image - but in real life, the opposite happened. The disappearing evidence of Iraq’s “weapons of mass destruction”, subsequent terror attacks, and the threat of ISIS all damaged trust in Western governments, and it has never recovered to 20th century levels. The Great Recession of 2008, triggered by risky trades that built a housing bubble primed to burst, further eroded citizens’ faith in institutions. The effects were widespread, and further resentment grew as banks were bailed out with taxpayers’ money - culminating in the Occupy movement, which was most prominent in New York, but nonetheless showed a presence around the world. Catwoman taunts Bruce Wayne like an anime profile picture to a Silicon Valley VC In many cases, dissatisfaction with concrete injustices has now compounded into a general apathy towards Western civilisation itself, and it’s rare to go a day on Twitter without seeing some edgy teen posting an ill-judged call for a communist revolution. Why do I bring this up in a review of a Batman movie? Because in the world of The Dark Knight Rises, Catwoman is that edgy teen. Careful what you wish for It’s been eight years since Harvey Dent died. The lie is instact and he’s held up as a symbol of justice, complete with his own public holiday in Gotham. Meanwhile, a weakened Bruce Wayne is holed up in a wing of his mansion, walking with a stick. Then something grabs his attention - a dextrous maid who steals from his safe, although he quickly realises she’s more interested in his fingerprints. Wayne catches up with Selina Kyle (later revealed to be Catwoman, as though that wasn’t painfully obvious from the start) and takes back his mother’s pearls. Her retort is to lift his car keys during a kiss, but not before licking her lips at a coming “storm” that she thinks will put Gotham’s elite in their place. “There’s a storm coming, Mr Wayne. You and your friends better batten down the hatches, because when it hits, you’re all gonna wonder how you ever thought you could live so large and leave so little for the rest of us.” - Selina Kyle But The Dark Knight Rises isn’t a revolutionary fantasy - it’s a warning. Once the city’s institutions are overthrown, Kyle clearly has regrets. “This was someone’s home,” she says wistfully, staring at a family photograph on a counter as her friends party around her. She’s the radical teen who realises the revolution she called for isn’t what she dreamt of, and ends up helping Batman to end it all. Power to the people Our main villian for the film - and the one who paid Kyle for Wayne’s fingerprints - is Bane. Oddly, he’s the only baddie in Christopher Nolan’s trilogy who seems superhuman. Scarecrow used drugs, the Joker was a terrorist, but Bane seems to have incredible strength, and at one point punches chunks out of a concrete column without showing any sign of pain. He also has a ridiculous voice, both in terms of tone and inflection, which makes him hard to take seriously. His first big move in Gotham is a siege at the stock exchange, which is surely a symptom of anti-banker sentiment during the film’s development. He and his accomplices use Wayne’s fingerprints to execute trades to take control of Wayne Enteprises and gain access to its military technology - including a generator that can be converted into a de facto nuclear bomb. I found it hard to believe said transactions would be completed, given that they were so clearly fraudulent. Bane’s goal is to escalate the violence and “return control of [the] city to the people”. He achieves this via another unbelievable scheme, whereby he lures what is apparently the entire Gotham police force except Gordon and Blake into the sewers and blows up the tunnels to trap them inside. From there, he executes what is essentially a full-on communist revolution, complete with a kangaroo court (chaired by Scarecrow), freed prisoners, and roaming gangs of enforcers. “An army will be raised. The powerful will be ripped from their decadent nests and cast out into the cold world that we know and endure. Courts will be convened. Spoils will be enjoyed. Blood will be shed.” - Bane The final sacrifice Even in the face of Bane’s ridiculousness, one of the biggest letdowns of The Dark Knight Rises is its sheer lack of Batman. Wayne spends much of his time out of action, and behaves erratically when he returns. With Rachel dead and no motivation to clean up Gotham once and for all, put Batman behind him, and settle down, Alfred is worried the saga will only end with Wayne in a coffin. Confronted with this concern, Wayne’s response is to yell and kick him out. Wayne is also far too careless about his identity with Catwoman, who instantly sells him out to Bane. From that point onwards, he’s in a remote prison watching the Gotham situation on TV. He does eventually escape, but even that is handled in a nonsensical way, with big, beefy Bruce Wayne struggling to make a jump that a literal child apparently successfully landed years ago. On his return to Gotham, it is revealed that Miranda Tate - real name Talia al Ghul - is the real villain. She was the one who escaped the prison as a child - Ra’s al Ghul’s child, no less. She wants to finish her father’s work in destroying Gotham. Bane protected her in the prison, and was excommunicated from the League of Shadows because Ra’s al Ghul couldn’t accept his love of his daughter. “Innocent is a strong word to throw around Gotham, Bruce. I honour my father by finishing his work. Vengeance against the man who killed him is simply a reward for my patience.” - Talia al Ghul In the finale, with the bomb set to blow, Batman flies it out to sea. Just before he does, he hints at his true identity to Gordon, who gets the message. It’s one of the few moments in the film that really works like its predecessors - Batman’s doing heroic things, and there’s a relatable personal thread, as Gordon looked after Wayne after his parents’ murder and is full of gratitude for Batman’s service. Presumably dying in the explosion, Batman becomes the icon he sought to be, complete with a statue. But Fox later finds that Wayne fixed the autopilot feature on his aerial vehicle, meaning he could have bailed before the blast. Continuing the renewed focus on personal narratives, in the last moments of the film, Alfred sees Wayne at a cafe with Selina. The two exchange a meme-worthy nod, and it’s heartwarming to know Wayne got a happy ending after all. An imperfect finale I’ll state it plainly: The Dark Knight Rises is the weakest of the trilogy. It benefits from Nolan’s style and the strong established characters, but there’s too much going on. It feels rushed, with a lot changes very quickly between short scenes. Additionally, much of the plot occurs on a macro scale, meaning the personal stories get lost amongst all the revolutionary montages and scene changes. It almost feels as though the filmakers felt they needed to up the stakes for the finale, but struggled to do so within The Dark Knight’s very grounded universe. By opting for big ideas and city-wide struggles, they sacrificed much of the relatable plot. This is compounded by the absence of Batman, with Wayne a recluse, broke, or in prison for a majority of the film’s running time. Coupled with the number of huge holes in characters’ motivations and plans, Rises is a little difficult to stomach after Batman Begins and The Dark Knight, which were both such stellar outings with extremely tight plots. However, I do appreciate the underlying themes and the film’s role as a 2012-era warning about the extreme “burn it all down” position held by so many in the modern day. And whatever might be said about everything else - the strange, the nonsensical, and the missed opportunities - there’s no denying the gravity of that ending. 3/5</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/the-dark-knight-rises_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/the-dark-knight-rises_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Dark Knight review - exploring the post-9/11 Western psyche</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/10/06/the-dark-knight-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Dark Knight review &amp;#45; exploring the post-9/11 Western psyche" /><published>2024-10-06T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-06T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/10/06/the-dark-knight-review</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="films" /><category term="reviews" /><category term="batman" /><summary type="html">If Batman Begins was popular, The Dark Knight was a sensation - and a controversial one at that. I remember listening to a radio debate around whether the film should have received a 12A rating due to its darkness and violence, and while it’s never particularly bloody, it certainly covers some serious themes.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/the-dark-knight_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/the-dark-knight_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Batman Begins review - all roads lead to Bruce Wayne</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/10/01/batman-begins-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Batman Begins review &amp;#45; all roads lead to Bruce Wayne" /><published>2024-10-01T01:01:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-01T01:01:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/10/01/batman-begins-review</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="films" /><category term="reviews" /><category term="batman" /><summary type="html">My life will soon undergo significant change, so to mark the end of the current era I’ve been revisiting some of the media that has meant the most to me - watching the films, playing the games, and listening to the music that has served as the background to significant personal moments across the last 15 years or so.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/batman-begins_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/batman-begins_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Death Stranding 2 at the Tokyo Game Show 2024</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/29/death-stranding-2-tgs-2024" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Death Stranding 2 at the Tokyo Game Show 2024" /><published>2024-09-29T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-29T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/29/death-stranding-2-tgs-2024</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="death-stranding" /><category term="playstation" /><summary type="html">🐈‍⬛ We’ve had another small glimpse of Death Stranding 2: On The Beach. During a 90-minute session at the Tokyo Game Show, Kojima Productions showed off a few new cutscenes and an odd Instagram-esque photo mode. The clips got my hopes up that Sam will spend more time with a fleshed-out team on his latest journey, giving more character to a game that had a lot of interesting ideas but too many soulless holograms for my taste.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>