<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-01T08:03:32+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Strat Packer’s blog</title><subtitle>Creative and intellectual output beyond the realm of my day job</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Once Upon a Time in Hollywood: Tarantino’s novel kills the mystery</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/01/once-upon-a-time-in-hollywood-novel-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Once Upon a Time in Hollywood&amp;#58; Tarantino's novel kills the mystery" /><published>2025-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/01/once-upon-a-time-in-hollywood-novel-review</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">As the first Quentin Tarantino film I saw at the cinema, I have a something of a soft spot for Once Upon a Time in Hollywood (2019). While I wasn’t as keen on the typically violent ending, the picture the director painted of 1960s Los Angeles was captivating, perfectly complemented by the period soundtrack and Leonardo DiCaprio and Brad Pitt’s performances as an actor and his stunt double navigating the unforgiving world of Hollywood after the peak of their careers. How does a story so entwined with certain visuals and music translate to the written word - especially when said novelisation is the author’s debut? We found out in 2021, when Tarantino published a 400-page reworking he described as “a complete rethinking of the entire story”. While it’s not terrible, I will say that I’m glad he gave us the film first, because the novel is not half as enthralling.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/once-upon-a-time-in-hollywood-novel_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/once-upon-a-time-in-hollywood-novel_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Forza Horizon 5 is coming to PlayStation 5</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/31/forza-horizon-5-playstation-5" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Forza Horizon 5 is coming to PlayStation 5" /><published>2025-01-31T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/31/forza-horizon-5-ps5</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="forza" /><category term="racing" /><category term="industry" /><summary type="html">🏁 Forza Horizon 5 is coming to PlayStation 5 this spring. Another Xbox crown jewel landing on Sony’s console raises some interesting questions about the future of the games industry. If all the studios Microsoft bought are too costly to run on Xbox sales alone and their games must be released more widely, what reason will be left to buy an Xbox to begin with?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GTA VI might get away with a $100 price tag, but your game can’t</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/24/gta-vi-price-100-dollars" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTA VI might get away with a $100 price tag, but your game can't" /><published>2025-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/24/gta-vi-100-dollar-price</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="industry" /><category term="grand-theft-auto" /><summary type="html">After a decade-long wait and with development costs reportedly stretching into the billions, it has long been rumoured that Rockstar might try to crank up the price of Grand Theft Auto VI when it launches. The standard price for games has already increased from £50 to £60 in recent years, and it has been speculated that GTA VI’s RRP could skyrocket all the way up to $100 (approximately £80). That would already be a punch in the gut for gamers reeling from the rising cost of living and a faltering job market, but it’s one they might be able to stomach for GTA VI in particular. Rockstar has a track record for producing high-quality titles, with GTA V (2013) and Red Dead Redemption 2 (2018) both receiving widespread acclaim. Many players are still exploring their sprawling worlds to this day.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/gta_vi_100_dollars_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/gta_vi_100_dollars_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Assassin’s Creed Shadows has been delayed again</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/10/assassins-creed-shadows-delayed" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assassin's Creed Shadows has been delayed again" /><published>2025-01-10T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/10/assassins-creed-shadows-delayed</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="assassins-creed" /><summary type="html">🏯 Assassin’s Creed Shadows has been delayed again. The release date for Ubisoft’s controversial title has dropped to 20th March to allow extra time for polish. To appease fans, the developer released a video showing off the game’s parkour. However, the environments steal the show for me. I have little confidence in its story or gameplay, but I might well be tempted to explore the world once Shadows is fully patched and heavily discounted.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Pathless Path: A call to action to escape your desk job</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/07/the-pathless-path-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Pathless Path&amp;#58; A call to action to escape your desk job" /><published>2025-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/07/the-pathless-path-review</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="business" /><category term="career" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">In The Pathless Path, Paul Millerd makes the case that life should be about more than work, and that people should invest more time and effort in finding their true calling - one that is more engaging and fulfilling than the daily grind. A rough representation of the daydream The Pathless Path inspired for me When Millerd’s own corporate consulting career was disrupted by health issues, he gained a new outlook on life. He left New York and spent time in Asia, first working freelance consulting gigs before developing online training courses and writing more. He found himself in a far happier place as a result. He argues that too many people unquestioningly follow a default path, where regular raises and promotions make it easy to continue in an unfulfilling career and switch off the voice questioning your happiness. With sufficient coping strategies, Millerd says people can tolerate consistent misery almost indefinitely. But if not that, then what else? The Pathless Path prompts readers to discover what they would be if they weren’t simply workers. By identifying what you enjoy doing, you can work backwards to build a life around that - ideally one that leaves you happier and better serves the people and communities around you. It’s inspiring stuff. I often daydream about a future where I manage to make a living from a software as a service project, this blog, or some other creative endeavour. I have no doubt that I’d wake up with greater motivation each day if granted that kind of agency and freedom to focus on what interests me. Millerd would argue that freedom is already there, but few actually recognise or take advantage of it. However, The Pathless Path almost overlooks the biggest factor that chains most people to their desks for 40 hours per week - money. When the author left his corporate job, he managed to find income through freelance consulting and moved to Taiwan, where the cost of living is lower. He does mention that those on the pathless path must learn to view money differently, but his biggest obstacle through the book seems to be a fear of making a fool of himself, rather than dread of ending up completely broke. I have a family to support and a mortgage to pay, and if I left my traditional career, I’m not confident I’d be able to find enough customers to avoid whittling my savings down to nothing and being forced to return to the rat race. Of course, I might be surprised if I ever did try it, but it feels as though holding a tolerable nine-to-five job is a necessary sacrifice to ensure long-term stability. Therefore, The Pathless Path was more of an escapist read - something philosophically interesting that I’d be keen to try if the mortgage was paid off, I somehow came across a large sum of money, or a side project gained some momentum, but that didn’t provide a practical path from A to B for me. 3/5</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/the-pathless-path_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/the-pathless-path_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy new year! Changes coming to Strat Packer’s blog in 2025</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/05/blog-changes-2025" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy new year! Changes coming to Strat Packer's blog in 2025" /><published>2025-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/05/blog-changes-2025</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">Happy new year to anybody who stumbles across this site and this article. I genuinely wish you and the people you love a pleasant 2025. Happy new year to all my online acquaintances! For more than three years now, this blog has existed in an ambiguous state. Is it a gaming news and reviews site? A place for retrospectives covering old games? A collection of thoughts on general geeky interests? An intermittent travel blog? This probably also raised some questions for the few people who gave my identity any thought. “Who is this Strat Packer guy?” you might have asked. At various points you’d have been forgiven for categorising me as a wannabe video games journalist, an indie gaming connoisseur, a pseudo-intellectual rambling about social science, a semi-serious runner, or some sort of wealthy globetrotter.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/happy-new-year_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/happy-new-year_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Long Drive: A surreal road trip that’s too weird to put down</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/12/29/the-long-drive-preview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Long Drive&amp;#58; A surreal road trip that's too weird to put down" /><published>2024-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/12/29/the-long-drive-preview</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="the-long-drive" /><category term="indie" /><summary type="html">It’s 2am, and I’m driving down an empty road in the middle of the desert. The pitch black night stretches out to the horizon, my car’s headlights and the stars providing the only illumination over the barren landscape. Suddenly, my engine dies and the lights cut out, plunging the scene into blackness. An ominous hum approaches from behind, before my dashboard is lit up in bright green by the UFO flying overhead. Panic takes hold. What’s going to happen to me? Out here in the wilderness, nobody would know if I was abducted - or worse.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/the-long-drive_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/the-long-drive_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Precinct: 80s police simulation with a retrowave kick</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/12/16/the-precinct-preview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Precinct&amp;#58; 80s police simulation with a retrowave kick" /><published>2024-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/12/16/the-precinct-preview</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="the-precinct" /><category term="indie" /><summary type="html">The Precinct threatens to scratch an itch I didn’t realise I had. Playing Falling Tree Games’ upcoming title, I realised I’d always thought that the action-packed parts of Grand Theft Auto roleplay cops’ jobs looked quite fun, but that the amount of grinding and bureaucracy to navigate to get there put me off. Averno City looks slick and is densely populated The Nottingham-based developer’s new game does the opposite, putting the paperwork aside and focusing on action inspired by 80s and 90s cop movies. It leans heavy into stereotypes - the main character is a fresh academy graduate and the son of a legendary officer, and even in the short demo encounters all the skeptical colleagues, jaded veterans, and hints of corruption you’d expect. It would all feel a bit derivative if it didn’t come in a package so polished that it reassures you the designers know what they’re doing. While The Precinct is a fully 3D game, its angles and zoom levels are reminiscent of 2D GTA. Averno City, while small, is densely populated and atmospheric, and the whole thing is set to convincing voice actors and a pulsing retrowave soundtrack. Gameplay sees your cop head out on his beat to fight crime in all its forms, from ticketing illegally parked cars to pursuing bank robbers. The Precinct’s longevity could depend heavily on the variety here. Thankfully there’s a long list of potential crimes in the police handbook - I just hope there are plenty of substories and unique dialogue to avoid low-level crimes feeling like a grind over time. Drive or pilot well enough and you're granted the option to call in support However, that may not matter if action feels solid enough. Combat is mostly a one-button affair, and in my opinion much of the fun lies in the vehicles. The driving model supports the retro cop show vibe, enabling long sideways slides when arriving on the scene, and the demo even includes a helicopter chase. What sets The Precinct apart are its police mechanics. The handbook tells you how much force you can use in any particular situation, and what the penalty should be for the culprit. You need to abide by these or face the repercussions. Pursuits also present some interesting options, as you’ll need to augment your own driving with tactical calls for backup from the rest of the force. I’ll certainly be keeping an eye on The Precinct ahead of its to-be-announced 2025 release date. The strength of the story and variety in the scenarios remain to be seen, but if the full game is as polished and engaging as the short slice of action Fallen Tree Games offered in the demo, it could be an indie gem.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/the-precinct_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/the-precinct_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Half-Life 2: 20th Anniversary Documentary</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/11/18/half-life-2-20th-anniversary-documentary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Half-Life 2&amp;#58; 20th Anniversary Documentary" /><published>2024-11-18T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-18T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/11/18/half-life-2-20th-anniversary-documentary</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="half-life" /><category term="retro" /><summary type="html">☢️ Can you believe that Half-Life 2 is 20 years old already? Rather than cobbling together a typical anniversary edition to rake in the cash, Valve made an updated version of the game free on Steam to mark the occasion. They also released a two-hour YouTube documentary documenting its development, which is fascinating and nostalgic in equal measure.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Spy Drops attempts to revive PlayStation-era stealth action</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/10/26/spy-drops-preview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spy Drops attempts to revive PlayStation-era stealth action" /><published>2024-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/10/26/spy-drops-preview</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="spy-drops" /><category term="indie" /><summary type="html">Spy Drops wears its inspiration on its sleeve. In the words of its creator, Rainy Night Creations, the upcoming indie title promises “PlayStation generation, low-polygon 3D stealth action”, and its visual language so closely matches its muse that any screenshot could be mistaken for the original Metal Gear Solid. The inspiration for Spy Drops is instantly recognisable Playing the recently released demo, it’s clear this is also true of the overall mood. In the opening cut scene, a gravelly-voiced colonel briefs Ripley on her mission in a monologue peppered with acronyms, namechecking artificial intelligence and other common themes of Hideo Kojima’s iconic series. We’re yet to see enough to know whether this is just lip service, or if it amounts to a compelling plot. Gameplay closely mirrors the MGS formula, tasking the player with sneaking through levels using cover and darkness. I’m not sure the mechanic was at play during the demo, but the game’s website says stages will have randomly generated layouts, which should drastically increase replayability. Engaging with the enemy As you’d expect, Ripley encounters enemy guards on her missions. While hand-to-hand combat is an option, sneaking up and grabbing them presents the option to either neutralise or kill them. Before doing so, you can also interrogate them to gain what are essentially gameplay hints, which is a nice addition. I wouldn’t say I was ever challenged during the demo - even when approaching a guard directly from the front it was easy enough to subdue them before they did much damage, and my only death came via a mishap with a proximity mine (whose description claimed it couldn’t deal damage to the player character). Squint a little and you'd be forgiven for thinking it's 1998 Items in general are an area that could be improved for the full release. New items in MGS were sparse, and each had a specific purpose that was explained via Codec dialogue. Conversely, Spy Drops throws new equipment at you from all angles with little information on what each gadget does, and it’s not helped by a clunky interface that can make it a bit of a hassle to assign and equip gear. Promising signs The only misfire when it comes to atmopshere is some of the audio choices - guards sometimes sound as though they’re wearing stiletto heels, and have little to say beyond: “Where are you?” The music, while fitting the bill in terms of mood, is a short and imperfect loop that sometimes distracts from the action. I also encountered a few performance issues that I wouldn’t have expected from a low-poly game, with stutters between certainly scene changes and animations - although hopefully that’s something that can be optimised out before release. I remain optimistic for Spy Drops - I’ve always daydreamed about what it might be like if somebody tried to emulate the Metal Gear Solid glory days, and this is already an amazing achievement for a one-man studio - but it remains to be seen how well the pieces will all fit together, and if it will successfully capture the tone and thematic elements that made the series so special.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/spy-drops_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/spy-drops_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>