<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-02-05T11:52:56+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Gran Turismo 7: Everything we know</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/05/everything-we-know-gran-turismo-7" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gran Turismo 7&amp;#58; Everything we know" /><published>2022-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/05/everything-we-know-gran-turismo-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/05/everything-we-know-gran-turismo-7">&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that I am &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; excited for &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/gran-turismo&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so when we got &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JlbMzBnfnzM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a 32-minute “deep dive” video&lt;/a&gt; from the PlayStation State of Play this week, it only seemed right for me to dissect every second of it try to gather all the little details and clues about what we can expect to see in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_15.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video starred series producer Kazunori Yamauchi, speaking via a translator. He touted the new game, which marks &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt;’s 25th anniversary, as “the most complete &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; to date” and revealed a whole range of features and details that we hadn’t seen before, including more about the game’s focus on “car culture” as well as the actual racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is a summary of what I could ascertain from the video, which confirmed it’s going to be a long wait until the 4th March release date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-cars&quot;&gt;The cars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yamauchi revealed that &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; will feature &lt;strong&gt;more than 400 cars&lt;/strong&gt;. Over the course of the video we were treated to shots of road cars, sports cars, GT cars, historic cars, rally cars, and concept cars, confirming that the catalogue has all the variety that we’ve come to expect from the series. It was promised that additional cars will be delivered via online updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were shown several places to buy cars. &lt;strong&gt;Brand Central&lt;/strong&gt; is a shopping centre where players can buy around 300 new cars from 2001 and later. The &lt;strong&gt;used car dealer&lt;/strong&gt; will sell a different lineup of cars on a daily basis. These will generally be more affordable, but some models (the example given was 90s Japanese sports cars) will actually accrue value. The last marketplace shown was &lt;strong&gt;Brighton Antiques&lt;/strong&gt;, a place to buy legendary and famous cars like the Le Mans-winning Ford GT40 and James Bond’s Aston Martin DB5.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the focus on “culture”, the developers have made an effort to tell the stories behind the cars. The Gran Turismo Cafe (more on that later) features car designers talking about their work, while there are also &lt;strong&gt;museums&lt;/strong&gt; that tell the stories of certain manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scope for customisation looks huge. The &lt;strong&gt;tuning shop&lt;/strong&gt; offers around 60 performance parts per car, and the number of setup options looks downright daunting. For cosmetics, &lt;strong&gt;GT Auto&lt;/strong&gt; has more than 650 aero parts, 130 wheel types, and 1,200 paint colours to use, as well as the traditional car wash and oil change options. The &lt;strong&gt;livery editor&lt;/strong&gt; now grants players more freedom, with a higher sticker limit and additional areas to place them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve built your dream vehicle, &lt;strong&gt;Scapes&lt;/strong&gt; - first shown off in the reveal trailer - lets you take it to more than 2,500 locations around the world to take photos, with enough camera options to get really arty and abstract. As usual, you can also take and customise photos from races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_11.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Showcase&lt;/strong&gt; is a feature that allows you to show off your creative work. It looks almost like a social network. Players can upload photos, replays, liveries, livery elements, helmets, and race suits for others to view, vote on, download, and apply to their own vehicles and drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-tracks&quot;&gt;The tracks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; features &lt;strong&gt;97 track layouts across 34 locations&lt;/strong&gt; (10 in the Americas, 15 in Europe, and nine in Asia and Oceania), and we were shown many of these in the video. The real tracks that appeared were…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Americas&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Europe&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Asia/Oceania&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Laguna Seca&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Brands Hatch&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Autopolis&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Willow Springs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Goodwood&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Suzuka&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Daytona&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Red Bull Ring&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Fuji Speedway&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Interlagos*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Monza&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tsukuba&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Nurburgring&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Mount Panorama&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Circuit de la Sarthe*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Barcelona-Catalunya*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Spa-Francorchamps*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Some circuits were not shown in the circuit selection screen, but were visible either through gameplay footage or other menus (e.g. licence tests).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the classic fictional &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; tracks were also shown to be back with a visual upgrade. Those shown in the video were…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Americas&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Europe&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Asia/Oceania&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Blue Moon Bay Speedway&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Deep Forest Raceway&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;High Speed Ring&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Northern Isle Speedway&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Dragon Trail&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Kyoto Driving Park&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trial Mountain&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Sardegna&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tokyo Expressway&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Maggiore&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Broad Bean Raceway&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Alsace&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I spotted 29 circuits over the course of the deep dive video. It’s possible I may have missed others (please let me know if so), but for now that would mean there are five other locations yet to be revealed - two in Europe, and three in the Americas. As with cars, we have also been promised that additional tracks will be delivered via online updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;physics-graphics-and-effects&quot;&gt;Physics, graphics, and effects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polyphony Digital boasted that &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;’s driving model was refined based on feedback from experts such as Lewis Hamilton, GT drivers, and tyre manufacturer Michelin. The physics simulation takes into account factors like car setup, wind, and slipstream to ensure realistic handling, and lap times in the game should reflect their real-life counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some features were notably flagged as unique to the PlayStation 5. These included &lt;strong&gt;ray tracing&lt;/strong&gt;, the use of the DualSense controller’s haptic triggers to provide handling feedback (for example, simulating a locked tyre), and a &lt;strong&gt;3D audio&lt;/strong&gt; system that is supposed to give a better sense of where sounds are coming from. It’ll be interesting to see how much is missing for PS4 owners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real star of the show as far as graphics and effects were concerned, however, was the day/night cycle and weather. The developers have used meteorological data to simulate cloud formations unique to each geographical region, so for example the skies will behave differently in California and Japan. Stars, the moon, and even planets will appear in the night sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;’s rain looks spectacular, particularly the way the water sprays off the tyres. Track moisture is dynamic, meaning that when it stops raining the racing line dries out first, and a &lt;strong&gt;weather radar&lt;/strong&gt; has been added to help players track incoming rain clouds. Additionally, it was explained that on large tracks it can be raining in some areas but not others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, it might seem like a small detail to mention, but one other thing I noticed during this section of the video is that spectators are not static any longer. In a timelapse video showing off the rain effects, I noted that people were walking around in the spectator areas in the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;campaign-mode&quot;&gt;Campaign mode&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously known as GT mode, &lt;strong&gt;campaign mode&lt;/strong&gt; is where many players will spend most of their time. The setup looks similar to previous &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; games - you’re given a small number if credits (it looks like 20,000) to buy a car, and earn additional credits and cars by winning races and series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of other interesting features were shown, but not explained. Firstly, “collector points” were granted when the player won a new car, and there was some sort of levelling system. Secondly, after a race a progress bar named “&lt;strong&gt;daily workout&lt;/strong&gt;” filled up. When the objective was completed, the reward was a “roulette ticket”, which had “availability” for a particular date. It’ll be interesting to see what this is, but it feels a bit loot box-y…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another notable addition is the &lt;strong&gt;Gran Turismo Cafe&lt;/strong&gt;, which we were told sits at the centre of the map. Players are given a car collection menu (a set of cars they must aim to acquire), and on completion they receive rewards (the roulette ticket showed up here, too) and unlock tracks. The cafe is also where some of the aforementioned car commentary comes into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-modes&quot;&gt;Other modes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plethora of other modes were also sprinkled throughout the video. The most notable for me was the &lt;strong&gt;Custom Race&lt;/strong&gt; mode, which didn’t always appear in older &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; titles. This is essentially the sandbox offered by other games like &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/project-cars&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project Cars&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Assetto Corsa&lt;/em&gt;, allowing the player to select a track, cars, weather conditions and so on to set up their own races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere there was a &lt;strong&gt;Circuit Experience&lt;/strong&gt; mode, designed to help you to learn new tracks, and “&lt;strong&gt;mission races&lt;/strong&gt;”, which are special events that differ from the usual formula, like drag races and drift trials. The classic &lt;strong&gt;licence tests&lt;/strong&gt; also return, putting players through their paces to learn racecraft and spend hours driving the same few metres to earn that elusive gold trophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music was the slightly odd focus of some of the modes shown. Replays can now be set to music, with the camera changing in time with the soundtrack, but the effect wasn’t so different to a standard replay in my opinion. The highlight in this rather niche genre was the &lt;strong&gt;Music Rally&lt;/strong&gt; mode - basically a checkpoint race where the countdown syncs to the beat of the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, we were shown some of &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;’s multiplayer options, including &lt;strong&gt;two-player local split screen&lt;/strong&gt;, which is welcome, if a bit of a throwback. Online, there are lobbies and “meeting places”, which we were told are good for playing with friends, and &lt;strong&gt;Sport Mode&lt;/strong&gt;, which is where we can partake in “serious racing” with players around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t sure how much more we’d see of &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; before its release on 4th March, but not only did this video drop a lot more detail, it also served to further whet my appetite for some racing in a month’s time. With the launch date approaching at a rapid pace, this may well be my final opportunity to speculate about the game before it comes out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With its attention to detail and huge range of modes that should cater to both the sim racing and arcade racing fans out there, this game has the potential to be something really special. The addition of the historical content and dedication to the stories behind the pretty cars is something I’ve never seen in a video game before, and shows that the designers and developers are truly dedicated to their subject matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s one thing I’m still a little skeptical about, it’s that we still haven’t seen any footage from a PlayStation 4 console - let alone the original model. PlayStation 5 players are worried that the existence of a PS4 version will mean the game will have to hold back in some respects, but my concern is over performance and missing features on last-gen hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, it’s rare for me to be this excited about a game, and it’s even rarer for me to have sustained that excitement through the entire pre-release period. With solid on-track action, beautiful graphics, a generous selection of cars and tracks, stunning weather, and all the colour and educational aspects that come with the focus on “car culture”, &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; could be the definitive racing game - we’ll just have to wait to find out for sure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="gran-turismo" /><category term="racing" /><summary type="html">It’s no secret that I am very excited for Gran Turismo 7, so when we got a 32-minute “deep dive” video from the PlayStation State of Play this week, it only seemed right for me to dissect every second of it try to gather all the little details and clues about what we can expect to see in March. The video starred series producer Kazunori Yamauchi, speaking via a translator. He touted the new game, which marks Gran Turismo’s 25th anniversary, as “the most complete Gran Turismo to date” and revealed a whole range of features and details that we hadn’t seen before, including more about the game’s focus on “car culture” as well as the actual racing. What follows is a summary of what I could ascertain from the video, which confirmed it’s going to be a long wait until the 4th March release date. The cars Yamauchi revealed that Gran Turismo 7 will feature more than 400 cars. Over the course of the video we were treated to shots of road cars, sports cars, GT cars, historic cars, rally cars, and concept cars, confirming that the catalogue has all the variety that we’ve come to expect from the series. It was promised that additional cars will be delivered via online updates. We were shown several places to buy cars. Brand Central is a shopping centre where players can buy around 300 new cars from 2001 and later. The used car dealer will sell a different lineup of cars on a daily basis. These will generally be more affordable, but some models (the example given was 90s Japanese sports cars) will actually accrue value. The last marketplace shown was Brighton Antiques, a place to buy legendary and famous cars like the Le Mans-winning Ford GT40 and James Bond’s Aston Martin DB5.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_15.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_15.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Microsoft, Activision Blizzard, and the future of gaming</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/22/microsoft-activision-blizzard" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Microsoft, Activision Blizzard, and the future of gaming" /><published>2022-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/22/microsoft-activision-blizzard</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/22/microsoft-activision-blizzard">&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a blog about the business of video games, but there was one piece of industry news this week that was such a shock that I had to cover it - Microsoft’s $69 billion acquisition of Activision Blizzard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/microsoft-activision-blizzard_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-long-time-coming&quot;&gt;A long time coming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really, this story started a lot earlier than that. Back in 2013, Microsoft was battered by critics following its announcement of the next-generation Xbox One console. While the Xbox 360 had won over gamers with its hefty library of acclaimed games, Microsoft’s promotional material for its new console was heavily focused on its multimedia capabilities and Kinect voice commands - an ethos embedded so deeply into the Xbox One’s design that it had an HDMI in port so users could route over video devices through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, along with some of the decisions around DRM and making the console online-only, was a serious misjudgement. Gamers previously addicted to &lt;em&gt;Gears of War&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Halo&lt;/em&gt; felt abandoned in favour of a more general, casual audience. Sony siezed its opportunity, using the slogan “for the players” for the competing PlayStation 4 and pushing a slew of exclusive titles to win over the masses - &lt;em&gt;Bloodborne&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Uncharted 4&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spider-Man&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;God of War&lt;/em&gt;. As of mid-2021, it was reported that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vgchartz.com/article/449842/switch-vs-ps4-vs-xbox-one-global-lifetime-sales-june-2021/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the PS4 had sold more than 115 million units&lt;/a&gt;, with the Xbox One lagging behind with sales of 50 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/microsoft-activision-blizzard_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the next generation came around in 2019, Microsoft was determined not to make the same mistake again. The new Xbox Series X was slightly more powerful than Sony’s PlayStation 5, and from the beginning it was clear that Microsoft’s focus was on the games - even the initial announcment trailer prominently featured Master Chief (&lt;em&gt;Halo Infinite&lt;/em&gt; would shortly follow), and the Xbox Game Pass became a clear focus for the company.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More significant changes were ongoing behind the scenes. Even as far back as 2014, Microsoft had acquired &lt;em&gt;Minecraft&lt;/em&gt; developer Mojang for $2.5 billion. Four developer acquisitions, including &lt;em&gt;Forza Horizon&lt;/em&gt; maker Playground Games, were announced at E3 2018, followed the next year by Double Fine, famous for &lt;em&gt;Psychonauts&lt;/em&gt;. The message was clear: Microsoft - and by extension Xbox - was all about the games now, and it would spare no expense in securing the manpower and creativity to make them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most significant acquisition for Xbox Game Studios came in September 2020, when it was announced Microsoft would pay $7.5 billion for ZeniMax Media, whose family of studios included Bethesda (&lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fallout 4&lt;/em&gt;), Arkane (&lt;em&gt;Prey&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Deathloop&lt;/em&gt;), id (&lt;em&gt;Doom&lt;/em&gt;), and MachineGames (&lt;em&gt;Wolfenstein&lt;/em&gt;). Shortly afterwards, it was confirmed that Bethesda’s as yet unnamed &lt;em&gt;Elder Scrolls VI&lt;/em&gt; game would be an Xbox and PC exclusive - a massive win for Microsoft considering that its predecessor &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt; sold more than 30 million copies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this was nothing compared to what was to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;activision-blizzard-king&quot;&gt;Activision Blizzard King&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a massive technology company trying to convince gamers to buy your console and subscribe to your games service, what’s the next biggest title you could add to your portfolio? You could certainly do a lot worse than industry heavyweights like &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Warcraft&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Overwatch&lt;/em&gt;, and even former PlayStation poster boys &lt;em&gt;Crash Bandicoot&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Spyro the Dragon&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;COD&lt;/em&gt; alone sells up to 30 million units per game, which is staggering when you consider that entries in the series are released on an annual basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there were the circumstances. Activision Blizzard has been under fire for nearly a year over its reported “frat boy” working culture, and in July 2021 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2021-07-22-state-of-california-sues-activision-blizzard-over-frat-boy-culture&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;was sued by the State of California&lt;/a&gt;. Amongst other accusations, the lawsuit alleged that female employees were subjected to “sexual harassment with no repercussion”. These claims were heavily covered in the gaming media and beyond, and would have dented the company’s reputation and, one would think by extension, its valuation in any potential deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/microsoft-activision-blizzard_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so Microsoft pounced. On 18th January 2022, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2022-01-18-microsoft-near-deal-to-buy-call-of-duty-maker-activision-blizzard-report&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Microsoft announced that it would pay $68.7 billion cash to acquire Activision Blizzard King&lt;/a&gt; (which also included the developer of the mobile phenomenon &lt;em&gt;Candy Crush&lt;/em&gt;). As far as many gamers were concerned, this came completely out of the blue, and sent shockwaves through Twitter and games news websites and blogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the initial announcement came a series of comments and clarifications. Microsoft said it was aware that Activision Blizzard games were popular across many platforms and that it planned to “continue to support those communities”. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2022-01-20-sony-says-it-expects-microsoft-to-ensure-activision-games-are-multiplatform&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sony issued a statement&lt;/a&gt; to say it expected Microsoft to “abide by contractual agreements and continue to ensure Activision games are multi-platform”. And &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2022-01-20/activision-employees-say-they-re-optimistic-about-acquisition&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;according to &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, employees at the company are optimistic that the new owner will help to bring about the cultural change required to make it a better place to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-next-for-gaming&quot;&gt;What next for gaming?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does all this mean for the average gamer? First, as the console wars intensify, expect more exclusives. Fine, you might think - I’ll just buy an Xbox and guarantee that I’ll be able to play &lt;em&gt;The Elder Scrolls&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/em&gt;. But what if (for example) Sony decides to buy EA and fragment the market further? Then, much like how you need Netflix, Amazon Prime, and Disney+ to watch all your favourite TV series, you’d need to splash out on an Xbox and a PlayStation to play all of your favourite games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alternative is that Microsoft is doing all of this to bolster its Game Pass offering. Third-party publishers might not see the value of putting their brand new flagship games on the streaming service and losing sales, but if the studios become a part of Xbox then that barrier is removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/microsoft-activision-blizzard_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking this a step further, could we eventually see Microsoft leave the console market altogether? What if Game Pass was eventually its main offering, allowing you to play a huge games library across your PC or - God forbid - your PlayStation? Perhaps we’ll even reach a point where physical hardware is not required, and instead you connect a controller to your TV and all Microsoft’s games are processed in the cloud and streamed to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody knows for sure what Microsoft’s long-term plan is except Microsoft itself. It’ll be interesting to see how all of this plays out - especially if it does come to the point where gamers are told that physical ownership is outdated, when many players take great pleasure in building a library of boxes and discs, and all the pride and security that come with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only time will tell, so watch this space.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="xbox" /><category term="industry" /><category term="call-of-duty" /><summary type="html">This isn’t a blog about the business of video games, but there was one piece of industry news this week that was such a shock that I had to cover it - Microsoft’s $69 billion acquisition of Activision Blizzard. A long time coming Really, this story started a lot earlier than that. Back in 2013, Microsoft was battered by critics following its announcement of the next-generation Xbox One console. While the Xbox 360 had won over gamers with its hefty library of acclaimed games, Microsoft’s promotional material for its new console was heavily focused on its multimedia capabilities and Kinect voice commands - an ethos embedded so deeply into the Xbox One’s design that it had an HDMI in port so users could route over video devices through it. This, along with some of the decisions around DRM and making the console online-only, was a serious misjudgement. Gamers previously addicted to Gears of War and Halo felt abandoned in favour of a more general, casual audience. Sony siezed its opportunity, using the slogan “for the players” for the competing PlayStation 4 and pushing a slew of exclusive titles to win over the masses - Bloodborne, Uncharted 4, Spider-Man, God of War. As of mid-2021, it was reported that the PS4 had sold more than 115 million units, with the Xbox One lagging behind with sales of 50 million. When the next generation came around in 2019, Microsoft was determined not to make the same mistake again. The new Xbox Series X was slightly more powerful than Sony’s PlayStation 5, and from the beginning it was clear that Microsoft’s focus was on the games - even the initial announcment trailer prominently featured Master Chief (Halo Infinite would shortly follow), and the Xbox Game Pass became a clear focus for the company.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/microsoft-activision-blizzard_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/microsoft-activision-blizzard_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Project Zomboid is a true sandbox game</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/29/project-zomboid-true-sandbox-game" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project Zomboid is a true sandbox game" /><published>2022-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/29/project-zomboid-true-sandbox-game</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/29/project-zomboid-true-sandbox-game">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; is yet another game that was sitting in my Steam library for a long time before I played it properly. Since the start of 2020, I’d clocked just ten hours (although granted a lot happened in the meantime). But when I saw its recent resurgence, I thought it was time to give it another go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-zomboid_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;virtual-playgrounds&quot;&gt;Virtual playgrounds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m always looking for better ways to explain what makes a game great for me. Recently, referring to a video about someone convincing his non-gamer girlfriend to play some games, &lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/gaming/comments/s9u9ta/friends_wife_started_playing_half_life_alyx_you/htpe90u/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a Redditor put it better than I could&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Her biggest complaint was that she couldn’t solve the problems as creatively as she wanted to and since she didn’t know common gaming tropes (like look at the thing in the room that’s a weird colour), it was difficult to figure out solutions that the game would actually accept.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even as somebody who recognises this kind of signposting, I think this is a reason why some games appeal to me more than others - for example, why I’ve never gotten into shooters as much as many other gamers. The games I enjoy - from &lt;em&gt;RollerCoaster Tycoon&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/the-sims&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, from &lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Assetto Corsa&lt;/em&gt; - all give the player an environment, a set of rules, and the freedom to do pretty much whatever they want. When the player asks a reasonable “Can I…?” question to these games, the answer is usually yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;into-the-wild&quot;&gt;Into the wild&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; takes this to a level I’ve never seen before. The game tasks the player with surviving a zombie apocalypse. They must find shelter, gather and prepare food, and defend themselves from the horde to live for as long as possible. There are no respawns - when your character dies, they’re dead. Everything that happens in between is up to your own inginuity.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d bounced off the game a few times because this can make it super difficult. A momentary lapse in concentration can lead to your character getting overrun, bitten, and infected. This meant I never lasted more than a few hours before losing everything. But like all good sandbox games, &lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; gives you the sliders to set up the scenario just how you want it. When somebody on Twitter recommended that I make things a bit easier for myself, I was finally able to interact with the game’s systems properly and came to understand them better, and that’s what got me hooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-zomboid_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game’s graphics are reminiscent of the original &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;, but the systems behind &lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; are immense. Everything from wellbeing to clothing, cooking to crafting, weather to vehicles, has such depth that each of them takes a while to learn on its own. In this respect it’s what I refer to as a “wiki game”, in that you’ll inevitably need to run the occasional web search to learn how to do something, but you don’t want to read online material for hours on end and ruin all the surprises for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-little-things&quot;&gt;The little things&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’ll save all that for the full review I’ll post soon once I’ve had more time to explore. Returning to my original point, what makes &lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; great is that you can intuit what to do based on what would work in real life. Examples of this that I’ve encountered so far include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Any empty container - bottles, pans, baths, etc. - can be filled with water, either to carry around with you and drink or to stockpile in case the utilities fail and the taps no longer run&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most clothing gathered by looting and from zombie corpses can be ripped into strips to dress your wounds if you’re scratched or bitten&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exercises like press-ups, sit-ups, and squats can help to keep your character fit, but your physical effectiveness will be reduced the next day when the corresponding muscles ache&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you can’t find an unlocked door or window to get into a building, you can smash a window instead - but you must remember to remove the broken glass or you’ll get cut climbing through&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level of detail is quite amazing. I imagine this is great for roleplayers, but even as a regular player it’s fantastic to be rewarded for thinking about small things that most games would ignore. Working out &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to do some things can be tricky - and that’s where the wiki comes in - but I feel like that is more than made up for each time you pull off your latest plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll cover &lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; in a much more detailed review in a few weeks, but for now I just wanted to say how much I’m enjoying it and encourage you to give it a go - even if it is with the difficulty turned down a notch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="project-zomboid" /><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">Project Zomboid is yet another game that was sitting in my Steam library for a long time before I played it properly. Since the start of 2020, I’d clocked just ten hours (although granted a lot happened in the meantime). But when I saw its recent resurgence, I thought it was time to give it another go. Virtual playgrounds I’m always looking for better ways to explain what makes a game great for me. Recently, referring to a video about someone convincing his non-gamer girlfriend to play some games, a Redditor put it better than I could: “Her biggest complaint was that she couldn’t solve the problems as creatively as she wanted to and since she didn’t know common gaming tropes (like look at the thing in the room that’s a weird colour), it was difficult to figure out solutions that the game would actually accept.” Even as somebody who recognises this kind of signposting, I think this is a reason why some games appeal to me more than others - for example, why I’ve never gotten into shooters as much as many other gamers. The games I enjoy - from RollerCoaster Tycoon to The Sims, from Grand Theft Auto to Assetto Corsa - all give the player an environment, a set of rules, and the freedom to do pretty much whatever they want. When the player asks a reasonable “Can I…?” question to these games, the answer is usually yes. Into the wild Project Zomboid takes this to a level I’ve never seen before. The game tasks the player with surviving a zombie apocalypse. They must find shelter, gather and prepare food, and defend themselves from the horde to live for as long as possible. There are no respawns - when your character dies, they’re dead. Everything that happens in between is up to your own inginuity.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-zomboid_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-zomboid_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">In defence of scripting in football games</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/15/defence-of-scripting-football-games" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In defence of scripting in football games" /><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/15/defence-of-scripting-football-games</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/15/defence-of-scripting-football-games">&lt;p&gt;Spend any length of time reading online forums for football games and you’ll come across complaints about “scripting” - the alleged way games like &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; artificially infuence games to create drama. This quirk of games’ design and programming is always portrayed in a negative light, and often rightly so, but I’d like to make a case for why it makes sense and improves the gameplay experience in certain circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-scripting&quot;&gt;What is scripting?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the critics, “scripting” - sometimes also referred to as “momentum” - is a perversion of the way football games should play. Unlike real football, &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; matches are under the complete control of a match engine, and by extension, the developers. And there have been accusations for years that EA Sports (and Konami, before &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/01/efootball-2022-first-impressions&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;eFootball&lt;/em&gt; killed the &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; series&lt;/a&gt;) has abused this power to create as much drama as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To those who are on the lookout for potential foul play, this invisible hand makes itself known in semi-predictable ways, usually to give teams suffering heavy losses a fighting chance or to prevent the player team from running away with every match, or the league title. Some of the most common complaints allege that scripting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Makes goals easier for both teams to score in the final minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Causes shots to hit the post, passes to go off course, etc. when the game doesn’t “want” the player to win the game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grants even the weakest opponents - and in particular goalkeepers - superstar skills if the game favours them in the match&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensures Career Mode rivals win the player wins, draws when the player draws, etc. to keep the title race as close as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many players say the biggest giveaway that scripting has taken effect is when one team has far more possession and shots on goal but fails to win. This has become something of a meme, particularly in &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/01/25/football-manager-addictive-spreadsheet/&quot;&gt;the stats-obsessed world of &lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and was probably at least partly responsible for the emergence of the expected goals (xG) metric in the real game.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of this may be coincidence, of course, and the big teams do suffer these frustrating matches in the Premier League and beyond. EA has denied that it scripting exists in &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; (as far as I know, Konami has never spoken on the issue), so it could be that what is observed is not the result of an algorithm designed to control the outcome of matches, and instead a culmunation of all the systems that simulate form, fatigue, skills, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the frequency of these events has convinced some players that scripting exists. What would be the developers’ motive to implement it, you might ask? The purported answer is that the added drama makes the game more emotional and therefore more addictive, as well as encouraging less skilled players by ensuring they always have a chance at securing a freak win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody except the developers knows whether scripting really exists in any given game, or to what level it influences matches, but I’ve seen enough evidence in my own play to suspect it’s there in some form. The assumption I’m never sure about, however, is that a “pure” football game would play better. The scripting rumours have persisted in one form or another since the mid-2000s, and there have been &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;some great football games&lt;/a&gt; in that time. So when does it work and when does it not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;when-scripting-works&quot;&gt;When scripting works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I will concede that scripting would be very frustrating in online game modes, where you usually only play each opponent once and therefore don’t have a chance for the luck to level out. It would also affect online rankings, promotion and relegation from divisions, and so on. It would be even worse if it spanned to modes where money is involved, but we have at least had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2021-03-03-fifa-scripting-lawsuit-withdrawn-after-ea-provides-plaintiffs-with-detailed-technical-information-and-access-to-speak-with-our-engineers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;confirmation from EA that there is no scripting in Ultimate Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But offline, I believe it can actually create a more enjoyable experience. This is certainly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the case my Chelsea side visit Burnley and lose to two wonder goals, but it can certainly liven up games against weaker teams. Statistically you’d expect the big club to pervail comfortably, but that’s not always the case in real life and constant 3-0 wins would get boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my best &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; games have been those where everything seems to be going the opposition’s way. When I play Southampton at home and they park the bus I can spend nearly the whole game trying to pick apart the AI’s defence, their goalkeeper performing all kinds of acrobatics when I get the odd shot away. When a chance falls to my striker with two minutes to go I expect him to miss because he’s barely been able to control the ball for 88 minutes, but when the ball hits the back of the net and secures the 1-0 win, that hard-fought triumph is one of the best feelings in the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “scripting” - or at least the randomised part of the game that leads people to &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; there is scripting - leads to added challenge and interesting stories in games that might have been nothing but boring domination. This reflects real life matches, when big teams have off days against bottom-of-the-table sides using very defensive setups, and really adds tension to the in-game title battle when I know City and Liverpool are winning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, scripting or not, unpredictability is what makes football the world’s favourite sport and what makes football games worth playing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="pro-evolution-soccer" /><category term="football" /><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">Spend any length of time reading online forums for football games and you’ll come across complaints about “scripting” - the alleged way games like FIFA and PES artificially infuence games to create drama. This quirk of games’ design and programming is always portrayed in a negative light, and often rightly so, but I’d like to make a case for why it makes sense and improves the gameplay experience in certain circumstances. What is scripting? According to the critics, “scripting” - sometimes also referred to as “momentum” - is a perversion of the way football games should play. Unlike real football, FIFA matches are under the complete control of a match engine, and by extension, the developers. And there have been accusations for years that EA Sports (and Konami, before eFootball killed the PES series) has abused this power to create as much drama as possible. To those who are on the lookout for potential foul play, this invisible hand makes itself known in semi-predictable ways, usually to give teams suffering heavy losses a fighting chance or to prevent the player team from running away with every match, or the league title. Some of the most common complaints allege that scripting: Makes goals easier for both teams to score in the final minutes Causes shots to hit the post, passes to go off course, etc. when the game doesn’t “want” the player to win the game Grants even the weakest opponents - and in particular goalkeepers - superstar skills if the game favours them in the match Ensures Career Mode rivals win the player wins, draws when the player draws, etc. to keep the title race as close as possible Many players say the biggest giveaway that scripting has taken effect is when one team has far more possession and shots on goal but fails to win. This has become something of a meme, particularly in the stats-obsessed world of Football Manager, and was probably at least partly responsible for the emergence of the expected goals (xG) metric in the real game.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIFA is my new year’s resolution (kind of)</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/08/fifa-new-years-resolution" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA is my new year's resolution &amp;#40;kind of&amp;#41;" /><published>2022-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/08/fifa-new-years-resolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/08/fifa-new-years-resolution">&lt;p&gt;There’s an episode of &lt;em&gt;South Park&lt;/em&gt; that first aired about a decade ago where Stan wakes up one day and everything is shit. The food he eats is shit. The chatter on the radio is shit. The new films at the cinema are shit. Everything he used to like is at best unremarkable and at worst unforgivably flawed. He has grown up, and in doing so has turned into a cynic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently realised that was what I had become in recent years. A duo of experience (a sense of having seen it all before) and jadedness (thanks in large part to online commenters finding fault in just about everything) meant I couldn’t enjoy a lot of things I used to. My favourite band’s latest album wasn’t a patch on their output in the early 2000s, and new games were full of microtransactions and soulless compared to classics from years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cutting-out-the-noise&quot;&gt;Cutting out the noise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 2022, I’ve decided to put a stop to this. I’m not the complete isolation “cabin in the woods” type, but I do believe that one of the pitfalls of the internet age is that we’re exposed to a deluge of opinion on just about everything. If you and a couple of your friends like a new TV series then that’s no longer enough - you’ll also feel inclined to seek out its subreddit and pore over the world’s thoughts on each episode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this works as intended, it’s amazing. We get fruitful discussions with people all over the place about interests that might not be popular where we’re from. When it doesn’t, we find ourselves second guessing everything we like, wondering what flaw a hypothetical cynic might point out. When that second mindset takes hold it becomes very difficult to enjoy anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; series, for example. The internet’s view of the games is that they change very little each year, lure kids into what are at best frivolous microtransactions and at worst casino-emulating lootboxes, and are plagued with bugs and scripted results. With all that in mind, why bother playing?&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;giving-games-a-chance&quot;&gt;Giving games a chance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I fancied playing a football game, and given that &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/01/efootball-2022-first-impressions&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;eFootball&lt;/em&gt; has effectively killed the &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; series&lt;/a&gt;, I switched on a digital copy of &lt;em&gt;FIFA 20&lt;/em&gt; that I picked up for about £5 in a sale last year to give it another go. Just as importantly, I made a conscious effort to make my mind a clean slate, free of past judgements and crticisms I’d read about the series. I decided I would judge it only by what was directly in front of me on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having played nearly a season’s worth of Career Mode in the last week, I can say that &lt;em&gt;FIFA 20&lt;/em&gt; is a solid football game. It looks great - the stadiums in particular look just like their real-world counterparts. The animations are as slick as you like. The opponents are challenging and varied, and some of my favourite matches are when teams come to Stamford Bridge to park the bus and I have to unpick their defences. And the whole thing has a lot of fanfare about it. &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; feels connected to the wider football world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Games are never perfect, and this is no exception - including in some of the ways commonly pointed out online. Career Mode itself does enough, but hasn’t substantially changed in years. Sometimes players don’t react the way you want or expect them to. And every so often you find yourself in a game where your relegation fodder opponents play like prime Barcelona and you’re in for a grind because the game &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; you to lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while I might previously have tuned out or lost interest, I now look past these minor annoyances and consider the sum of the game. I think about some of the retro games I’ve played - &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;even all-time classics like &lt;em&gt;PES5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - and know they also had flaws that were overlooked because I was simply having too much fun. Then I stop analysing everything, focus on the game, and try to let the atmosphere absorb me as I push for the next goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lifes-too-short-not-to-have-fun&quot;&gt;Life’s too short not to have fun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the attitude I’m trying to keep with me in 2022. Whether it’s in gaming, film, television, music - even politics - I’m going to try to cut myself off from the online commentary, consume media and make my own mind up before I read about anything, and hopefully find more fun and enjoyment than I have for some without the internet spoiling everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not about putting up with bad games or manipulative practices. I’ll still call out features I think could be improved and content I think should have been included in the box price. But I want my enjoyment or disappointment with each game to come from my personal preferences and judgements - not what somebody else got stuck in my head before I even started playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So happy new year to everybody who has stumbled upon &lt;em&gt;The Strat Pack&lt;/em&gt;! I hope you have a fantastic 2022 and discover a ton of things you love. And if you find any gems you think I’d like, please do share them with me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">There’s an episode of South Park that first aired about a decade ago where Stan wakes up one day and everything is shit. The food he eats is shit. The chatter on the radio is shit. The new films at the cinema are shit. Everything he used to like is at best unremarkable and at worst unforgivably flawed. He has grown up, and in doing so has turned into a cynic. I recently realised that was what I had become in recent years. A duo of experience (a sense of having seen it all before) and jadedness (thanks in large part to online commenters finding fault in just about everything) meant I couldn’t enjoy a lot of things I used to. My favourite band’s latest album wasn’t a patch on their output in the early 2000s, and new games were full of microtransactions and soulless compared to classics from years ago. Cutting out the noise For 2022, I’ve decided to put a stop to this. I’m not the complete isolation “cabin in the woods” type, but I do believe that one of the pitfalls of the internet age is that we’re exposed to a deluge of opinion on just about everything. If you and a couple of your friends like a new TV series then that’s no longer enough - you’ll also feel inclined to seek out its subreddit and pore over the world’s thoughts on each episode. When this works as intended, it’s amazing. We get fruitful discussions with people all over the place about interests that might not be popular where we’re from. When it doesn’t, we find ourselves second guessing everything we like, wondering what flaw a hypothetical cynic might point out. When that second mindset takes hold it becomes very difficult to enjoy anything. Take the FIFA series, for example. The internet’s view of the games is that they change very little each year, lure kids into what are at best frivolous microtransactions and at worst casino-emulating lootboxes, and are plagued with bugs and scripted results. With all that in mind, why bother playing?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Classic Splinter Cell is back after a 15-year hiatus!</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/18/splinter-cell-remake" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Classic Splinter Cell is back after a 15-year hiatus!" /><published>2021-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/18/splinter-cell-remake</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/18/splinter-cell-remake">&lt;p&gt;Ubisoft has announced that it’s working on a &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake! This Christmas miracle landed on my desk just in time for the last article of the year, so join me one last time in 2021 as we run through what we know (and what we don’t) about this long-awaited revival of a beloved series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a long time coming. There hasn’t been a &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; game at all since 2013’s &lt;em&gt;Blacklist&lt;/em&gt;, and many fans (myself included) feel there hasn’t been an entry that has respected the series’ stealth ethos in more than 15 years. After all that time, many thought that Sam Fisher might never return to the shadows, and so many rumours circulated over the years that it became easy to dismiss any talk of a new game instantly. But here we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/splinter-cell_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you believe the people in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HH1_ZCSf_HY&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the promotional YouTube video&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; is valued as the series that defined what Ubisoft could make - and could be - at a time when it was largely known for &lt;em&gt;Rayman&lt;/em&gt;. Fast forward to 2021 and you might be a little nervous, as the company is now known for churning out regular &lt;em&gt;Assassin’s Creed&lt;/em&gt; games and its recent player-angering announcement that it would be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pcgamer.com/ubisofts-nft-scheme-criticized-as-useless-costly-ecologically-mortifying-by-french-trade-union/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;introducing NFTs to some of its upcoming titles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, all the noises coming from the developers in the video make it sound like they understand and cherish what made &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; special. All the key elements - the importance of light and shadow, the little details like realistic bullet holes in fish tanks, and of course Sam’s signature night vision and infrared goggles - are discussed. The team also note the cinematic nature of the game and its story (although there’s been no word yet on whether fan favourite Michael Ironside will reprise the lead role or not).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-do-we-know&quot;&gt;What do we know?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But really, we currently know very little about the new &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake. After dissecting the video and &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ubisoft.com/en-us/article/4adJLuhgYrPboHAPRfK7Oz/splinter-cell-remake-begins-development-at-ubisoft-toronto&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the accompanying Ubisoft press release&lt;/a&gt;, I can say only the following for certain (as far as anything is certain in gaming):&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The remake is being developed by Ubisoft Toronto and is in “the earliest stages of development”, so don’t expect it any time soon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game is being rebuilt using the Snowdrop engine, which is the same one used by Ubisoft’s upcoming &lt;em&gt;Avatar&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; games&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many of the team are “stealth purists” who worked on earlier &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; games and want to their “spirit” to “remain intact”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game will remain linear, which hopefully means &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; will avoid the curse of Ubisoft’s frequently bland open-world collectathons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unlike more recent games in the series, the remake will reward players who play tactically with the objective to “be a ghost”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The remake will receive a visual upgrade with possible innovation in animation, AI, and audio - Ubisoft says this will deliver “the spirit of the old with the comfort of the new”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in summary: not much. We can essentially say that Ubisoft is working on a &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake that will be available at some point in the distant future and will bear some level of resemblance to the older games in the series, but details are certainly very thin on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cautious-optimism&quot;&gt;Cautious optimism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s probably too early to get excited, but as somebody who’s been waiting for a “real” &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; game since 2006’s &lt;em&gt;Double Agent&lt;/em&gt; (or 2005’s &lt;em&gt;Chaos Theory&lt;/em&gt;, if we’re being less generous) it’s very difficult not to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the unease underlying any optimism about the &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake is necessary because of how much the games industry has changed since the first game’s release in 2002. New entries in beloved series are launched as £60 microtransaction shopfronts, single player campaigns bizarrely require internet connections, and companies that always have their sights set on the next trendy buzzword now see NFTs as their next big moneymaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/splinter-cell_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent example of a rerelease gone wrong was &lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto Trilogy - The Definitive Edition&lt;/em&gt;, which initially looked like some easy fan service to restore some old favourites but turned awry when Rockstar delivered an often ugly, glitchy mess for the full retail price of a brand new game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake falter in a similar way? For now I can take some comfort in the developers’ words and the fact that this appears to be a full remake (unlike &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt;, which was only a remaster), but we’ll only find out for sure as we get more details, gameplay videos, and eventually get our hands on the full game. It’s going to be a long wait for sure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="splinter-cell" /><category term="stealth" /><summary type="html">Ubisoft has announced that it’s working on a Splinter Cell remake! This Christmas miracle landed on my desk just in time for the last article of the year, so join me one last time in 2021 as we run through what we know (and what we don’t) about this long-awaited revival of a beloved series. It’s been a long time coming. There hasn’t been a Splinter Cell game at all since 2013’s Blacklist, and many fans (myself included) feel there hasn’t been an entry that has respected the series’ stealth ethos in more than 15 years. After all that time, many thought that Sam Fisher might never return to the shadows, and so many rumours circulated over the years that it became easy to dismiss any talk of a new game instantly. But here we are. If you believe the people in the promotional YouTube video, Splinter Cell is valued as the series that defined what Ubisoft could make - and could be - at a time when it was largely known for Rayman. Fast forward to 2021 and you might be a little nervous, as the company is now known for churning out regular Assassin’s Creed games and its recent player-angering announcement that it would be introducing NFTs to some of its upcoming titles. Still, all the noises coming from the developers in the video make it sound like they understand and cherish what made Splinter Cell special. All the key elements - the importance of light and shadow, the little details like realistic bullet holes in fish tanks, and of course Sam’s signature night vision and infrared goggles - are discussed. The team also note the cinematic nature of the game and its story (although there’s been no word yet on whether fan favourite Michael Ironside will reprise the lead role or not). What do we know? But really, we currently know very little about the new Splinter Cell remake. After dissecting the video and the accompanying Ubisoft press release, I can say only the following for certain (as far as anything is certain in gaming):</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/splinter-cell_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/splinter-cell_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">You’re in the zone until you’re not</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/12/youre-in-the-zone-until-youre-not" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You're in the zone until you're not" /><published>2021-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/12/youre-in-the-zone-until-youre-not</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/12/youre-in-the-zone-until-youre-not">&lt;p&gt;Flow is a weird thing, all inconsistent and unpredictable. When I go to play a video game, one of two things can happen - either I will bounce straight off it almost immediately, or I’ll become completely immersed and play for hours and hours over a period of weeks before eventually burning out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent examples of games that haven’t properly captured my attention include &lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/the-sims&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I’m sure they’re high-quality games, but they just didn’t grip me. And because they haven’t proven themselves to me in that way yet, I don’t know if they ever will. Meanwhile, I can go months without getting into &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/01/25/football-manager-addictive-spreadsheet/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Fallout 4&lt;/em&gt; and suddenly something will click and I’ll be sucked in all over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/verstappen-cc.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-flow-state&quot;&gt;The flow state&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is it that special place where a game keeps calling you back? Where you think about it when you’re not playing? I feel like it’s the same thing as flow, which is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;described by Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A flow state… is the mental state in which a person performing some activity is fully immersed in a feeling of energised focus, full involvement, and enjoyment in the process of the activity. In essence, flow is characterised by the complete absorption in what one does, and a resulting transformation in one’s sense of time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got thinking about this after seeing several examples of flow in action:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/10/running-formula-1-for-your-feet&quot;&gt;When I go running&lt;/a&gt;, sometimes I’m on complete autopilot, while other times I really feel the strain of each metre I cover.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been picking up my guitar more often recently. Sometimes I can play for hours and things just feel and sound right, but sometimes my timing and tone feels a little off no matter what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In sport, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/azzEnM6-Isk?t=295&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Max Verstappen’s almost-perfect qualifying lap&lt;/a&gt; at the Saudi Arabian Grand Prix, in which he appeared to be in a supreme flow state because colliding with a barrier on the final corner.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I described earlier in the article, my personal experience is that this phenomenon can also apply to gaming, both for the esports elites and for the casual gamer who can’t stop playing a title they’re hooked on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-into-the-zone&quot;&gt;Getting into the zone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what puts you “in the zone”? For me, a flow state sits on the border between comfort and discomfort. If a task is too easy then it is mundane. If it is too difficult then I may get frustrated or feel I’m not making progress and give up. In between, where an activity is challenging enough to keep me engrossed but easy enough that I feel like I’m achieving something, is where the best games keep me coming back for session after session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/transport-fever&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transport Fever 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. When I first picked it up I was playing it for weeks, battling to turn a profit on my transportation empire. But as I became more experienced with the game I developed a reliable strategy to repay the initial loan and build a functioning network. At this point the game became less challenging and it didn’t hold my attention as well as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tag/racing&quot;&gt;Racing games&lt;/a&gt; - most recently for me &lt;em&gt;Assetto Corsa&lt;/em&gt; - are also a good example of this theory in action. When I first play a new motorsport game, one of the key tasks is to finetune the AI until it provides just enough challenge and I am not regularly finishing either first or last. It’s a tricky balancing act, and when I get it right I can drive consecutive endurance races for a while. However, if I stop playing the game for long enough for any reason, my driving skills fade slightly, the game gets harder, and it’s more difficult to get back into because losing all the time is frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enabling-flow-with-game-design&quot;&gt;Enabling flow with game design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can this teach us about game design? If enabling a flow state is the way to keep players playing, this seems to leave devs with two options…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is to finetune difficulty to a level where a specific group of players find their zone. An example of this is the Amiga classic &lt;em&gt;Deluxe Galaga&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/11/20/pi-hut-retro-gaming-kit-retropie&quot;&gt;which I recently wrote about&lt;/a&gt; - you can’t change the difficulty and must raise your game to the challenge. This approach is less common in modern day gaming, probably because publishers want games to make as much money as possible, and setting the bar too high may alienate less skilled players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other option is to give the players the toolbox required to build their own perfect challenge. The AI ability and aggression sliders in most modern racing games are an example of this, as is the multitude of self-imposed challenges possible (and cheats available) in a sandbox game like &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;. However, the downside of this approach is that the player must invest a chunk of time to find the right balance for their ability, and less committed players may drop off before they find their own personal sweet spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s for more intelligent and serious minds than mine to decide what is the best answer for any particular game, but personally I vastly prefer the latter option. Not only does the sandbox approach let me tweak the game to the perfect level to induce my own flow state, but it also lets me adjust it for other states - if I’m tired, for example, or just want to experiment with the game’s sandbox rather than seeking victory or achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo © &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/79618484@N02/48733228773&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Interceptor73&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/?ref=ccsearch&amp;amp;atype=rich&quot;&gt;CC BY 2.0&lt;/a&gt;). Cropped.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">Flow is a weird thing, all inconsistent and unpredictable. When I go to play a video game, one of two things can happen - either I will bounce straight off it almost immediately, or I’ll become completely immersed and play for hours and hours over a period of weeks before eventually burning out. Recent examples of games that haven’t properly captured my attention include Project Zomboid and The Sims 4. I’m sure they’re high-quality games, but they just didn’t grip me. And because they haven’t proven themselves to me in that way yet, I don’t know if they ever will. Meanwhile, I can go months without getting into Football Manager or Fallout 4 and suddenly something will click and I’ll be sucked in all over again. The flow state What is it that special place where a game keeps calling you back? Where you think about it when you’re not playing? I feel like it’s the same thing as flow, which is described by Wikipedia as follows. “A flow state… is the mental state in which a person performing some activity is fully immersed in a feeling of energised focus, full involvement, and enjoyment in the process of the activity. In essence, flow is characterised by the complete absorption in what one does, and a resulting transformation in one’s sense of time.” I got thinking about this after seeing several examples of flow in action: When I go running, sometimes I’m on complete autopilot, while other times I really feel the strain of each metre I cover. I’ve been picking up my guitar more often recently. Sometimes I can play for hours and things just feel and sound right, but sometimes my timing and tone feels a little off no matter what I do. In sport, see Max Verstappen’s almost-perfect qualifying lap at the Saudi Arabian Grand Prix, in which he appeared to be in a supreme flow state because colliding with a barrier on the final corner.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/verstappen-cc.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/verstappen-cc.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Things missing from The Sims 4</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/05/things-missing-the-sims-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Things missing from The Sims 4" /><published>2021-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/05/things-missing-the-sims-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/05/things-missing-the-sims-4">&lt;p&gt;I wrote last week about &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/11/27/how-to-break-the-sims-4&quot;&gt;my first impressions of &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (spoiler alert: they weren’t great). At the time I had a general feeling that the game lacked the quirkiness of previous titles in the series, but couldn’t quite put my finger on what exactly was missing from the latest release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had an extra week to play the game and think more deeply about it, and I’ve been keeping a running list of all the things I noticed that were in previous versions of &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; but are not in &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;. I’ve recreated this below, and will continue adding for as long as I keep playing the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/the-sims-4_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: There are likely to be some items on this list that either are in the game (and I just haven’t played long enough to see them) or were added in&lt;/em&gt; The Sims 4&lt;em&gt;’s many expansions. Let me know if so, but I’ll probably still keep them here - in the former scenario I’ve obviously seen a situation where they should have applied but didn’t, and in the latter it’s still not right that something that came with previous base games isn’t included now.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;burglars-burglaries-and-burglar-alarms&quot;&gt;Burglars, burglaries, and burglar alarms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with one that’s close to &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; fans’ hearts, every game prior to &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; had a burglar that would sometimes appear on your lot at night with a creepy little tune and try to steal your stuff. If you were prepared, you had an alarm and the police were immediately summoned. If you weren’t, your only hope was to try to wake your Sim and get them to call the police before the intruder could flee. Unfortunately this much-loved mechanic, which mixed things up from time to time, has completely disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;variety-when-inviting-sims-over&quot;&gt;Variety when inviting Sims over&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; also seemingly strips back the possible responses when inviting Sims over to your house to hang out. The older games would keep track of their work schedules, give excuses (the frequency of which depended on your Sim’s relationship with them), and throw wildcards like asking if friends could come, too. Since getting started with &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;, the only rejections I’ve had are if a Sim is sleeping (and they all wake at 7am, apparently) or if my Sim’s relationship is low enough that the two are mortal enemies.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sims-breaking-the-fourth-wall&quot;&gt;Sims breaking the fourth wall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of Simlish’s most iconic moments were when Sims used to turn directly to the camera and yell, normally to complain about their needs. There were also times from &lt;em&gt;The Sims 2&lt;/em&gt; onwards when Sims would quickly celebrate or complain about their next interactions depending on whether they matched their personalities or aspirations. As well as Sims being less vocal in general, these moments are gone in &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;, which plays it much straighter - an odd choice for a game that is actually much &lt;em&gt;easier&lt;/em&gt; than it used to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sims-with-working-ears&quot;&gt;Sims with working ears&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, if your Sim was sleeping in a room and somebody turned on a TV or stereo, they’d wake up and complain about the noise. In the series’ latest entry I can put my toddler to bed a tile away from a sound system blasting at full volume and they’ll sleep through it without any issues at all. Maybe this was deliberate - TVs and stereos are seemingly attractive objects to Sims left to their own devices - but it’s another example of a small omission that detracts from the game’s realism and challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/the-sims-4_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reliable-sim-autonomy&quot;&gt;Reliable Sim autonomy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years ago, Sims were roughly capable of taking care of themselves. They didn’t always get it perfectly right, but their AI was passable and they wouldn’t usually die if unattended. In fact, sometimes it was entertaining to hit the triple speed button and see what they got up to of their own accord. In &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; they all seem to have had lobotomies. Sometimes Sims will choose interactions that satisfy their needs, but if you give them an hour or two to themselves it’s much more common to see them stood on the spot, shrugging their shoulders and stretching until you intervene again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;strange-non-player-characters&quot;&gt;Strange non-player characters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the Social Bunny, the Sim Shrink, and Mrs. Crumplebottom? The Tragic Clown might have made an eventual comeback, but other than him, many of the fun and quirky side characters that used to show up in specific circumstances (usually emotionally extreme situations) or wander lots causing mischief have simply been cut out, which is a shame because they were key contributors to the slightly surreal atmosphere of the earlier games.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="the-sims" /><category term="life-sims" /><summary type="html">I wrote last week about my first impressions of The Sims 4 (spoiler alert: they weren’t great). At the time I had a general feeling that the game lacked the quirkiness of previous titles in the series, but couldn’t quite put my finger on what exactly was missing from the latest release. I’ve had an extra week to play the game and think more deeply about it, and I’ve been keeping a running list of all the things I noticed that were in previous versions of The Sims but are not in The Sims 4. I’ve recreated this below, and will continue adding for as long as I keep playing the game. Disclaimer: There are likely to be some items on this list that either are in the game (and I just haven’t played long enough to see them) or were added in The Sims 4’s many expansions. Let me know if so, but I’ll probably still keep them here - in the former scenario I’ve obviously seen a situation where they should have applied but didn’t, and in the latter it’s still not right that something that came with previous base games isn’t included now. Burglars, burglaries, and burglar alarms Starting with one that’s close to The Sims fans’ hearts, every game prior to The Sims 4 had a burglar that would sometimes appear on your lot at night with a creepy little tune and try to steal your stuff. If you were prepared, you had an alarm and the police were immediately summoned. If you weren’t, your only hope was to try to wake your Sim and get them to call the police before the intruder could flee. Unfortunately this much-loved mechanic, which mixed things up from time to time, has completely disappeared. Variety when inviting Sims over The Sims 4 also seemingly strips back the possible responses when inviting Sims over to your house to hang out. The older games would keep track of their work schedules, give excuses (the frequency of which depended on your Sim’s relationship with them), and throw wildcards like asking if friends could come, too. Since getting started with The Sims 4, the only rejections I’ve had are if a Sim is sleeping (and they all wake at 7am, apparently) or if my Sim’s relationship is low enough that the two are mortal enemies.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/the-sims-4_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/the-sims-4_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Breaking The Sims 4 in ten hours</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/27/how-to-break-the-sims-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking The Sims 4 in ten hours" /><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/27/how-to-break-the-sims-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/27/how-to-break-the-sims-4">&lt;p&gt;Having played a lot of &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; as a child, I was interested to see &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; on offer for just a few pounds in the recent Steam sale. It was obvious that this was a way to get players hooked and sell more expansions, but I thought it was a good chance to try out the most recent game in one of the series I’ve spent the most hours with and write a review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may have guessed from the title of this article, I didn’t get that far. So sit back, relax, and enjoy the story of how I got bored with &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; within a couple of hours - and what I did to keep myself entertained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-impressions&quot;&gt;First impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t dwell on it, but &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; is one of those games that sits in a special type of DRM hell, in that even if you buy it on Steam, your first ten minutes with EA’s latest life sim are likely to be spent dusting off the Origin client so you can actually play it. It’ll leave you longing for the days of &lt;em&gt;The Sims 2&lt;/em&gt;, back when you could just buy a disc, install the game, and play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I could finally start the game, what was evident is that EA were going for the largest market possible here. &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/09/01/asus-geforce-dual-gtx1060-o6g-review/&quot;&gt;My modest gaming rig&lt;/a&gt; plays most games from 2017 at their highest settings, but very few set themselves up that way after assessing my hardware. &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; automatically pushed all the sliders to the right - performance shouldn’t be an issue for many people here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not to say that everything is an upgrade or works perfectly. I noticed plenty of features that functioned well in previous &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; games, but are either absent or cause issues here. In Create-A-Sim, clothes can no longer be customised via a colour wheel, for example. More frustratingly, Sims frequently just ignore tasks assigned to them, which drop off their queues with no notification. This is especially frustrating when the task is critical, like giving a toddler some food before they are taken away. &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the game just didn’t like the pathing in the house I built, but this is also the first time in however many hours of &lt;em&gt;Sims&lt;/em&gt; play that I’ve had to look up the cheat to reset a Sim who was seemingly just stuck. After a few more hours, NPCs I’d never met before also had a habit of strolling into my house, chatting with my toddlers or taking the rubbish out for my Sims. Weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-bored&quot;&gt;Getting bored&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accusation leveled at &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; by some older fans was that the focus of the game has shifted. It’s no longer about life simulation, they say, and more geared towards giving casual players the tools to build the house of their dreams and deck it out in fashionable items available via expansion and “stuff” packs. There’s an element of that here, but the thing that dented my enthusiasm for a playthrough was just an overwhelming feeling of monotony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it’s because I’m an older, more weary gamer now, but there really was a sense that I’d seen everything Live Mode had to offer before. &lt;em&gt;The Sims 3&lt;/em&gt; piled on the narrative with neighbourhood exploration and quests, but a lot of that seems to be gone (perhaps to be restored by expansions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the way Sims interact with each other and the things around them, the main new feature is a series of mood states (e.g. happy, sad, flirty) that affect actions a Sim can take. While these do seem to affect Sims’ responses to others’ interactions, the new options available to the Sim experiencing the mood are mostly small variants on interactions we’ve seen a thousand times before: telling a self-deprecating joke if embarrassed, for example, or “attempting to flirt” if they’re down in the dumps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I’m just not the target audience anymore, but this all felt very underwhelming. I was simply retreading ground I’d already covered as far back as &lt;em&gt;The Sims 2&lt;/em&gt;, and there weren’t enough new quirks and surprises to keep me interested. &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; also seems incredibly easy. My Sim wanted a relationship, so I spoke to somebody on the street and went from casual conversation to flirting, kissing, agreeing to be partners, WooHooing, and trying for a baby all in one in-game evening. There was no challenge to it. So I made an executive decision: I abandoned the goal of writing a full review, and instead set out to test the game’s limits until they broke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;breaking-the-game&quot;&gt;Breaking the game&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After noticing how easy the game’s romance systems were, I set out on my own challenge - to see how many babies my Sim could father before things all came tumbling down around him. My Sim got into a routine, chatting to new people on the street, inviting them inside for a date, and trying for a baby the same day. It was ridiculous how easy this all was. He ended up with six simultaneous girlfriends, all of whom were potentially pregnant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It still seemed too easy, so I decided to add some peril by inviting all of them to a party at one of the girlfriends’ houses. I expected this to spark a wave of arguments and break-ups, but astoundingly they were all happy to chat and dance together as a group, somehow unaware of the ridiculous social dynamics at play. Nobody even batted an eyelid as Strat Packer disappeared upstairs to WooHoo with his first girlfriend, and he even used the opportunity to hit it off with her sister, adding a seventh potential heir to the rotation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmm… How to up the stakes further? I invited all of the heavily pregnant Sims over to hang out and invited as many as possible to join the household (limited by the eight-Sim cap). Before too long, my Sim was living with three girlfriends and four children, with an additional four kids floating around the neighbourhood from the others. Also amusing was that only one of the other mothers decided to call my Sim to tell him about the birth of his son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This latest move sparked the chaos I was looking for. Four children would have been challenging enough on their own, but it was the love square that really brought the spice. In attempting to take care of the kids, I couldn’t keep an eye on all my adult Sims at once, meaning that any automatic flirtation or kissing set in motion a log chain of fury, slaps, and mirror pep talks that finally gave the entertainment I was seeking. It turned out that balancing childcare and three relationships was the equivalent of a hard mode for &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;, finally delivering the challenge I was looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;findings-and-conclusion&quot;&gt;Findings and conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from adding another crazy &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; story to the internet’s massive archive, what I learnt from all this is that &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; is just not very good as a vanilla life simulation game. It lacks the charm that the early entries in the series had, there aren’t enough new surprises to keep a long-time player entertained, and it’s even broken in some places where it wasn’t before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the increased performance (specifically when handling ten or more Sims on the same lot at once) and inconsistent social system make it an entertaining playground for those who approach the game as a sandbox to complete unorthodox challenges or just to push the simulation to its limits. The potential for chaos here is huge, and if all you want to do is play God and watch things fall apart inside a virtual dollhouse, &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; is well worth the £4 or so it is frequently reduced to in Steam sales.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="the-sims" /><category term="life-sims" /><summary type="html">Having played a lot of The Sims as a child, I was interested to see The Sims 4 on offer for just a few pounds in the recent Steam sale. It was obvious that this was a way to get players hooked and sell more expansions, but I thought it was a good chance to try out the most recent game in one of the series I’ve spent the most hours with and write a review. As you may have guessed from the title of this article, I didn’t get that far. So sit back, relax, and enjoy the story of how I got bored with The Sims 4 within a couple of hours - and what I did to keep myself entertained. First impressions I won’t dwell on it, but The Sims 4 is one of those games that sits in a special type of DRM hell, in that even if you buy it on Steam, your first ten minutes with EA’s latest life sim are likely to be spent dusting off the Origin client so you can actually play it. It’ll leave you longing for the days of The Sims 2, back when you could just buy a disc, install the game, and play. When I could finally start the game, what was evident is that EA were going for the largest market possible here. My modest gaming rig plays most games from 2017 at their highest settings, but very few set themselves up that way after assessing my hardware. The Sims 4 automatically pushed all the sliders to the right - performance shouldn’t be an issue for many people here. That’s not to say that everything is an upgrade or works perfectly. I noticed plenty of features that functioned well in previous The Sims games, but are either absent or cause issues here. In Create-A-Sim, clothes can no longer be customised via a colour wheel, for example. More frustratingly, Sims frequently just ignore tasks assigned to them, which drop off their queues with no notification. This is especially frustrating when the task is critical, like giving a toddler some food before they are taken away.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Easy retro gaming with Retropie</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/20/pi-hut-retro-gaming-kit-retropie" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Easy retro gaming with Retropie" /><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/20/pi-hut-retro-gaming-kit-retropie</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/20/pi-hut-retro-gaming-kit-retropie">&lt;p&gt;Anyone who reads this blog will know that I like to play some emulated games from time to time - normally revisiting PlayStation 2 classics like &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;PES 5&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/10/gran-turismo-3-retrospective&quot;&gt;Gran Turismo 3&lt;/a&gt;. But retro gaming on a PC has its downsides. You need to install an emulator for each console, clog up your hard drive with ROMs, and tweak settings to make sure the graphics look good on a modern monitor. Surely there must be an easier way to play old favourites?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some friends recently gave me an amazing gift that provides the answer. The Raspberry Pi retro gaming kit, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepihut.com/products/raspberry-pi-retro-gaming-bundle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;available from The Pi Hut&lt;/a&gt;, consists of a Raspberry Pi 4, the required memory card and cables, and two SNES-style controllers. It’s more than capable of running the free &lt;a href=&quot;https://retropie.org.uk/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Retropie&lt;/a&gt; retro gaming distribution, which includes emulators for a large range of systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/retropie_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll write a full explanation of how to set up and configure Retropie at a later date, but it’s all deliciously simple stuff: plug in the cables, install Linux and Retropie, copy some games over to the preconfigured network share, and get going. It’s also ridiculously easy to get a PlayStation 4 or Xbox One controller working either via USB or (with a little more tweaking) wireless, so I can’t speak to the quality of the USB controllers that came in the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retropie can play games from a huge number of systems, including the PlayStation, PSP, Dreamcast, GameCube, Nintendo 64, several Game Boys, NES, SNES, and many more. Some of the more modern emulators don’t work due to the Raspberry Pi’s processor, unfortunately - but hey, you can’t have everything. I’ll just have to continue playing those games on my PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/retropie_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what the kit and Retropie give me is a neat little box that can sit under my TV and play a variety of digital retro games to break up my day. So far, that’s meant quite a bit of the 1995 game &lt;em&gt;Formula 1&lt;/em&gt; for the PS1, and - after quite a bit of fuss trying to get the Amiga emulator working - the absolute classic &lt;em&gt;Deluxe Galaga&lt;/em&gt;. It really all works rather well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll return to Retropie and how to set it up in future, including full details of the Amiga setup, but for now I just wanted to say how great this little kit is (and you could probably put it together even cheaper by buying the Pi outright). Until then, I’ve got some retro games to play…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="hardware" /><category term="retro" /><category term="racing" /><category term="motorsport" /><summary type="html">Anyone who reads this blog will know that I like to play some emulated games from time to time - normally revisiting PlayStation 2 classics like PES 5 and Gran Turismo 3. But retro gaming on a PC has its downsides. You need to install an emulator for each console, clog up your hard drive with ROMs, and tweak settings to make sure the graphics look good on a modern monitor. Surely there must be an easier way to play old favourites? Some friends recently gave me an amazing gift that provides the answer. The Raspberry Pi retro gaming kit, available from The Pi Hut, consists of a Raspberry Pi 4, the required memory card and cables, and two SNES-style controllers. It’s more than capable of running the free Retropie retro gaming distribution, which includes emulators for a large range of systems. I’ll write a full explanation of how to set up and configure Retropie at a later date, but it’s all deliciously simple stuff: plug in the cables, install Linux and Retropie, copy some games over to the preconfigured network share, and get going. It’s also ridiculously easy to get a PlayStation 4 or Xbox One controller working either via USB or (with a little more tweaking) wireless, so I can’t speak to the quality of the USB controllers that came in the box. Retropie can play games from a huge number of systems, including the PlayStation, PSP, Dreamcast, GameCube, Nintendo 64, several Game Boys, NES, SNES, and many more. Some of the more modern emulators don’t work due to the Raspberry Pi’s processor, unfortunately - but hey, you can’t have everything. I’ll just have to continue playing those games on my PC.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/11/retropie_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/11/retropie_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>