<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-05-06T18:21:45+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Resident Evil HD Remaster (PS4) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/06/resident-evil-hd-remaster-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Resident Evil HD Remaster (PS4) retrospective" /><published>2022-05-02T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/06/resident-evil-hd-remaster-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/06/resident-evil-hd-remaster-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;Everyone has a series or two that are widely regarded as the pinnacle of video games that they’ve never got around to playing. For me, &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; is one of them. The first game in the series, which now spans nine core titles and numerous spin-offs and remakes, was released on the PlayStation in 1996. I have a vague recollection of playing a snippet on an old demo disc, but other than that I’d somehow avoided playing it for 26 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even after I’d decided to pick up 2015’s &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil HD Remaster&lt;/em&gt; on PS4, I had my apprehensions. Certain games have a “you had to be there” quality to them - I bounced off the old &lt;em&gt;Pokemon&lt;/em&gt; games when I tried to play them in recent years, for example. Even with retouched graphics and controls, would the base game still stand up in 2022 for someone without the nostalgia Capcom were likely banking on with this release? It was time to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setting-the-scene&quot;&gt;Setting the scene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; dumps you straight into the thick of the action. You can choose to play as either Chris Redfield or Jill Valentine (I chose the latter, and later learnt they have unique perks), members of the elite S.T.A.R.S. team, who are investigating the disappearance of their sister squad amidst a growing spate of murders in Raccoon City. When they are attacked by a pack of demonic dogs they are chased to a mansion, where they seek refuge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game pleasingly coheres with the dramatic principle of unity of place, as you spend its entirety exploring the mansion, finding missing members of your team, and uncovering the dark secrets it holds regarding the T-Virus and the Umbrella Corporation. The set-up is simple and the twists are all flagged well in advance, but the execution is strong enough that it’s still gripping, and by the end of the game you’ll know the map like the back of your hand.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mansion is split into rooms, which function as cells much like the areas in earlier &lt;em&gt;Metal Gear Solid&lt;/em&gt; titles. The camera is static, changing between angles when the player character reaches the edge of the screen. This has the benefit of allowing for some beautifully detailed static backgrounds, but the revamped controls aren’t suited to it. When the camera changes, so does the direction you need to run, and you can end up spinning in circles if you don’t adjust quickly enough - frustrating at the best of times, but especially awful when you’re running from an enemy and it hinders your escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also something of a mixed bag when it comes to how the game &lt;em&gt;uses&lt;/em&gt; the camera. Sometimes it rewards close attention, showing a zombie around a 90-degree corner with a conveniently placed mirror to give you a heads up. Other times it’s not so kind, and a particularly annoying recurrence was areas that forced me to run directly into the camera, only for a zombie to be hidden right behind it ready to pounce before I had a chance to react.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-horror-themed-puzzle-box&quot;&gt;A horror-themed puzzle box&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; expecting survival horror, but quickly discovered that the bulk of the game was actually more puzzle-based. You spend your time exploring the mansion, memorising routes, and passing trials to win keys. You’ll be traversing the map time and again as you solve challenges and unlock new rooms, and discovering what’s behind a previously locked door is a treat - enemies are usually just an inconvenience along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The puzzles themselves are usually about deciding which objects go together in which order and knowing where to use them. They’re challenging enough to make you think, but follow a coherent enough course of logic that they’re not so difficult you’ll be stuck for ages wondering what to do. Some involve some basic memorisation or mental maths, and my notes for this article were interspersed with jotted-down codes, numbers, and colours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the puzzles and use of the map are cool, the inventory management system is not. You have limited slots and can only swap items out in storage boxes in safe rooms. This means you need to keep as much space open as possible for new items, and if you realise you need a previous item for a puzzle you’ll have to trudge back through the zombie-filled corridors for it. This makes trial and error expensive - especially with limited ammo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;facing-your-fears&quot;&gt;Facing your fears&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the puzzles are the stars, the enemies add the colour. Over the game’s 11-hour span you’ll encounter various types of zombies, dogs, snakes, plants, crows, bees, and more. They’re all quite intimidating, especially given the stakes the save system introduces, but entering a room to see a giant spider right above my head - seemingly rendered in more detail than anything else in the game - is certainly a moment that lingers in the memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The zombies themselves have fairly basic AI. They’ll move towards you at various speeds, then either grab or swipe at you, and mainly serve to keep you on your toes while you’re darting to and from puzzle points. They don’t generally move between rooms, but they do persist in rooms you leave them in, so you’ll be taking mental notes of which areas to stay well away from. On rare occasions a zombie will burst through a door or window into the room you’re in, and it happens so intermittently that it’s always a shock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shooting takes some getting used to. Your character has an auto lock-on, but sometimes they don’t face the way they’re aiming so lining your shot up can still be tricky. There’s some randomisation at play, meaning the same type of enemy can take different numbers of shots to kill, and zombies have such long death animations that it can be difficult to tell when they’re finished, making it easy to waste ammo in a game where it’s already sparse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll soon learn that it’s best to avoid fights with random zombies where possible. The bosses are memorable and intense enough to get the heart racing, ranging from an even bigger spider to gigantuan snakes. Jill’s health is relatively weak and even a regular enemy can normally kill you in a few hits, but the challenge tends to dissapate once you nail a run-and-gun technique - by modern standards, you’re mostly fighting the camera and controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ps1-era-quirks&quot;&gt;PS1-era quirks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed the additional details you can learn by interacting with items. These one-line notes can help to build suspense - for example, when a rope looks “recently cut” or firewood looks “fresh” and you &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; someone is close by - or can provide hints when examining puzzle-related objects. There are also a few diaries dotted around that tell some quite heartbreaking stories of the subjects and scientists contending with the T-Virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cool feature - especially for a game of this age - is the number of story branches and optional areas. I noticed after finishing &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; that my ending was assigned a number, and discovered online that as well as multiple endings there were also many scenes and items I hadn’t seen (I &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; there was a reason I kept finding shotgun shells…).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typewriters serve as the game’s save mechanism, and you as the player must find ink ribbon, which is consumed each time you save in a safe room. This adds a tactical element - you must plan not only for your next fight, but also the journey there - but it can make it costly to work out the slightly clunky controls early on when dying sets you back so far, and if you use too much ribbon too quickly then you can end up essentially being held hostage by the game, forced to play on until you find more or lose your progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only other gripe is that &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; can be quite fussy with the angle at which you approach items to interact with them. You must be very precise, or Jill just won’t pick objects up. In one particularly bad example this fussiness led me to believe I couldn’t collect the grenade launcher, and I fought a challenging boss fight without it before later realising my mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;holding-strong&quot;&gt;Holding strong&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve called out &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; for some of its residual jank through this article, but I don’t want to give the impression that I didn’t enjoy it. The story, the mechanics, and the general atmosphere together make it something special, and while the HD remaster has had quite a facelift, it’s amazing that the core of the game - still present in this version - holds up so well after 26 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern video games tend to hold your hand so much that gameplay becomes a case of a following a list of instructions on the HUD. &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; was a refreshing departure into a time in video game history where the player was provided with very little guidance. It requires you to keep mental notes and act on your hunches, and is more rewarding as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throw in the detail in the notes and diaries, and all the background mathematics that randomise various elements of the environment, and you’ve got a game that still stands its ground in 2022. Even if, like me, you never played the 1996 version or the GameCube upgrade, I’d urge you to give &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil HD Remaster&lt;/em&gt; a go. If you can look past a few rough edges in the camera and combat, it’s a great refinement of a classic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="resident-evil" /><category term="horror" /><category term="survival" /><summary type="html">Everyone has a series or two that are widely regarded as the pinnacle of video games that they’ve never got around to playing. For me, Resident Evil is one of them. The first game in the series, which now spans nine core titles and numerous spin-offs and remakes, was released on the PlayStation in 1996. I have a vague recollection of playing a snippet on an old demo disc, but other than that I’d somehow avoided playing it for 26 years. Even after I’d decided to pick up 2015’s Resident Evil HD Remaster on PS4, I had my apprehensions. Certain games have a “you had to be there” quality to them - I bounced off the old Pokemon games when I tried to play them in recent years, for example. Even with retouched graphics and controls, would the base game still stand up in 2022 for someone without the nostalgia Capcom were likely banking on with this release? It was time to find out. Setting the scene Resident Evil dumps you straight into the thick of the action. You can choose to play as either Chris Redfield or Jill Valentine (I chose the latter, and later learnt they have unique perks), members of the elite S.T.A.R.S. team, who are investigating the disappearance of their sister squad amidst a growing spate of murders in Raccoon City. When they are attacked by a pack of demonic dogs they are chased to a mansion, where they seek refuge. The game pleasingly coheres with the dramatic principle of unity of place, as you spend its entirety exploring the mansion, finding missing members of your team, and uncovering the dark secrets it holds regarding the T-Virus and the Umbrella Corporation. The set-up is simple and the twists are all flagged well in advance, but the execution is strong enough that it’s still gripping, and by the end of the game you’ll know the map like the back of your hand.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Buying MP3s is stupidly difficult</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/29/buying-mp3s-is-too-difficult" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buying MP3s is stupidly difficult" /><published>2022-04-23T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/29/buying-mp3s-is-too-difficult</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/29/buying-mp3s-is-too-difficult">&lt;p&gt;Many video game fans mourn what has happened to their hobby in recent years. With the announcement of each new game, from even the most acclaimed studios, a question lingers - have the developers followed the trend and stuffed it full of microtransactions? And all too often the answer is yes. How could it possibly get any worse, gamers ask? Well friends, I tried buying some music last week and I’ve seen how bad things could become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think it’s unreasonable to want to buy some MP3s. Yes, nearly every song in existence is available for free on Spotify, but what would I do if that service ever ceased to exist, or got locked behind a paywall? It makes sense to keep a trickle of your favourite songs coming in to your offline library so you can own the music, keep it, and listen to it on the Tube without paying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having relied too much on Spotify for years, I wasn’t up to speed with MP3 pricing and was expecting to get ripped off, but I was pleasantly surprised to find that most songs are a reasonable 99p, with a few slightly below that. That’s not too bad when you consider that as far back as the early 2000s you’d buy a CD album for £10 with an average of ten songs or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;amazon-music&quot;&gt;Amazon Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first stop was Amazon, because that was where I bought my digital music in the early 2010s, but I was shocked to find just how badly the customer experience had deteriorated since my last visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your first steps are to open the homepage, search for a song, and click it - so far, so good. But instead of treating songs like normal items for purchase, Amazon now redirects you to an Amazon Music page that &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; wants you to stream them instead. To buy a track, you have to find a what is basically a hidden menu item under Purchase Options &amp;gt; MP3 Music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/buying-mp3-downloads_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This takes you to another page plastered with Amazon Music stream buttons, but at least this time there are prices next to each song that you can use to purchase them. If you click one of these, you’ll be taken to a page that &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; like the Amazon basket, but it’s not. If you don’t click Buy there and then, it’s gone. That’s right - if you want to buy MP3s on Amazon in 2022, you have to purchase each song or album &lt;em&gt;individually&lt;/em&gt;. So if you have a list of 40 tracks to buy like I did, you’d have to go through the whole process separately for each one. I didn’t have time for that, so I moved on.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;itunes-store&quot;&gt;iTunes Store&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I Googled for alternatives, but there are basically no modern MP3 stores, so I went to the only other one I knew - the iTunes Store. For a company known for its slick user interfaces, Apple has really let itself down here. iTunes as a whole feels like a relic from the mid-2000s, and the store is weirdly unreliable for what is basically pages loading in a browser. I even had to restart the application a couple of times when it wouldn’t load anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/buying-mp3-downloads_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it does work, there is once again no basket. Ever the optimist, I decided to try adding the songs I wanted to my account’s wish list in the hope that I could review and purchase them all together later. But lo and behold, there’s no option to buy the whole list at once! If &lt;a href=&quot;https://discussions.apple.com/thread/5886224&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the Apple forums&lt;/a&gt; are to be believed, this &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; a feature but was removed because some users complained they were accidentally clicking the Buy All button. Sigh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With no other options, I persevered. At least all the individual buy buttons were lined up nicely with all the songs in my wish list. But buying the tracks only revealed &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; problems. You see, there’s no grouping when you buy songs from the iTunes Store - every track you buy triggers a separate transaction on your payment card and a separate confirmation email. Resigned to spamming myself, I got about halfway through my 40-song list before my bank started blocking the transactions and I had to switch cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/buying-mp3-downloads_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d think that the wealthiest company in the world would notice if its purchasing system was so convoluted that users were blocked from buying its products because the payments looked fraudulent, but apparently not. However, to give Apple credit where it’s due, downloading the songs to my iPhone was really smooth afterwards - much more so than it would have been if I’d bought the songs from Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;get-it-before-its-gone&quot;&gt;Get it before it’s gone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s sad that there’s no good option to buy and own digital music anymore, and that the stores that remain are so neglected by some of the biggest companies in the world. Amazon and Apple are clearly set on chasing Spotify and earning their money through subscriptions, but that model doesn’t suit everyone, and even if that is their strategy, is it really necessary to be so anti-consumer as to remove features that made it easier for customers to buy things and &lt;em&gt;give you more of their money&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s only a matter of time until these storefronts become so delapidated that they close down completely, so if you have any desire to build a digital music library then I’d suggest you move quickly to download your favourites before they’re gone. Past that? I don’t think it’s unreasonable to predict a rise in CD sales in the near future - buying a physical disk and ripping it could soon be your only option if you want to legally own MP3 music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let’s hope this isn’t the future of gaming. At the moment the digital options are there, but in you can still buy a boxed copy of your favourites and keep them on a shelf so you can still play them in years to come (&lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review&quot;&gt;in most cases, anyway&lt;/a&gt;). Having seen what’s happened in the music industry, it’s all too easy to imagine a future where subscription services rule and the possibility of true ownership is ripped away from us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html">Many video game fans mourn what has happened to their hobby in recent years. With the announcement of each new game, from even the most acclaimed studios, a question lingers - have the developers followed the trend and stuffed it full of microtransactions? And all too often the answer is yes. How could it possibly get any worse, gamers ask? Well friends, I tried buying some music last week and I’ve seen how bad things could become. I don’t think it’s unreasonable to want to buy some MP3s. Yes, nearly every song in existence is available for free on Spotify, but what would I do if that service ever ceased to exist, or got locked behind a paywall? It makes sense to keep a trickle of your favourite songs coming in to your offline library so you can own the music, keep it, and listen to it on the Tube without paying. Having relied too much on Spotify for years, I wasn’t up to speed with MP3 pricing and was expecting to get ripped off, but I was pleasantly surprised to find that most songs are a reasonable 99p, with a few slightly below that. That’s not too bad when you consider that as far back as the early 2000s you’d buy a CD album for £10 with an average of ten songs or so. Amazon Music My first stop was Amazon, because that was where I bought my digital music in the early 2010s, but I was shocked to find just how badly the customer experience had deteriorated since my last visit. Your first steps are to open the homepage, search for a song, and click it - so far, so good. But instead of treating songs like normal items for purchase, Amazon now redirects you to an Amazon Music page that really wants you to stream them instead. To buy a track, you have to find a what is basically a hidden menu item under Purchase Options &amp;gt; MP3 Music. This takes you to another page plastered with Amazon Music stream buttons, but at least this time there are prices next to each song that you can use to purchase them. If you click one of these, you’ll be taken to a page that looks like the Amazon basket, but it’s not. If you don’t click Buy there and then, it’s gone. That’s right - if you want to buy MP3s on Amazon in 2022, you have to purchase each song or album individually. So if you have a list of 40 tracks to buy like I did, you’d have to go through the whole process separately for each one. I didn’t have time for that, so I moved on.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/buying-mp3-downloads_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/buying-mp3-downloads_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">F1 22’s announcement video was a colossal waste of time</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/22/f1-22-announcement-colossal-waste-of-time" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="F1 22's announcement video was a colossal waste of time" /><published>2022-04-22T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-22T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/22/f1-2022-announcement-colossal-waste-of-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/22/f1-22-announcement-colossal-waste-of-time">&lt;p&gt;Racing game fans across Reddit and Twitter were excited this week after EA revealed that not only did they have the Imola Grand Prix to look forward to this weekend, but on Thursday they would also get a glimpse of the latest game in the Codemasters F1 series: the hotly anticipated &lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/f1-22-announcement_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the reveal turned out to be peak 2022 gaming and social media. After a day of countdowns, the official YouTube channel premiered &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K5RLRoRWUds&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;an announcement video&lt;/a&gt; that was just 30 seconds long, showed no gameplay, and contained only the following bland marketing phrases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• The future is here&lt;br /&gt;
• Next generation machines&lt;br /&gt;
• Racing redefined&lt;br /&gt;
• Rivalries renewed&lt;br /&gt;
• Enter the new era&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got a release date for the new game - 1st July 2022 - but the whole exercise was largely pointless. A tweet would have more than sufficed. The reaction was a mixture of disappointment, bemusement, and apprehension about what the lack of substance meant for the finished product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;beyond-the-video&quot;&gt;Beyond the video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the video was bereft of detail, we did get a little more information - and a few pretty screenshots - on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ea.com/en-gb/games/f1/f1-22&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the newly launched &lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;, so I thought I’d dive in and try to decipher what I could from the sales copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;New season, new rules: Take your seat for a new season as redesigned cars and overhauled rules redefine race day with the authentic 2022 lineup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means basically nothing. The latest iteration in an annual sports game series will include the latest cars and driver lineup? Colour me surprised.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Race day, redefined: Take control of your virtual F1® experience with immersive and broadcast options for Pit Stops, Formation Laps, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from one unnecessary comma and many unnecessary capital letters, what does this say? “Immersive” is the most abused word in gaming, but juxtaposed against “broadcast” maybe it means they’ve added TV-style cameras for formation laps and pit stops alongside the usual in-car angles? I wonder if the new pit stop format might take its cues from &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/01/gran-turismo-7-guide-race-strategy-pit-stops&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;digging-into-the-detail&quot;&gt;Digging into the detail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait - there’s more! Hidden near the bottom of the website there’s a link to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ea.com/en-gb/games/f1/f1-22/news/f1-22-announce&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;an announcement page&lt;/a&gt;, which again provides just the &lt;em&gt;tiniest&lt;/em&gt; drop more detail. There’s slightly more text here, so I’ll just pull out the highlights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Take your seat for the new era of F1® with the sport’s stunning new cars and a new handling model that recreates the intense wheel-to-wheel racing that’s had us on the edge of our seats so far in the 2022 Formula 1® season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handling in the previous games was passable but not amazing, so a new model is welcome as long as it’s a solid improvement. That said, I’ll believe it when I see it because EA also says various parts of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are being overhauled every year and many of them stay largely the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/f1-22-announcement_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Plus, test your talent amongst the iconic Florida palm trees around the 19 challenging corners of the vibrant new Miami International Autodrome, and go flat out as F1® Sprint comes to the game for the first time in F1® 22.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ll also get the newest circuit on the calendar, which isn’t surprising. As for the sprint races… They’re an addition that few fans want in real F1, but I suppose that’s not up to EA and Codemasters to decide. They could be entertaining in video game form, although I do wonder how they’ll work for players who drive even the full races on shorter settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;F1® 22 also includes VR compatibility on PC via Oculus Rift and HTC Vive to give you the ultimate immersive F1® experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be the big one for a lot of people, and I have no idea why they didn’t mention it in the announcement video. Fans have been waiting for &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt; to be able to play &lt;em&gt;F1&lt;/em&gt; in virtual reality, so Oculus Rift and HTC Vive support will have those with the right equipment very excited indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Get a taste of the glitz and glamor of Formula 1® in F1® Life, a new space for you to unlock and show off supercars, clothing, accessories, and more for the world to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know what F1 Life is exactly, but this description certainly makes it sound like it’s going to be completely irrelevant to the core gameplay. Those “supercars, clothing, accessories, and more” sound like the perfect opportunity to slip in more microtransactions, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My Team and Career Mode return in F1® 22 with fresh new features, along with two-player split screen, F2™, online multiplayer and all the features you know and love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose this is good to know, but there’s nothing new or unexpected here - someone was obviously trying to hit their word count. If any of this stuff was missing then there’d be a backlash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EA has promised more detail “in the coming weeks”, but that’s it for now. Given the feature list above, it seems the game is veering slightly further in the casual direction with F1 Life. For those who play the games for the actual racing, there’ll be a lot riding on that new handling model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="formula-1" /><category term="racing" /><summary type="html">Racing game fans across Reddit and Twitter were excited this week after EA revealed that not only did they have the Imola Grand Prix to look forward to this weekend, but on Thursday they would also get a glimpse of the latest game in the Codemasters F1 series: the hotly anticipated F1 22. Unfortunately, the reveal turned out to be peak 2022 gaming and social media. After a day of countdowns, the official YouTube channel premiered an announcement video that was just 30 seconds long, showed no gameplay, and contained only the following bland marketing phrases: • The future is here • Next generation machines • Racing redefined • Rivalries renewed • Enter the new era We got a release date for the new game - 1st July 2022 - but the whole exercise was largely pointless. A tweet would have more than sufficed. The reaction was a mixture of disappointment, bemusement, and apprehension about what the lack of substance meant for the finished product. Beyond the video While the video was bereft of detail, we did get a little more information - and a few pretty screenshots - on the newly launched F1 22 website, so I thought I’d dive in and try to decipher what I could from the sales copy. New season, new rules: Take your seat for a new season as redesigned cars and overhauled rules redefine race day with the authentic 2022 lineup. This means basically nothing. The latest iteration in an annual sports game series will include the latest cars and driver lineup? Colour me surprised.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/f1-22-announcement_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/f1-22-announcement_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA 22 Career Mode&amp;#58; TSP United &amp;#8211; escaping the lower leagues" /><published>2022-04-15T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-15T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1">&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t bought a &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; game in years, but I couldn’t resist picking up &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt; when I learnt that EA has finally given us the tools to emulate &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;the classic Master League experience&lt;/a&gt;, creating a brand new club and taking them from football’s bottom rung to continental glory. I’ve always enjoyed reading about people’s Career Mode journeys, so I thought I’d share how it’s going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-setup&quot;&gt;The setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually burn out on &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; Career Mode quite quickly. When you start a game with a big team like Chelsea, a few tactical additions to your squad are all you need to win it all, and from there it’s just a matter of bringing through young players to sustain the success and build your legacy. So this time around, I was determined to do something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I created my own club, TSP United - complete with a snazzy purple kit - and dumped them in League Two. When you create a club in Career Mode you begin with a randomly generated squad of unskilled players with which to ascend the ladder, and to make things even more challenging I decided that I would not spend a penny in transfer fees. Instead, my focus would be on bringing through youth players, with the odd free signing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202122---league-two&quot;&gt;2021/22 - League Two&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took some time to settle in before my first season gained momentum. I had a shaky start as I learnt the game and worried that I’d made things too difficult for myself, but eventually I found some rhythm and form, and by the end of the season TSP United won the league with a couple of games to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other highlights included an extended League Cup run that saw us reach the quarter finals, earning scrappy wins against Premier League heavyweights Wolves and Newcastle before taking a battering against Manchester United.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/fifa-22-career-mode_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This season was also all about learning my squad. &lt;strong&gt;Prince&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Johnson&lt;/strong&gt; established themselves as the first-choice strike partnership, with the former earning the League Two golden boot by the end of the year. I also started to put the feelers out for youth talent, with &lt;strong&gt;Greenwood&lt;/strong&gt;, a young left-back, making the most first-team appearances. The foundations were laid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best original player&lt;/strong&gt; - Prince, the goal machine&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - N/A (no signings made)&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Greenwood, our cup left-back&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202223---league-one&quot;&gt;2022/23 - League One&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the start of the second season, my best players were &lt;em&gt;just about&lt;/em&gt; pushing the 70 Overall mark. I also made efforts to bolster the squad by signing free agents &lt;strong&gt;Acuna&lt;/strong&gt; (RB) and &lt;strong&gt;Pierre&lt;/strong&gt; (RW). The latter would prove invaluable, with more than 10 goals and 15 assists coming in from the right wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After another slow start, we went on an immense run of mid-season form and won the league with six games left to play, with &lt;strong&gt;Prince&lt;/strong&gt; rising to the challenge and continuing his scoring habit. Injuries to regulars &lt;strong&gt;Thornton&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Prior&lt;/strong&gt; meant that newly promoted youth prospects &lt;strong&gt;Green&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Groves&lt;/strong&gt; could enjoy extended runs in the first team to boost their development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/fifa-22-career-mode_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside all of this, TSP United also managed to win the Papa John’s Trophy in the most dramatic fashion possible. The highlight of the campaign was a thrilling 7-6 semi-final victory over Mansfield Town, before we went to Wembley to take on Port Vale. The final was best described as a demolition, with young &lt;strong&gt;Groves&lt;/strong&gt; playing to the occasion and scoring a hat trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best original player&lt;/strong&gt; - Prince, topping the league scorers chart again&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - Pierre, both scorer and creator&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Groves, the centre midfield maestro&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;looking-forward&quot;&gt;Looking forward&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve reached the point where I’m comfortable with the game and comfortable with my squad, who seem much more capable and cohesive than they were two seasons ago. But at the same time I know there will be a point (maybe next season in the Championship?) where the opposition becomes too strong for my squad’s technical ability and things get a lot tougher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re on the right track, and hopefully we’ll be hitting the Premier League before too long. Until then, it’s a race against time for my young players - I hope they’ll be able to develop quickly enough to handle the big stage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">I hadn’t bought a FIFA game in years, but I couldn’t resist picking up FIFA 22 when I learnt that EA has finally given us the tools to emulate the classic Master League experience, creating a brand new club and taking them from football’s bottom rung to continental glory. I’ve always enjoyed reading about people’s Career Mode journeys, so I thought I’d share how it’s going. The setup I usually burn out on FIFA Career Mode quite quickly. When you start a game with a big team like Chelsea, a few tactical additions to your squad are all you need to win it all, and from there it’s just a matter of bringing through young players to sustain the success and build your legacy. So this time around, I was determined to do something different. This time I created my own club, TSP United - complete with a snazzy purple kit - and dumped them in League Two. When you create a club in Career Mode you begin with a randomly generated squad of unskilled players with which to ascend the ladder, and to make things even more challenging I decided that I would not spend a penny in transfer fees. Instead, my focus would be on bringing through youth players, with the odd free signing. 2021/22 - League Two It took some time to settle in before my first season gained momentum. I had a shaky start as I learnt the game and worried that I’d made things too difficult for myself, but eventually I found some rhythm and form, and by the end of the season TSP United won the league with a couple of games to go. Other highlights included an extended League Cup run that saw us reach the quarter finals, earning scrappy wins against Premier League heavyweights Wolves and Newcastle before taking a battering against Manchester United.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Formula 1: Why now’s the time to choose a backup series</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/08/formula-1-time-to-choose-backup-series" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Formula 1&amp;#58; Why now's the time to choose a backup series" /><published>2022-04-08T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-08T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/08/formula-1-time-to-choose-backup-series</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/08/formula-1-time-to-choose-backup-series">&lt;p&gt;The last decade or so has been a bad time to be a fan of many things. Your favourite film has had an unimaginative reboot because Hollywood had no new ideas, the latest entry in your favourite video game series is &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review&quot;&gt;a live service bursting with microtransactions&lt;/a&gt;, and if you’re particularly unlucky your football club is now being run for profit rather than silverware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even governing bodies haven’t been immune to the madness of chasing money at any cost. The last World Cup was held in Putin’s Russia and the next will be hosted by Qatar amidst &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/football/59253789&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;all sorts of human rights issues&lt;/a&gt;. And while UEFA are no saints in this regard (the 2019 Europa League final in Baku being just one example), fans were forced to take action against the Super League in an attempt to hold on to the lesser of two evils and maintain at least &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; level of fairness and sporting integrity in European club football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/formula-1-cc_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-brief-history&quot;&gt;A brief history&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at least we could still rely on Formula 1. While the sport’s previous ownership wasn’t exactly immune to the lures of a big cheque - they were the ones who signed up for races in places like Abu Dhabi and Bahrain, after all - Bernie Ecclestone and his team understood the sport’s history and tradition and its most loyal fans. In fact, you could argue that this was to a fault, as Formula 1 was slow to embrace new trends like social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberty Media’s 2016 takeover was met with some skepticism over whether the new American owners would embrace the spirit of Formula 1, but in the years that followed, most of the changes were positive. We got the halo to better protect drivers, plus an upgraded presentation package with better graphics, a heightened social media presence, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JBFPP_BG-qo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;an adrenaline-triggering intro and theme tune&lt;/a&gt; to add a bit of fanfare to race weekends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most questionable addition at this point was Netflix’s &lt;em&gt;Drive to Survive&lt;/em&gt; series, which promised a behind-the-scenes view of the sport but confused dedicated fans with dishonest editing, artificial drama, and a disorientating structure. Still, it helped to bring Formula 1 further into the mainstream, and additional followers could only be a good thing, right?&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-slippery-slope&quot;&gt;A slippery slope&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But large organisations never know where to stop, and since the COVID pandemic things have been pushed even further. The heart of Liberty’s strategy seems to be to secure as much money as possible, even if that means alliances with states with questionable human rights records. Saudi Arabia and Qatar have secured long deals when many believe they shouldn’t even have been considered as destinations for the pinnacle of motorsport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia has complications even beyond this. Despite the nation having a bottomless pit of money to spend on facilities, we somehow ended up with another bland (and barely finished) street circuit with blind corners and walls close on each side - the perils of which have been seen through many incidents, not least &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8yLNmb2-yrQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mick Schumacher’s massive qualifying crash this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberty are also keen to capitalise on the growing American fan base that &lt;em&gt;Drive to Survive&lt;/em&gt; has helped to cultivate. In 2022 we will see a Grand Prix in Miami, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/formula1/60932994&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Las Vegas recently joined the 2023 calendar&lt;/a&gt;. While it’s certainly a better curcuit than its 1980s counterpart in the Caesars Palace car park, it’s yet another street circuit - a bland rectangle when there are so many purpose-built race tracks in the world - even in America - going unused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this might be tolerable if there were any assurances that Formula 1’s heritage - and in particular Silverstone, Monaco, Spa-Francorchamps, Monza, Suzuka, and Interlagos - would be protected. But new CEO Stefano Domenicali has suggested that even the Belgian Grand Prix, which arguably takes place at the best circuit on the calendar, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.autosport.com/f1/news/f1-ready-to-drop-current-races-to-make-way-for-new-grands-prix/9134981/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;could be one of the first to face the axe&lt;/a&gt; to make room for all these new races on a crowded calendar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;contingency-plans&quot;&gt;Contingency plans&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not quite enough for me to abandon Formula 1 after so many decades - &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt; - but the warning signs are there. While the sport inevitably needed to be brought into the 21st century, everything points to Liberty Media trying to squeeze out every cent it can, no matter what the cost in terms of tradition and the enjoyment of long-standing fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what can we do? It doesn’t seem that Formula 1 itself is all that keen to listen to fans - Spa ranked as fans’ second-favourite circuit in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.formula1.com/en/latest/article.new-global-fan-survey-reveals-f1s-most-popular-team-and-driver.2evqTWEPsWYeBlw9vmSyBs.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;last year’s fan survey&lt;/a&gt; and yet it’s rumoured to be at risk of being discarded entirely. So the only option looks to be to hedge your bets and pick up some backup series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could be the feeder formulas - while F2 and F3 tour with F1, &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-4&quot;&gt;Formula 4&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-ford&quot;&gt;Formula Ford&lt;/a&gt; are more grassroots and visit smaller regional circuits. Outside of open-wheel racing there are endurance series like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gt-world-challenge.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GT World Challenge&lt;/a&gt; and famous races like the Le Mans 24h and Bathurst 12h. And if you still fancy some action at even higher speeds, there’s always &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indycar.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IndyCar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you’ll need to hunt down TV coverage, but often these series are streamed for free online. It’ll also take some time to get used to the teams, drivers, and stories - but didn’t we all have to do that with Formula 1 at some point? My point is that it’s better to build up the knowledge now than to be completely lost later on, because at the moment it seems like it’s only a matter of time before Formula 1 becomes unrecognisable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/105731165@N07/26747780448&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Artes Max&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 2.0&lt;/a&gt;). Cropped.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="formula-1" /><category term="formula-4" /><category term="formula-ford" /><category term="motorsport" /><summary type="html">The last decade or so has been a bad time to be a fan of many things. Your favourite film has had an unimaginative reboot because Hollywood had no new ideas, the latest entry in your favourite video game series is a live service bursting with microtransactions, and if you’re particularly unlucky your football club is now being run for profit rather than silverware. Even governing bodies haven’t been immune to the madness of chasing money at any cost. The last World Cup was held in Putin’s Russia and the next will be hosted by Qatar amidst all sorts of human rights issues. And while UEFA are no saints in this regard (the 2019 Europa League final in Baku being just one example), fans were forced to take action against the Super League in an attempt to hold on to the lesser of two evils and maintain at least some level of fairness and sporting integrity in European club football. A brief history But at least we could still rely on Formula 1. While the sport’s previous ownership wasn’t exactly immune to the lures of a big cheque - they were the ones who signed up for races in places like Abu Dhabi and Bahrain, after all - Bernie Ecclestone and his team understood the sport’s history and tradition and its most loyal fans. In fact, you could argue that this was to a fault, as Formula 1 was slow to embrace new trends like social media. Liberty Media’s 2016 takeover was met with some skepticism over whether the new American owners would embrace the spirit of Formula 1, but in the years that followed, most of the changes were positive. We got the halo to better protect drivers, plus an upgraded presentation package with better graphics, a heightened social media presence, and an adrenaline-triggering intro and theme tune to add a bit of fanfare to race weekends. The most questionable addition at this point was Netflix’s Drive to Survive series, which promised a behind-the-scenes view of the sport but confused dedicated fans with dishonest editing, artificial drama, and a disorientating structure. Still, it helped to bring Formula 1 further into the mainstream, and additional followers could only be a good thing, right?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/formula-1-cc_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/formula-1-cc_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Gran Turismo 7: A guide to race strategy and pit stops</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/01/gran-turismo-7-guide-race-strategy-pit-stops" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gran Turismo 7&amp;#58; A guide to race strategy and pit stops" /><published>2022-04-01T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-01T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/01/gran-turismo-7-guide-race-strategy-pit-stops</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/01/gran-turismo-7-guide-race-strategy-pit-stops">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tag/gran-turismo&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s strategy system is both a blessing and a curse. With everything handled during the race, you never reach the halfway mark and realise you forgot to configure it, but on the other hand it becomes difficult to plan ahead and you’re forced to make a lot of snap decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/gran-turismo-7-strategy-pit-stops_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many more subtle or advanced features, it’s also not terribly well explained by the game. Since managing your tyres and fuel becomes critically important once you get to the longer races towards the end of &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;, I thought I’d put together an article about what I’ve learnt through a combination of both general racing knowledge and trial and error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;before-the-race&quot;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your first step to strategic success is to check what tyre degradation and fuel consumption multipiers apply. &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; simulates endurance races by having both progress more quickly in some events, so before making any estimates about how long you can go on particular compounds or a full tank of fuel, make sure you know what you’re dealing with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slightly oddly for a game that otherwise provides a decent range of strategy options, you must start with a full fuel tank. What you can choose, however, is your starting tyre compound. You need to have purchased each compound at GT Auto before it becomes available, and some races will bar you from entering if you don’t have a particular type of tyre (e.g. racing or sport).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/gran-turismo-7-strategy-pit-stops_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, softer tyres are faster - but that doesn’t apply in the long run if they’re threadbare before your first pit stop. I tend to err on the side of caution with hard tyres to start the race. This opens up more strategy options later on once we’ve seen how they fare (which we’ll cover later).&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll also want to have a rough plan in mind for the race. You’ll probably have an idea of the number of laps you can run for based on the lap count and degradation multipliers. While &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; does a great job of scaling almost everything to simulate endurance races, one thing it can’t change is lap and stop times. This means that because the majority of races are fairly short, fewer pit stops (ideally one) are normally better - it’s very difficult to make up the time difference a second stop makes in so few laps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;early-in-the-race&quot;&gt;Early in the race&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of the race, even before the lights go green, use the D-pad to dial back to one of the leanest fuel mixes. Watch the Laps Remaining counter during the first couple of laps and make sure it comfortably covers half of the race distance (assuming you’re aiming for one stop).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of race laps probably won’t exactly match your car’s fuel consumption, so you might find yourself with a little extra to burn in the lap or two before your stop, in which case you can nudge the fuel mix up a notch. If instead you’re running light, either switch to a leaner mix or lift and coast into some of the corners. The time lost from either of these options is normally less than the delay if you needed to add a second pit stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/gran-turismo-7-strategy-pit-stops_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep your driving as smooth as possible to avoid excessive tyre wear - if you hear screeching, you’re going too hard on them. Your target is to make it to the 50 per cent mark with nearly exactly zero fuel and half of your tyres or more remaining. As your stop nears, check your tyres. If the wear is less than 20 per cent, they’ll probably go to the end, unless you’d prefer to be extra safe and exchange a few more seconds in the pit box for a new set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more extremely important word of advice: In the laps preceding your stop, pay special attention to the pit entry as you pass it. You don’t want to be worrying about which side of the track it’s on and whereabouts it is on your in lap. Your worst nightmare is failing to prepare, missing it entirely, and running out of fuel (and yes, I’m speaking from experience).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;making-your-pit-stop&quot;&gt;Making your pit stop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the time comes, carefully enter the pitlane, conscious that missing it could screw your whole race up. If it’s a straight entry you can go as fast as you like - there are no pitlane speeding penalties. But be extremely cautious if there is a chicane on the entry, as catching a wall could cost you dear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/gran-turismo-7-strategy-pit-stops_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first menu that appears lets you choose the new set of tyres your crew will fit. If your tyre wear was low, you can select Don’t Change and carry on. Otherwise, you might consider a change to harder tyres if you were sliding around the corners and hanging on at the end of your first stint, or softer tyres if you think the extra grip will make the longer stop worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second menu handles refuelling and is slightly more confusingly labelled. The entire bar represents your car’s fuel tank capacity and the filled in portion is your current remaining fuel. “Cruising Range” is the number of laps your remaining fuel will last at your current consumption rate, and the diamond above the bar shows how much you’ll need to finish the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/gran-turismo-7-strategy-pit-stops_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you’re planning on changing your fuel mix during the second stint (a viable option if you were cautious at the start and have enough leeway), the trick here is to sit and wait until the filled portion of the bar extends beyond the diamond, then hit the Don’t Refuel button. Of course, if you don’t need any more fuel at all (a rare occurrence), you can hit it right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;weather-and-tyre-choice&quot;&gt;Weather and tyre choice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exception to the guidance above is when the weather conditions change during the race. If it starts or stops raining, the track will get progressively wetter or drier, and you’ll need to monitor grip levels to judge when to change tyre compounds. It can be useful to keep an eye on the AI’s choices as a barometer of the conditions, but bear in mind that they tend to go from dries, to inters, to wets (or the reverse), and in relatively short races it may be quicker to switch straight between dry and wet tyres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it starts raining, switch to the weather radar on the HUD. If it’s anything more than the briefest shower then it’s probably sensible to pit for wets. Again, the time scaling means that it doesn’t take very long at all for the track to get wet enough to lose a lot of time every lap on dries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/gran-turismo-7-strategy-pit-stops_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it stops raining, it’s a more difficult judgement call. Again, check the weather radar to make sure there isn’t any more rain on the way, and then it’s all about deciding when enough of a dry line has emerged to pit for dry tyres. Do this too early and you’ll lose tons of time in the next couple of laps as you slide around. To make slicks work on a drying track, take extra care to stick to the dry line - otherwise you’ll be skating into the barriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As changes to the conditions force you to switch tyres, you’ll need to adjust your fuel mix choices to match. If you were conserving fuel but it starts or stops raining, consider going all out on Mix 1 on your in lap - you’ll be able to refuel when you stop for your new tyres. The other factor to consider is that driving in the rain generally involves earlier braking, more coasting, and more gradual application of power, so your fuel is likely to last longer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="gran-turismo" /><category term="racing" /><summary type="html">Gran Turismo 7’s strategy system is both a blessing and a curse. With everything handled during the race, you never reach the halfway mark and realise you forgot to configure it, but on the other hand it becomes difficult to plan ahead and you’re forced to make a lot of snap decisions. Like many more subtle or advanced features, it’s also not terribly well explained by the game. Since managing your tyres and fuel becomes critically important once you get to the longer races towards the end of Gran Turismo 7, I thought I’d put together an article about what I’ve learnt through a combination of both general racing knowledge and trial and error. Before the race Your first step to strategic success is to check what tyre degradation and fuel consumption multipiers apply. Gran Turismo 7 simulates endurance races by having both progress more quickly in some events, so before making any estimates about how long you can go on particular compounds or a full tank of fuel, make sure you know what you’re dealing with. Slightly oddly for a game that otherwise provides a decent range of strategy options, you must start with a full fuel tank. What you can choose, however, is your starting tyre compound. You need to have purchased each compound at GT Auto before it becomes available, and some races will bar you from entering if you don’t have a particular type of tyre (e.g. racing or sport). As usual, softer tyres are faster - but that doesn’t apply in the long run if they’re threadbare before your first pit stop. I tend to err on the side of caution with hard tyres to start the race. This opens up more strategy options later on once we’ve seen how they fare (which we’ll cover later).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/gran-turismo-7-strategy-pit-stops_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/gran-turismo-7-strategy-pit-stops_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Gran Turismo 7 (PS4) review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gran Turismo 7 (PS4) review" /><published>2022-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review">&lt;p&gt;Writing a review for &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; having observed what has happened to it in the three weeks since its release is a hugely difficult task. The truth is that there is a fantastic racing game here – possibly the best ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in writing a review it is impossible to ignore that the game’s experience is soured by implementations of some of the dirtiest tactics the video game industry has been perfecting in recent years in order to extract every penny possible from players. So you’ve been warned – I’m going to be saying a lot of nice things about the racing, but make sure you read until the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: On the day this review was due to be published,&lt;/em&gt; Gran Turismo &lt;em&gt;creator Kazunori Yamauchi published &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.playstation.com/2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-an-update-from-polyphony-digital/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a blog post&lt;/a&gt; announcing several upcoming updates that address many of the negative points in this article (although notably not the always online problem). So although everything here is true at the time of publication, there is hope on the horizon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;driving-fast-shiny-cars&quot;&gt;Driving fast, shiny cars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s start where &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; deliver: out on the tarmac. Even on the PlayStation 4, the game is gorgeous. I wrote in &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/11/gran-turismo-7-ps4&quot;&gt;my first impressions article&lt;/a&gt; about how the beauty of the vehicles often led to a conflict between my sim racer instinct to use the first-person view and a desire to use the chase camera to see more of the cars. The circuits look great too, even if things are a little sparse trackside in some areas, with HD revamps of some of the beloved fictional &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; tracks a particular treat to race on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sound design is just as good. You’d expect a big-budget racing game to have great-sounding engines, but &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; really goes above and beyond when it comes to the small touches it would be easy to overlook. Polyphony Digital has thought of everything, from the clunk as you run over a kerb to the rumble as you race across road markings on street circuits. Rain and spray pattering on your windscreen sounds just right, and even the post-race reward screen is set to the metallic clicking of a car cooling down.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of the rain, the weather system really deserves all the attention it has received. Wet racing is a joy, feeling slightly less grippy without turning tracks into ice rinks, as in some other games. Transitions are natural, moving from bright sunshine to torrential rain with no sudden, jarring changes, and when things go in the other direction there is an immense satisfaction to keeping your car on the drying racing line with the jeopardy of puddles all around you, knowing even a small mistake could cost a lot of time. Even little details, like water sitting for longer under bridges, have been accounted for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would describe the handling itself as weighty. &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; lacks the sense of speed of some racers, but this is more of a technical game - every corner must be carefully considered in terms of speed and angle. Control is the name of the game, and the best moments occur when you’re right on the edge, just keeping it together enough to execute a clean pass on the outside of a turn. Coming in straight from &lt;em&gt;F1 2021&lt;/em&gt;, it took me a few races to work out what exactly the game wanted from me in terms of braking and turn-in, but when you get into a rhythm, getting it right feels amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HUD provides some fairly detailed options for a simcade racing game in switchable tabs in the bottom right-hand corner. Some of the most useful are settings for traction control and your fuel mix, as well as a zoomable weather radar that shows any rain due to pass over the circuit. The latter two are invaluable in the late game once you’re running longer races and need to start thinking about strategies, stints, and pit stops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AI you race against keeps things interesting, too. Your opponents will make natural-looking mistakes, diving too deep into a turn under pressure or getting out of shape at the rear on the exit. Occasionally they’ll even land in the gravel and bring out the yellow flags. In longer races they also make (mostly) sensible and varied strategy decisions, keeping you on your toes as you make real-time calculations about fuel loads and tyre compounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were to call out one thing missing from &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;’s gameplay (and people do), it would be the lack of a damage model. Cars can get scratched, but as in previous entries, you won’t be denting the bumper or smashing windows here. This seems to be a deal breaker for some, but for me &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; has always been about sporting competition. When you race with that philosophy, collisions should be minimal, and many serious racers compete with damage turned off in other games anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hanging-out-at-the-café&quot;&gt;Hanging out at the café&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right from the opening montage, which documents the history of the automobile and the development of car culture, it is clear that this is a game for real car geeks. It is apparent in so many small touches that &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; was developed by people who really know their stuff and is designed to be played by motorheads keen to savour every detail about the cars. When you gain or lose a position in a race, you even get a little pop-up telling you exactly which model of car you’ve just passed or been passed by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Car culture is also the focal point of Career Mode. After buying your first car, you are invited to check out the Gran Turismo Café, where your pals serve you up themed menus of cars to collect – for example, you might be tasked with obtaining a few hatchbacks or Porsches. Once you have all the cars on your current menu you can return to the café and get some genuinely educational background on the manufacturer or class. It’s a simple mechanic, but (somewhat ironically) the café menus prevent the game from feeling like a simple list of races to be completed and add some extra charm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the campaign serves as a guided tour through automotive history. Its dedication to this also adds variety to the racing – the Japanese cars race in Japan and the European cars in Europe. You could argue that other racing games, which mix cars, manufacturers, and geographies all over the place, are more realistic in this respect, but you get much more of a sense of location when you’re at Daytona racing against Dodges and Chevrolets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The races themselves are the standard &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; affair, progressing from road cars to purpose-built racing cars via trucks and rally. The game makes the most of its new weather system with races that transition from day to night, dry to wet, and vice versa. Beyond class, manufacturer, and region, most race entries are limited based on Performance Points – a single number that summarises how well a car drives. You’ll quickly familiarise yourself with the art of getting the best out of your cars in the right areas – for example, top speed at Monza – while keeping this figure under the limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strange design choice was to configure 95 per cent of the game’s races with extremely staggered rolling starts, making them feel more like overtake challenges than motorsport events. On one hand this reduces time spent staring at empty tarmac and provides more memorable manoeuvres, but on the other it can lead to some frustrating scenarios where you’re fractionally quicker than the lead cars but can’t catch them because you started so far behind. Luckily, grid starts are an option for Custom Races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite the odd structure, there are moments when it undeniably feels very &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt;. Whether you’re blasting your first souped-up entry-level Japanese sports car through the streets of Tokyo or slamming a Ferrari F430 around the Circuit de Barcelona-Catalunya, there’s simply an enjoyment to be found in the sights and sounds of good, clean motor racing that is difficult to describe but is not replicated in most other titles in the genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ordering-off-menu&quot;&gt;Ordering off-menu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cars you need for the café menus are all available as prizes for winning races, so your credits are free to be spent on modifications, upgrades, and additional vehicles. For the latter, you have three choices: Brand Central, which is full of standard manufacturers, many of which have museums covering their history; the used car dealership; and the Hagerty Collection, which sells “legendary” cars like notable race winners and cars from films. Somewhat gratingly, the latter two shopfronts rotate their stock regularly, increasing the pressure on players to grab their favourites before they’re gone by splurging on credits with microtransactions (more on those later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_8.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World GT Series Championship is a fitting end to the 39-menu café campaign, but some of the best racing is in the post-game, where you can race GT3-level cars against more skilled AI opponents. Here you must get into a rhythm, clipping the apex and the kerbs on every corner, and one mistake can be fatal to your chances of a win. It’s amazing how &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; can make a 10-lap event feel like a proper endurance race, with a multitude of possible strategies, many of which are utilised by the AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your own strategy is up to you, although a single stop works most of the time. Unlike many racers – notably in my recent memory &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/08/03/project-cars-2-winning-setup-strategy/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project Cars 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;’s strategy system works entirely on the fly. When you pit you are given two straightfoward menus to choose your next tyre compound and how much fuel to bring onboard. This makes it much easier to adapt your strategy mid-race – a must when it starts raining – and avoids those frustrating moments where you forget to set your strategy before the race and have to mess around with fussy HUD menus while driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Licence tests – a beloved feature of previous &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; games – make their return, with five licences consisting of ten tests each. I played each until I passed, but purists will spend hours chasing the gold medals before moving on to the new missions, which are very similar in structure. Tasks range from overtaking cars to drifting around corners and running as far as you can on just a few drops of fuel. The only downside to these modes is the PlayStation 4’s rather slow loading times, which are bearable for normal races but drag on a bit when you’re jumping quickly from track to track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of the PS4, you may have noticed that I haven’t really mentioned the platform until now. That’s because, as far as I’m aware, the last-gen version of &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; has all the features of the PS5 version except those the console is physically incapable of, like haptic feedback and ray tracing. It looks great for a game running on a nearly nine-year-old console, with just a few frame rate stutters in the most demanding of scenarios, like racing against 19 other cars at Spa-Francorchamps as the sun rises. In short, not owning a PS5 should not prevent you from enjoying this game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-ugly-side-of-modern-gaming&quot;&gt;The ugly side of modern gaming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s time to get into the thick of it. Since &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;’s launch there have been many complaints about its economy. Namely, these are that cars are too expensive, race prizes are too small, and that this pushes players towards spending real-world money on virtual cars via microtransactions. To begin with, I gave Polyphony Digital the benefit of the doubt – I had a great time with the café campaign, won and upgraded a lot of cars, and bought a couple of big hitters with my winnings. Even if I’d never own every single car, the game was perfectly playable for me as an average gamer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_9.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But after observing further developments and giving it more consideration, I’m not so sure. When you think about how certain parts of &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; work, you’re reminded more of a free-to-play mobile game than a £60 AAA title. Some cars rotate through the used car lot and vintage dealership, and you’ll receive invitations to buy premium cars from Brand Central. All of these are time-limited, and cars can cost millions of credits. If your favourite model appears and you don’t have the credits on hand, what can you do to secure it before it disappears? Well, spend your real money, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wouldn’t bother me too much – I never interact with these kinds of microtransactions on principle and I have no ambition to own every car – but eventually you realise that this is the game’s foundation and the reason why it needs to be a live service. Two weeks after release there was considerable server downtime, and it turns out that when &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t have an internet connection, 95 per cent of the game just… disappears. You can play simple arcade races with about 20 cars and that’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_10.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no reason at all for so many of the game’s single-player features to be online-only, other than if the developers want to prevent players from enjoying it by themselves in order to extort money from them. Polyphony Digital needs you to play &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; online so it can optimise the economy by tweaking race prizes and dangling shiny cars in front of your face to tempt you to get your credit card out. It’s like if EA removed Career Mode from &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; entirely and made Ultimate Team the entire game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-slightly-sour-aftertaste&quot;&gt;A slightly sour aftertaste&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; had been offline, like previous games in the series, none of the above would have been possible and it would have been a certain five out of five, possibly the best racing game ever. But if the developers insist on holding the reins to a full-price game, always looking for places to make more money, then I’m going to have to be more restrained. And it leaves an even more bitter taste in the mouth that things were tipped even further in the house’s favour with updates after most reviews had been published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much exactly this affects your enjoyment of the game will depend on how you play it. If, like me, you want to buy a few main cars, tune them up, and run them in some long races against challenging AI, then you’ll probably have no problem. If on the other hand you have ambitions of collecting all 425 cars in the game, &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt;-style, or there’s a very specific classic car you dream of buying, you’re likely to find the low credit rewards and extortionate prices on time-limited cars much more grating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_11.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake, &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; is a world-class racer on track and the first part of this review is still valid. It feels and looks fantastic. There are hours upon hours of enjoyment to be had not only from the career scenarios but also from setting up Custom Races of various lengths with different conditions and classes on all the tracks you’ve unlocked via the café.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just unfortunate that it is flawed under the hood – at worst exploitative and at best a beloved game you won’t be able to play most of in subsequent decades when the developers have switched the servers off. I definitely fall into the latter camp with my play style, but I wouldn’t be doing my job as a reviewer if I didn’t mark it down at least a bit. Your mileage may vary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4/5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="gran-turismo" /><category term="racing" /><summary type="html">Writing a review for Gran Turismo 7 having observed what has happened to it in the three weeks since its release is a hugely difficult task. The truth is that there is a fantastic racing game here – possibly the best ever. But in writing a review it is impossible to ignore that the game’s experience is soured by implementations of some of the dirtiest tactics the video game industry has been perfecting in recent years in order to extract every penny possible from players. So you’ve been warned – I’m going to be saying a lot of nice things about the racing, but make sure you read until the end. Note: On the day this review was due to be published, Gran Turismo creator Kazunori Yamauchi published a blog post announcing several upcoming updates that address many of the negative points in this article (although notably not the always online problem). So although everything here is true at the time of publication, there is hope on the horizon! Driving fast, shiny cars But let’s start where Gran Turismo 7 does deliver: out on the tarmac. Even on the PlayStation 4, the game is gorgeous. I wrote in my first impressions article about how the beauty of the vehicles often led to a conflict between my sim racer instinct to use the first-person view and a desire to use the chase camera to see more of the cars. The circuits look great too, even if things are a little sparse trackside in some areas, with HD revamps of some of the beloved fictional Gran Turismo tracks a particular treat to race on. The sound design is just as good. You’d expect a big-budget racing game to have great-sounding engines, but Gran Turismo 7 really goes above and beyond when it comes to the small touches it would be easy to overlook. Polyphony Digital has thought of everything, from the clunk as you run over a kerb to the rumble as you race across road markings on street circuits. Rain and spray pattering on your windscreen sounds just right, and even the post-race reward screen is set to the metallic clicking of a car cooling down.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review_2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 2 retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/03/18/call-of-duty-modern-warfare-2-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Call of Duty&amp;#58; Modern Warfare 2 retrospective" /><published>2022-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/03/18/call-of-duty-modern-warfare-2-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/03/18/call-of-duty-modern-warfare-2-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;I have good memories of the &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare&lt;/em&gt; trilogy. Between 2007 and 2011, I bought all the games pretty much on release. This was one of the most popular series around at the time, mostly because of its famous online multiplayer. But while I played online sometimes, that wasn’t really the focal point of these games for me, and I spent more time playing through the campaigns and completing the Special Ops with my friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/cod-modern-warfare-2_12.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago, while I was sat waiting for my annoyingly delayed &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/gran-turismo&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; delivery, I started flicking around my PS4’s menus and landed on &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 2 Campaign Remastered&lt;/em&gt;. I’ve tried to play &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty 4&lt;/em&gt; multiple times in recent years and have never made it past the opening mission (Crew Expendable) because it feels too familiar, but I found &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt; was a distant enough memory that I was able to get into it and play through the campaign to see how well it stands up in the modern day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enough-of-a-story-for-a-shooter&quot;&gt;Enough of a story for a shooter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare 2&lt;/em&gt; was published in 2009, war was a distant thing and therefore seemed fair ground for an entertainment product. This certainly speaks to the young, Western perspective I viewed it from at the time of my first playthrough, as the first mission in the campaign has you fighting in Afghanistan, where there was an ongoing conflict even at that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, given recent real-world developments it was especially jarring to be fighting through dense urban areas from the off. Infinity Ward did try to add some nuance. It’s made clear early in the mission (Team Player) that we’re the good guys and we only shoot if the locals shoot first, and on each death you’re presented with a different philosophical quote – many of which are on the futility of war and lament the needless loss of life it causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/cod-modern-warfare-2_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these attempts at moral grounding are juxtaposed against our pals shouting things like “Whoa, baby!” as huge buildings are levelled, presumably with collateral. And that’s just one example - warfare is always presented with a certain cool factor, despite the aforementioned attempts to convey its futility. There are shooters out there that handle war less sensitively than &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/em&gt;, but in such worrying circumstances there was the occasional moment when the discomfort proved too much and I had to take a break.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Story has never been a priority for me with &lt;em&gt;COD&lt;/em&gt; games – I mainly play for the action and the challenge – but when listening to the cut scenes and reading up on the lore it was hard to ignore the modern day parallels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt; it is explained that the West thought Russia was an ally after the events of &lt;em&gt;COD 4&lt;/em&gt;, but nationalism prevailed and made it an enemy once again. Disinformation is also a theme at some points, nowhere more so than in the infamous No Russian mission – a false flag terrorist attack on a Russian airport blamed on the US and used as justification for the start of World War III. Again, having moved to a more populated area at higher risk of terrorism than where I lived in 2009, I found myself more sensitive to the brutality of this mission than I was the first time around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/cod-modern-warfare-2_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the story is essentially the US fending off a Russian attack on home soil while elite teams hunt the ultranationalist leader Makarov, and then the treasonous Lieutenant Shepherd, who emerges as the main antagonist. There are also some levels set in Brazil, on a random oil rig, and breaking Captain Price out of the gulag – because where else would the West’s top soldiers possibly be when Washington DC is being invaded?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But none of that is very important – nobody expects a masterpiece of a story from a mainstream first-person shooter anyway, and the whole thing is merely a construct to enable set pieces and opportunities for the player to feel heroic. There’s not much else to it. The other main note I took on the story element of the campaign was about how often the player characters black out, but that was already a well-known &lt;em&gt;COD&lt;/em&gt; tradition by this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fast-dense-and-action-packed&quot;&gt;Fast, dense, and action-packed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The campaign took about seven hours to complete, but I think you could cut that to six once you subtract the time I spent writing notes and waiting on the PS4’s painfully slow screenshot feature. Some might criticise that as short, but for me it’s a good length – long enough to take a few sittings to finish, but short enough to be densely packed with unique moments and possible to complete for people with lives beyond video games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/cod-modern-warfare-2_13.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you couldn’t possibly complain about is the variety. Over the course of &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare 2&lt;/em&gt;’s campaign you’ll be participating in urban warfare, ice pick climbs, stealthy blizzard infiltrations, snowmobile chases, gunfights in American suburbs, favela shootouts, and – of course – Burger Town defence. Many shooters are just endless corridors full of enemies to pick off, but I have to hand it to Infinity Ward here. They really went all out to include as many memorable settings and set pieces in this trilogy as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing &lt;em&gt;COD&lt;/em&gt; has always done well is making you feel like you’re part of a team, with your comrades shouting updates and commands to you at all times. This is especially true of Captain Price, who is once again built up as some sort of legendary hero/father figure after he busts out of prison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This peaks during the final stand-off with Shepherd, in which the player is stabbed very early on and (once again) passes in and out of consciousness while Price does all the cool fighting. In a ridiculous sequence, the player character pulls the knife out of their own stomach by mashing the square button and somehow throws it at Shepherd with enough power and precision to kill him. Price stands up, brushes himself off, returns his trademark hat to his head, says something cool, and the game is over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/cod-modern-warfare-2_10.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sidenote here: While the credits roll we see that the events of World War III are now presented as dioramas in a museum. It’s a neat little idea and a nice reminder of everything we did over the campaign. What’s weirder is that after completing the game we can revisit the museum from the main menu, gun in hand, and murder the defenceless exhibits – friends, foes, and civilians alike. You win some, you lose some when it comes to tone, eh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-eternal-cod-formula&quot;&gt;The eternal &lt;em&gt;COD&lt;/em&gt; formula&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare 2&lt;/em&gt;’s gameplay is solid - responsive and satisfying - which comes as standard for a modern &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/em&gt; game. The &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare&lt;/em&gt; formula that was so successful in &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty 4&lt;/em&gt; sees a few refinements here, but it’s amazing how similar this 2009 game feels to 2020’s battle royale entry &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty: Warzone&lt;/em&gt; (that’s also because some locations from the campaign were copied and pasted across, but that’s another story).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, don’t expect puzzles, or any kind of thinking at all, really. &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare 2&lt;/em&gt; is all about the spectacle, even if its means of providing you with said spectacle doesn’t make much sense. For example, if you enter a room where the enemy has deployed smoke grenades to hide their positions, they have almost certainly left a weapon with a thermal scope near your entry point. All you have to do is pick it up and fire away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/cod-modern-warfare-2_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The environments themselves are actually very good-looking, even when taking into account that I was playing the remastered version. I would even say they look better than &lt;em&gt;Warzone&lt;/em&gt;. The advantage of a linear game is that more attention can be given to each room or street and the player can be guided in certain directions, and this produced so many pretty views that it was difficult to decide which screenshots to include in this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AI is good enough to deliver the shooting galleries that these games promise, and that’s all you could really ask of it. Enemies execute the usual “run towards the player and sometimes take cover” routine. Unless it’s a designated stealth mission everybody knows where you are at all times, and there are no noticeable differences between factions in terms of behaviour - the game tends to give enemies RPGs and increase their numbers to up the difficulty towards the end, rather than making them smarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/cod-modern-warfare-2_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One quirk I noticed concerning the AI is that enemies do not tend to emerge from cover unless they have sight of you. This is cheating slightly, but it’s excusable to prevent the player exploiting cracks in fences and other vantage points that enemies would be defenceless against.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More frustrating is that the AI seems to be incredibly effective at range with grenades. This leads to some frustrating deaths (especially if you don’t know where the grenade came from), but a solid sense of achievement when you do progress past a tricky bit - that is until the final missions, when there are so many enemies and so little cover that some segments feel like trial and error rather than an opportunity to exhibit any type of skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;worthy-of-a-revisit&quot;&gt;Worthy of a revisit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So does &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 2&lt;/em&gt; meet the expectations of the modern gamer? I’m slightly out of the loop when it comes to first-person shooters, but I was pleasantly surprised at how much I enjoyed myself and how much I looked forward to getting back to the game between sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/cod-modern-warfare-2_11.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story isn’t important or coherent enough to worry about, although some of the design choices - especially those made with the intent to shock audiences - don’t play out as well as they did in 2009. However, the action is solid, the campaign is short enough that it never outstays its welcome, and there’s enough variety between the various missions and set pieces that you’ll keep pushing on for as long as it takes to get to the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you’ve got a copy of the game gathering dust on your Xbox 360 shelf and six hours to spare, I’d recommend giving it a go. &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare 2&lt;/em&gt; may not go down in history as an all-time classic, but it serves well as the gaming equivalent of a blockbuster action film - slightly tone deaf, but with enough gunfights, explosions, and chases to make it memorable.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="call-of-duty" /><category term="shooters" /><summary type="html">I have good memories of the Modern Warfare trilogy. Between 2007 and 2011, I bought all the games pretty much on release. This was one of the most popular series around at the time, mostly because of its famous online multiplayer. But while I played online sometimes, that wasn’t really the focal point of these games for me, and I spent more time playing through the campaigns and completing the Special Ops with my friends. A couple of weeks ago, while I was sat waiting for my annoyingly delayed Gran Turismo 7 delivery, I started flicking around my PS4’s menus and landed on Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 2 Campaign Remastered. I’ve tried to play Call of Duty 4 multiple times in recent years and have never made it past the opening mission (Crew Expendable) because it feels too familiar, but I found MW2 was a distant enough memory that I was able to get into it and play through the campaign to see how well it stands up in the modern day. Enough of a story for a shooter When Modern Warfare 2 was published in 2009, war was a distant thing and therefore seemed fair ground for an entertainment product. This certainly speaks to the young, Western perspective I viewed it from at the time of my first playthrough, as the first mission in the campaign has you fighting in Afghanistan, where there was an ongoing conflict even at that time. Still, given recent real-world developments it was especially jarring to be fighting through dense urban areas from the off. Infinity Ward did try to add some nuance. It’s made clear early in the mission (Team Player) that we’re the good guys and we only shoot if the locals shoot first, and on each death you’re presented with a different philosophical quote – many of which are on the futility of war and lament the needless loss of life it causes. But these attempts at moral grounding are juxtaposed against our pals shouting things like “Whoa, baby!” as huge buildings are levelled, presumably with collateral. And that’s just one example - warfare is always presented with a certain cool factor, despite the aforementioned attempts to convey its futility. There are shooters out there that handle war less sensitively than Call of Duty, but in such worrying circumstances there was the occasional moment when the discomfort proved too much and I had to take a break.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/03/cod-modern-warfare-2_4.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/03/cod-modern-warfare-2_4.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">First impressions: Should you buy Gran Turismo 7 on PlayStation 4?</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/03/11/gran-turismo-7-ps4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First impressions&amp;#58; Should you buy Gran Turismo 7 on PlayStation 4?" /><published>2022-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/03/11/gran-turismo-7-ps4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/03/11/gran-turismo-7-ps4">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; is a now a week old and I’ve just finished all the café menus in Campaign Mode. There’s still plenty to do and I’d like to try out more modes and let the dust settle a bit before I publish my full review, but I did want to address one of the concerns I had going in – is it worth it on PS4?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry if this is an anticlimax, but the answer is definitely yes. The most obvious difference to the PS5 version is that the graphics don’t have quite the same level of detail, but the visuals - especially on the cars - are very pretty. In fact, they’re so pretty that when playing &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; I have a constant internal battle between my sim racer instinct for first person view and an urge to use chase cam to see more of the beautiful cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not to say that the tracks are shabby. They don’t always have a huge amount going on trackside, but there are some faithful recreations of real-life classics here, alongside some upgraded &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; favourites. Having recently replayed &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/10/gran-turismo-3-retrospective&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it’s surreal driving through such detailed, HD recreations of the nostalgic fictional circuits like the High Speed Ring. I can only imagine how those playing in 4K on PS5 must feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weather transitions, which were &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/02/05/everything-we-know-gran-turismo-7#physics-graphics-and-effects&quot;&gt;expected to be the star of the game&lt;/a&gt;, add an extra level of depth to the environments. The conditions on a circuit can go from sunny to gloomy to raining in just a couple of laps without any jarring changes. On this note, wet racing is a joy, unlike in most other racing games. A damp track brings reduced grip, but it doesn’t feel like you’re racing on an ice rink or spinning out of control randomly running through puddles.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than slightly less shiny graphics, the one noticeable concession PS4 users are forced to make compared to PS5 players is on speed. It’s widely documented that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jTvc8_55l3E&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;menus and load times can be a little slow on PS4&lt;/a&gt;. It’s not too bad when loading “proper” events, but can feel like a bit of a throwback to the PS2 days when loading lots of different tracks for licence tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only other place I noticed the game pushing the PS4 to its limits was on a couple of frame rate stutters. However, this only affected a 20-car race at Spa-Francorchamps (possibly the longest circuit in the game) at sunrise (think of all those beams of light), so I feel like it can be excused, and I only encountered it once in what is so far about 18 hours of gameplay anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final note: There has been a lot of fuss around microtransactions that allow you to buy credits. While it’s always a shame to see a feature like this bolted onto a beloved series, they are completely unnecessary. The game can be played perfectly well without spending anything other than the box price. You’ll be grinding for a while if you want to collect every car in the game, but completing the café menus provides more than enough credits to upgrade your cars and buy a few high-end trophy vehicles by the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, if you have a PS4 and even a passing interest in motorsport, you should buy &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;. I was &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/08/21/gran-turismo-7-campaign-mode/&quot;&gt;massively hyped&lt;/a&gt; for this game before it came out and now it’s here I can’t stop playing, even after completing the main campaign. Stay tuned for the full review in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="gran-turismo" /><category term="racing" /><summary type="html">Gran Turismo 7 is a now a week old and I’ve just finished all the café menus in Campaign Mode. There’s still plenty to do and I’d like to try out more modes and let the dust settle a bit before I publish my full review, but I did want to address one of the concerns I had going in – is it worth it on PS4? Sorry if this is an anticlimax, but the answer is definitely yes. The most obvious difference to the PS5 version is that the graphics don’t have quite the same level of detail, but the visuals - especially on the cars - are very pretty. In fact, they’re so pretty that when playing Gran Turismo 7 I have a constant internal battle between my sim racer instinct for first person view and an urge to use chase cam to see more of the beautiful cars. That’s not to say that the tracks are shabby. They don’t always have a huge amount going on trackside, but there are some faithful recreations of real-life classics here, alongside some upgraded Gran Turismo favourites. Having recently replayed Gran Turismo 3, it’s surreal driving through such detailed, HD recreations of the nostalgic fictional circuits like the High Speed Ring. I can only imagine how those playing in 4K on PS5 must feel. Weather transitions, which were expected to be the star of the game, add an extra level of depth to the environments. The conditions on a circuit can go from sunny to gloomy to raining in just a couple of laps without any jarring changes. On this note, wet racing is a joy, unlike in most other racing games. A damp track brings reduced grip, but it doesn’t feel like you’re racing on an ice rink or spinning out of control randomly running through puddles.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gran-turismo-7-ps4_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Parkitect: How to build a rollercoaster your guests will love</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/03/04/parkitect-how-to-build-rollercoaster" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parkitect&amp;#58; How to build a rollercoaster your guests will love" /><published>2022-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/03/04/parkitect-how-to-build-rollercoaster</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/03/04/parkitect-how-to-build-rollercoaster">&lt;p&gt;Chris Sawyer’s all-time classic &lt;em&gt;RollerCoaster Tycoon&lt;/em&gt; will always be the king of theme park management games, but Texel Raptor’s 2018 title &lt;em&gt;Parkitect&lt;/em&gt; does an amazing job of augmenting its addictive gameplay with the graphical fidelity and quality of life features you’d expect from a modern game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, &lt;em&gt;Parkitect&lt;/em&gt;’s guests are if anything &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; fussy about what they will and won’t ride than their &lt;em&gt;RCT&lt;/em&gt; equivalents. I’ve built many a rollercoaster that has brought a creative vision from my head into reality, but failed to attract many paying customers and had to run at a loss or be shut down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I thought I’d put together an article detailing everything I’ve learnt about planning, building, testing, and running rollercoasters in &lt;em&gt;Parkitect&lt;/em&gt; to help others get it right the first time round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/parkitect-rollercoasters_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ride-statistics&quot;&gt;Ride statistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s take a look at what we’ll be judged on. While &lt;em&gt;Parkitect&lt;/em&gt; attempts to simulate the chaos of hundreds of guests randomly making their way around a theme park, drawn from one shiny attraction to the next, as with any game there’s a lot of maths going on under the surface. In this case, every ride - rollercoasters included - is judged on three main metrics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Excitement&lt;/strong&gt; dictates how - well - &lt;em&gt;excited&lt;/em&gt; your guests will get about your new ride, and increases the likelihood that they will show interest in it. It is dictated by the length of the ride, track variation, speed, and G-forces, as well as decoration and quirks like whether or not the rollercoaster goes underground. It is penalised if Intensity is too high or the ride is too short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now your rollecoaster has a guest’s attention, they need to decide if they want to ride it. Each guest has a preferred ride &lt;strong&gt;Intensity&lt;/strong&gt; rating, against which they will assess the ride to determine whether it is too boring or too daring. High drops, G-forces, and speeds all increase Intensity, so you’ll want to watch out when designing your track - though there are some techniques we can use to keep it at an acceptable level, which we’ll discuss later.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/parkitect-rollercoasters_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nausea&lt;/strong&gt;, as the name would suggest, tells you how likely your guests are to throw up after riding your rollercoaster. It increases with the number of inversions and drops in your track design and the level of G-force riders are subjected to. Keep it at a moderate level to avoid overworking your janitors, and maybe keep a bin near the exit for those with weak stomachs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been deliberately vague and given you just enough information to get a feel for rollercoaster building here, but if you want to know exactly how Excitement, Intensity, and Nausea are calculated (and therefore potentially spoil the game for yourself), &lt;a href=&quot;https://parkitect.fandom.com/wiki/Coaster_Stat_Calculation_Guide&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Parkitect Wiki&lt;/a&gt; has an extremely detailed page with tons of detail, complete with equations and graphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;initial-considerations&quot;&gt;Initial considerations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting to sound complicated? Don’t worry - we’ll walk through the ample tools &lt;em&gt;Parkitect&lt;/em&gt; provides to help us manage these metrics in a little bit. However, we need to do a little bit of planning before we break ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, carefully consider where you’re going to build the new ride. Unless you’re building a junior coaster or deliberately aiming for low intensity, it’s likely that a rollercoaster will be one of your park’s big attractions and draw in crowds. Therefore we want to place it somewhere it will bring people past less exciting rides and shops, increasing the probability that something will catch their eye and they’ll part with more of their hard-earned cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/parkitect-rollercoasters_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also the subject of space. It would be incredibly tricky to build a new rollercoaster in an area populated with many other rides, so try to find an open plot to set it on. Although the exact track layout, drop height, and so on will change as you build, it’s good to have at least a rough idea of the type of coaster you’re aiming for so you can ensure you have enough space. There’s nothing worse than having to start from scratch because you keep hitting the park boundaries and having to compromise on your vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a similar note, think specifically about where the rollercoaster’s station will sit. The station is likely to be the first segment of track you place, and therefore the hardest to undo without ripping everything up. It’s vital that you leave enough space for the entrance and exit, and that it will be possible to route paths gracefully over, under, or around the other parts of the track to link up with the main path and let guests in and out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;designing-your-track&quot;&gt;Designing your track&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you’ve probably guessed from my description of the metrics above (and, y’know, common sense), track design is the most crucial part of any ride. There are infinite possibilities here, and just because a rollercoaster is unorthodox or unusual it doesn’t mean it has a bad design. That said, there are some &lt;em&gt;general&lt;/em&gt; rules you’re likely to want to stick to in most cases…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most rollercoasters have a single lift hill (or powered launch) at the start of the ride. After the first drop, the train is carried by its own momentum through subsequent hills, drops, inversions, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep the track design varied, with different turns and drops and special track elements. Guests don’t want to ride the same loop five times in a row (and that’s probably too intense for most of them anyway)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Try to intertwine the track with itself and those of other rides. This doesn’t seem to offer an Excitement boost like it used to in the classic &lt;em&gt;RollerCoaster Tycoon&lt;/em&gt; games, but it looks more interesting and it means nearby scenery can easily contribute to multiple rides’ statistics&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/parkitect-rollercoasters_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For fast corners, use longer track pieces, gentler curves, and banking. This reduces the lateral G-force your guests have to endure - they’ll thank you for not being shunted from side to side&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Implement block brakes to divide the track into sections. This increases the number of trains you can use and stops them from crashing into each other if a train gets stuck. Just make sure the train can gain enough momentum to complete the track after the brakes are released (e.g. don’t put block brakes right before a loop)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Put block brakes before the station, always. If one of your coasters ever has an unexplained crash, it’s likely because the station brakes failed and another train arrived at speed, colliding with one loading passengers&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tests-and-measurements&quot;&gt;Tests and measurements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you build your rollercoaster, &lt;em&gt;Parkitect&lt;/em&gt; will send a phantom train around the track to show you how it fares. For this reason, it can be useful to open the ride dialogue box and set the number of cars to that which you intend to use - otherwise you might be in for a shock when the ride opens. Each time the ghost train completes the track (or the portion of it that exists), the current Excitement, Intensity, and Nausea metrics will be displayed, which should give you advance warning of any problematic elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/parkitect-rollercoasters_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your other best friend when diagnosing issues - which usually centre around surplus Intensity - is the overlay function, pictured above. This feature, found under the Graphs tab of the ride dialogue box, shows you the exact G-force levels at each part of the track, with the extremes in each direction marked on the track in red and blue. Even a quick glance at the output should help to identify areas that contribute more Intensity than needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How&lt;/em&gt; you fix these issues is another question entirely and depends on the exact problem. However, high G-forces are generally remediated by smoothening out the track. Softening curves, using more banking, and reducing the size of drops and loops are all usually good moves when it comes to reducing the Intensity score and avoiding that dreaded and frustrating “&amp;lt;Ride Name&amp;gt; looks too intense for me!” guest thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;finishing-touches-and-operation&quot;&gt;Finishing touches and operation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once your trains can finish your track and the ride’s metrics are satisfactory, it’s time to think theming. Again, the only limit here is your imagination, and some people produce some fantastically creative rides, but to make your coaster as appealing as possible to guests you should place at least &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; decorative elements close to the track. You can see what &lt;em&gt;Parkitect&lt;/em&gt; thinks of your efforts by checking the Decoration score on the Statistics tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/parkitect-rollercoasters_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your last consideration before opening the rollercoaster is pricing. &lt;em&gt;Parkitect&lt;/em&gt;’s default prices are very low, not least because guests are usually willing to pay quite a bit for a new ride with plenty of Excitement. This isn’t an exact science. There are a lot of factors at play and finding the optimal price requires some monitoring of queue length and guest thoughts (if you see “&amp;lt;Ride Name&amp;gt; is a really good deal!”, time to bump it up). I usually charge around $12 for my more popular rollercoasters, but the consensus online seems to be much higher and there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/ThemeParkitect/comments/a3od1k/any_rules_of_thumb_for_pricing_like_the_rct/ebjml22/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;some very detailed explanations&lt;/a&gt; out there for those willing to invest the time to read up on it in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, you should have a thrilling, well-decorated rollercoaster, making a tidy profit by attracting crowds of guests with carefully calculated pricing! My final piece of advice is to keep an eye on your ride for a while after opening. &lt;em&gt;Parkitect&lt;/em&gt; seems to simulate the weight of guests in the train, so a half-empty train with an uneven distribution of passengers might produce different results to your tests and lead to a stuck train. You did put those block brakes in to prevent another train arriving, didn’t you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this article has been useful in planning, building, testing, and running your latest attraction. If you think there’s anything I could add to this guide please let me know using the details below.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="parkitect" /><category term="management" /><summary type="html">Chris Sawyer’s all-time classic RollerCoaster Tycoon will always be the king of theme park management games, but Texel Raptor’s 2018 title Parkitect does an amazing job of augmenting its addictive gameplay with the graphical fidelity and quality of life features you’d expect from a modern game. Unfortunately, Parkitect’s guests are if anything more fussy about what they will and won’t ride than their RCT equivalents. I’ve built many a rollercoaster that has brought a creative vision from my head into reality, but failed to attract many paying customers and had to run at a loss or be shut down. With that in mind, I thought I’d put together an article detailing everything I’ve learnt about planning, building, testing, and running rollercoasters in Parkitect to help others get it right the first time round. Ride statistics First, let’s take a look at what we’ll be judged on. While Parkitect attempts to simulate the chaos of hundreds of guests randomly making their way around a theme park, drawn from one shiny attraction to the next, as with any game there’s a lot of maths going on under the surface. In this case, every ride - rollercoasters included - is judged on three main metrics: Excitement dictates how - well - excited your guests will get about your new ride, and increases the likelihood that they will show interest in it. It is dictated by the length of the ride, track variation, speed, and G-forces, as well as decoration and quirks like whether or not the rollercoaster goes underground. It is penalised if Intensity is too high or the ride is too short. Now your rollecoaster has a guest’s attention, they need to decide if they want to ride it. Each guest has a preferred ride Intensity rating, against which they will assess the ride to determine whether it is too boring or too daring. High drops, G-forces, and speeds all increase Intensity, so you’ll want to watch out when designing your track - though there are some techniques we can use to keep it at an acceptable level, which we’ll discuss later.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/03/parkitect-rollercoasters_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/03/parkitect-rollercoasters_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>