<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-14T19:58:01+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Cities: Skylines II review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2024/01/14/cities-skylines-ii-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cities&amp;#58; Skylines II review" /><published>2024-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2024/01/14/cities-skylines-ii-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2024/01/14/cities-skylines-ii-review">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines II&lt;/em&gt; is Paradox Interactive’s follow-up to 2015’s &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/cities-skylines&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a city builder that served as a spiritual successor to &lt;em&gt;SimCity&lt;/em&gt; in the aftermath of EA’s 2013 mess. In the following years, the original &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt; received no fewer than 11 expansion packs, as well as a smaller number of cosmetic add-ons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;366&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tvd63NN3qR4?si=ZoE9LYWbDctSKKrF&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, Paradox decided &lt;em&gt;Cities&lt;/em&gt;’ systems needed more a more fundamental overhaul, and thus the sequel was delivered in October 2023. The release was plagued by reports of bugs and performance issues, with accusations it was rushed into stores. But it looked enjoyable enough in the footage I saw, and I decided to give it a go when I &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/11/21/notes-brief-stay-austin-tx&quot;&gt;returned from Austin&lt;/a&gt; and had a little more free time to spare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-brand-new-toolbox&quot;&gt;A brand new toolbox&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise of &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines II&lt;/em&gt; is much the same as its predecessors. The player is the founding mayor of a new city on a small plot of land and must keep things running by ensuring vital services are provided while balancing their finances.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s obvious that a lot of effort has been put into improving the toolset players use to build their cities. You won’t use any of these more often the road tool, which has been revamped with new features to better handle lanes, crossings, and more. The only frustration is that it’s still hard to find space for supports at complex junctions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/cities-skylines-ii_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public transport options have more depth than ever. After building tracks and designing lines, you now can now choose how many vehicles are assigned to each line and set pricing to try to convince the Cims to ditch their cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a departure from the original &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt;, terraforming is now free. This has received a mixed response online, with some accusations that this was a necessary change due to issues with how building plots look when they sit on slopes, but I quite like being able to build elevated highways and railways without worrying about cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;artificial-general-intelligence&quot;&gt;Artificial general intelligence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning players will be all too aware that in the original game even the best-planned city would eventually collapse under the load of traffic, and all these tools wouldn’t count for much if the beautiful cities they enabled simply ground to a halt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the traffic simulation has been completely redone. While vehicles used to plot the shortest route from A to B and stick to it, they now seem to actively respond to the traffic around them. This includes better use of lanes, but also opens up the possibility of taking an alternative route if their first choice is congested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/cities-skylines-ii_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not mean that road design is no longer a consideration. If you fail to consider how Cims will use your roads – particularly when zoning new areas that will place additional strain on existing infrastructure – you will encounter traffic jams. The difference is that these both form, and can be resolved, in a natural way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a simulation, &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines II&lt;/em&gt; offers more depth than any previous city builder. In particular, the decision making used by vehicles and pedestrians means that the player must consider traffic flow in a realistic way, rather than second-guessing an ultimately flawed approximation, as in the first game. This enables lifelike solutions to lifelike problems, and leads to a more natural-looking city as the end result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cooking-the-books&quot;&gt;Cooking the books&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a true city builder isn’t just about constructing a beautiful virtual model village – the genre is underpinned by management mechanics that require you to run a stable economy while keeping your city’s citizens happy. Unfortunately, this is the area where I found &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines II&lt;/em&gt; to be the most lacking in its current state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equation is the same as it ever was. The population expects basic services (power, water, sanitation, and so on), and running the infrastructure to provide it costs money. The player must balance the books by setting taxation levels for residents and businesses, and selling excess capacity to neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/cities-skylines-ii_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue for &lt;em&gt;Cities II&lt;/em&gt; as a game is that it seems impossible to lose. On the side of citizens’ happiness, there’s little demand for said services because any delta to your current capacity is outsourced to neighbouring cities. No waste management facilities? No problem – there are already dustbin lorries taking care of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accounting is just as flawed. Early in the game, when my expenditure on services exceeded my tax revenue, I noticed that my monthly budget was still in the green due to “government subsidies” that would mysteriously appear in my income whenever needed to balance things out. More confusingly, my cash balance would often increase even when the budget screen showed I should be losing money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes &lt;em&gt;Cities II&lt;/em&gt; feel rather empty as a management game. My only theory is that perhaps Paradox decided the early game was too challenging in testing and tried to smooth out the numbers for inexperienced players. Unfortunately, it now feels like the whole thing is on guardrails, and that you couldn’t fail even if you tried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;something-to-build-on&quot;&gt;Something to build on&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines II&lt;/em&gt; is a frustrating game in its current state. The potential of the upgraded tools and AI systems is clear, but there’s little satisfaction to be found in a game that can be played carelessly with minimal risk of failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradox Interactive appears to have recognised this, along with complaints about the game’s performance, and has suspended the game’s original roadmap to try to address its more fundamental issues. (For the record, &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines II&lt;/em&gt; was a smooth experience for me until my city reached a high population, and even then, the worst I saw were some frame rate stutters when quickly moving the camera.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, your decision over whether to purchase the game or not will come down to your passion for city builders and your faith in the developer. If you’re anxious to try out the latest in the genre and trust Paradox to build on this foundation then you’ll probably get a lot of fun out of it, but if you’re less fussed then it might be better to wait until the patches have been applied and perhaps even grab a discount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3/5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="reviews" /><category term="strategy" /><category term="management" /><category term="cities-skylines" /><summary type="html">Cities: Skylines II is Paradox Interactive’s follow-up to 2015’s Cities: Skylines, a city builder that served as a spiritual successor to SimCity in the aftermath of EA’s 2013 mess. In the following years, the original Cities: Skylines received no fewer than 11 expansion packs, as well as a smaller number of cosmetic add-ons. At some point, Paradox decided Cities’ systems needed more a more fundamental overhaul, and thus the sequel was delivered in October 2023. The release was plagued by reports of bugs and performance issues, with accusations it was rushed into stores. But it looked enjoyable enough in the footage I saw, and I decided to give it a go when I returned from Austin and had a little more free time to spare. A brand new toolbox The premise of Cities: Skylines II is much the same as its predecessors. The player is the founding mayor of a new city on a small plot of land and must keep things running by ensuring vital services are provided while balancing their finances.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2024/01/cities-skylines-ii_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2024/01/cities-skylines-ii_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Merry Christmas from Strat Packer</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/21/merry-christmas-from-strat-packer" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Merry Christmas from Strat Packer" /><published>2023-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/21/merry-christmas-from-strat-packer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/21/merry-christmas-from-strat-packer">&lt;p&gt;If your December has been anywhere near as busy as mine then you’ll understand the dearth of articles and videos in recent weeks, as a few ongoing reviews and retrospectives have taken a back seat to social events and Christmas preparations (and rightfully so). Don’t worry - I’ll return to those projects in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, though, I’d just like to say that I hope anybody out there who stumbles upon this humble little blog has a merry Christmas and a new year full of happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking on a personal level, 2023 has been transformational for me. I’ve reached a satisfying place professionally and have connected with some inspiring people both IRL and in the pleasant little corner of Twitter I’ve found myself settling into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s hope that 2024 continues in a similar vein for us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– &lt;strong&gt;Strat Packer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;highlights-of-2023&quot;&gt;Highlights of 2023&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you get bored over the Christmas break and need some reading material to tide you over, look no further. Below is a list of some of my favourite articles from 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;video-games&quot;&gt;Video games&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/09/10/starfield-searching-for-god&quot;&gt;Searching for God in &lt;em&gt;Starfield&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/07/08/yazuka-6-song-of-life-retrospective&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yakuza 6: The Song of Life&lt;/em&gt; retrospective&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/09/25/ea-sports-fc-24-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt; review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;travel-and-leisure&quot;&gt;Travel and leisure&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/11/21/notes-brief-stay-austin-tx&quot;&gt;Notes from a brief stay in Austin, TX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/09/03/how-to-run-half-marathon-better&quot;&gt;How to run a half marathon (better)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/05/14/lesson-curiosity-japan&quot;&gt;A lesson in curiosity from Japan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/07/21/f1-arcade-london&quot;&gt;F1 Arcade, London&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;philosophy-and-sociology&quot;&gt;Philosophy and sociology&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/09/17/anxiety-locus-of-control-gratitude&quot;&gt;Anxiety, locus of control, and gratitude&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/06/10/why-we-believe-morality-in-decline&quot;&gt;Why do we think morality is in decline?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;films-music-and-books&quot;&gt;Films, music, and books&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/11/11/atlas-shrugged-ayn-rand&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; by Ayn Rand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/07/15/asteroid-city-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt; review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/04/23/panic-at-the-disco-viva-las-vengeance-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viva Las Vengeance&lt;/em&gt; review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/08/25/gran-turismo-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/01/13/glass-onion-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt; review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/03/18/the-menu-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Menu&lt;/em&gt; review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">If your December has been anywhere near as busy as mine then you’ll understand the dearth of articles and videos in recent weeks, as a few ongoing reviews and retrospectives have taken a back seat to social events and Christmas preparations (and rightfully so). Don’t worry - I’ll return to those projects in 2024. For now, though, I’d just like to say that I hope anybody out there who stumbles upon this humble little blog has a merry Christmas and a new year full of happiness. Speaking on a personal level, 2023 has been transformational for me. I’ve reached a satisfying place professionally and have connected with some inspiring people both IRL and in the pleasant little corner of Twitter I’ve found myself settling into. Let’s hope that 2024 continues in a similar vein for us all. – Strat Packer Highlights of 2023 If you get bored over the Christmas break and need some reading material to tide you over, look no further. Below is a list of some of my favourite articles from 2023. Video games •   Searching for God in Starfield •   Yakuza 6: The Song of Life retrospective •   EA Sports FC 24 review Travel and leisure •   Notes from a brief stay in Austin, TX •   How to run a half marathon (better) •   A lesson in curiosity from Japan •   F1 Arcade, London Philosophy and sociology •   Anxiety, locus of control, and gratitude •   Why do we think morality is in decline? Films, music, and books •   Atlas Shrugged by Ayn Rand •   Asteroid City review •   Viva Las Vengeance review •   Gran Turismo review •   Glass Onion review •   The Menu review</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes from a brief stay in Austin, TX</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/21/notes-brief-stay-austin-tx" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes from a brief stay in Austin, TX" /><published>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/21/notes-brief-stay-austin-tx</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/21/notes-brief-stay-austin-tx">&lt;p&gt;Through a stroke of good fortune I was recently invited to spend a few days in Austin, Texas, and having never been to the United States I jumped at the chance. The city wasn’t on my to-visit list and I had minimal prior knowledge about the local area, so I had little idea of what to expect from my visit to the Lone Star State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/austin-tx_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dots-and-lines&quot;&gt;Dots and lines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first things I noted on arriving in the US is how spread out everything is. Each shop and restaurant is on its own large plot, like in &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/cities-skylines&quot;&gt;a city builder game&lt;/a&gt;, and because everybody drives everywhere you can’t be sure if your journey is actually walkable even if your destination is ten minutes away as the crow flies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the sides of the mammoth roads, which are full of the kind of vehicles you have to climb up into, are an abundance of billboards - most commonly for food, locally brewed beers, and lawyers. I always thought the ubiquity of &lt;em&gt;Better Call Saul&lt;/em&gt;-style adverts was a media exaggeration, but they really do line the highways.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until you’re there, it’s hard to appreciate how little consideration seems to be given to public transport in some US cities. I saw some buses and a tram, but the car is king. Even though the eight-lane highways are frequently congested, this means Uber is your primary means of getting around as a visitor, which rapidly spirals in cost - in one day alone I spent more than $55 zipping between landmarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cautious-optimism&quot;&gt;Cautious optimism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A benefit of so many Uber trips is that I could speak to a variety of locals, who were in equal measure excited about the tech boom and cautious about the preservation of what in their view makes Austin unique. Not a journey passed without the driver discussing AI, Elon Musk, and the Cybertruck. This mostly took a positive tone - or in one case absolute awe when trying to describe &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tesla.com/giga-texas&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the futuristic local Tesla factory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps these topics were self-selecting due to my easy identification as a visiting foreigner in tech, but they were still discussed enthusiastically. Everyone also mused on how much the city has grown and changed in recent years, and a few mentioned the ongoing campaign to ensure the area’s cultural hallmarks aren’t lost in the ongoing transformation (under the tagline “keep Austin weird”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample size I amassed isn’t anywhere near enough to generalise confidently, but I’d sum up the Texas residents I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; speak to as friendly and - perhaps more importantly - optimistic. It was refreshing that even those who brought up concerns about elements of the current situation were still positive, rather than envious or bitter, about technological innovation and the people who make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;exploring-downtown&quot;&gt;Exploring downtown&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I escaped the office to head downtown, I took a car to the Texas State Capitol - an Italian Renaissance-inspired building with a red granite exterior which is taller than even the US Capitol. While the structure itself is impressive, I enjoyed exploring the grounds, where amongst other things there was a miniature Statue of Liberty standing on a plinth and a large tablet inscribed with the Ten Commandments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/austin-tx_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The streets to the south are a bustling area full of eateries, bars, and venues for comedy and music. I was around at the wrong time of day for most of this, but it was a pleasant enough walk and there were some beautiful murals dotted around. It’s clear there’s a developing homeless problem, but as of yet it’s nothing compared to the scenes from San Francisco that are frequently posted online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet further south is the Colorado River, around which there are relaxed, leafy trails full of joggers and cyclists. The path passes under South Congress Bridge, which is famous for housing around a million bats in the crevices of its architecture. I couldn’t see them in the daytime, but it was a slightly surreal experience to suddenly realise where I was as I heard their loud collective chirping above me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think there are many more landmarks to see if I return, but it feels like an evening downtown is a key part of the Austin experience that I missed out on. I’ll try to find an opportunity for that next time - I’d really like to go back, stay in town a little longer, and create more downtime to chat, relax, and soak up the optimistic vibe.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="travel" /><category term="usa" /><category term="technology" /><category term="business" /><summary type="html">Through a stroke of good fortune I was recently invited to spend a few days in Austin, Texas, and having never been to the United States I jumped at the chance. The city wasn’t on my to-visit list and I had minimal prior knowledge about the local area, so I had little idea of what to expect from my visit to the Lone Star State. Dots and lines One of the first things I noted on arriving in the US is how spread out everything is. Each shop and restaurant is on its own large plot, like in a city builder game, and because everybody drives everywhere you can’t be sure if your journey is actually walkable even if your destination is ten minutes away as the crow flies. Along the sides of the mammoth roads, which are full of the kind of vehicles you have to climb up into, are an abundance of billboards - most commonly for food, locally brewed beers, and lawyers. I always thought the ubiquity of Better Call Saul-style adverts was a media exaggeration, but they really do line the highways.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/11/austin-tx_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/11/austin-tx_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Atlas Shrugged by Ayn Rand</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/11/atlas-shrugged-ayn-rand" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Atlas Shrugged by Ayn Rand" /><published>2023-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/11/atlas-shrugged-ayn-rand</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/11/atlas-shrugged-ayn-rand">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; is something of an anomaly. For every online commenter promoting Ayn Rand’s modern classic as essential reading, there’s a critic advising against ever picking it up at all, and it’s hard to separate opinions based on incompatibility with the holder’s politics from those critiquing it as a work of literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/atlas-shrugged_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was hard to justify committing to a 1,200-page novel when I might just have been wasting my time, but I recently decided it was time to take the plunge and form my own opinions. With a slight trepidation - and, admittedly, a curiosity to learn more about the philosophy that &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/bioshock&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; opposed so strongly - I finally took it on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-disaster-of-denying-reality&quot;&gt;The disaster of denying reality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a tragic scene about halfway through &lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; where a diesel-powered passenger train breaks down outside a tunnel in the Colorado mountains. The local workers know there is no option but to hold the train – there are no other diesel engines available, and sending a coal-powered locomotive through such a long and poorly ventilated passage would almost certainly end in disaster.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One passenger – a politician – is not satisfied with their explanations, and sends a telegram to the train company’s CEO in New York demanding the train continues its journey. The CEO urges one of his executives to make it happen, and the executive sends a carefully worded telegram to the local workers ordering them to find “an engine” to send the train “safely” to its destination “without unnecessary delay”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this point in the story laws have been passed, ostensibly to clamp down on out-of-control barons of industry, that tie men to their jobs. They are not allowed to quit or to be sacked, which strips them of the power to object. If they refuse to follow orders or attempt to leave their roles, they will be put in front of a governmental tribunal that will likely bar them from all future work, condemning them to poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those in charge of the area know that this puts them in an impossible situation. The careful wording of the executive’s message absolves him of any responsibility – he can claim the selection of a coal engine was incompetence on their part, or blame them for the politician’s anger if they rightly hold the train where it is. Some of them scheme and try to find ways to deflect potential blame onto their coworkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, despite everybody working on the line knowing that setting the train off with a coal engine is the wrong decision and completely immoral, nobody speaks up to stop it. They know that to do so would be to choose to save the lives of those on board, but would entrap themselves, their wives, and their children in a life of poverty when they would be sentenced for illegally resigning from their roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody wants the final call on their conscience. But rather than facing reality, they turn their backs on it, and the order is passed all the way from the CEO down to the lowliest worker – a boy who is paid simply to follow commands and not to think for himself. He sets the train off, and 300 people die in the subsequent disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;decoupling-effort-and-reward&quot;&gt;Decoupling effort and reward&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ayn Rand’s novel about a parallel, dystopian United States is littered with accounts of failures and accidents caused by the incompetence that stems from overreaching laws seeking misguided justice, but the Colorado rail disaster is the first that she describes in such grim detail, meaning it hits much harder emotionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point in the book, the protagonist, capable railway chief operating officer Dagny Taggart, is living in an isolated house in the countryside, having left the city and her job to flee the imposing and ever encroaching regulations that are stifling her best efforts to keep the railroad running and America moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disaster marks something of a turning point. When she hears the news on the radio she rushes back to her office, realising that she simply cannot stand by and watch the growing incompetence cause such harm. It is her duty to do her best in spite of the opposing forces that are promoting mediocrity in all areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the doers who are the heroes in &lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; – those like Dagny who make things happen, with the optimism to imagine a better world and the competence to deliver on their ideas. Rand’s characters believe they are entitled to the reward that their intellect and commitment brings in exchange for providing work, a living, and of course the benefits of the technologies they invent to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is juxtaposed against a homeless man’s account of a car factory he previously worked at, where the owners decided the workers would be paid by need, not by effort or ability, as voted on at an annual meeting. He explains the effect: “[The worker] had to beg in public for relief from his needs… listing all his troubles and miseries… because it’s miseries, not work, that had become the coin of the realm.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result of the scheme? The man and his competent colleagues’ output flagged as they avoided expending effort that would sap their energy and health and for which they would not be rewarded. In the end, the entire scheme failed and the car factory closed down, putting everyone out of work, damaging the local economy, and condemning even those who were originally on lower wages to zero income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;literally-atlas-shrugged&quot;&gt;Literally &lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was immediately struck by the parallel to the modern clamour on social media to stake a claim as to who is least privileged and to provide praise and reward on this basis, rather than celebrating those who strive to build, produce, achieve, and make the world a better and more prosperous place regardless of their background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a book published in 1957, &lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; contains an astounding number of such likenesses to the world in 2023, and if it were more widely read and understood (which perhaps it would be if it wasn’t 1,200 pages long) I think it would be referenced more often than &lt;a href=&quot;https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/wow-this-is-just-like-1984&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the “literally &lt;em&gt;Nineteen Eighty-Four&lt;/em&gt;” meme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The men in Washington waging war on the industrialists are driven by ideology over reason, and go unchecked because they have successfully driven fear into the public that they could lose their livelihoods if they dare challenge them. Even when the leadership are presented with objective facts that show their policies are failing, they simply accuse the dissenter of being obtuse and illogical – “that’s only theory”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This secondary assault on language is part and parcel of the antagonists’ philosophy – countries adopting their policies around the world prepend “People’s State” to their names, and the changes are all announced in the name of fairness and prosperity. Objective reality is denied and ignored in favour of subjective beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deep-rooted problems with their worldview are explained in depth in a rogue radio broadcast by John Galt, the leader of a strike by the country’s greatest innovators that demands the return of meritocracy. His rant, which spans some 60 pages, is essentially an essay detailing Rand’s objectivist philosophy, accusing the “looters” of acting more out of hatred for the rich than concern for the poor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Destruction is the only end that the mystics’ creed has ever achieved… If they profess to be moved by love, yet are not deterred by piles of human corpses, it is because the truth about their souls is worse than the obscene excuse you have allowed them, the excuse that the end justifies the means and that the horrors they practice are means to nobler ends. The truth is that those horrors are their ends…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The mystics’ scramble for spoils is only a screen to conceal from their mind the nature of their motive… They do not want to own your fortune; they want you to lose it; they do not want to succeed, they want you to fail; they do not want to live, they want you to die…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leaders’ doublethink reaches cartoonish levels shortly after, when Galt is  caught and his captors repeatedly state that he is not imprisoned or under arrest even when he’s being held by armed guard in a locked-off hotel. They then insist that they want him to work with them “voluntarily” while putting him through electrical torture. By this point they’ve spent so long convincing themselves of their good intentions and ignoring reality that it seems they genuinely struggle to tell the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;objectivity-as-a-foundation&quot;&gt;Objectivity as a foundation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; often seems to be sniggered at online, usually with the implication that it’s a book a privileged university student reads to inform a naïve worldview, but for me it was both gripping as a story and - while I don’t agree with every view expressed by the positively-framed characters - it’s a book that sends a clear and undeniable message: competence is vital to a flourishing and sustainable society, and competence can only thrive when objective fact is held above all else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of publication nobody could have known the unprecedented era of peace and prosperity that the world was about to embark upon. While developments since then have been undoubtedly positive, they have also created a layer of abstraction in most peoples’ daily lives. I don’t need to think about where food comes from, how my home is powered, or what my computer is made of. These things just… appear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we squabble over sports, social policies, and which Netflix series shoudn’t have been cancelled, &lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; serves as a reminder that we should never take our eyes off the work that is essential to our way of life. The preferences and beliefs we have the luxury of holding shouldn’t interfere with societal underpinnings that were built on rationality, science, and the study of objective fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not to say that we shouldn’t challenge convention - by all means, if somebody has an innovative new approach then it should be trialled and adopted if successful. But it’s a dangerous game to tear down proven and relied-upon systems because the alternative looks good through the rose-tinted lenses of ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; imagines a world where an ideology that places emotion before practicality gains enough momentum that it disrupts the production of materials, transportation systems, and food supply chains. Just as the COVID-19 pandemic demonstrated just how precarious our modern lifestyles are, Rand’s novel warns us not to take the fundamentals and the people who make them work for granted.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="reviews" /><category term="business" /><summary type="html">Atlas Shrugged is something of an anomaly. For every online commenter promoting Ayn Rand’s modern classic as essential reading, there’s a critic advising against ever picking it up at all, and it’s hard to separate opinions based on incompatibility with the holder’s politics from those critiquing it as a work of literature. It was hard to justify committing to a 1,200-page novel when I might just have been wasting my time, but I recently decided it was time to take the plunge and form my own opinions. With a slight trepidation - and, admittedly, a curiosity to learn more about the philosophy that BioShock opposed so strongly - I finally took it on. The disaster of denying reality There’s a tragic scene about halfway through Atlas Shrugged where a diesel-powered passenger train breaks down outside a tunnel in the Colorado mountains. The local workers know there is no option but to hold the train – there are no other diesel engines available, and sending a coal-powered locomotive through such a long and poorly ventilated passage would almost certainly end in disaster.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/11/atlas-shrugged_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/11/atlas-shrugged_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FC 24 Career Mode: Everton – fighting for Premier League survival</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/05/fc-24-career-mode-everton-part-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FC 24 Career Mode&amp;#58; Everton &amp;#8211; fighting for Premier League survival" /><published>2023-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/05/ea-fc-career-mode-everton-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/05/fc-24-career-mode-everton-part-1">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a year since I last updated my &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Career Mode series, guiding TSP United into England’s top flight. With my enthusiasm for &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/ea-sports-fc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; yet to wane, I thought it was time to start a new campaign with a new club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;366&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lIIoK1mN7dk?si=dz72swPam1LqnwI1&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick note before we start: If you read the previous series, you might be aware that I play Career Mode with some special rules to increase the challenge. Last time around that was a ban on paid-for transfers to focus on youth development, but I’ve slightly altered my guidelines this time around for added entertainment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transfers in must be realistic.&lt;/strong&gt; That means that if a player is at a club that is significantly outperforming my team, he wouldn’t want to sign for us, and he’s off limits even if I have enough money to buy him.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bid responses must be realistic.&lt;/strong&gt; If a player is kicking up a fuss and has requested a transfer, I must accept reasonable bids for him. Likewise, if a much bigger team makes an offer for one of my stars, he’s going to want to leave for Champions League football, and I must let him go.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No free agents.&lt;/strong&gt; The services of some very useful players become available free of charge in Career Mode, and I probably abused this to an extent last time out. This time, free agents are completely off limits.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, all this adds up to: “I’m trying to make Career Mode as realistic as possible, and therefore I must consider what decision would be made in real life, rather than the choice that benefits me most according to the game’s mechanics.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setting-the-scene&quot;&gt;Setting the scene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve read or watched any of my recent &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/ea-sports-fc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FC 24&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; content, you’ll probably have noticed that I was playing a Chelsea Career Mode as Mauricio Pochettino. But after a couple of seasons I’d finally won the Premier League, and between my tactics and the players’ development, it felt like the game was getting a bit easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the beginning of the 2025/26 season, I tried applying for jobs at teams lower in the Premier League, but for whatever reason they always rejected me. To force the issue, I skipped through months until I was finally sacked by Chelsea, and once I was unemployed I was offered only a single role: that of Everton manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/fc-24-career-mode_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an ambitious job, and I inherited a mess. With six games to go, Everton were 18th in the league with just 23 points. Brighton, Burnley and Nottingham Forest were also entangled in the relegation scrap, with Middlesbrough well off the pace in 20th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More problematic was the squad situation. The team I took over was in bad form, stripped of key players, and lacking a natural left back. While my main focus was Premier League survival, I also began work in the background to shift the deadwood, and opened talks regarding moves for some of my favourite Chelsea youth talent, who stood no chance of game time at Stamford Bridge after my departure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202526---premier-league&quot;&gt;2025/26 - Premier League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first game in charge was a return to Tottenham, and I immediately took a more cautious approach with an emphasis on safe passes. The drop in player quality - a lack of pace and finesse - made it difficult to penetrate the defence, but we did manage to keep it tight at the back, earning a 0-0 draw in a drab affair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any impressions that survival would be easy were destroyed in midweek when we lost 3-1 to Fulham at home, but the following weekend saw a shock smash-and-grab as Everton snatched a 2-0 win away at Old Trafford, sneaking our goals after somehow surviving sustained pressure from Manchester United.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/fc-24-career-mode_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our wings were clipped once again as Aston Villa took all three points in a scrappy game at Goodison Park that saw plenty of chances for the home team, but little quality finishing. A late consolation goal from Beto was all we could muster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With two games to go, Everton sat in 17th, just above the drop zone, with a two-point advantage and a game in hand over 18th-placed Burnley. With a superior goal difference, one point from our final two games would be enough to secure survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First up was a dramatic away clash against fellow strugglers Brighton. Despite going 2-0 down inside ten minutes, my Everton team eventually fought back to 3-3, but conceded an 86th-minute penalty after Joao Pedro was brought down by a last-ditch challenge by right-back Patterson. Mbuemo converted, we lost 4-3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/fc-24-career-mode_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meant our Premier League survival rested on our final day fixture at home to Wolves. Burnley were still two points behind, but with their last fixture taking them away to the Amex Stadium, there was every chance they could still escape the drop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The critical match couldn’t have started better, with Vargas netting an opener straight from kick-off, but Wolves equalised via Guedes after 17 minutes and quickly took control of the game, eventually taking a 3-1 lead as he completed his hat trick. At the other end, Beto failed to capitalise on countless opportunities, and while Everton did eventually pull one goal back, we relinquished control of our fate in a 4-2 defeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There had been no news from the Amex when referee blew the final whistle, but it turned out we’d been very lucky. Burnley had earned a draw at Brighton and closed the gap to one point, so we were effectively one goal from relegation, but as it was, we’d survived by the skin of our teeth in 17th place with 27 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/fc-24-career-mode_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d done enough to keep Poch in a job, but there was a lot of work to do ahead of the 2026/27 season. A number of deals made in the background meant a refreshed Everton squad would be assembled in time for August, but I’ll maintain some suspense and save the full details of the comings and goings for Part 2…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best player&lt;/strong&gt; - Beto, a ray of hope in an otherwise dismal squad&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - N/A, but the window is approaching…&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - N/A, check back next season&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="ea-sports-fc" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">It’s been a year since I last updated my FIFA 22 Career Mode series, guiding TSP United into England’s top flight. With my enthusiasm for EA Sports FC 24 yet to wane, I thought it was time to start a new campaign with a new club. A quick note before we start: If you read the previous series, you might be aware that I play Career Mode with some special rules to increase the challenge. Last time around that was a ban on paid-for transfers to focus on youth development, but I’ve slightly altered my guidelines this time around for added entertainment: Transfers in must be realistic. That means that if a player is at a club that is significantly outperforming my team, he wouldn’t want to sign for us, and he’s off limits even if I have enough money to buy him.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/11/fc-24-career-mode_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/11/fc-24-career-mode_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Like a Dragon: Hands on with both new games at EGX 2023</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/14/like-a-dragon-hands-on-egx-2023" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Like a Dragon&amp;#58; Hands on with both new games at EGX 2023" /><published>2023-10-14T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/14/like-a-dragon-hands-on-egx-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/14/like-a-dragon-hands-on-egx-2023">&lt;p&gt;I attended my first post-pandemic &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/egx&quot;&gt;EGX&lt;/a&gt; this week in London, and while the event itself was certainly subdued compared to previous years, I was very excited to get my hands on two new entries in the &lt;em&gt;Like a Dragon&lt;/em&gt; series ahead of their release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;366&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tLzeBN6utDc?si=x7ZxIHOPuzCAS8Az&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While both are brand new games, &lt;em&gt;The Man Who Erased His Name&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Infinite Wealth&lt;/em&gt; come from two very different angles that could be said to represent the series’ past and future. Here are my initial thoughts after trying them for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;like-a-dragon-gaiden-the-man-who-erased-his-name&quot;&gt;Like a Dragon Gaiden: The Man Who Erased His Name&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staking a claim amongst the longest video game titles ever, &lt;em&gt;Like a Dragon Gaiden: The Man Who Erased His Name&lt;/em&gt; picks up the story of fan favourite protagonist Kazuma Kiryu from where it was left off in &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/07/08/yazuka-6-song-of-life-retrospective&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yakuza 6: The Song of Life&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. While it will be released on PlayStation 4, it is probably also the first game in the &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt; series to be developed with the primary focus on the PlayStation 5 and Xbox Series X.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My demo gave me 15 minutes to run around a neon-soaked theme park for the wealthy, designed after a Japanese castle. It was unclear how far into the story this segment takes place, but Kiryu was going by his Joryu moniker after faking his death to protect his adopted family. The island was packed with the amusements you’d expect from a &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt; game, and was a really visually arresting setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/like-a-dragon_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In classic style, as soon as Kiryu arrives he’s greeted by way of a fight with a group of thugs. Combat gameplay feels very smooth, and Kiryu’s secret agent-style persona gives him some special gadgets to use. I can’t remember the specific names, but these include a dash, drones, a grenade, and a lasso. They fit perfectly with classic &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt;’s frantic combat and are a lot of fun to deploy in battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the rest of my time exploring the island. The boutique has outfits far quirkier than I remember in previous titles, and the arena gave me further opportunity to test my fighting skills against waves of enemies. Overall, I’m very much looking forward to this game’s release in November, and it felt great to slide back into Kiryu’s shoes and return to the original &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt; formula after &lt;em&gt;Like a Dragon&lt;/em&gt;’s turn-based battles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;like-a-dragon-infinite-wealth&quot;&gt;Like a Dragon: Infinite Wealth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Infinite Wealth&lt;/em&gt; is the next mainline &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/like-a-dragon&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Like a Dragon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; game starring new lead Ichiban Kasuga and featuring RPG-style party combat. After nearly an hour of queueing I entered the Sega booth to find Ichiban washed up in Hawaii and having formed a squad of four, featuring a noticeably aged Kazuma Kiryu. My 20-minute demo allowed me to explore the beach and a small area of the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main impression is that the game is basically more of the same following 2020’s &lt;em&gt;Yakuza: Like a Dragon&lt;/em&gt;. The available mission didn’t sound too interesting, so I mainly roamed Hawaii to see what I could find, getting into some fights along the way. Combat has been refined a little, with movement allowed within a circle that can trigger contextual moves involving objects or teammates, and Kiryu has a special ability that breaks up the turn-based fights with some real-time brawling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the Hawaiian setting exposes more of the series’ shortcomings than previous games. It’s not as exciting or packed as &lt;em&gt;The Man Who Erased His Name&lt;/em&gt;’s neon theme park, but more problematic are the the English-speaking locals. Most of them sound like that one weirdo from the last game, but worse is that they reveal just how basic NPC dialogue is. Then again, perhaps this is nothing new for some fans - is this just what it’s like to play a &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/yakuza&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; game if you speak Japanese?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;egx-2023---an-event-in-decline&quot;&gt;EGX 2023 - an event in decline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sega’s &lt;em&gt;Like a Dragon&lt;/em&gt; offerings were certainly my personal highlight of this year’s EGX (formerly the Eurogamer Expo, and recently transplanted to Earls Court to the ExCel). I also had a great time hanging out with friends in the arcade and retro areas, which were a lot of fun and had plenty of consoles and machines to try out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/like-a-dragon_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the main reason I (and probably many others) go to these events is to try out new and upcoming games. Sega brought two &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt; games, two &lt;em&gt;Persona&lt;/em&gt; games, and a &lt;em&gt;Sonic&lt;/em&gt; game. &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros. Wonder&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3&lt;/em&gt; were also present, but there was little else in terms of major studios and series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In years gone by there would be huge displays from the likes of Microsoft and EA, but with the big players preferring their own tightly-controlled showcases there was no sign of them on the floor here. Unfortunately it seems that EGX as an event may be in decline, with a lower quality offering for the admission fee. I can only hope the Eurogamer team is able to turn it around before it suffers the same fate as E3.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="yakuza" /><category term="like-a-dragon" /><category term="egx" /><category term="events" /><category term="london" /><summary type="html">I attended my first post-pandemic EGX this week in London, and while the event itself was certainly subdued compared to previous years, I was very excited to get my hands on two new entries in the Like a Dragon series ahead of their release. While both are brand new games, The Man Who Erased His Name and Infinite Wealth come from two very different angles that could be said to represent the series’ past and future. Here are my initial thoughts after trying them for myself. Like a Dragon Gaiden: The Man Who Erased His Name Staking a claim amongst the longest video game titles ever, Like a Dragon Gaiden: The Man Who Erased His Name picks up the story of fan favourite protagonist Kazuma Kiryu from where it was left off in Yakuza 6: The Song of Life. While it will be released on PlayStation 4, it is probably also the first game in the Yakuza series to be developed with the primary focus on the PlayStation 5 and Xbox Series X.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/10/like-a-dragon_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/10/like-a-dragon_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FC 24 Career Mode: How to scout and develop youth players</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/07/ea-sports-fc-24-how-to-scout-develop-youth-players" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FC 24 Career Mode&amp;#58; How to scout and develop youth players" /><published>2023-10-07T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-07T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/07/ea-sports-fc-24-how-to-scout-develop-youth-players</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/07/ea-sports-fc-24-how-to-scout-develop-youth-players">&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest joys of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/ea-sports-fc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s Career Mode is to scout the next generation of talent and nurture them until they’re world class, continuing your team’s legacy without the need for hundreds of millions of pounds of spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;366&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/B-BpWXR8fcA?si=TbsAiUg_4CzRIo-o&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s tremendously satisfying to develop young players, but a solid youth setup also helps to slow down Career Mode, maintaining a long-term challenge in a game that encourages you to buy the world’s top stars and dominate from the off. Here’s how to get started with scouting, signing, and training promising youngsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: left; margin-top: 20px; padding: 10px; background: #ffd900; width: 97%; border-radius: 5px;&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note&lt;/b&gt;: This is an updated version of &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players&quot;&gt;a previous &lt;i&gt;FIFA&lt;/i&gt; article&lt;/a&gt;. While there are &lt;i&gt;some&lt;/i&gt; new features, unfortunately Career Mode hasn't changed much since then.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hiring-and-assigning-scouts&quot;&gt;Hiring and assigning scouts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to address is the top of your youth academy funnel - namely, hiring a decent scout. Head to the youth staff page and assess your current options. The most important factors are their experience rating (reflecting how likely they are to find players) and judgement (how accurately they assess players’ abilities).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/fc-24-youth-development_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your current scouts are no good, you can spend some of your transfer budget on a new one. When you’re satisfied with their skills, you need to send them to set up a scouting network. You can choose which country they’re searching in, how long they’re there for, and select specific player traits you want them to look for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I’m biased, but I usually like to fill my team with young English players, so I send my scout out on broad, long-term assignments in England and leave him to it. If you have different priorities then you might want to mix things up with shorter searches in different countries and with different criteria and parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reviewing-scout-reports&quot;&gt;Reviewing scout reports&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a short set-up period, your scouts will begin to deliver monthly reports to your inbox. These consist of a list of players with rough estimations of their current and potential abilities (which is why the scout’s judgement rating was so important).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/fc-24-youth-development_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To filter this list down, I normally start with a baseline potential OVR rating - usually 80 if I’m managing a Premier League side, or 83 to 85 at a top team. If a player has no chance of exceeding this lower limit then it’s very unlikely that they’ll ever feature in my first team even if they develop perfectly, so I send them on their way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the upper bounds of a player’s potential are above my threshold then I turn my attention to their minimum potential. If it’s also quite high - say in the mid-70s - then I’ll recruit the youngster to see how they develop in my academy. If it’s lower, there’s a risk they’ll be a dud. I leave them on the report so my scout can take a closer look and return with an updated assessment of their potential ability next month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;managing-your-youth-squad&quot;&gt;Managing your youth squad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with scouting, you’ll receive monthly updates on your youth squad as their OVR ratings improve and their potential ability becomes more accurate. It might sound brutal, but the main purpose of this report is to check who falls short. If one of your recruits’ potential OVR falls below your minimum threshold, don’t be afraid to let them go and free up space in your youth academy. Football is a harsh world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/fc-24-youth-development_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a player progresses to an acceptable OVR rating - usually in the mid-60s, for me - and plays in a position where he’s likely to get game time, it’s time for a promotion to the senior team to continue his development with the big boys. Beware that once a player leaves the youth squad you will lose visibility of his potential, so try not to promote players while their potential OVR range is too wide if you can help it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally a player will essentially force a promotion. You’ll recieve an email telling you he’s unsettled, with a choice between adding him to your main squad or losing him. If a player is still in my academy then he usually has decent potential (otherwise he’d have been dropped), so I normally offer him a professional contract and then loan him out if he’s not quite good enough to play alongside the first team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-team-experience&quot;&gt;First-team experience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the time finally comes, either through judgement or coercion, ensure your young players get some decent game time in the first team so they can reach their full potential. I normally treat them as though they have a few more OVR points than they do, filling my bench with youngsters and subbing them on whenever I’ve established a solid lead and can risk a few mistakes from inexperience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cup matches, which are arguably less important and are more likely to be against lower-level opposition, should be a big opportunity for young players to get some minutes on the pitch. Consider starting some young talent in the cup - particularly goalkeepers, who aren’t likely candidates to be subbed on during other games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/fc-24-youth-development_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New for &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/ea-sports-fc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FC 24&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Career Mode is a feature that allows you to hire and fire coaches of varying ability. This directly influences the speed and degree to which your players improve, so ensure you have enough coaches, that they’re as skilled as possible, and they’re suited to your playstyle to help boost your youngsters’ development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when you try your best, circumstances (or the sheer number of youth players you’re farming) don’t always allow for everyone to get the minutes they need on the pitch. If a player isn’t playing regularly then don’t be afraid to send them out on loan. Incoming offers are always for loans with the option to buy and the other club will walk away if you try to negotiate, but don’t be put off by this bug - delegating the response to your director of football will allow you to renegotiate a standard loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow this pattern, exposing young players to first-team football via the bench, cup starts, and loans. You should see their OVR increase by a few points per season (you can check this on the Squad Hub screen). Eventually some will develop enough to earn starting places in your lineup, and maybe - if you’re lucky - in a few seasons’ time a new world superstar will graduate from your youth academy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="ea-sports-fc" /><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">One of the greatest joys of EA Sports FC 24’s Career Mode is to scout the next generation of talent and nurture them until they’re world class, continuing your team’s legacy without the need for hundreds of millions of pounds of spending. It’s tremendously satisfying to develop young players, but a solid youth setup also helps to slow down Career Mode, maintaining a long-term challenge in a game that encourages you to buy the world’s top stars and dominate from the off. Here’s how to get started with scouting, signing, and training promising youngsters. Note: This is an updated version of a previous FIFA article. While there are some new features, unfortunately Career Mode hasn't changed much since then.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/10/fc-24-youth-development_2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/10/fc-24-youth-development_2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">EA Sports FC 24: How to defend</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/02/ea-sports-fc-24-how-to-defend" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EA Sports FC 24&amp;#58; How to defend" /><published>2023-10-02T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/02/ea-sports-fc-24-how-to-defend</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/02/ea-sports-fc-24-how-to-defend">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2023/09/25/ea-sports-fc-24-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the new incarnation of the series previously known as &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt;, is a great football game, but one of the few issues marring the on-pitch action is how difficult it is to defend well, prevent opposition goals, and keep clean sheets. In this article I’ll share what I’ve learnt about how to keep things tight at the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;366&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OLL4YwgzD58?si=OFlyARnx2pp4FkKG&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ea-induced-difficulty&quot;&gt;EA-induced difficulty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll start by saying that EA does not make defending easy in &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/ea-sports-fc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FC 24&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and the game becomes all the more frustrating when you go on the attack and compare your own defensive woes to your AI opponent’s apparent ease at shutting you out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AI seems to make interceptions and blocks much more easily than you do, and even smaller teams can play intricate passes to cut into your box or smash long efforts into the top corner like some kind of prime Lampard-Gerrard hybrid.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an opponent tries to play balls over or through your defence to run on to, it can feel impossible to catch up once they’re past your back line, and in one-on-one situations goalkeepers are prone to sliding at attackers’ feet, leaving an open goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rethinking-your-defence&quot;&gt;Rethinking your defence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, my defensive record was initially awful in Career Mode, and for my first week with the game I’d usually conceded the most goals of any team in the league. When I analysed my mistakes I realised I’d fallen into several bad habits that were costing me, and since addressing them my defence has kept regular clean sheets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/ea-fc-defending_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before we jump in, there’s some groundwork to be done. First, make sure you’re aware which defending style you’re using in the settings. These range from Legacy to Advanced, with varying levels of control. On Legacy, for example, the player can control various aspects of pressing but has no standing tackle button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d also suggest reviewing the AI proficiency sliders for both your and your opponent’s players. Giving your goalkeeper an edge and nudging down your opponent’s passing/shooting accuracy can make &lt;em&gt;FC 24&lt;/em&gt; much more enjoyable. Some would call this cheating, but a subtle tweak via these settings is much more rewarding than dropping down a whole difficulty level and winning every week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;steps-to-more-effective-defending&quot;&gt;Steps to more effective defending&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the above factors sorted, you’ve probably configured things as well as you can. With the game side of things taken care of, it’s time to focus on the football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-set-up-your-tactics&quot;&gt;1. Set up your tactics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take advantage of &lt;em&gt;FC 24&lt;/em&gt;’s Game Plans, which enable you to swiftly change your strategy all the way from Ultra Attacking to Ultra Defensive in-game using the directional buttons. On more defensive settings, shift players’ roles (for example, move your wing-backs to full-back positions, or your CAM to CM).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/ea-fc-defending_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Altering individuals’ intructions can also help - particularly when it comes to limiting runs by more defensive-minded players with the Stay Back While Attacking option. You could also consider a change to your overall team tactics (I usually set my Ultra Defensive Game Plan to Park the Bus to keep everyone behind the ball).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-be-careful-with-your-passing&quot;&gt;2. Be careful with your passing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say attack is the best form of defence, and it’s certainly very difficult for your opponent to score when you have the ball. Think about your passes, particularly in your own half, and consider that playing a backwards pass and keeping the ball is usually preferable to losing possession to an attacker in a stupid area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-stand-off-and-slow-down&quot;&gt;3. Stand off and slow down&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My instinct from the &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; days is to sprint around and launch into tackles, pressing high to win the ball for my team. But &lt;em&gt;FC 24&lt;/em&gt; is slower and more thoughtful. Slowing down and standing off your opponent helps to conserve energy and block passing avenues, while also reducing the risk your momentum will get you turned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/ea-fc-defending_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking this one step further, you can help your team to hold their shape and mark their men more effectively by switching to a player suited to the area of the pitch the ball is currently in. For example, switching to your defensive midfielder will allow your centre back to run back and slot back into his place in the defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-dont-abuse-the-secondary-press&quot;&gt;4. Don’t abuse the secondary press&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;FC 24&lt;/em&gt; has a new secondary press feature that lets you hold R1 to bring an AI-controlled defender into play to hassle the man on the ball, and one of the worst habits I’ve apparently retained from &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;the glory days of &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is to hold this down for the bulk of my time off the ball in an attempt to squeeze them out of possession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, EA Sports’ latest release is more tactical than previous football games, and this often left the AI to exploit space created by players I’d dragged out of position. Instead, let them mark their own men, and use this option &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; sparingly, only to apply pressure while you block a pass or mark a potential recipient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;5-jockey-when-you-get-close&quot;&gt;5. Jockey when you get close&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jockeying - holding L2 to square up to the player in possession side-on - has been in &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; for years, but in &lt;em&gt;FC 24&lt;/em&gt; it seems to be more effective than ever before. Not only are you more likely to make a block or interception while jockeying, but the AI appears to behave differently, slowing down and looking backwards with its passes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So once your defender is close enough, be sure to jockey to hold up play and put yourself in a good position for a block or a standing tackle. Only go for the latter when your defender has an unobstructed path to the ball or you’ll give away a lot of free kicks, which is unnecessary when jockeying alone is such a powerful move.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="ea-sports-fc" /><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">EA Sports FC 24, the new incarnation of the series previously known as FIFA, is a great football game, but one of the few issues marring the on-pitch action is how difficult it is to defend well, prevent opposition goals, and keep clean sheets. In this article I’ll share what I’ve learnt about how to keep things tight at the back. EA-induced difficulty I’ll start by saying that EA does not make defending easy in FC 24, and the game becomes all the more frustrating when you go on the attack and compare your own defensive woes to your AI opponent’s apparent ease at shutting you out. The AI seems to make interceptions and blocks much more easily than you do, and even smaller teams can play intricate passes to cut into your box or smash long efforts into the top corner like some kind of prime Lampard-Gerrard hybrid.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/10/ea-fc-defending_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/10/ea-fc-defending_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">EA Sports FC 24 (PS5) review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/09/25/ea-sports-fc-24-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EA Sports FC 24 (PS5) review" /><published>2023-09-25T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-09-25T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/09/25/ea-sports-fc-24-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/09/25/ea-sports-fc-24-review">&lt;p&gt;In about 2011, when I was a religious &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; player and could beat just about anyone who challenged me, I played against a flatmate who decimated me. It was like a whole different game - instead of the passing game most teams played, he’d go on long runs and spam the right stick, performing unpredictable tricks and skill moves to breeze past defenders before setting up a tap-in on the edge of the six-yard box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;366&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ATW52CUvfoc?si=6UbyQHoyhP_LCMHx&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the next decade, that seemed to be the play style EA Sports was catering to with its incremental annual releases. In an era when football took off on social media, and a 15-second clip of Ronaldo or Messi (later Mbappe) pulling off an audacious flick was far more likely to go viral than any in-depth tactical analysis, football gaming followed suit, and it felt like the pace of the game would only ever increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I picked up a copy of last year’s &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA 23&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in a mid-season sale, I found they’d had a change of heart. Here was one of the weightiest, slowest football titles I’d ever played. Sure, you could still set a pacey player like Mykhailo Mudryk off on a storming run down the wing, but first you’d have to pick your way intricately through the midfield before perfectly timing and angling your pass to him. Hitting X (or A) and hoping was no longer enough, because interceptions were far more common.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One year and one title change later, and we have the clumsily named &lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt;. With my own club, Chelsea, having been through something of a transformation over the summer, the prospect of a recovery Career Mode save tempted me more than usual to buy a copy at launch, with all of my fingers and toes crossed in the hope that the developers retained its predecessor’s more thoughtful football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-solid-performance&quot;&gt;A solid performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that &lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt; takes last year’s match engine and builds on it, and if anything the on-pitch action is slower and &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; physical than it was last year. You really do need to consider the momentum of both player and ball, planning your touches ahead of time just as you would in real life. Anything less will lead to frustration as you bundle into opposition defenders and lose the ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That isn’t to say that there’s no pace to be found. If you can find the space and carve out the perfect pass to your forwards, you can set them off on sprints towards the goal line. If you have rapid players in your front line then it seems easier now to stay ahead of defenders once you beat them - it’s the difficulty in getting to that point that prevents this from becoming an overpowered way to score certain goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/ea-sports-fc-24_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an enjoyable game of football, but development always creates new frustrations. &lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt;’s goalkeepers are more frustrating than ever, and sometimes it feels like the AI is capable of pulling off superhuman saves while your own keeper flaps at just about everything. The same holds true of interceptions and tackles - any even slightly predictable pass you try to play will be cut out on higher difficulties, while most of your time off the ball is spent fighting the AI positioning to get into place for a block or challenge that would be impossible without manual movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this is probably due to &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/01/15/defence-of-scripting-football-games&quot;&gt;an underlying momentum or balancing feature&lt;/a&gt;, aimed at keeping matches balanced and interesting by aiding the weaker team. The byproduct of this is that it frequently feels like it’s as easy to beat Manchester City or Tottenham 4-0 as it is to lose by a similar margin to Brentford or Fulham. Like every year, some tinkering with the difficulty sliders is required to prevent fringe players at Premier League minnows from hitting the top corner from 35 yards every game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another small criticism, albeit one that breaks immersion, is that AI players seem &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; prone to knocking the ball metres ahead of themselves to run on to. This can work to great effect if said player is Mohammed Salah, but looks ridiculous when it’s a lower league cup opponent and it’s been happening all match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;football-20&quot;&gt;Football 2.0&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt; is a game of two halves, and its real problems become apparent when you pay attention to what happens off the pitch, away from the main action. With the departure of the FIFA licence, it feels as though EA decided that football was no longer enough and they needed to create a whole new &lt;em&gt;Rocket League&lt;/em&gt;-style sport to keep the social media generation on board post-rebranding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grass and studs and mud are still there, but while &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; used to attempt a faithful recreation of a real matchday broadcast, the authenticity is now hidden under more overlays and pop-ups than a &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-1&quot;&gt;Formula 1&lt;/a&gt; sprint race. This is all in the name of an ever-expanding feature called HyperMotion - or at least EA’s desire to show it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/ea-sports-fc-24_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While &lt;em&gt;FIFA 23&lt;/em&gt; featured HyperMotion goal replays (slow-motion replays with dramatically overlaid statistics showing the distance to goal or xG for a shot, for example), &lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt; takes it to a whole new level, and any set piece now appears to be fair game for any number of messy overlays, from attempts on goal to possession, result odds, and even player fatigue expressed as a percentage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other changes also sully EA’s once-pristine presentation and pull you out of the illusion. Match intros and lineups - once great for building the pre-game atmosphere - have been cut in favour of sweeping shots of the stadium and the players in the changing rooms. Bookings are sometimes delivered via a first-person ref cam where some of the player models look terrifying. And offside decisions are confirmed via a camera which I can only imagine is a recreation of what VAR will look like in 2050.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the quirky stuff - the weird kits, coloured lines, and so on - used to be confined to Ultimate Team, but now it feels like the entire game has been adjusted to target those with short attention spans. The impossible camera angles and “augmented reality” graphics are everywhere, and all together they only serve to make &lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt; feel less like authentic football and more like… well, a video game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problems-off-the-pitch&quot;&gt;Problems off the pitch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wholesale TikTok-ification of &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt;’s presentation would have been easier to stomach if EA had delivered significant upgrades elsewhere - specifically in Career Mode, where I spend most of my time. Unfortunately there’s little to report on here, as besides a new feature that requires to you sign coaches for your club to influence your team’s development, very little has changed for a number of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/ea-sports-fc-24_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt;’s case also isn’t helped by the fact that it generally feels much buggier than previous iterations in the series. Apparently swapping out all those &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; logos for &lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC&lt;/em&gt; ones took a lot of development time, because a lot seems to have slipped through the net. Even in just my first ten hours, I encountered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•   An in-match graphical glitch that made me thankful I don’t suffer from epilepsy&lt;br /&gt;
•   One of my defenders becoming invisible (and playing everyone onside)&lt;br /&gt;
•   Away team players on the pre-match screen dying their hair white&lt;br /&gt;
•   My team’s fans leaving the stadium early even when I’m winning 4-0&lt;br /&gt;
•   A substitute who was warming up teleporting across the touchline at half-time&lt;br /&gt;
•   Numbers being shown the wrong way round on the substitution board (still)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All things considered, &lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt; is a hard game to sum up. Typically, I might score a &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; game four out of five if it was strong on the pitch but failed to bring anything new to Career Mode, but the bugs and the overbearing cyber-football elements detract further from this year’s game in my eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully the bugs will be fixed in updates, and there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an option to turn off many of the HyperMotion overlays, but &lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt; has taken a discouraging direction and it seems faithfully recreating real-life football has tumbled down EA’s list of priorities faster than Sheffield United back to the Championship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a fantastic game of football here if you focus on what &lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt; delivers on the pitch and disregard the fluff around it, but it’s getting harder to find. It’ll be interesting to see where EA goes next, but the key to surviving the 2023/24 season will be turning HyperMotion graphics off and sticking to the gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3/5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="ea-sports-fc" /><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">In about 2011, when I was a religious FIFA player and could beat just about anyone who challenged me, I played against a flatmate who decimated me. It was like a whole different game - instead of the passing game most teams played, he’d go on long runs and spam the right stick, performing unpredictable tricks and skill moves to breeze past defenders before setting up a tap-in on the edge of the six-yard box. For the next decade, that seemed to be the play style EA Sports was catering to with its incremental annual releases. In an era when football took off on social media, and a 15-second clip of Ronaldo or Messi (later Mbappe) pulling off an audacious flick was far more likely to go viral than any in-depth tactical analysis, football gaming followed suit, and it felt like the pace of the game would only ever increase. But when I picked up a copy of last year’s FIFA 23 in a mid-season sale, I found they’d had a change of heart. Here was one of the weightiest, slowest football titles I’d ever played. Sure, you could still set a pacey player like Mykhailo Mudryk off on a storming run down the wing, but first you’d have to pick your way intricately through the midfield before perfectly timing and angling your pass to him. Hitting X (or A) and hoping was no longer enough, because interceptions were far more common.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/09/ea-sports-fc-24_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/09/ea-sports-fc-24_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Anxiety, locus of control, and gratitude</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/09/17/anxiety-locus-of-control-gratitude" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anxiety, locus of control, and gratitude" /><published>2023-09-17T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-09-17T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/09/17/anxiety-locus-of-control-directing-gratitude</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/09/17/anxiety-locus-of-control-gratitude">&lt;p&gt;One benefit of increased awareness of my emotions and their origins is that I can identify patterns that show the effectiveness (or lack thereof) of my own wellness practices. In the last month or so I spotted a link between anxiety, locus of control, and gratitude that I thought was worth sharing for the benefit of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;locus-of-control&quot;&gt;Locus of control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite blogs is that of the social psychologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://jonathanhaidt.substack.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jonathan Haidt&lt;/a&gt;, co-author of &lt;em&gt;The Coddling of the American Mind&lt;/em&gt;. His site features articles on a range of topics, from technology and social media to play during childhood, but a concept he returns to regularly is that of locus of control and its role in our mental lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As established by the psychologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Locus_of_control&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Julian Rotter&lt;/a&gt; in the 1950s, one’s locus of control can be either &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; (whereby you feel like you are the driving force in your life) or &lt;em&gt;external&lt;/em&gt; (where you feel as though you are at the mercy of external forces). &lt;a href=&quot;https://jonathanhaidt.substack.com/p/mental-health-liberal-girls&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Haidt notes&lt;/a&gt; extensive research that shows “people with an internal locus of control are happier and achieve more” and applies some interesting mappings to political perspectives and generational differences, but that’s not our focus in this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tweeted openly before about &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thestratpack/status/1696601289520460192&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;anxiety and my path out of it&lt;/a&gt;, but on considering the concept of internal and external loci of control, something suddenly clicked in my head regarding the ways I tried to nurture my own mental health, why some worked better than others, and how they nudged my own instincts on determinism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-gratitude-paradox&quot;&gt;The gratitude paradox&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point in my life I couldn’t see a future at all. I was working in a career with low pay and little chance of progression, and things like home ownership appeared to be out of the question for life. Anxiety wasn’t an issue. I had little to win or lose, so my aim was just to grab whatever enjoyable experiences I could along the journey.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might expect my evential move to a more lucrative profession to have brought greater stability, but along with the imposter syndrome that comes with a career change, a panic set in that this was possibly my only shot at self-determination, and if circumstances changed I might lose all that potential and sink back down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to improve my mindset by practicing gratitude, noting how nice it was to have a flat of my own and to enjoy the taste of my home cooking, but running contrary to my expectations this actually introduced &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; worry. As I tried to appreciate those small pleasures, my thoughts turned to what might happen if I &lt;em&gt;lost&lt;/em&gt; those things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;intrinsic-gratitude&quot;&gt;Intrinsic gratitude&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, I’ve found a new perspective that harnesses the benefits of an internal of locus of control to make gratitude work for me as a force for calm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than focusing on things around me, I’ve begun to practice gratitude more for &lt;em&gt;my intrinsic qualities&lt;/em&gt; - the rationality, determination, and so on that allow me to do things like completing complex technical work, &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/09/03/how-to-run-half-marathon-better&quot;&gt;running half marathons&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/09/10/starfield-searching-for-god&quot;&gt;making 15-minute videos about the religious connotations of a video game&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These characteristics increase the likelihood that I will thrive whatever life throws at me, and will hopefully grant me the ability to carve out a living and an intellectual life for myself regardless of the external circumstances I have to contend with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, my gratitude practice has become a way of reinforcing an internal locus of control and building confidence that I’ll have what it takes to handle any adversity that might come my way in future. To paraphrase the stoics, I can’t control the world, but I can control my reaction to it, and it’s easier to find comfort when I believe that reaction will be strong enough to overcome nearly any challenge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="psychology" /><category term="philosophy" /><summary type="html">One benefit of increased awareness of my emotions and their origins is that I can identify patterns that show the effectiveness (or lack thereof) of my own wellness practices. In the last month or so I spotted a link between anxiety, locus of control, and gratitude that I thought was worth sharing for the benefit of others. Locus of control One of my favourite blogs is that of the social psychologist Jonathan Haidt, co-author of The Coddling of the American Mind. His site features articles on a range of topics, from technology and social media to play during childhood, but a concept he returns to regularly is that of locus of control and its role in our mental lives. As established by the psychologist Julian Rotter in the 1950s, one’s locus of control can be either internal (whereby you feel like you are the driving force in your life) or external (where you feel as though you are at the mercy of external forces). Haidt notes extensive research that shows “people with an internal locus of control are happier and achieve more” and applies some interesting mappings to political perspectives and generational differences, but that’s not our focus in this article. I’ve tweeted openly before about anxiety and my path out of it, but on considering the concept of internal and external loci of control, something suddenly clicked in my head regarding the ways I tried to nurture my own mental health, why some worked better than others, and how they nudged my own instincts on determinism. The gratitude paradox At one point in my life I couldn’t see a future at all. I was working in a career with low pay and little chance of progression, and things like home ownership appeared to be out of the question for life. Anxiety wasn’t an issue. I had little to win or lose, so my aim was just to grab whatever enjoyable experiences I could along the journey.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>