<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-06T20:04:52+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Strat Packer’s blog</title><subtitle>Creative and intellectual output beyond the realm of my day job</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Concord’s failure should be a wake-up call for the video game industry</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/06/concord-live-service-fail" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Concord's failure should be a wake-up call for the video game industry" /><published>2024-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/06/concord-live-service-fail</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="concord" /><category term="playstation" /><category term="industry" /><summary type="html">What a week it’s been in the video game industry! We’ve witnessed one of the most remarkable failures ever, as Concord - the Firewalk Studios-developed live service game into which Sony had invested so much in the hope it would be the next big thing - was shut down after just two weeks in operation. Much of the criticism of the title was written off by its supporters and the press as “hate”, but this story is actually a culmination of a number of factors that should not be swept under the carpet. If they are, then game developers and publishers might miss the important lessons that should be learnt from Concord’s demise.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/concord_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/concord_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Year In Between - my debut novel is available now!</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/02/the-year-in-between-novel" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Year In Between - my debut novel is available now!" /><published>2024-08-26T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-26T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/02/the-year-in-between-novel</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="the-year-in-between" /><category term="writing" /><category term="books" /><summary type="html">My first ever novel, The Year In Between, is now available for purchase! The book was a labour of love that took hundreds of hours to finish, but I’m aware that competition is fierce for your hard-earned money and the limited space on your bookshelf, so I’ve put together a short article to give you a better idea of the themes it explores and what to expect should you choose to read it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/the-year-in-between_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/the-year-in-between_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GTA IV’s Liberty City is still the best virtual city ever made</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/08/25/grand-theft-auto-iv-liberty-city" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTA IV's Liberty City is still the best virtual city ever made" /><published>2024-08-25T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-25T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/08/25/grand-theft-auto-iv-liberty-city</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="grand-theft-auto" /><category term="retro" /><summary type="html">In its review upon the game’s release in 2008, GamesRadar called Liberty City “the biggest reason to delve into GTA IV”. Its writers said it was “easily 100 times more detailed” than the map of its predecessor, Grand Theft Auto: San Andreas, concluding that altogether, the city was “convincingly like the real thing”. GTA IV tells story of Niko Bellic, but Liberty City has a life of its own It truly was like nothing we’d ever seen. Spanning three islands totalling just over six square miles, GTA IV’s map was nowhere near as expansive as the region depicted by Rockstar’s 2004 title, but it was perhaps the densest video game setting ever built in terms of population and detail - and certainly in character. For players focused on the story and the violence, many of the small touches that made Liberty City such a great virtual city probably passed by unnoticed. But even then, they undoubtedly felt that what they were playing was a premium product, even if they didn’t know why. My goal in this article is to pick apart those minutae that make GTA IV’s world such a compelling imitiation of a real-life city.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/gta-iv_9.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/gta-iv_9.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Notice anything different?</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/08/25/notice-anything-different" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notice anything different?" /><published>2024-08-25T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-25T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/08/25/notice-anything-different</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">🎨 Notice anything different? In preparation for some big upcoming news, I’ve given my website a lick of paint. I’m hoping the new design will make it easier to find the best articles (as well as just generally looking cooler). Feel free to drop me an email if you have any ideas to make it even better.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Heartbound: An intriguing Early Access indie game about life itself</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/08/03/heartbound-preview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heartbound&amp;#58; An intriguing Early Access indie game about life itself" /><published>2024-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/08/03/heartbound-preview</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="heartbound" /><category term="indie" /><summary type="html">How does your experience of a game change if you can listen to its developer talk for hours every day? That’s the rather unusual question presented by Heartbound, an Early Access game whose creator is also a streamer. But whether you’ve caught Thor online or not, the indie game has plenty of intrigue to unpack in its own right. Heartbound has been a while in the making. The first version of the indie game was made available under Steam’s Early Access programme in December 2018, and its ironically-named developer Pirate Software - fronted by Jason Thor Hall - has been adding content as it’s become ready ever since. As of August 2024, the game currently consists of three of a planned five segments, one of which does not yet have an ending, and which take about three hours to play through altogether. Unusually, Thor streams his work on Twitch and YouTube, where he has a combined 3 million followers at the time of writing. There aren’t many games whose developers discuss their design philosophy online for hours every day, and it makes for a unique experience when playing the portion of the game that is currently available.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/heartbound_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/heartbound_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Japan: Presence and attention to detail</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/05/12/japan-presence-attention-to-detail" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Japan&amp;#58; Presence and attention to detail" /><published>2024-05-12T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-12T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/05/12/japan-presence-pride-attention-to-detail</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="travel" /><category term="japan" /><category term="philosophy" /><summary type="html">A holiday brings a chance to unwind, time to focus on things beyond day-to-day life, and often an opportunity to take in another culture. Combined, these factors can produce a unique state of mind, and I find that one of the most difficult parts of any trip where it arises is to properly observe and harness the new perspective that brings before it disappears once again under the tide of work and life admin. That’s why I’m working through the jet lag to type this out before the weekend is through. The trip itself – another couple of weeks in Japan – was fast-paced and thoroughly enjoyable. I spent my time between the bustle of Tokyo and more rural parts of Hokkaido, packing in as much good food and karaoke as possible along the way. But wherever I am in Japan, my eye is always drawn back to the attention to detail and earnestness ingrained in its culture. This is demonstrated in everything from an elaborate shop window display to consideration for others in public spaces. Following my last visit, I wrote about the hospitality and curiosity of those I met on my travels. My return served as something of a follow-up meditation session, and offered a chance to further concentrate and expand upon those thoughts, and properly consider what use they might be to me in my regular life.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/japan_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/japan_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes from a brief stay in New York</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/04/16/notes-brief-stay-new-york-ny" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes from a brief stay in New York" /><published>2024-04-16T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/04/16/notes-brief-stay-new-york-ny</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="travel" /><category term="usa" /><summary type="html">I’m used to big cities. I’ve lived in London for more than a decade and have spent time in various European capitals, Tokyo, Abu Dhabi, Las Vegas, and Austin. But as Manhattan emerged over the horizon on the cab ride from JFK Airport, I realised that none of these had prepared me for New York City, where the endless looming towers made each street feel as enclosed as the Midtown Tunnel. While New York has a heavy media presence - Friends, Seinfeld, Annie Hall, Ghostbusters, and so on - my strongest impression of the city came from its gritty representation in Grand Theft Auto IV. Liberty City seemed an impossible feat in 2008, and served as a kind of virtual tourist experience to escape the confines of my hometown. But returning to it after I got home, it was as though its scale had shrunk significantly while I was away, and it felt more game-like than ever before. The reason for this is that real-life Manhattan is not only bigger than I expected vertically, but also has a gigantic footprint. On my first full day, I decided to walk from where I was staying in the Financial District up to Central Park via various landmarks - what turned out to be nearly five miles through bustling, diverse districts that at once felt very similar to London and unmistakably foreign. Despite capturing the vibe well, Rockstar’s approximation feels like a small village by comparison.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/new-york_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/new-york_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Stellar Blade is a challenging and stylistic gaming nostalgia trip</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/04/01/stellar-blade-demo-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stellar Blade is a challenging and stylistic gaming nostalgia trip" /><published>2024-04-01T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-01T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/04/01/stellar-blade-demo-review</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="stellar-blade" /><category term="industry" /><summary type="html">The Stellar Blade demo is here! There are many adjectives that could be applied to Level Up’s much-discussed PlayStation 5 exclusive - beautiful, unique, gruesome, and challenging, to name a few - but for me, more than anything else, the upcoming action-adventure title is a nostalgia trip to previous eras of gaming. Back in the early 2000s, when I was a child, I didn’t have much of my own money for games. My purchases were gated by my parents, who knew nearly nothing about what was worth paying for, and my only gauge of quality was a review in the odd gaming magazine. Subsequently, box art and blurbs came into play, and there were some real wildcards in my collection that I asked for purely on a whim. Sometimes this paid off - games like Operation: WinBack and King of Bowling 2 were off the beaten path, hardly classics, but a lot of fun with friends. It was this blind experimentation that also led me to more praised games that I just hadn’t heard of through friends, like Smuggler’s Run and early Final Fantasy entries. Of course, other times I happened across the occasional stinker, but these were few and far between, and the sunk cost meant I stuck with most of my purchases anyway.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/stellar-blade_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/stellar-blade_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Apple Watch Series 8 review: You’ll get it when you get one</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/03/10/apple-watch-series-8-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apple Watch Series 8 review&amp;#58; You'll get it when you get one" /><published>2024-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/03/10/apple-watch-series-8-review</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="reviews" /><category term="apple" /><category term="wearables" /><category term="running" /><summary type="html">I can’t remember a technology product I’ve been so undecided on for so long as the Apple Watch. Since the first generation launched in 2015, I’ve watched Apple’s iteration from afar, always unsure as to whether a smartwatch could ever provide enough benefit to warrant a price tag of at least a few hundred pounds. A lot of it came down to a question of intrusion - if I’ve been working to reduce the number of notifications interrupting my life, why would I want them strapped to my wrist? But with certain changes approaching in my life that will put strain on my time management, I decided to give the Apple Watch a go to reduce the number of times I need to pick up my phone, while implementing measures to limit distractions. First, I would keep the number of notifications pushed to the watch to a minimum, and second, I would make much better use of Siri and the Shortcuts app to make it easier to retrieve the information I need most often without opening any apps.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/apple-watch_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/apple-watch_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Sims (PC) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/02/11/the-sims-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sims (PC) retrospective" /><published>2024-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/02/11/the-sims-retrospective</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="the-sims" /><category term="strategy" /><category term="simulation" /><category term="retro" /><summary type="html">If you think of The Sims today, you’ll likely think of the EA money printing machine and its endless conveyor belt of expansion and stuff packs. The modern games have a cutesy, sanitised face, and the bright marketing material reflects their apparent positioning as a platform for teenage girls to build their dream homes and lifestyles, rather than a semi-accurate and challenging simulation of life’s ups and downs. That wasn’t always the case. When the original game was released in 2000, it did contain some humour (especially through Maxis’s renowned flavour text) but the game itself was an attempt to explore social and architectural themes through the most realistic recreation of life possible with the technology of the time – and as a result of its limitations, one that often strays into unsettling territory.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/the-sims_4.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/the-sims_4.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>