<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-15T11:29:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">In defence of scripting in football games</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/15/defence-of-scripting-football-games" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In defence of scripting in football games" /><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/15/defence-of-scripting-football-games</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/15/defence-of-scripting-football-games">&lt;p&gt;Spend any length of time reading online forums for football games and you’ll come across complaints about “scripting” - the alleged way games like &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; artificially infuence games to create drama. This quirk of games’ design and programming is always portrayed in a negative light, and often rightly so, but I’d like to make a case for why it makes sense and improves the gameplay experience in certain circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-scripting&quot;&gt;What is scripting?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the critics, “scripting” - sometimes also referred to as “momentum” - is a perversion of the way football games should play. Unlike real football, &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; matches are under the complete control of a match engine, and by extension, the developers. And there have been accusations for years that EA Sports (and Konami, before &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/01/efootball-2022-first-impressions&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;eFootball&lt;/em&gt; killed the &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; series&lt;/a&gt;) has abused this power to create as much drama as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To those who are on the lookout for potential foul play, this invisible hand makes itself known in semi-predictable ways, usually to give teams suffering heavy losses a fighting chance or to prevent the player team from running away with every match, or the league title. Some of the most common complaints allege that scripting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Makes goals easier for both teams to score in the final minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Causes shots to hit the post, passes to go off course, etc. when the game doesn’t “want” the player to win the game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grants even the weakest opponents - and in particular goalkeepers - superstar skills if the game favours them in the match&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensures Career Mode rivals win the player wins, draws when the player draws, etc. to keep the title race as close as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many players say the biggest giveaway that scripting has taken effect is when one team has far more possession and shots on goal but fails to win. This has become something of a meme, particularly in &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/01/25/football-manager-addictive-spreadsheet/&quot;&gt;the stats-obsessed world of &lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and was probably at least partly responsible for the emergence of the expected goals (xG) metric in the real game.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of this may be coincidence, of course, and the big teams do suffer these frustrating matches in the Premier League and beyond. EA has denied that it scripting exists in &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; (as far as I know, Konami has never spoken on the issue), so it could be that what is observed is not the result of an algorithm designed to control the outcome of matches, and instead a culmunation of all the systems that simulate form, fatigue, skills, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the frequency of these events has convinced some players that scripting exists. What would be the developers’ motive to implement it, you might ask? The purported answer is that the added drama makes the game more emotional and therefore more addictive, as well as encouraging less skilled players by ensuring they always have a chance at securing a freak win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody except the developers knows whether scripting really exists in any given game, or to what level it influences matches, but I’ve seen enough evidence in my own play to suspect it’s there in some form. The assumption I’m never sure about, however, is that a “pure” football game would play better. The scripting rumours have persisted in one form or another since the mid-2000s, and there have been &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;some great football games&lt;/a&gt; in that time. So when does it work and when does it not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;when-scripting-works&quot;&gt;When scripting works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I will concede that scripting would be very frustrating in online game modes, where you usually only play each opponent once and therefore don’t have a chance for the luck to level out. It would also affect online rankings, promotion and relegation from divisions, and so on. It would be even worse if it spanned to modes where money is involved, but we have at least had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2021-03-03-fifa-scripting-lawsuit-withdrawn-after-ea-provides-plaintiffs-with-detailed-technical-information-and-access-to-speak-with-our-engineers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;confirmation from EA that there is no scripting in Ultimate Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But offline, I believe it can actually create a more enjoyable experience. This is certainly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the case my Chelsea side visit Burnley and lose to two wonder goals, but it can certainly liven up games against weaker teams. Statistically you’d expect the big club to pervail comfortably, but that’s not always the case in real life and constant 3-0 wins would get boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my best &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; games have been those where everything seems to be going the opposition’s way. When I play Southampton at home and they park the bus I can spend nearly the whole game trying to pick apart the AI’s defence, their goalkeeper performing all kinds of acrobatics when I get the odd shot away. When a chance falls to my striker with two minutes to go I expect him to miss because he’s barely been able to control the ball for 88 minutes, but when the ball hits the back of the net and secures the 1-0 win, that hard-fought triumph is one of the best feelings in the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “scripting” - or at least the randomised part of the game that leads people to &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; there is scripting - leads to added challenge and interesting stories in games that might have been nothing but boring domination. This reflects real life matches, when big teams have off days against bottom-of-the-table sides using very defensive setups, and really adds tension to the in-game title battle when I know City and Liverpool are winning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, scripting or not, unpredictability is what makes football the world’s favourite sport and what makes football games worth playing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="pes" /><category term="football" /><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">Spend any length of time reading online forums for football games and you’ll come across complaints about “scripting” - the alleged way games like FIFA and PES artificially infuence games to create drama. This quirk of games’ design and programming is always portrayed in a negative light, and often rightly so, but I’d like to make a case for why it makes sense and improves the gameplay experience in certain circumstances. What is scripting? According to the critics, “scripting” - sometimes also referred to as “momentum” - is a perversion of the way football games should play. Unlike real football, FIFA matches are under the complete control of a match engine, and by extension, the developers. And there have been accusations for years that EA Sports (and Konami, before eFootball killed the PES series) has abused this power to create as much drama as possible. To those who are on the lookout for potential foul play, this invisible hand makes itself known in semi-predictable ways, usually to give teams suffering heavy losses a fighting chance or to prevent the player team from running away with every match, or the league title. Some of the most common complaints allege that scripting: Makes goals easier for both teams to score in the final minutes Causes shots to hit the post, passes to go off course, etc. when the game doesn’t “want” the player to win the game Grants even the weakest opponents - and in particular goalkeepers - superstar skills if the game favours them in the match Ensures Career Mode rivals win the player wins, draws when the player draws, etc. to keep the title race as close as possible Many players say the biggest giveaway that scripting has taken effect is when one team has far more possession and shots on goal but fails to win. This has become something of a meme, particularly in the stats-obsessed world of Football Manager, and was probably at least partly responsible for the emergence of the expected goals (xG) metric in the real game.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIFA is my new year’s resolution (kind of)</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/08/fifa-new-years-resolution" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA is my new year's resolution &amp;#40;kind of&amp;#41;" /><published>2022-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/08/fifa-new-years-resolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/08/fifa-new-years-resolution">&lt;p&gt;There’s an episode of &lt;em&gt;South Park&lt;/em&gt; that first aired about a decade ago where Stan wakes up one day and everything is shit. The food he eats is shit. The chatter on the radio is shit. The new films at the cinema are shit. Everything he used to like is at best unremarkable and at worst unforgivably flawed. He has grown up, and in doing so has turned into a cynic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently realised that was what I had become in recent years. A duo of experience (a sense of having seen it all before) and jadedness (thanks in large part to online commenters finding fault in just about everything) meant I couldn’t enjoy a lot of things I used to. My favourite band’s latest album wasn’t a patch on their output in the early 2000s, and new games were full of microtransactions and soulless compared to classics from years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cutting-out-the-noise&quot;&gt;Cutting out the noise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 2022, I’ve decided to put a stop to this. I’m not the complete isolation “cabin in the woods” type, but I do believe that one of the pitfalls of the internet age is that we’re exposed to a deluge of opinion on just about everything. If you and a couple of your friends like a new TV series then that’s no longer enough - you’ll also feel inclined to seek out its subreddit and pore over the world’s thoughts on each episode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this works as intended, it’s amazing. We get fruitful discussions with people all over the place about interests that might not be popular where we’re from. When it doesn’t, we find ourselves second guessing everything we like, wondering what flaw a hypothetical cynic might point out. When that second mindset takes hold it becomes very difficult to enjoy anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; series, for example. The internet’s view of the games is that they change very little each year, lure kids into what are at best frivolous microtransactions and at worst casino-emulating lootboxes, and are plagued with bugs and scripted results. With all that in mind, why bother playing?&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;giving-games-a-chance&quot;&gt;Giving games a chance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I fancied playing a football game, and given that &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/01/efootball-2022-first-impressions&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;eFootball&lt;/em&gt; has effectively killed the &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; series&lt;/a&gt;, I switched on a digital copy of &lt;em&gt;FIFA 20&lt;/em&gt; that I picked up for about £5 in a sale last year to give it another go. Just as importantly, I made a conscious effort to make my mind a clean slate, free of past judgements and crticisms I’d read about the series. I decided I would judge it only by what was directly in front of me on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having played nearly a season’s worth of Career Mode in the last week, I can say that &lt;em&gt;FIFA 20&lt;/em&gt; is a solid football game. It looks great - the stadiums in particular look just like their real-world counterparts. The animations are as slick as you like. The opponents are challenging and varied, and some of my favourite matches are when teams come to Stamford Bridge to park the bus and I have to unpick their defences. And the whole thing has a lot of fanfare about it. &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; feels connected to the wider football world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Games are never perfect, and this is no exception - including in some of the ways commonly pointed out online. Career Mode itself does enough, but hasn’t substantially changed in years. Sometimes players don’t react the way you want or expect them to. And every so often you find yourself in a game where your relegation fodder opponents play like prime Barcelona and you’re in for a grind because the game &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; you to lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while I might previously have tuned out or lost interest, I now look past these minor annoyances and consider the sum of the game. I think about some of the retro games I’ve played - &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;even all-time classics like &lt;em&gt;PES5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - and know they also had flaws that were overlooked because I was simply having too much fun. Then I stop analysing everything, focus on the game, and try to let the atmosphere absorb me as I push for the next goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lifes-too-short-not-to-have-fun&quot;&gt;Life’s too short not to have fun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the attitude I’m trying to keep with me in 2022. Whether it’s in gaming, film, television, music - even politics - I’m going to try to cut myself off from the online commentary, consume media and make my own mind up before I read about anything, and hopefully find more fun and enjoyment than I have for some without the internet spoiling everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not about putting up with bad games or manipulative practices. I’ll still call out features I think could be improved and content I think should have been included in the box price. But I want my enjoyment or disappointment with each game to come from my personal preferences and judgements - not what somebody else got stuck in my head before I even started playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So happy new year to everybody who has stumbled upon &lt;em&gt;The Strat Pack&lt;/em&gt;! I hope you have a fantastic 2022 and discover a ton of things you love. And if you find any gems you think I’d like, please do share them with me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">There’s an episode of South Park that first aired about a decade ago where Stan wakes up one day and everything is shit. The food he eats is shit. The chatter on the radio is shit. The new films at the cinema are shit. Everything he used to like is at best unremarkable and at worst unforgivably flawed. He has grown up, and in doing so has turned into a cynic. I recently realised that was what I had become in recent years. A duo of experience (a sense of having seen it all before) and jadedness (thanks in large part to online commenters finding fault in just about everything) meant I couldn’t enjoy a lot of things I used to. My favourite band’s latest album wasn’t a patch on their output in the early 2000s, and new games were full of microtransactions and soulless compared to classics from years ago. Cutting out the noise For 2022, I’ve decided to put a stop to this. I’m not the complete isolation “cabin in the woods” type, but I do believe that one of the pitfalls of the internet age is that we’re exposed to a deluge of opinion on just about everything. If you and a couple of your friends like a new TV series then that’s no longer enough - you’ll also feel inclined to seek out its subreddit and pore over the world’s thoughts on each episode. When this works as intended, it’s amazing. We get fruitful discussions with people all over the place about interests that might not be popular where we’re from. When it doesn’t, we find ourselves second guessing everything we like, wondering what flaw a hypothetical cynic might point out. When that second mindset takes hold it becomes very difficult to enjoy anything. Take the FIFA series, for example. The internet’s view of the games is that they change very little each year, lure kids into what are at best frivolous microtransactions and at worst casino-emulating lootboxes, and are plagued with bugs and scripted results. With all that in mind, why bother playing?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Classic Splinter Cell is back after a 15-year hiatus!</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/18/splinter-cell-remake" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Classic Splinter Cell is back after a 15-year hiatus!" /><published>2021-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/18/splinter-cell-remake</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/18/splinter-cell-remake">&lt;p&gt;Ubisoft has announced that it’s working on a &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake! This Christmas miracle landed on my desk just in time for the last article of the year, so join me one last time in 2021 as we run through what we know (and what we don’t) about this long-awaited revival of a beloved series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a long time coming. There hasn’t been a &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; game at all since 2013’s &lt;em&gt;Blacklist&lt;/em&gt;, and many fans (myself included) feel there hasn’t been an entry that has respected the series’ stealth ethos in more than 15 years. After all that time, many thought that Sam Fisher might never return to the shadows, and so many rumours circulated over the years that it became easy to dismiss any talk of a new game instantly. But here we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/splinter-cell_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you believe the people in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HH1_ZCSf_HY&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the promotional YouTube video&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; is valued as the series that defined what Ubisoft could make - and could be - at a time when it was largely known for &lt;em&gt;Rayman&lt;/em&gt;. Fast forward to 2021 and you might be a little nervous, as the company is now known for churning out regular &lt;em&gt;Assassin’s Creed&lt;/em&gt; games and its recent player-angering announcement that it would be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pcgamer.com/ubisofts-nft-scheme-criticized-as-useless-costly-ecologically-mortifying-by-french-trade-union/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;introducing NFTs to some of its upcoming titles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, all the noises coming from the developers in the video make it sound like they understand and cherish what made &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; special. All the key elements - the importance of light and shadow, the little details like realistic bullet holes in fish tanks, and of course Sam’s signature night vision and infrared goggles - are discussed. The team also note the cinematic nature of the game and its story (although there’s been no word yet on whether fan favourite Michael Ironside will reprise the lead role or not).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-do-we-know&quot;&gt;What do we know?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But really, we currently know very little about the new &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake. After dissecting the video and &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ubisoft.com/en-us/article/4adJLuhgYrPboHAPRfK7Oz/splinter-cell-remake-begins-development-at-ubisoft-toronto&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the accompanying Ubisoft press release&lt;/a&gt;, I can say only the following for certain (as far as anything is certain in gaming):&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The remake is being developed by Ubisoft Toronto and is in “the earliest stages of development”, so don’t expect it any time soon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game is being rebuilt using the Snowdrop engine, which is the same one used by Ubisoft’s upcoming &lt;em&gt;Avatar&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; games&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many of the team are “stealth purists” who worked on earlier &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; games and want to their “spirit” to “remain intact”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game will remain linear, which hopefully means &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; will avoid the curse of Ubisoft’s frequently bland open-world collectathons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unlike more recent games in the series, the remake will reward players who play tactically with the objective to “be a ghost”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The remake will receive a visual upgrade with possible innovation in animation, AI, and audio - Ubisoft says this will deliver “the spirit of the old with the comfort of the new”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in summary: not much. We can essentially say that Ubisoft is working on a &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake that will be available at some point in the distant future and will bear some level of resemblance to the older games in the series, but details are certainly very thin on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cautious-optimism&quot;&gt;Cautious optimism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s probably too early to get excited, but as somebody who’s been waiting for a “real” &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; game since 2006’s &lt;em&gt;Double Agent&lt;/em&gt; (or 2005’s &lt;em&gt;Chaos Theory&lt;/em&gt;, if we’re being less generous) it’s very difficult not to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the unease underlying any optimism about the &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake is necessary because of how much the games industry has changed since the first game’s release in 2002. New entries in beloved series are launched as £60 microtransaction shopfronts, single player campaigns bizarrely require internet connections, and companies that always have their sights set on the next trendy buzzword now see NFTs as their next big moneymaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/splinter-cell_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent example of a rerelease gone wrong was &lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto Trilogy - The Definitive Edition&lt;/em&gt;, which initially looked like some easy fan service to restore some old favourites but turned awry when Rockstar delivered an often ugly, glitchy mess for the full retail price of a brand new game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake falter in a similar way? For now I can take some comfort in the developers’ words and the fact that this appears to be a full remake (unlike &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt;, which was only a remaster), but we’ll only find out for sure as we get more details, gameplay videos, and eventually get our hands on the full game. It’s going to be a long wait for sure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="splinter-cell" /><category term="stealth" /><summary type="html">Ubisoft has announced that it’s working on a Splinter Cell remake! This Christmas miracle landed on my desk just in time for the last article of the year, so join me one last time in 2021 as we run through what we know (and what we don’t) about this long-awaited revival of a beloved series. It’s been a long time coming. There hasn’t been a Splinter Cell game at all since 2013’s Blacklist, and many fans (myself included) feel there hasn’t been an entry that has respected the series’ stealth ethos in more than 15 years. After all that time, many thought that Sam Fisher might never return to the shadows, and so many rumours circulated over the years that it became easy to dismiss any talk of a new game instantly. But here we are. If you believe the people in the promotional YouTube video, Splinter Cell is valued as the series that defined what Ubisoft could make - and could be - at a time when it was largely known for Rayman. Fast forward to 2021 and you might be a little nervous, as the company is now known for churning out regular Assassin’s Creed games and its recent player-angering announcement that it would be introducing NFTs to some of its upcoming titles. Still, all the noises coming from the developers in the video make it sound like they understand and cherish what made Splinter Cell special. All the key elements - the importance of light and shadow, the little details like realistic bullet holes in fish tanks, and of course Sam’s signature night vision and infrared goggles - are discussed. The team also note the cinematic nature of the game and its story (although there’s been no word yet on whether fan favourite Michael Ironside will reprise the lead role or not). What do we know? But really, we currently know very little about the new Splinter Cell remake. After dissecting the video and the accompanying Ubisoft press release, I can say only the following for certain (as far as anything is certain in gaming):</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/splinter-cell_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/splinter-cell_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">You’re in the zone until you’re not</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/12/youre-in-the-zone-until-youre-not" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You're in the zone until you're not" /><published>2021-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/12/youre-in-the-zone-until-youre-not</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/12/youre-in-the-zone-until-youre-not">&lt;p&gt;Flow is a weird thing, all inconsistent and unpredictable. When I go to play a video game, one of two things can happen - either I will bounce straight off it almost immediately, or I’ll become completely immersed and play for hours and hours over a period of weeks before eventually burning out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent examples of games that haven’t properly captured my attention include &lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/the-sims&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I’m sure they’re high-quality games, but they just didn’t grip me. And because they haven’t proven themselves to me in that way yet, I don’t know if they ever will. Meanwhile, I can go months without getting into &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/01/25/football-manager-addictive-spreadsheet/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Fallout 4&lt;/em&gt; and suddenly something will click and I’ll be sucked in all over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/verstappen-cc.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-flow-state&quot;&gt;The flow state&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is it that special place where a game keeps calling you back? Where you think about it when you’re not playing? I feel like it’s the same thing as flow, which is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;described by Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A flow state… is the mental state in which a person performing some activity is fully immersed in a feeling of energised focus, full involvement, and enjoyment in the process of the activity. In essence, flow is characterised by the complete absorption in what one does, and a resulting transformation in one’s sense of time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got thinking about this after seeing several examples of flow in action:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/10/running-formula-1-for-your-feet&quot;&gt;When I go running&lt;/a&gt;, sometimes I’m on complete autopilot, while other times I really feel the strain of each metre I cover.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been picking up my guitar more often recently. Sometimes I can play for hours and things just feel and sound right, but sometimes my timing and tone feels a little off no matter what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In sport, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/azzEnM6-Isk?t=295&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Max Verstappen’s almost-perfect qualifying lap&lt;/a&gt; at the Saudi Arabian Grand Prix, in which he appeared to be in a supreme flow state because colliding with a barrier on the final corner.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I described earlier in the article, my personal experience is that this phenomenon can also apply to gaming, both for the esports elites and for the casual gamer who can’t stop playing a title they’re hooked on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-into-the-zone&quot;&gt;Getting into the zone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what puts you “in the zone”? For me, a flow state sits on the border between comfort and discomfort. If a task is too easy then it is mundane. If it is too difficult then I may get frustrated or feel I’m not making progress and give up. In between, where an activity is challenging enough to keep me engrossed but easy enough that I feel like I’m achieving something, is where the best games keep me coming back for session after session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/transport-fever&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transport Fever 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. When I first picked it up I was playing it for weeks, battling to turn a profit on my transportation empire. But as I became more experienced with the game I developed a reliable strategy to repay the initial loan and build a functioning network. At this point the game became less challenging and it didn’t hold my attention as well as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tag/racing&quot;&gt;Racing games&lt;/a&gt; - most recently for me &lt;em&gt;Assetto Corsa&lt;/em&gt; - are also a good example of this theory in action. When I first play a new motorsport game, one of the key tasks is to finetune the AI until it provides just enough challenge and I am not regularly finishing either first or last. It’s a tricky balancing act, and when I get it right I can drive consecutive endurance races for a while. However, if I stop playing the game for long enough for any reason, my driving skills fade slightly, the game gets harder, and it’s more difficult to get back into because losing all the time is frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enabling-flow-with-game-design&quot;&gt;Enabling flow with game design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can this teach us about game design? If enabling a flow state is the way to keep players playing, this seems to leave devs with two options…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is to finetune difficulty to a level where a specific group of players find their zone. An example of this is the Amiga classic &lt;em&gt;Deluxe Galaga&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/11/20/pi-hut-retro-gaming-kit-retropie&quot;&gt;which I recently wrote about&lt;/a&gt; - you can’t change the difficulty and must raise your game to the challenge. This approach is less common in modern day gaming, probably because publishers want games to make as much money as possible, and setting the bar too high may alienate less skilled players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other option is to give the players the toolbox required to build their own perfect challenge. The AI ability and aggression sliders in most modern racing games are an example of this, as is the multitude of self-imposed challenges possible (and cheats available) in a sandbox game like &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;. However, the downside of this approach is that the player must invest a chunk of time to find the right balance for their ability, and less committed players may drop off before they find their own personal sweet spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s for more intelligent and serious minds than mine to decide what is the best answer for any particular game, but personally I vastly prefer the latter option. Not only does the sandbox approach let me tweak the game to the perfect level to induce my own flow state, but it also lets me adjust it for other states - if I’m tired, for example, or just want to experiment with the game’s sandbox rather than seeking victory or achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo © &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/79618484@N02/48733228773&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Interceptor73&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/?ref=ccsearch&amp;amp;atype=rich&quot;&gt;CC BY 2.0&lt;/a&gt;). Cropped.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">Flow is a weird thing, all inconsistent and unpredictable. When I go to play a video game, one of two things can happen - either I will bounce straight off it almost immediately, or I’ll become completely immersed and play for hours and hours over a period of weeks before eventually burning out. Recent examples of games that haven’t properly captured my attention include Project Zomboid and The Sims 4. I’m sure they’re high-quality games, but they just didn’t grip me. And because they haven’t proven themselves to me in that way yet, I don’t know if they ever will. Meanwhile, I can go months without getting into Football Manager or Fallout 4 and suddenly something will click and I’ll be sucked in all over again. The flow state What is it that special place where a game keeps calling you back? Where you think about it when you’re not playing? I feel like it’s the same thing as flow, which is described by Wikipedia as follows. “A flow state… is the mental state in which a person performing some activity is fully immersed in a feeling of energised focus, full involvement, and enjoyment in the process of the activity. In essence, flow is characterised by the complete absorption in what one does, and a resulting transformation in one’s sense of time.” I got thinking about this after seeing several examples of flow in action: When I go running, sometimes I’m on complete autopilot, while other times I really feel the strain of each metre I cover. I’ve been picking up my guitar more often recently. Sometimes I can play for hours and things just feel and sound right, but sometimes my timing and tone feels a little off no matter what I do. In sport, see Max Verstappen’s almost-perfect qualifying lap at the Saudi Arabian Grand Prix, in which he appeared to be in a supreme flow state because colliding with a barrier on the final corner.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/verstappen-cc.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/verstappen-cc.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Things missing from The Sims 4</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/05/things-missing-the-sims-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Things missing from The Sims 4" /><published>2021-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/05/things-missing-the-sims-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/05/things-missing-the-sims-4">&lt;p&gt;I wrote last week about &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/11/27/how-to-break-the-sims-4&quot;&gt;my first impressions of &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (spoiler alert: they weren’t great). At the time I had a general feeling that the game lacked the quirkiness of previous titles in the series, but couldn’t quite put my finger on what exactly was missing from the latest release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had an extra week to play the game and think more deeply about it, and I’ve been keeping a running list of all the things I noticed that were in previous versions of &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; but are not in &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;. I’ve recreated this below, and will continue adding for as long as I keep playing the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/the-sims-4_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: There are likely to be some items on this list that either are in the game (and I just haven’t played long enough to see them) or were added in&lt;/em&gt; The Sims 4&lt;em&gt;’s many expansions. Let me know if so, but I’ll probably still keep them here - in the former scenario I’ve obviously seen a situation where they should have applied but didn’t, and in the latter it’s still not right that something that came with previous base games isn’t included now.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;burglars-burglaries-and-burglar-alarms&quot;&gt;Burglars, burglaries, and burglar alarms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with one that’s close to &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; fans’ hearts, every game prior to &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; had a burglar that would sometimes appear on your lot at night with a creepy little tune and try to steal your stuff. If you were prepared, you had an alarm and the police were immediately summoned. If you weren’t, your only hope was to try to wake your Sim and get them to call the police before the intruder could flee. Unfortunately this much-loved mechanic, which mixed things up from time to time, has completely disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;variety-when-inviting-sims-over&quot;&gt;Variety when inviting Sims over&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; also seemingly strips back the possible responses when inviting Sims over to your house to hang out. The older games would keep track of their work schedules, give excuses (the frequency of which depended on your Sim’s relationship with them), and throw wildcards like asking if friends could come, too. Since getting started with &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;, the only rejections I’ve had are if a Sim is sleeping (and they all wake at 7am, apparently) or if my Sim’s relationship is low enough that the two are mortal enemies.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sims-breaking-the-fourth-wall&quot;&gt;Sims breaking the fourth wall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of Simlish’s most iconic moments were when Sims used to turn directly to the camera and yell, normally to complain about their needs. There were also times from &lt;em&gt;The Sims 2&lt;/em&gt; onwards when Sims would quickly celebrate or complain about their next interactions depending on whether they matched their personalities or aspirations. As well as Sims being less vocal in general, these moments are gone in &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;, which plays it much straighter - an odd choice for a game that is actually much &lt;em&gt;easier&lt;/em&gt; than it used to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sims-with-working-ears&quot;&gt;Sims with working ears&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, if your Sim was sleeping in a room and somebody turned on a TV or stereo, they’d wake up and complain about the noise. In the series’ latest entry I can put my toddler to bed a tile away from a sound system blasting at full volume and they’ll sleep through it without any issues at all. Maybe this was deliberate - TVs and stereos are seemingly attractive objects to Sims left to their own devices - but it’s another example of a small omission that detracts from the game’s realism and challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/the-sims-4_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reliable-sim-autonomy&quot;&gt;Reliable Sim autonomy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years ago, Sims were roughly capable of taking care of themselves. They didn’t always get it perfectly right, but their AI was passable and they wouldn’t usually die if unattended. In fact, sometimes it was entertaining to hit the triple speed button and see what they got up to of their own accord. In &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; they all seem to have had lobotomies. Sometimes Sims will choose interactions that satisfy their needs, but if you give them an hour or two to themselves it’s much more common to see them stood on the spot, shrugging their shoulders and stretching until you intervene again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;strange-non-player-characters&quot;&gt;Strange non-player characters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the Social Bunny, the Sim Shrink, and Mrs. Crumplebottom? The Tragic Clown might have made an eventual comeback, but other than him, many of the fun and quirky side characters that used to show up in specific circumstances (usually emotionally extreme situations) or wander lots causing mischief have simply been cut out, which is a shame because they were key contributors to the slightly surreal atmosphere of the earlier games.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="the-sims" /><category term="life-sims" /><summary type="html">I wrote last week about my first impressions of The Sims 4 (spoiler alert: they weren’t great). At the time I had a general feeling that the game lacked the quirkiness of previous titles in the series, but couldn’t quite put my finger on what exactly was missing from the latest release. I’ve had an extra week to play the game and think more deeply about it, and I’ve been keeping a running list of all the things I noticed that were in previous versions of The Sims but are not in The Sims 4. I’ve recreated this below, and will continue adding for as long as I keep playing the game. Disclaimer: There are likely to be some items on this list that either are in the game (and I just haven’t played long enough to see them) or were added in The Sims 4’s many expansions. Let me know if so, but I’ll probably still keep them here - in the former scenario I’ve obviously seen a situation where they should have applied but didn’t, and in the latter it’s still not right that something that came with previous base games isn’t included now. Burglars, burglaries, and burglar alarms Starting with one that’s close to The Sims fans’ hearts, every game prior to The Sims 4 had a burglar that would sometimes appear on your lot at night with a creepy little tune and try to steal your stuff. If you were prepared, you had an alarm and the police were immediately summoned. If you weren’t, your only hope was to try to wake your Sim and get them to call the police before the intruder could flee. Unfortunately this much-loved mechanic, which mixed things up from time to time, has completely disappeared. Variety when inviting Sims over The Sims 4 also seemingly strips back the possible responses when inviting Sims over to your house to hang out. The older games would keep track of their work schedules, give excuses (the frequency of which depended on your Sim’s relationship with them), and throw wildcards like asking if friends could come, too. Since getting started with The Sims 4, the only rejections I’ve had are if a Sim is sleeping (and they all wake at 7am, apparently) or if my Sim’s relationship is low enough that the two are mortal enemies.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/the-sims-4_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/the-sims-4_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Breaking The Sims 4 in ten hours</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/27/how-to-break-the-sims-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking The Sims 4 in ten hours" /><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/27/how-to-break-the-sims-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/27/how-to-break-the-sims-4">&lt;p&gt;Having played a lot of &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; as a child, I was interested to see &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; on offer for just a few pounds in the recent Steam sale. It was obvious that this was a way to get players hooked and sell more expansions, but I thought it was a good chance to try out the most recent game in one of the series I’ve spent the most hours with and write a review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may have guessed from the title of this article, I didn’t get that far. So sit back, relax, and enjoy the story of how I got bored with &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; within a couple of hours - and what I did to keep myself entertained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-impressions&quot;&gt;First impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t dwell on it, but &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; is one of those games that sits in a special type of DRM hell, in that even if you buy it on Steam, your first ten minutes with EA’s latest life sim are likely to be spent dusting off the Origin client so you can actually play it. It’ll leave you longing for the days of &lt;em&gt;The Sims 2&lt;/em&gt;, back when you could just buy a disc, install the game, and play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I could finally start the game, what was evident is that EA were going for the largest market possible here. &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/09/01/asus-geforce-dual-gtx1060-o6g-review/&quot;&gt;My modest gaming rig&lt;/a&gt; plays most games from 2017 at their highest settings, but very few set themselves up that way after assessing my hardware. &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; automatically pushed all the sliders to the right - performance shouldn’t be an issue for many people here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not to say that everything is an upgrade or works perfectly. I noticed plenty of features that functioned well in previous &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; games, but are either absent or cause issues here. In Create-A-Sim, clothes can no longer be customised via a colour wheel, for example. More frustratingly, Sims frequently just ignore tasks assigned to them, which drop off their queues with no notification. This is especially frustrating when the task is critical, like giving a toddler some food before they are taken away. &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the game just didn’t like the pathing in the house I built, but this is also the first time in however many hours of &lt;em&gt;Sims&lt;/em&gt; play that I’ve had to look up the cheat to reset a Sim who was seemingly just stuck. After a few more hours, NPCs I’d never met before also had a habit of strolling into my house, chatting with my toddlers or taking the rubbish out for my Sims. Weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-bored&quot;&gt;Getting bored&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accusation leveled at &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; by some older fans was that the focus of the game has shifted. It’s no longer about life simulation, they say, and more geared towards giving casual players the tools to build the house of their dreams and deck it out in fashionable items available via expansion and “stuff” packs. There’s an element of that here, but the thing that dented my enthusiasm for a playthrough was just an overwhelming feeling of monotony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it’s because I’m an older, more weary gamer now, but there really was a sense that I’d seen everything Live Mode had to offer before. &lt;em&gt;The Sims 3&lt;/em&gt; piled on the narrative with neighbourhood exploration and quests, but a lot of that seems to be gone (perhaps to be restored by expansions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the way Sims interact with each other and the things around them, the main new feature is a series of mood states (e.g. happy, sad, flirty) that affect actions a Sim can take. While these do seem to affect Sims’ responses to others’ interactions, the new options available to the Sim experiencing the mood are mostly small variants on interactions we’ve seen a thousand times before: telling a self-deprecating joke if embarrassed, for example, or “attempting to flirt” if they’re down in the dumps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I’m just not the target audience anymore, but this all felt very underwhelming. I was simply retreading ground I’d already covered as far back as &lt;em&gt;The Sims 2&lt;/em&gt;, and there weren’t enough new quirks and surprises to keep me interested. &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; also seems incredibly easy. My Sim wanted a relationship, so I spoke to somebody on the street and went from casual conversation to flirting, kissing, agreeing to be partners, WooHooing, and trying for a baby all in one in-game evening. There was no challenge to it. So I made an executive decision: I abandoned the goal of writing a full review, and instead set out to test the game’s limits until they broke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;breaking-the-game&quot;&gt;Breaking the game&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After noticing how easy the game’s romance systems were, I set out on my own challenge - to see how many babies my Sim could father before things all came tumbling down around him. My Sim got into a routine, chatting to new people on the street, inviting them inside for a date, and trying for a baby the same day. It was ridiculous how easy this all was. He ended up with six simultaneous girlfriends, all of whom were potentially pregnant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It still seemed too easy, so I decided to add some peril by inviting all of them to a party at one of the girlfriends’ houses. I expected this to spark a wave of arguments and break-ups, but astoundingly they were all happy to chat and dance together as a group, somehow unaware of the ridiculous social dynamics at play. Nobody even batted an eyelid as Strat Packer disappeared upstairs to WooHoo with his first girlfriend, and he even used the opportunity to hit it off with her sister, adding a seventh potential heir to the rotation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmm… How to up the stakes further? I invited all of the heavily pregnant Sims over to hang out and invited as many as possible to join the household (limited by the eight-Sim cap). Before too long, my Sim was living with three girlfriends and four children, with an additional four kids floating around the neighbourhood from the others. Also amusing was that only one of the other mothers decided to call my Sim to tell him about the birth of his son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This latest move sparked the chaos I was looking for. Four children would have been challenging enough on their own, but it was the love square that really brought the spice. In attempting to take care of the kids, I couldn’t keep an eye on all my adult Sims at once, meaning that any automatic flirtation or kissing set in motion a log chain of fury, slaps, and mirror pep talks that finally gave the entertainment I was seeking. It turned out that balancing childcare and three relationships was the equivalent of a hard mode for &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;, finally delivering the challenge I was looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;findings-and-conclusion&quot;&gt;Findings and conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from adding another crazy &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; story to the internet’s massive archive, what I learnt from all this is that &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; is just not very good as a vanilla life simulation game. It lacks the charm that the early entries in the series had, there aren’t enough new surprises to keep a long-time player entertained, and it’s even broken in some places where it wasn’t before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the increased performance (specifically when handling ten or more Sims on the same lot at once) and inconsistent social system make it an entertaining playground for those who approach the game as a sandbox to complete unorthodox challenges or just to push the simulation to its limits. The potential for chaos here is huge, and if all you want to do is play God and watch things fall apart inside a virtual dollhouse, &lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt; is well worth the £4 or so it is frequently reduced to in Steam sales.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="the-sims" /><category term="life-sims" /><summary type="html">Having played a lot of The Sims as a child, I was interested to see The Sims 4 on offer for just a few pounds in the recent Steam sale. It was obvious that this was a way to get players hooked and sell more expansions, but I thought it was a good chance to try out the most recent game in one of the series I’ve spent the most hours with and write a review. As you may have guessed from the title of this article, I didn’t get that far. So sit back, relax, and enjoy the story of how I got bored with The Sims 4 within a couple of hours - and what I did to keep myself entertained. First impressions I won’t dwell on it, but The Sims 4 is one of those games that sits in a special type of DRM hell, in that even if you buy it on Steam, your first ten minutes with EA’s latest life sim are likely to be spent dusting off the Origin client so you can actually play it. It’ll leave you longing for the days of The Sims 2, back when you could just buy a disc, install the game, and play. When I could finally start the game, what was evident is that EA were going for the largest market possible here. My modest gaming rig plays most games from 2017 at their highest settings, but very few set themselves up that way after assessing my hardware. The Sims 4 automatically pushed all the sliders to the right - performance shouldn’t be an issue for many people here. That’s not to say that everything is an upgrade or works perfectly. I noticed plenty of features that functioned well in previous The Sims games, but are either absent or cause issues here. In Create-A-Sim, clothes can no longer be customised via a colour wheel, for example. More frustratingly, Sims frequently just ignore tasks assigned to them, which drop off their queues with no notification. This is especially frustrating when the task is critical, like giving a toddler some food before they are taken away.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-sims-4_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Easy retro gaming with Retropie</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/20/pi-hut-retro-gaming-kit-retropie" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Easy retro gaming with Retropie" /><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/20/pi-hut-retro-gaming-kit-retropie</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/20/pi-hut-retro-gaming-kit-retropie">&lt;p&gt;Anyone who reads this blog will know that I like to play some emulated games from time to time - normally revisiting PlayStation 2 classics like &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;PES 5&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/10/gran-turismo-3-retrospective&quot;&gt;Gran Turismo 3&lt;/a&gt;. But retro gaming on a PC has its downsides. You need to install an emulator for each console, clog up your hard drive with ROMs, and tweak settings to make sure the graphics look good on a modern monitor. Surely there must be an easier way to play old favourites?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some friends recently gave me an amazing gift that provides the answer. The Raspberry Pi retro gaming kit, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepihut.com/products/raspberry-pi-retro-gaming-bundle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;available from The Pi Hut&lt;/a&gt;, consists of a Raspberry Pi 4, the required memory card and cables, and two SNES-style controllers. It’s more than capable of running the free &lt;a href=&quot;https://retropie.org.uk/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Retropie&lt;/a&gt; retro gaming distribution, which includes emulators for a large range of systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/retropie_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll write a full explanation of how to set up and configure Retropie at a later date, but it’s all deliciously simple stuff: plug in the cables, install Linux and Retropie, copy some games over to the preconfigured network share, and get going. It’s also ridiculously easy to get a PlayStation 4 or Xbox One controller working either via USB or (with a little more tweaking) wireless, so I can’t speak to the quality of the USB controllers that came in the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retropie can play games from a huge number of systems, including the PlayStation, PSP, Dreamcast, GameCube, Nintendo 64, several Game Boys, NES, SNES, and many more. Some of the more modern emulators don’t work due to the Raspberry Pi’s processor, unfortunately - but hey, you can’t have everything. I’ll just have to continue playing those games on my PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/retropie_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what the kit and Retropie give me is a neat little box that can sit under my TV and play a variety of digital retro games to break up my day. So far, that’s meant quite a bit of the 1995 game &lt;em&gt;Formula 1&lt;/em&gt; for the PS1, and - after quite a bit of fuss trying to get the Amiga emulator working - the absolute classic &lt;em&gt;Deluxe Galaga&lt;/em&gt;. It really all works rather well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll return to Retropie and how to set it up in future, including full details of the Amiga setup, but for now I just wanted to say how great this little kit is (and you could probably put it together even cheaper by buying the Pi outright). Until then, I’ve got some retro games to play…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="hardware" /><category term="retro" /><category term="racing" /><category term="motorsport" /><summary type="html">Anyone who reads this blog will know that I like to play some emulated games from time to time - normally revisiting PlayStation 2 classics like PES 5 and Gran Turismo 3. But retro gaming on a PC has its downsides. You need to install an emulator for each console, clog up your hard drive with ROMs, and tweak settings to make sure the graphics look good on a modern monitor. Surely there must be an easier way to play old favourites? Some friends recently gave me an amazing gift that provides the answer. The Raspberry Pi retro gaming kit, available from The Pi Hut, consists of a Raspberry Pi 4, the required memory card and cables, and two SNES-style controllers. It’s more than capable of running the free Retropie retro gaming distribution, which includes emulators for a large range of systems. I’ll write a full explanation of how to set up and configure Retropie at a later date, but it’s all deliciously simple stuff: plug in the cables, install Linux and Retropie, copy some games over to the preconfigured network share, and get going. It’s also ridiculously easy to get a PlayStation 4 or Xbox One controller working either via USB or (with a little more tweaking) wireless, so I can’t speak to the quality of the USB controllers that came in the box. Retropie can play games from a huge number of systems, including the PlayStation, PSP, Dreamcast, GameCube, Nintendo 64, several Game Boys, NES, SNES, and many more. Some of the more modern emulators don’t work due to the Raspberry Pi’s processor, unfortunately - but hey, you can’t have everything. I’ll just have to continue playing those games on my PC.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/11/retropie_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/11/retropie_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">PC Building Simulator review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/13/pc-building-simulator-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PC Building Simulator review" /><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/13/pc-building-simulator-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/13/pc-building-simulator-review">&lt;p&gt;This week I decided it was time to start tackling my backlog - all those games sitting on the virtual shelf waiting to be enjoyed. One of the most recent additions to the pile was &lt;em&gt;PC Building Simulator&lt;/em&gt;, a 2018 release from The Irregular Corporation that promises edutainment as you learn how to build a computer through the medium of video games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/pc-building-simulator_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t sure what to expect, to be honest. How much of a game was there to be built out of the task of preparing a system to play games? &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/09/01/asus-geforce-dual-gtx1060-o6g-review/&quot;&gt;When I built my PC&lt;/a&gt; the reward was that I got to play said games, so barring some sort of gameception I couldn’t see how &lt;em&gt;PC Building Simulator&lt;/em&gt; could deliver. Despite these doubts, I dived into this recent Epic Games freebie anyway…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-challenge&quot;&gt;The challenge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here’s the setup: In &lt;em&gt;PC Building Simulator&lt;/em&gt; you take on the role of the new owner of a small IT shop, and spend your time servicing and building PCs for customers to make money and grow your business. The basic loop is that you’ll check your email for jobs, take delivery of the computer, diagnose the problem, order and install parts, sometimes install and run software or perform other maintenance tasks, and send it back to the customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your assignments become more complex as the game progresses, introducing new mechanics or getting more vague, with customers requesting “upgrades” or sending in broken systems without knowing what exactly the issue is. They also set budgets, so you need to meet their requirements without maxing out their PC build with the latest 3090 Ti. Some also hint at little details, noting that they like a particular parts manufacturer or cable colour, for example, and they’ll complain if you install used components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/pc-building-simulator_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your progression is limited by two factors. First, your access to parts in the game’s online store is dependent on your current level. As you level up, you’ll gain access to the flashier manufacturers and latest tech. Second, when customers receive their upgraded machines they’ll leave an online review, which influences a star rating that dictates which jobs you can pick up. This adds some variety to the jobs and components you’ll see as you play.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-toolset&quot;&gt;The toolset&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game provides several different perspectives on all of this. At its most abstracted level, you play the technician in first person, walking around your office between different shelves, workbenches, and your desk. Emails and the online shop are accessed via your computer. At the end of the corridor is the exit door, clicking on which brings up the calendar and lets you progress to the next day. This adds a strategic element: Have you done everything you can today? Are any customers’ deadlines set to pass? And what delivery speed should you pay for from the parts shop in order to meet them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the meat of the game is in the PC building itself. After moving a system to your workbench you can start to take it apart and play with the pieces inside. You’ll be tasked with installing new parts, removing viruses (read: installing anti-virus from a USB stick and running a scan), cleaning filthy PCs with compressed air, using a tool called 3Dmark to benchmark gaming systems, and so on. Some customers, as the title of the game suggests, will even ask you to build a PC from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/pc-building-simulator_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PC Building Simulator&lt;/em&gt;’s computers are well rendered enough to satisfy tech geeks, with plenty of real-world parts depicted in decent detail. The controls are about as good as they could be: Click a part to remove, then click and hold to undo each screw holding it in. Probably the fussiest of the tasks is cleaning out a PC, which requires equipping the compressed air and holding down the mouse button to spray it around the case. The dust disappears in regions that share only a tenuous link to your movements - frustrating when you’re trying to clean up the one remaining component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also worth noting that it’s not always clear exactly where a part should go - for example, there may be multiple drive bays and the game expects you to use one in particular. You must also prove every PC you work on can boot to the operating system, which requires individually plugging in the power cable, monitor, keyboard, and mouse (they won’t boot at all without any of these). This becomes monotonous after completing a couple of assignments, but you’ll be doing it for as long as you play the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-difficulty&quot;&gt;The difficulty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned above, the difficulty of the jobs ramps up as you progress, with more complex work requested or some diagnostic work needed. Things never get &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; challenging, however - at least as far as I played - because everything always comes down to ordering a new part, removing some screws, and slotting the right pieces into place. Even when the problem isn’t known by the customer, it’s often explicitly stated elsewhere - for example, a “CPU not found” message in the BIOS when attempting to boot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, much of the difficulty in &lt;em&gt;PC Building Simulator&lt;/em&gt; lies in resource management. Your workshop only has room to store a few customers’ PCs, so getting them in and out as quickly as possible is crucial to maximising your income. And if you have multiple boxes waiting for new parts, it is more efficient to bundle those orders together and pay one delivery fee rather than buying them separately as you identify each requirementr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/pc-building-simulator_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a similar way, some tasks take a long time to complete and can be run simultaneously for efficiency. Specifically here I’m thinking of 3Dmark, which through some highly sophisticated testing I worked out takes about &lt;em&gt;90 seconds&lt;/em&gt; to run to completion. You can buy additional workbenches for your workshop once you reach the higher levels, meaning that if you time it right you can leave one PC running this test while you work on another. If you like min-maxing mechanics, you’ll enjoy these elements of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-vibe&quot;&gt;The vibe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given some of the frustrations I noted earlier, you’re likely to want to dip in and out of the game in short bursts, and luckily the day progression system is - by design or by accident - quite well suited to this. While some strategy and simulation games fuel marathons that span into the early hours as you always feel you need to finish “just one more X”, I found it quite easy to boot the game up after work, fix a few PCs over a few days, and save and quit just after proceeding to the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PC Building Simulator&lt;/em&gt; also has some jokey elements that provide the typical colour required to liven up these sorts of otherwise bland simulator games. There’s some genuinely enjoyable writing in customers’ emails, with some strongly characterised as stereotypical authors, film buffs, or gamers, with associated humour in their issues and responses. As with any IT job, you also sometimes find some amusing files on users’ desktops (although unfortunately you’re not able to open any of them to see what’s inside).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/pc-building-simulator_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also as good a place as any to note that the game has a sandbox mode, which can be a nice way to chill out when the grind and constant deadline pressure of the career mode gets too much. This has all the parts unlocked from the start (which admittedly is a bit of a nightmare when the component menus are sorted alphabetically with no filtering) and it was a nice distraction to try to build something as close to my real-life PC as possible, or put together a fantasy gaming rig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-judgement&quot;&gt;The judgement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m split on whether &lt;em&gt;PC Building Simulator&lt;/em&gt; belongs in the “pointless simulator game” category or not. One one hand, the business building element is nice and makes me wish I could make a decent living by building systems with my hands and helping people like my in-game character. There’s a relaxing vibe to finishing a build, hearing the money clink in the till, and feeling like you’re progressing and building your little tech company up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, all of this comes at a cost, and that cost is feeling your heart sink every few seconds when you realise you have another boring task to complete (oh, I’ve got &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; set of screws to remove or cables to insert?). This feeling is exacerbated when you find yourself unable to return a PC to a customer because you forgot some minute, inconsequential part - normally a PCI lock or inner case element. This requires you to take the PC back to the workbench, remove the cover, install the part, screw the cover back on, and sometimes run the boot test again, and is perhaps the worst thing about the game - why not just let me return the PC and have the customer complain about a small part being missing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, &lt;em&gt;PC Building Simulator&lt;/em&gt; will please the sort of tech nerd who salivates over the latest processors and graphics cards (or at least ones from 2018), but for me delivers none of the satisfaction of building a real PC because you’re always working between guardrails. When the main building mechanics could work as a touchscreen game, highlighting the next step without any thought on the player’s part, there’s no real challenge here beyond knowing roughly what each component in a PC does. I’m sure there are people out there who’ll love this, and I might revisit it for an hour or two from time to time, but the frustrations are too much to keep me hooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3/5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="pc-building-simulator" /><category term="simulator" /><category term="hardware" /><summary type="html">This week I decided it was time to start tackling my backlog - all those games sitting on the virtual shelf waiting to be enjoyed. One of the most recent additions to the pile was PC Building Simulator, a 2018 release from The Irregular Corporation that promises edutainment as you learn how to build a computer through the medium of video games. I wasn’t sure what to expect, to be honest. How much of a game was there to be built out of the task of preparing a system to play games? When I built my PC the reward was that I got to play said games, so barring some sort of gameception I couldn’t see how PC Building Simulator could deliver. Despite these doubts, I dived into this recent Epic Games freebie anyway… The challenge So here’s the setup: In PC Building Simulator you take on the role of the new owner of a small IT shop, and spend your time servicing and building PCs for customers to make money and grow your business. The basic loop is that you’ll check your email for jobs, take delivery of the computer, diagnose the problem, order and install parts, sometimes install and run software or perform other maintenance tasks, and send it back to the customer. Your assignments become more complex as the game progresses, introducing new mechanics or getting more vague, with customers requesting “upgrades” or sending in broken systems without knowing what exactly the issue is. They also set budgets, so you need to meet their requirements without maxing out their PC build with the latest 3090 Ti. Some also hint at little details, noting that they like a particular parts manufacturer or cable colour, for example, and they’ll complain if you install used components. Your progression is limited by two factors. First, your access to parts in the game’s online store is dependent on your current level. As you level up, you’ll gain access to the flashier manufacturers and latest tech. Second, when customers receive their upgraded machines they’ll leave an online review, which influences a star rating that dictates which jobs you can pick up. This adds some variety to the jobs and components you’ll see as you play.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/11/pc-building-simulator_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/11/pc-building-simulator_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sid Meier’s Memoir! review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/05/sid-meiers-memoir-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sid Meier's Memoir! review" /><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/05/sid-meiers-memoir-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/11/05/sid-meiers-memoir-review">&lt;p&gt;A book I preordered six months ago finally landed on my doormat in October. &lt;em&gt;Sid Meier’s Memoir!&lt;/em&gt;, the autobiography by the genuis game designer behind groundbreaking and much-loved strategy games like &lt;em&gt;Civilization&lt;/em&gt;, turned out not only to have the title that fans of his games hoped it would, but also to be far more insightful than the average book written by a developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with the events leading to MicroProse’s 1982 founding, &lt;em&gt;Memoir!&lt;/em&gt; covers the full span of Meier’s career, from the early days developing solo and using every trick in the book to pitch titles to games stores all the way to the internal politics that forced the founding of Firaxas and the gradual winning back of some of his most prized intellectual property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/sid-meiers-memoir.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m always wary of books by famous creators. More often than not they cover the who, where, and what of their careers - I worked at this company, I released this game, this person gave me some great advice - but not the how or the why. Maybe they think the bigger audience doesn’t have an interest in the intricacies of how great works are put together, and therefore decide to focus more on the glamour and big names in their industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sid Meier, on the other hand, gives a great deal more information about the games themselves. Each of &lt;em&gt;Memoir!&lt;/em&gt;’s chapters is dedicated to one or more titles in his extensive back catalogue, and the format varies for each. Expect insights into the inner workings of MicroProse and Firaxis, stories from Meier’s childhood and time staying with family in Switzerland, and stories about how other passions like music and golf influenced his titles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the passages where Meier gets into game design itself are what set this book apart and will keep you turning the pages. When discussing his games, he zeroes in on the individual decisions that made or broke them. What shape should each space on the map be? How much of a story does a strategy game need? When should a free roaming game end? &lt;em&gt;Memoir!&lt;/em&gt; covers each of these questions and more. It rarely gets very technical, but as somebody who dabbled in bedroom game development in his youth, it really is fascinating to see how the pros approach conundrums like these.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meier also shares the rules that helped to make his games what they are - nobody should die in a Sid Meier game, for example, and the golden rule is that the player should always be given interesting decisions to make, with realism never coming at the expense of fun (something that I incidentally discussed in &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;my retrospective of &lt;em&gt;Pro Evolution Soccer 5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last game covered by &lt;em&gt;Memoir!&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;Sid Meier’s Starships&lt;/em&gt;, which was released in 2015. That final chapter is to me the most poignant of the whole book. In it, the author discusses the difference between Sid Meier and &lt;em&gt;Sid Meier!&lt;/em&gt;, and reflects on the way his career and the games industry have both developed since the 1980s. I won’t ruin the rest, but it was moving to read something so candid from such a legendary figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m probably the perfect target audience for this book - nerdy, with some amateur game development experience and a history of playing Sid Meier-created and -inspired games - but I don’t think I’m overselling it when I say this is the perfect video game autobiography. If you have even a passing interest in gaming (even outside of the strategy genre), game development, or Sid Meier himself, I’d certainly recommend picking up a copy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="strategy" /><category term="civilization" /><summary type="html">A book I preordered six months ago finally landed on my doormat in October. Sid Meier’s Memoir!, the autobiography by the genuis game designer behind groundbreaking and much-loved strategy games like Civilization, turned out not only to have the title that fans of his games hoped it would, but also to be far more insightful than the average book written by a developer. Starting with the events leading to MicroProse’s 1982 founding, Memoir! covers the full span of Meier’s career, from the early days developing solo and using every trick in the book to pitch titles to games stores all the way to the internal politics that forced the founding of Firaxas and the gradual winning back of some of his most prized intellectual property. I’m always wary of books by famous creators. More often than not they cover the who, where, and what of their careers - I worked at this company, I released this game, this person gave me some great advice - but not the how or the why. Maybe they think the bigger audience doesn’t have an interest in the intricacies of how great works are put together, and therefore decide to focus more on the glamour and big names in their industry. Sid Meier, on the other hand, gives a great deal more information about the games themselves. Each of Memoir!’s chapters is dedicated to one or more titles in his extensive back catalogue, and the format varies for each. Expect insights into the inner workings of MicroProse and Firaxis, stories from Meier’s childhood and time staying with family in Switzerland, and stories about how other passions like music and golf influenced his titles. However, the passages where Meier gets into game design itself are what set this book apart and will keep you turning the pages. When discussing his games, he zeroes in on the individual decisions that made or broke them. What shape should each space on the map be? How much of a story does a strategy game need? When should a free roaming game end? Memoir! covers each of these questions and more. It rarely gets very technical, but as somebody who dabbled in bedroom game development in his youth, it really is fascinating to see how the pros approach conundrums like these.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/11/sid-meiers-memoir.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/11/sid-meiers-memoir.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Brands Hatch has the best views in UK motorsport</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/10/31/brands-hatch-best-views-uk-motorsport" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brands Hatch has the best views in UK motorsport" /><published>2021-10-31T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-31T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/10/31/brands-hatch-best-circuit-watch-racing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/10/31/brands-hatch-best-views-uk-motorsport">&lt;p&gt;I went to Brands Hatch this weekend to see some of the action at the 50th Formula Ford Festival. &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/10/26/exploring-brands-hatch-at-the-formula-ford-festival/&quot;&gt;I stopped by the same event back in 2018&lt;/a&gt;, but after a few more years visiting more circuits, I can safely say that Brands Hatch is the absolute best when it comes to viewing angles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no doubt that Silverstone is the pinnacle of UK motorsport venues, but Brands Hatch really stands out among the mid-tier circuits hosting events smaller than &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-1&quot;&gt;Formula 1&lt;/a&gt; Grands Prix. Its facilities are far better than I was expecting the first time I visited, but its beauty comes in its views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/brands-hatch-formula-ford_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike circuits like &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/08/29/btcc-formula-4-thruxton/&quot;&gt;Thruxton&lt;/a&gt;, which have only a few spectator areas, at Brands Hatch fans are allowed to walk the full perimeter of the track - and the differences in elevation between the various sections mean that often the majority of the course is visible from any individual spot you settle on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a complete view is what you’re after, the main grandstand on the main straight is the spot for you. Sitting atop Paddock Hill, these seats give great views down into Turn 1, with the more distant Druids hairpin to your left, Graham Hill bend straight ahead, and Clearways to the right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/brands-hatch-formula-ford_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to get closer to the action, Brands Hatch has you covered in that respect, too. Pictured is the view standing right next to the fence at the start line, but the other top spot for motorsport fans who like to smell the oil and hear the tyres squeal is Druids - cross the footbridge and you can stand right on the inside of the hairpin, metres away from the cars.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less-explored parts of the circuit also give great views. The photo below was taken from a little verge on the Southbank, where you can watch the drivers exit Druids and head down through Graham Hill bend - and even from there you can still keep an eye on what’s happening up at Paddock Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/brands-hatch-formula-ford_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading back in the other direction, there are also good angles to be found around Surtees, Clearways, and Clark Curve, which are often the scene of intense on-track battles and spins (even more so on wet days like Saturday) as drivers test their cars’ limits around these long, fast corners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s worth mentioning that Formula Ford uses Brands Hatch’s Indy configuration. Events with faster cars use the Grand Prix circuit, which doubles the length of the lap and opens up many more potential viewing spots, even if it removes the aforementioned complete visibility factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/brands-hatch-formula-ford_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one downside, and the thing that will stop me visiting as often as I otherwise might, is that the circuit’s transport links are in decline. Buses between Swanley station and Brands Hatch have been cut back, leaving only a five-hour window between the first and last buses, and the last bus didn’t even turn up on Saturday, forcing me to take a taxi to get home. With fewer and less reliable buses, taxis are now the only option, really reducing Brands Hatch’s affordability as a day out for those of us without cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, when you can get there, it’s definitely worth it to spend a day wandering around the track and taking in the views from different corners. No other circuit I’ve been to has come close in terms of variety and just how picturesque the whole place is. So if you want to watch motorsport but don’t know where to start, give Brands Hatch a go.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="motorsport" /><category term="formula-ford" /><summary type="html">I went to Brands Hatch this weekend to see some of the action at the 50th Formula Ford Festival. I stopped by the same event back in 2018, but after a few more years visiting more circuits, I can safely say that Brands Hatch is the absolute best when it comes to viewing angles. There’s no doubt that Silverstone is the pinnacle of UK motorsport venues, but Brands Hatch really stands out among the mid-tier circuits hosting events smaller than Formula 1 Grands Prix. Its facilities are far better than I was expecting the first time I visited, but its beauty comes in its views. Unlike circuits like Thruxton, which have only a few spectator areas, at Brands Hatch fans are allowed to walk the full perimeter of the track - and the differences in elevation between the various sections mean that often the majority of the course is visible from any individual spot you settle on. If a complete view is what you’re after, the main grandstand on the main straight is the spot for you. Sitting atop Paddock Hill, these seats give great views down into Turn 1, with the more distant Druids hairpin to your left, Graham Hill bend straight ahead, and Clearways to the right. If you want to get closer to the action, Brands Hatch has you covered in that respect, too. Pictured is the view standing right next to the fence at the start line, but the other top spot for motorsport fans who like to smell the oil and hear the tyres squeal is Druids - cross the footbridge and you can stand right on the inside of the hairpin, metres away from the cars.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/10/brands-hatch-formula-ford_2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/10/brands-hatch-formula-ford_2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>