<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-05-14T22:03:15+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A lesson in curiosity from Japan</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/05/14/lesson-curiosity-japan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A lesson in curiosity from Japan" /><published>2023-05-14T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-05-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/05/14/lesson-curiosity-japan</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/05/14/lesson-curiosity-japan">&lt;p&gt;I recently returned from a couple of weeks out in Japan, and while I saw and experienced some amazing places, sights, and foods, I think the thing that will stay with me from this trip is more of an attitude I hope I will be able to retain long after the end of my holiday and absorb into my own life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/japan.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that always strikes me when I visit Japan is the level of curiosity on display for niche subjects. One example of this can be seen on TV every day - each area of the country has its own specialties, and on any channel you can find presenters visiting little local restaurants, cafes, shops, and so on to try them and speak to their creators about how they are made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;positivity-personified&quot;&gt;Positivity personified&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my most recent visit, I was lucky enough to see this outlook personified. In the buildup to my trip, I’d asked if a friend of a friend could help me get tickets to an event. As it turned out, he didn’t just buy a ticket, but also came with me and invited me to hang out with this friends the day before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We couldn’t communicate fluently (my Japanese and his English are both very basic) but we had a great time together. I think more than anything he was delighted that I’d taken an interest in one of his passions, and as we departed he gave me a very sentimental goodbye gift with a handwritten thank you message, which was more touching than I’d been expecting.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially it made me smile, but over time I considered it more deeply, thinking about the place it had come from, and realised how jaded modern life has made me. Especially since the dawn of the internet, life has me on high alert, always wary of being taken advantage of, and always conscious that no matter what I do, there will always be somebody better out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when I was on the receiving end of such kindness in Japan, my main concern was worry about whether my reactions might seem rude or ungrateful. It’s like the anxiety instilled in me by all those online horror stories, arguments, and comparisons has adjusted my natural response to focus on damage control, rather than gratitude or pure enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-have-control&quot;&gt;You have control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, one of the podcast episodes waiting in my queue when I got home was the dating expert Matthew Hussey &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dR-plImpf_8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;speaking on Modern Wisdom&lt;/a&gt;. In a discussion about dating trends, he shared a poignant message that can essentially be summed up as: “Your actions dictate your life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a part with relevance spanning well beyond dating, Hussey discouraged listeners from focusing on macro-level issues. An obsession with politics and global trends will affect your outlook and hold you back, when in fact your personal outcomes might be entirely different. And even if things do turn out the way the statistics suggest, you have more control than you think, and adjusting your actions can help to bring about different results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His advice was to approach life with curiosity, asking questions like “How can this work out?”, “How can I be impressed by this person?”, and “What can I learn here?” Having read many books to overcome (or at least heavily reduce) anxiety in the last year, it immediately struck me that these questions all seek the positive, rather than fearing negative outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps there’s some confirmation bias at play here, but to me, this seems to match what I learnt from my new friend. His gift now sits on a shelf in my flat, and I hope that long after the aura of my holiday as faded away it will still serve as a reminder in my daily life to stay grateful and curious.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="travel" /><category term="japan" /><category term="philosophy" /><summary type="html">I recently returned from a couple of weeks out in Japan, and while I saw and experienced some amazing places, sights, and foods, I think the thing that will stay with me from this trip is more of an attitude I hope I will be able to retain long after the end of my holiday and absorb into my own life. One thing that always strikes me when I visit Japan is the level of curiosity on display for niche subjects. One example of this can be seen on TV every day - each area of the country has its own specialties, and on any channel you can find presenters visiting little local restaurants, cafes, shops, and so on to try them and speak to their creators about how they are made. Positivity personified On my most recent visit, I was lucky enough to see this outlook personified. In the buildup to my trip, I’d asked if a friend of a friend could help me get tickets to an event. As it turned out, he didn’t just buy a ticket, but also came with me and invited me to hang out with this friends the day before. We couldn’t communicate fluently (my Japanese and his English are both very basic) but we had a great time together. I think more than anything he was delighted that I’d taken an interest in one of his passions, and as we departed he gave me a very sentimental goodbye gift with a handwritten thank you message, which was more touching than I’d been expecting.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/05/japan.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/05/japan.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Panic! at the Disco – Viva Las Vengeance review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/04/23/panic-at-the-disco-viva-las-vengeance-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Panic! at the Disco &amp;#8211; Viva Las Vengeance review" /><published>2023-04-23T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-23T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/04/23/viva-las-vengeance-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/04/23/panic-at-the-disco-viva-las-vengeance-review">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viva Las Vengeance&lt;/em&gt; is perhaps the greatest album ever to have almost completely passed me by, and I don’t think I’m alone in that. It was only via a coincidental search that I caught the titular single and Middle of a Breakup on Panic! at the Disco’s YouTube channel, and there seemed to be very little fanfare in the buildup to the album’s August 2022 release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/viva-las-vengeance_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I did realise the record was out, I listened through it exactly once on Spotify, my expectations fairly low given the more pop-focused direction of its predecessor, &lt;em&gt;Pray for the Wicked&lt;/em&gt;. Maybe I was in the wrong mood or too distracted, but I didn’t think much of it, and skipped on tickets for the tour when I saw Brandon Urie was playing the album in full at gigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How foolish I was. In mid-April 2023, I spotted an article from earlier in the year that said that Panic! at the Disco were no more, with Urie having wound down the project to focus on his family. In a mournful mood (&lt;em&gt;Pretty. Odd.&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Death of a Bachelor&lt;/em&gt; are two of my favourite albums), I revisited &lt;em&gt;Viva Las Vengeance&lt;/em&gt; to see if anything clicked, or if I could piece together anything about his state of mind when writing and recording it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I got beyond the two opening singles, I was entranced. Far from the last record’s bland pop, &lt;em&gt;Viva Las Vengeance&lt;/em&gt; is deliberately recorded as a tribute to 1970s rock, and in that sense almost serves as a sequel to &lt;em&gt;Pretty. Odd.&lt;/em&gt;’s 1960s tones. While there’s plenty of variety, these influences are most apparent in the Queen-style harmonies and Brian May-inspired solos.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the benefit of hindsight, lyrics about sex and partners begin to look more like metaphors for Urie’s relationship with fame, the music industry, and Panic! itself. Look below the surface and there are allusions to his love-hate feelings for his station in life and ponderings about what might have been had he never been thrust into the limelight. If you think this sounds like self-pity, sometimes it is, but it never outstays its welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, &lt;em&gt;Viva Las Vengeance&lt;/em&gt; is a grower. What at first appears to be surface-level showmanship and derivative composition shows greater depth the more you listen. If this does turn out to be Panic! at the Disco’s last album - and it appears it will be, at least for the moment - then we should be thankful that the final release expanded their top two to a top three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;track-by-track&quot;&gt;Track by track&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Viva Las Vengeance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The opener sets the mood for the album, with a feeling that Urie is resigned to giving in to the pressures on him (“shut up and go to bed”). He’s not going out without a bang, though, as referenced by both the song’s final lyrics and the screaming falsetto with which they’re delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Middle of a Breakup&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Energetic, catchy, and the pick of the album’s singles for me. My theory is that what initially felt like a typical Panic! sexual theme (“make-up sex in the middle of a breakup”) may actually be referring to the joy of performing shows for fans even while falling out of love with the music industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Don’t Let the Light Go Out&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As slow and emotional as the album gets, with Urie expressing his gratitude for a partner that challenges him in all the right ways. Heartfelt, with a nice buildup, although the “heavy machinery” line is a little clunky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Local God&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Probably the most interesting song on the album lyrically, as Urie appears to imagine what his life might have been like if he hadn’t become famous. A pleasant change of pace with some nice guitar work in the middle eight as he wholesomely muses on “teaching little kids how to rock and roll”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Star Spangled Banner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A stadium anthem with a chant-like chorus and jazzy, uptempo verses telling stories that seem to hark back to Urie’s teenage years. This nostalgic reflection on his and the band’s beginnings will be a recurring theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. God Killed Rock and Roll&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If the album’s Queen influences weren’t obvious enough elsewhere, Panic! really hit the nail on the head here with some piano sections that sound like they’re ripped straight from Bohemian Rhapsody. Urie’s voice once again steals the show with the refrain, full of rock history references.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Say It Louder&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Feels like an interlude between two halves of the album, and serves as a flip side to Local God as Urie takes a moment to revel in Panic!’s success. In retrospect, the slow middle section about committing a rock show to memory reads like a mourning of the parts of the lifestyle he does enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Sugar Soaker&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lifts the mood as probably the most fun song on the record, even if it lacks the depth of many others. This upbeat, riff-based track has call-and-response verses before hitting a lively, catchy chorus that show off Urie’s vocal acumen with a clever chord switchout the second time round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Something About Maggie&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This track almost feels like a little tribute to &lt;em&gt;Pretty. Odd.&lt;/em&gt; in the middle of the album, complete with some familiar-sounding horns in the latter stages. Some lyrics in the verses could potentially be read as an acknowledgment of long-time fans’ criticisms of Panic!’s last, poppier album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Sad Clown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Almost certainly evidence that Urie knew he was quitting well before the public announcement. “Leave me alone,” he screams, amongst lyrics alluding to disillusionment with endless performances and online criticism. The verse melody and It’s My Life-style riff are personal highlights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11. All By Yourself&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A slower number that I think deserved to be the final, farewell song. The lyrics speak to the universal experience of feeling down and locking yourself in your room to listen to a record, feeling that the artist is speaking directly to you and inspiring you to get back on your feet and achieve something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12. Do It to Death&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If I were to point to a weak point on the album, it’s probably this last song, which is just a little too repetitive for my tastes. The verses the most interesting segments, but make up on a small fraction of the track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5/5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="panic-at-the-disco" /><category term="guitar" /><summary type="html">Viva Las Vengeance is perhaps the greatest album ever to have almost completely passed me by, and I don’t think I’m alone in that. It was only via a coincidental search that I caught the titular single and Middle of a Breakup on Panic! at the Disco’s YouTube channel, and there seemed to be very little fanfare in the buildup to the album’s August 2022 release. When I did realise the record was out, I listened through it exactly once on Spotify, my expectations fairly low given the more pop-focused direction of its predecessor, Pray for the Wicked. Maybe I was in the wrong mood or too distracted, but I didn’t think much of it, and skipped on tickets for the tour when I saw Brandon Urie was playing the album in full at gigs. How foolish I was. In mid-April 2023, I spotted an article from earlier in the year that said that Panic! at the Disco were no more, with Urie having wound down the project to focus on his family. In a mournful mood (Pretty. Odd. and Death of a Bachelor are two of my favourite albums), I revisited Viva Las Vengeance to see if anything clicked, or if I could piece together anything about his state of mind when writing and recording it. Once I got beyond the two opening singles, I was entranced. Far from the last record’s bland pop, Viva Las Vengeance is deliberately recorded as a tribute to 1970s rock, and in that sense almost serves as a sequel to Pretty. Odd.’s 1960s tones. While there’s plenty of variety, these influences are most apparent in the Queen-style harmonies and Brian May-inspired solos.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/04/viva-las-vengeance_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/04/viva-las-vengeance_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Menu review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/03/18/the-menu-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Menu review" /><published>2023-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/03/18/the-menu-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/03/18/the-menu-review">&lt;p&gt;I’m very glad I didn’t go to see &lt;em&gt;The Menu&lt;/em&gt; at the cinema. Not because it’s a bad film, but because as somebody who suffers from intermittent anxiety,  visiting a restaurant can sometimes be quite a tense experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/the-menu_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will I like the food? If I don’t, should I eat it anyway? Will I seem uncultured if I don’t recognise the more exotic menu items? Are the waiting staff secretly judging me based on our brief interactions or overheard comments? &lt;em&gt;The Menu&lt;/em&gt; takes these anxieties, which I’m sure are common to some degree amongst much of the population, and cranks the dial up to 11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dinner-is-served&quot;&gt;Dinner is served&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relatively mundane opening sees a group of customers pay $1,250 a head to visit an exclusive restaurant on an island, but even as they tuck in to their first courses, there are glances and comments that set off those internal alarm bells. It really makes for quite uncomfortable viewing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the guests are an obsessive foodie and his date, a restaurant critic, an actor, and a group of fintech bros. It feels like a very &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/01/13/glass-onion-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; kind of group. For the first third of the film we watch them tour the island and eat, with a looming sense of dread (owed to an expertly creepy performance from Hong Chau as the maitre d’, Elsa) and some very sharp comedic writing.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, like &lt;em&gt;Triangle of Sadness&lt;/em&gt; (which at some point I’ll see if I remember enough of to write a review), &lt;em&gt;The Menu&lt;/em&gt; takes a lavish, exclusive experience that most people could only dream of enjoying and takes it completely off the rails. To its credit, &lt;em&gt;unlike&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Triangle of Sadness&lt;/em&gt;, the writing maintains its edge after this point and the second half is not entirely predictable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;threading-the-needle&quot;&gt;Threading the needle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trailer made it look like the film would end in simple bloodshed, but although there is some action and slashing involved, I can assure you that it retains its expertise in making you shift awkwardly in your seat throughout. In fact, it takes a huge amount of skill to blend psychological horror and dining cringe to such a degree while maintaining a natural pacing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particular credit goes to Ralph Fiennes, whose character Julian Slowik teeters on the border between gentleman and madman, having quite reasonable conversations with his guests one moment and asking the unthinkable of them the next. In many ways, he makes the film, balancing the needle at just the right point between comedy and thriller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing &lt;em&gt;The Menu&lt;/em&gt; has a knack for is giving you hope before snatching it away - with a dash of wit to stop the mood from feeling too sinister. Just when it appears to be heading for a ridiculous ending - and the eventual denouement is still its weakest element - it changes course yet again. A classic? Maybe not. But &lt;em&gt;The Menu&lt;/em&gt; is well worth two hours of your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;4/5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="films" /><summary type="html">I’m very glad I didn’t go to see The Menu at the cinema. Not because it’s a bad film, but because as somebody who suffers from intermittent anxiety, visiting a restaurant can sometimes be quite a tense experience. Will I like the food? If I don’t, should I eat it anyway? Will I seem uncultured if I don’t recognise the more exotic menu items? Are the waiting staff secretly judging me based on our brief interactions or overheard comments? The Menu takes these anxieties, which I’m sure are common to some degree amongst much of the population, and cranks the dial up to 11. Dinner is served The relatively mundane opening sees a group of customers pay $1,250 a head to visit an exclusive restaurant on an island, but even as they tuck in to their first courses, there are glances and comments that set off those internal alarm bells. It really makes for quite uncomfortable viewing. Among the guests are an obsessive foodie and his date, a restaurant critic, an actor, and a group of fintech bros. It feels like a very Knives Out kind of group. For the first third of the film we watch them tour the island and eat, with a looming sense of dread (owed to an expertly creepy performance from Hong Chau as the maitre d’, Elsa) and some very sharp comedic writing.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/03/the-menu_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/03/the-menu_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons in management from Jose Mourinho</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/03/12/jose-mourinho-management" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons in management from Jose Mourinho" /><published>2023-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/03/12/jose-mourinho-management</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/03/12/jose-mourinho-management">&lt;p&gt;Apologies for the near two-month gap between articles. Some changes in my personal life required my attention, but things are more settled now and updates should come more regularly - albeit with &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/01/08/what-to-expect-tsp-2023&quot;&gt;a slightly different flavour&lt;/a&gt; than before, and more variety in the subject matter I’ll be covering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest artefact to catch my attention is Patrick Barclay’s book &lt;em&gt;Mourinho: Further Anatomy of a Winner&lt;/em&gt;. As a Chelsea fan, Jose holds a special place in my heart despite his subsequent spells at Manchester United and Spurs, and his special relationship with his players and media mind games have always made him an interesting figure beyond mere club allegiance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book has only been updated as far as Chelsea’s 2015 Premier League title success, so there’s no coverage of Mourinho’s recent, more turbulent managerial stints, but it still provided some fascinating insights from the perspectives of both the press and the people who knew him best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;man-management&quot;&gt;Man management&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recruitment is a key part of football - especially for a manager at Chelsea or Real Madrid - but something that shone through clearly is Mourinho’s attention to individuals’ progression. Take this account from Joe Cole, who faced a tough start at Chelsea, but later showed dramatic improvement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“His criticism is always constructive - he’ll always sit me down and talk about my game and what he wants me to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mourinho was always on the lookout for those who wanted to learn, and was a firm believer that players are most likely to reach their potential when they are open to advice, rather than just relying on their natural ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-supportive-presence&quot;&gt;A supportive presence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mourinho was often described as a kind of “big brother” to his players, capable of being stern when needed, but often behaving as though he was one of them, trading jokes and joining in with their wild celebrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But his impact went beyond the squad, and he had a reputation for being friendly with everybody he met, including stewards and ball boys - even when playing away at opponents’ stadiums. When he initially parted ways with Chelsea in 2007, many around the club were reportedly distraught.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, even the less savoury side of Mourinho’s character - the wild accusations made against opponents and officials, for example - appears to stem from a desire to take one for the team. These moments would usually occur after poor performances, and meant that the headlines would often be about his remarks rather than what happened on the pitch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forward-as-one&quot;&gt;Forward as one&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a similar vein, Mourinho always strove for an inclusive dressing room. He wanted all his players to love and trust each other, reportedly even going as far as to mandate that the entire squad should eat together at the same table to preserve unity and prevent the formation of cliques within the club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mourinho always wanted to ensure that his team was performing as a collective - not relying on a few talented individuals - and the attention he paid to the entire squad meant that, somewhat unsually, even fringe players who struggled for first team minutes often spoke highly of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such was his focus on team spirit, in fact, that Mourinho reportedly didn’t even give the final team talk before most matches. Instead, he would give his directions earlier in the day, and a different player would be responsible for giving the last, rousing pre-game speech each week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inspiring-confidence&quot;&gt;Inspiring confidence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s not to say that Mourinho himself couldn’t motivate his men. One figure interviewed (unfortunately I didn’t note who) said that a good coach “must make his men feel big, not small”, and that’s precisely what he did. Here’s John Terry, for example, on Chelsea’s culture during the seasons between 2004 and 2006 when they won back-to-back titles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When you’ve got a manager drumming it into you every day that you are the best… it rubs off on the players and we go out there believing it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chelsea didn’t come from nowhere when Roman Abramovich arrived, but those seasons were the start of a period of domestic dominance. Mourinho’s approach here reminds me of the old saying, “Dress for the job you want, not the job you have” - only here he was mentally dressing his players for success. And given his track record, you can only say that it worked.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="football" /><category term="business" /><category term="managment" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">Apologies for the near two-month gap between articles. Some changes in my personal life required my attention, but things are more settled now and updates should come more regularly - albeit with a slightly different flavour than before, and more variety in the subject matter I’ll be covering. The latest artefact to catch my attention is Patrick Barclay’s book Mourinho: Further Anatomy of a Winner. As a Chelsea fan, Jose holds a special place in my heart despite his subsequent spells at Manchester United and Spurs, and his special relationship with his players and media mind games have always made him an interesting figure beyond mere club allegiance. The book has only been updated as far as Chelsea’s 2015 Premier League title success, so there’s no coverage of Mourinho’s recent, more turbulent managerial stints, but it still provided some fascinating insights from the perspectives of both the press and the people who knew him best. Man management Recruitment is a key part of football - especially for a manager at Chelsea or Real Madrid - but something that shone through clearly is Mourinho’s attention to individuals’ progression. Take this account from Joe Cole, who faced a tough start at Chelsea, but later showed dramatic improvement: “His criticism is always constructive - he’ll always sit me down and talk about my game and what he wants me to do.” Mourinho was always on the lookout for those who wanted to learn, and was a firm believer that players are most likely to reach their potential when they are open to advice, rather than just relying on their natural ability. A supportive presence Mourinho was often described as a kind of “big brother” to his players, capable of being stern when needed, but often behaving as though he was one of them, trading jokes and joining in with their wild celebrations. But his impact went beyond the squad, and he had a reputation for being friendly with everybody he met, including stewards and ball boys - even when playing away at opponents’ stadiums. When he initially parted ways with Chelsea in 2007, many around the club were reportedly distraught.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Glass Onion review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/13/glass-onion-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Glass Onion review" /><published>2023-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/13/glass-onion-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/13/glass-onion-review">&lt;p&gt;Just before Christmas 2022, Netflix released &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt;, the next film in the &lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt; series. Expecting another clever, witty mystery from Rian Johnson I sat down to watch it over the holiday period, but was disappointed to find it did not deliver anything close to the quality of its predecessor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/glass-onion_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before anybody takes this article the wrong way, I’ll start by saying this: &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt; is a good film. It looks great, the mystery is intriguing in part, there’s some enjoyable dialogue (particularly from Daniel Craig), and it kept me more engaged from start to finish than most modern releases do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt; is not even close to being &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; good as &lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt;. While there a number of reasons for this, in this article I’ll focus on what I think are the two biggest problems (with &lt;strong&gt;plenty of spoilers&lt;/strong&gt; along the way, so I advise that you actually watch the film before reading any further).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;intro-and-setup&quot;&gt;Intro and setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things start out promisingly enough. A bunch of prominent people receive puzzle boxes containing invitations to a billionaire’s private island, where it appears he’ll be hosting a murder mystery event. Given the genre, it’s clear something will go wrong, so from the start you’re keen to see what it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These opening scenes are very heavy on comedic lines, which makes the tone a little odd, but &lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt; also subverted some of the genre’s conventions, so it’s not necessarily surprising. Lastly, we see Benoit Blanc himself receive a box, but - importantly - we’re not shown how or why.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group get to the island and hang out a bit, and we are introduced to Edward Norton’s character, who falls into the “rich, slightly hippie asshole” archetype. There’s some tension with his ex-business partner, who nobody seems to want around, and she lashes out at the group and says they’re all leeches who rely on the billionaire for survival. Alongside this there’s some motive setup, with several characters given reasons to despise him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At dinner, Blanc solves the murder mystery before the fake death even occurs, but things get more complicated when a muscly vlogger chokes and the police say they can’t make it to the island before morning. The power goes out, people scatter, and somebody shoots the ex-partner. Seems like the legendary detective Benoit Blanc has a lot of work to do, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem-1-restarting-halfway-through&quot;&gt;Problem #1: Restarting halfway through&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well… wrong. Because the first mistake &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt; makes after building all this intrigue is to take us right back to the start of the story. This isn’t a short flashback, either - instead of watching Blanc solve the mystery, we need to retread a lot of ground to find out exactly how he got involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, the person who got shot was not in fact Andi, Miles Bron’s former business partner. She was already mysteriously killed in her own home prior to the whole event, and when her twin sister Helen asked Benoit Blanc to investigate her death, he convinced her to come to the island to pose as her sister and help him. He said it would be dangerous, but she was sold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/glass-onion_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spend what feels like an eternity waiting for the film to catch up with itself as we watch them prepare. Helen doesn’t consider herself as capable as the “shitheads” in the group, but acts more intelligently than them throughout. For example, between meeting Blanc and arriving on the island, she reads and memorises all her sister’s diaries to the degree of detail that she can pose as her in front of people who used to be her closest friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the present, we see that the person we now know as Helen is not actually dead - the bullet was blocked by her sister’s journal. This removes what could have been an emotional moment for Blanc (as he persuaded her to go to the island), but it turns out that the tear we saw him shed was actually due to him rubbing hot sauce in his eye. This part in particular felt like the filmakers choosing being clever over telling an engaging story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blanc, almost certainly the series’ main draw, then spends the rest of the film marvelling over Helen’s superhuman detective abilities. Even when she accidentally gets drunk (she’s usually a teetotaller) there are no negative consequences and she’s more effective than him. And when Blanc &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; get to take centre stage for the traditional “whodunnit?” speech, it’s actually just a huge filibuster to buy time for Helen to snoop around elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem-2-the-murderer-is-obvious&quot;&gt;Problem #2: The murderer is obvious&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More problematic is that &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt;’s resolution is completely predictable, and I called it shortly after the group arrived on the island. Murder mystery films usually have an obvious suspect who the audience is led to believe is the culprit before a surprise bait and switch in the final stages, but this film does no such thing, and the answer is just sitting there throughout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue is it’s clear from the start that writer Rian Johnson’s worldview approximately matches that of the average Twitter user. The original &lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt; had a character describe another as an “alt-right troll dipshit”, one of &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt;’s main characters is an exaggerated men’s rights vlogger with zero redeeming qualities, and there are a few lines in the first two thirds of the film where characters sneer about his slide to “the right” and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/glass-onion_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I am expressing no personal political opinions here (this is an entertainment site, after all) - just noting that throughout the films we get clues as to the writer’s own perspective on things, and this meta eventually proves enough for us to predict who he would likely portray as a murderer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because with the vlogger killed early on, which of the remaining characters would somebody with this outlook despise the most? Perhaps tech billionaires were front of mind given the recent furore around Twitter and Elon Musk, but Miles Bron was the obvious standout for me. Surprise, surprise - Blanc and Helen eventually deduce that he killed his ex-business partner, and for the finale we get to watch Bron grow increasingly frustrated as Helen trashes his expensive house, even burning the Mona Lisa, which he has out on loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone watching for a murder mystery on the level of the excellent &lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt;, it was disappointing not only that the story was so easy to predict, without any extra twist, but that the final scene also passed up the opportunity for any clever resolution to indulge in the fantasy of breaking a billionaire’s stuff. The film as a whole deserved a better ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll go back to what I said at the beginning - all this isn’t enough to make &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt; a bad film. It was clever (sometimes more so than it needed to be), occasionally beautiful, and Craig even got a few laughs out of me. I’ll certainly watch any further films in the series - I’ll just be hoping that they’re more like &lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt; than this messy yet predictable instalment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3/5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="films" /><summary type="html">Just before Christmas 2022, Netflix released Glass Onion, the next film in the Knives Out series. Expecting another clever, witty mystery from Rian Johnson I sat down to watch it over the holiday period, but was disappointed to find it did not deliver anything close to the quality of its predecessor. Before anybody takes this article the wrong way, I’ll start by saying this: Glass Onion is a good film. It looks great, the mystery is intriguing in part, there’s some enjoyable dialogue (particularly from Daniel Craig), and it kept me more engaged from start to finish than most modern releases do. However, Glass Onion is not even close to being as good as Knives Out. While there a number of reasons for this, in this article I’ll focus on what I think are the two biggest problems (with plenty of spoilers along the way, so I advise that you actually watch the film before reading any further). Intro and setup Things start out promisingly enough. A bunch of prominent people receive puzzle boxes containing invitations to a billionaire’s private island, where it appears he’ll be hosting a murder mystery event. Given the genre, it’s clear something will go wrong, so from the start you’re keen to see what it is. These opening scenes are very heavy on comedic lines, which makes the tone a little odd, but Knives Out also subverted some of the genre’s conventions, so it’s not necessarily surprising. Lastly, we see Benoit Blanc himself receive a box, but - importantly - we’re not shown how or why.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/glass-onion_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/glass-onion_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What to expect from TSP in 2023</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/08/what-to-expect-tsp-2023" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What to expect from TSP in 2023" /><published>2023-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/08/what-to-expect-tsp-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/08/what-to-expect-tsp-2023">&lt;p&gt;It’s been quite a ride for &lt;em&gt;The Strat Pack&lt;/em&gt; since the site’s original soft launch in September 2021. More than a year later, after a site design upgrade and 76 articles, my musings on games and adjacent interests have amassed nearly 50,000 views, which is certainly more than I expected at the start. I appreciate everybody for taking the time to read them, and especially those who have emailed in to give their views and chat about their favourites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some articles have performed much as I’d have hoped - &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/02/19/newbies-guide-buying-formula-1-models&quot;&gt;my introduction to Formula 1 model collecting&lt;/a&gt; is the fourth most read article here, for example - but often there is a huge disconnect between the effort I expend writing an article (and how proud I am of it) and its reception, and that can be tough. A simple how-to guide can sometimes yield tens of thousands of views, while a sprawling retrospective can get nowhere near breaking into triple figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can add to that the pressure that I have put myself under to deliver weekly articles. This has a few knock-on effects, including the occasional rushed news or opinion piece when I run out of time, but the biggest consequence is forcing me to play games to a schedule. If I have a review or retrospective slated in for a specific date, I’ll sacrifice my evenings for the preceding week for play sessions to finish it, even if I’m not in the mood. But gaming is a longstanding hobby of mine, and it shouldn’t feel like a chore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I also feel like I’ve already covered most of the older games that immediately sprang to mind when I started the site, and there aren’t enough new titles I’m interested in to provide a consistent flow of content. When I paused work on posts over the Christmas break, I found myself playing a lot of endurance races in &lt;em&gt;Automobilista 2&lt;/em&gt;, and that wouldn’t be fertile ground for many articles without repeating myself a whole lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fear not - it may sound like I’m building up to shutting down the site, or at the very least going on hiatus, but what I actually want to say is that in 2023 I’ll be taking a more relaxed approach to &lt;em&gt;The Strat Pack&lt;/em&gt;. Articles will go up when I have something specific that I’m enthusiastic to write about - not on a fixed weekly basis - and I’ll open up the subject matter more often to films, television, music, and so on to accommodate this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome (I hope) is that although posts might be slightly less frequent, they’ll be of higher quality when they are published, and will be worth your time to read. It might sacrifice some numbers from algorithms that demand regular updates, but I think this approach will produce a site I can be more proud of, give me more time to play games I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to play, and be more accommodating to other changes in my life heading into the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for stopping by, and I hope you will continue to do so. Please &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thestratpack&quot;&gt;follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for updates regarding new articles, and I hope to connect with many more of you as the year goes on. All the best for 2023!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><summary type="html">It’s been quite a ride for The Strat Pack since the site’s original soft launch in September 2021. More than a year later, after a site design upgrade and 76 articles, my musings on games and adjacent interests have amassed nearly 50,000 views, which is certainly more than I expected at the start. I appreciate everybody for taking the time to read them, and especially those who have emailed in to give their views and chat about their favourites. Some articles have performed much as I’d have hoped - my introduction to Formula 1 model collecting is the fourth most read article here, for example - but often there is a huge disconnect between the effort I expend writing an article (and how proud I am of it) and its reception, and that can be tough. A simple how-to guide can sometimes yield tens of thousands of views, while a sprawling retrospective can get nowhere near breaking into triple figures. You can add to that the pressure that I have put myself under to deliver weekly articles. This has a few knock-on effects, including the occasional rushed news or opinion piece when I run out of time, but the biggest consequence is forcing me to play games to a schedule. If I have a review or retrospective slated in for a specific date, I’ll sacrifice my evenings for the preceding week for play sessions to finish it, even if I’m not in the mood. But gaming is a longstanding hobby of mine, and it shouldn’t feel like a chore. Furthermore, I also feel like I’ve already covered most of the older games that immediately sprang to mind when I started the site, and there aren’t enough new titles I’m interested in to provide a consistent flow of content. When I paused work on posts over the Christmas break, I found myself playing a lot of endurance races in Automobilista 2, and that wouldn’t be fertile ground for many articles without repeating myself a whole lot. Fear not - it may sound like I’m building up to shutting down the site, or at the very least going on hiatus, but what I actually want to say is that in 2023 I’ll be taking a more relaxed approach to The Strat Pack. Articles will go up when I have something specific that I’m enthusiastic to write about - not on a fixed weekly basis - and I’ll open up the subject matter more often to films, television, music, and so on to accommodate this. The outcome (I hope) is that although posts might be slightly less frequent, they’ll be of higher quality when they are published, and will be worth your time to read. It might sacrifice some numbers from algorithms that demand regular updates, but I think this approach will produce a site I can be more proud of, give me more time to play games I want to play, and be more accommodating to other changes in my life heading into the new year. Thanks for stopping by, and I hope you will continue to do so. Please follow me on Twitter for updates regarding new articles, and I hope to connect with many more of you as the year goes on. All the best for 2023!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – making history</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/25/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA 22 Career Mode&amp;#58; TSP United &amp;#8211; making history" /><published>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/25/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/25/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-4">&lt;p&gt;Last time out in my &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Career Mode series I was lucky to hold on to my job as TSP United manager after a disappointing 2026/27 season. Would I be able to handle the mounting pressure in England’s top flight with the board’s expectations ever increasing? Perhaps this photo might give you a clue…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a reminder, I’m playing this Career Mode campaign with special custom rules for some added challenge. I’m not to spend a penny on players (signing free agents is fine) and the focus is on &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players&quot;&gt;scouting and developing youth players&lt;/a&gt;. So my main source of new talent through this whole thing is to send a scout out around England occasionally and see what he brings back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this is the fourth instalment of my TSP United Career Mode series. Click here to catch up on the first six seasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/06/17/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-2&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – hitting the big time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/09/16/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-3&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – cup runs to remember&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202728---premier-league&quot;&gt;2027/28 - Premier League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a rough last season, I didn’t opt to make any signings heading into 2027/28, instead making some rearrangements as young players returned from loan. Notably, Gale took the spot between the sticks, relegating the inconsistent Parkin to the bench. Departures included former regular striker Prince, one of the few remaining original TSP United players.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were off the mark quickly and went on a frankly insane run of form considering our recent struggles, ending up top after ten games, having won 25 of the 30 available points. Gale was making saves well beyond his ability on paper, and by December I was wondering whether we might be on course to do a Leicester (who ironically were our closest title rivals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stumbled slightly over the Christmas period, lacking the squad depth to handle two games a week, but stayed on Leicester’s tail. As Chelsea took the top spot we were scraping victories, often coming back from steep deficits to win. But our form prevailed, and with five games left we inched ahead of the Blues. The fate of the league season was in our hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we beat Arsenal and Newcastle emphatically, Chelsea lost to City, putting us four points ahead. We had a chance to win the league in our penultimate game of the season at the Etihad, and didn’t let it go to waste. Pierre and Vaughan both netted braces, and the scoring was capped off by Goddard as we thrashed Pep Guardiola’s team and were crowned Premier League champions at the end of a truly improbable season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best player&lt;/strong&gt; - Annumanian, who broke Vaughan’s scoring record&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - N/A, because we made no signings&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Gale, who became the new first-choice GK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202829---premier-league&quot;&gt;2028/29 - Premier League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a league title under our belts, my sights were firmly set on a grand European finale to this Career Mode campaign. With most of our players improving, there was no need for huge squad changes, but I did bring Hunter into the first team at LM, moving the declining legend Willis to the bench.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We beat Man United in the Community Shield and made a strong start in the league despite losing Vaughan to a three-month injury. Our Champions League campaign was less smooth. We drew a tricky group, which featured both Inter and Bayern, and a defeat to the latter in the final group stage match saw us tumble out into the Europa League. The dream was over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unexpectedly, the Premier League became something of a saunter and we retained our title with a couple of games to go. Meanwhile, our Europa League run saw us face off with Manchester United, Villareal, and AC Milan, setting up a final date with a Liverpool team we’d smashed 4-0 just days before with a second-string lineup, on the final day of the league season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first team made no mistake on the big occasion. TSP United applied the early pressure before Pierre headed in a Hunter corner in the fifth minute. A fantastic Alisson performance kept Liverpool in the game, but goals from Annumanian and Vaughan meant we were four goals clear by half time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pierre got a fifth early in the second half, and when Neto was shown a red card we controlled the rest of the game. Proceedings were capped off by Willis, a late substitute, who grabbed the sixth and final goal in stoppage time with perhaps his last kick of a ball for TSP United. Maybe our Champions Leauge bid fell short, but we were European champions nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best player&lt;/strong&gt; - Annumanian, pushing the limits yet again&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - N/A, because we made no signings&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Hancock, straight in at CB on his loan return&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">Last time out in my FIFA 22 Career Mode series I was lucky to hold on to my job as TSP United manager after a disappointing 2026/27 season. Would I be able to handle the mounting pressure in England’s top flight with the board’s expectations ever increasing? Perhaps this photo might give you a clue… As a reminder, I’m playing this Career Mode campaign with special custom rules for some added challenge. I’m not to spend a penny on players (signing free agents is fine) and the focus is on scouting and developing youth players. So my main source of new talent through this whole thing is to send a scout out around England occasionally and see what he brings back. Note that this is the fourth instalment of my TSP United Career Mode series. Click here to catch up on the first six seasons: • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – hitting the big time • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – cup runs to remember 2027/28 - Premier League Despite a rough last season, I didn’t opt to make any signings heading into 2027/28, instead making some rearrangements as young players returned from loan. Notably, Gale took the spot between the sticks, relegating the inconsistent Parkin to the bench. Departures included former regular striker Prince, one of the few remaining original TSP United players.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Splinter Cell remake details on series’ 20th birthday</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/18/splinter-cell-20th-anniversary-remake" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Splinter Cell remake details on series' 20th birthday" /><published>2022-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/18/splinter-cell-20th-anniversary-remake</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/18/splinter-cell-20th-anniversary-remake">&lt;p&gt;Fans on the &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; subreddit were speculating recently about what Ubisoft might do for the series’ 20th anniversary. While &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/12/18/splinter-cell-remake&quot;&gt;the upcoming remake&lt;/a&gt; stoked some excitement, the publisher has been so neglectful of Sam Fisher and his pals in recent years that many expected nothing at all this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/splinter-cell-20th-anniversary-remake_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it turns out we did get something! &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XfJpSeit3zI&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The video uploaded to the Ubisoft YouTube account&lt;/a&gt; was as full of marketing fluff as you might expect, but it did include some interesting bits and pieces - including a look back at the series’ history and a very brief discussion of the upcoming game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-from-the-past&quot;&gt;Learning from the past&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part of the video focused on the past, and chiefly on the original &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt;, which was released in 2002. While there was some nostalgia to be enjoyed, watching a bunch of Ubisoft staffers sitting around a table and talking about their experiences as players wasn’t particularly interesting, and we didn’t get any worthwhile insight into the game’s development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the usual discussion of the series’ technical innovations (lighting, flowing drapes, fish tanks, and so on) there was a somewhat interesting discussion of Sam Fisher’s character, in which they pointed out how he was more human the usual video game lead character, speaking to enemies, defying orders to save people uninvolved in the mission, and so on.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this wasn’t groundbreaking stuff, it was nice to see that the people working on the remake appreciate this side of Sam’s character, as well as the slower, stealthier gameplay that made the first few titles what they were. Also interesting was that at one point they mentioned they had read &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1TaxVlnfcGVy56oQt4HHlCopUOAfAqATFF7IqT7zm5wM/edit&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the open letter fans wrote to Ubisoft&lt;/a&gt; pleading for a return to the series’ roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;news-on-the-future&quot;&gt;News on the future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us on nicely to the second half of the video, which was definitely the highlight, because this was the part where we were drip fed a few more precious details about the upcoming &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There will be more variance in the game’s AI - for example, standard security guards will respond to threats less adeptly than elite mercenaries, who will “behave like trained professionals”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio occlusion will form a part of the stealth, with sounds bouncing off of and being absorbed by different surfaces depending on material&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was some vague talk about a desire to make Sam’s movements more “immersive” as the player moves through the levels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The team were very clear that stealth is the priority, and they are working to ensure that zero-kill mission completion is possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The “harsh” three-strikes-and-you’re-out alarms from the early games will be scaled back, giving the player a chance to de-escalate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regarding the story, there was more allusion to changing “things that haven’t aged particularly well”, without any specifics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So along with &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/12/18/splinter-cell-remake&quot;&gt;the initial details&lt;/a&gt; there’s plenty to think about, even if concrete details are still thin on the ground. Unfortunately, the team ended the video with a warning that they would be “going dark for a while” to focus on development, so it’s anyone’s guess when we’ll get more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need something to keep you occupied in the meantime, head over to the Ubisoft Store, where the original &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; is free until 30th November.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="splinter-cell" /><category term="stealth" /><summary type="html">Fans on the Splinter Cell subreddit were speculating recently about what Ubisoft might do for the series’ 20th anniversary. While the upcoming remake stoked some excitement, the publisher has been so neglectful of Sam Fisher and his pals in recent years that many expected nothing at all this week. But it turns out we did get something! The video uploaded to the Ubisoft YouTube account was as full of marketing fluff as you might expect, but it did include some interesting bits and pieces - including a look back at the series’ history and a very brief discussion of the upcoming game. Learning from the past The first part of the video focused on the past, and chiefly on the original Splinter Cell, which was released in 2002. While there was some nostalgia to be enjoyed, watching a bunch of Ubisoft staffers sitting around a table and talking about their experiences as players wasn’t particularly interesting, and we didn’t get any worthwhile insight into the game’s development. As well as the usual discussion of the series’ technical innovations (lighting, flowing drapes, fish tanks, and so on) there was a somewhat interesting discussion of Sam Fisher’s character, in which they pointed out how he was more human the usual video game lead character, speaking to enemies, defying orders to save people uninvolved in the mission, and so on.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/splinter-cell-20th-anniversary-remake_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/splinter-cell-20th-anniversary-remake_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3 (Xbox 360) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/11/call-of-duty-modern-warfare-3-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Call of Duty&amp;#58; Modern Warfare 3 (Xbox 360) retrospective" /><published>2022-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/11/call-of-duty-modern-warfare-3-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/11/call-of-duty-modern-warfare-3-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;With a bit more time on my hands this week, I decided to dust off my Xbox One and play through a game that I sunk many an hour into on the Xbox 360 about a decade ago (although it turns out not in the way I thought) - &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3&lt;/em&gt;. As the final game in the first-person shooter series’ most popular and iconic trilogy, this one had a lot to live up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2011, almost 11 years ago to the day at the time of writing, Activision released the Infinity Ward-developed &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3&lt;/em&gt;, marking the final instalment in a trilogy that set &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/call-of-duty&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; free from the confines of its traditional World War II setting, redefined online multiplayer, and elevated the series as a whole to become an instantly recognisable pillar of mainstream gaming and a reliable moneymaker for the publisher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With so much focus on the game’s multiplayer, the campaign is the topic of far less discussion. In fact, when I started playing it via the Xbox One’s backwards compatibility (sidenote - for some reason this required an 11GB game update, and it arguably would have been quicker to dig out my 360), I started earning achievements after the first couple of missions. Apparently the multiplayer, and in particular the co-op Special Ops, were such a distraction that I never completed &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt;’s campaign back in the day.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setting-the-scene&quot;&gt;Setting the scene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jumping back into it in 2022, &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; picks up right after &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/18/call-of-duty-modern-warfare-2-retrospective&quot;&gt;the bizarre final events of &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, with Price and Nikolai rushing Soap to a safehouse for medical assistance. The logo on the title screen tells us what to expect, as “WW3” morphs into &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; - this game is set to tackle war on a huge scale, as Makarov-engineered Russian aggression targets states around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conveying this urgency, we’re thrown straight into a mission in New York, bypassing the usual &lt;em&gt;COD&lt;/em&gt; tutorial. We mount an assault to take back the New York Stock Exchange, board a Russian submarine, and a high-speed chase ensues through the harbour. Unusually for the series, this is about all we’ll see of the US, as most of the game’s action takes place in Europe (although oddly, and perhaps in an effort not to alienate a large part of the audience, most missions are still played from the perspective of US troops).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then play as Yuri, helping Captain Price evacuate the injured Soap (who after &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt; has apparently ascended to NPC legend status) as the safehouse comes under attack. We miss the extraction chopper and fall down a slope into a river, but Price rescues us - an instant reminder of what a guy he is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a series first, the next mission is played from a Russian perspective, as we fill the shoes of a guard on the president’s private jet. The plane is attacked by Makarov’s terrorists, and there are some cool zero-G moments during the shootouts as the plane plummets to the ground. We locate the president in the wreckage, but just as we’re about to extract him Makarov appears and kidnaps him. Before shooting us dead, he says Russia will take control of Europe even if it has to burn it to the ground in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;going-underground&quot;&gt;Going underground&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next is a stealth mission with Price and Soap as you investigate a tip that Makarov is transporting something to London. This features a challenging sniper segment, but all that good work is undone when you must fire mortar that is painfully slow and prevents you from moving to avoid hits. When you eventually reach your destination, you find the cargo is already gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shipment is in a warehouse in Tower Hamlets, which allows for a nice level visually, with the grimy industrial estate juxtaposed against the bright lights of Canary Wharf in the background. As with many missions in &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; this starts quiet before turning into an all-out firefight against hordes of enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad guys eventually jump into a random waiting Tube train, and I can forgive the questionable accuracy as we chase them through the tunnels on a truck just because the sequence is pretty cool, especially as the chase bursts through packed commuter platforms. The train derails at Westminster and you fight your way up through the station to surface level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A suspect van arrives and is shot down, but it’s not the only one. We’re whisked away to this game’s answer to &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt;’s No Russian - a wholly unnecessary segment where we play a camera-wielding dad filming his wife and little girl on holiday in London. A van pulls up, Russians in gas masks jump out, and we see our family killed in a chemical attack. The next cut scene tells us that similar attacks are taking place across Europe, paving the way for a Russian invasion, so why did this need to be playable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-european-tour&quot;&gt;A European tour&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US forces move in on Hamburg to rescue the vice president in a mission that plays out much more like classic &lt;em&gt;COD&lt;/em&gt;, with an opening that seems to be deliberately reminiscent of the D-Day beach landings and large-scale battles between opposing squads across vast areas. It’s perhaps telling in terms of the series’ direction that there’s not much else notable about this level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then play as Yuri once again, alternating between on-foot and chopper turret sections as he and the gang attempt to locate an arms dealer who has been working with Makarov. He tells us that his bomb maker, Volk, is headed for Paris. This mission is set apart by its finale, which sees you fight through a sandstorm. Everything turns orange and black, and the effects and lighting make this look very nice even by today’s standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next big set piece mission takes us to Paris, where the American squad are wearing gas masks because there is still toxic residue from the chemical attacks in the air. This is the first of several parts of &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; that feel like they’re paying homage to the &lt;em&gt;Wolfenstein&lt;/em&gt; games, as we drop down into creepily lit catacombs descorated with skulls and bones to find Volk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This culminates in a car chase with some on-rails shooting, ending in some seriously excessive ramming as we disable Volk’s vehicle and capture him. The last segment is a battle on a bridge, at the end of which an explosion causes the Eiffel Tower to topple into the Seine. They just couldn’t resist the visuals, which form a part of some of the game’s promotional images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;return-to-castle-makarov&quot;&gt;Return to Castle Makarov&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volk says Makarov is in Prague, so Yuri and co. are sent to infiltrate the city to get close to the castle in preparation. This is full-on &lt;em&gt;Wolfenstein&lt;/em&gt;, from the architecture to the black armour worn by the Russian soldiers. Soap mimics Price in Chernobyl mode - the flawless guide whose footsteps we must follow as we creep around in the shadows avoiding enemy patrols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is ripped straight from the original &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare&lt;/em&gt;, and there are some moments where the Russian soldiers must be straight-up blind not to see us, it is perhaps the best mission in the game simply because it has more character than most of the others. This is further elevated when it goes loud (as they all do) and we find ourselves helping the Czech resistance to take on the Russians in huge battles in the city’s streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hide out in a church that is serving as a resistance HQ until morning, planning to snipe Makarov when he arrives for a meeting. Our contact betrays us and blows us up, and when we wake we have to protect Price as he carries an injured Soap through the streets. Just before he dies, Soap finds the strength to tell Price that Makarov knows Yuri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Price punches us down some stairs to interrogate us, and in a flashback we see that Yuri did indeed previously work with Makarov, but that he was betrayed, turned good, and attempted to stop the No Russian massacre. Apparently this is enough to convince Price, but he won’t admit it because he just says he won’t kill us “for now” and it’s never mentioned again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more Price-led stealth as we infiltrate the castle - as in &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt;, this mostly consists of him doing all the cool stuff while we wait behind. Things are mixed up in an interesting way when he kills the lights in a prison area and we use our night vision to take out helpless enemies, but this lasts all of 20 seconds before they drop flares and can see again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_8.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learn the Russian president’s daughter is in Berlin and that he is likely to give up his nuclear codes to Makarov if she is located and taken hostage. The US team in Germany go after her, repeatedly disobeying orders to extract after the first team is destroyed by Russian forces, and we only catch a brief glimpse of her before she’s whisked away in a chopper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tying-up-the-loose-ends&quot;&gt;Tying up the loose ends&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With his daughter in enemy hands, Yuri and Price need to locate the Russian president in a Siberian diamond mine before he gives up the launch codes. Our fight through the mine ends in a bizarre vertical breach as we plant explosives on the floor and drop down to rescue the president. Yuri gets blown up but Price helps him to the chopper, which takes off and leaves US team leader Sandman (did I mention him before?) to his presumable death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US and Russia declare peace (European countries too, I hope, since they’ve been on the receiving end of invasions throughout the game) but Makarov is still at large, and Price can’t have that. We get to play as the legend himself for the first time as he and Yuri don juggernaut armour and launch an assault on the Dubai hotel where Makarov is staying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_9.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we reach the top, a chopper fires a rocket that leaves Yuri impaled. He tells us to leave him and go after Makarov, so we jump onto his helicopter as it takes off and fight the pilots. Somehow both of us surive the ensuing crash, and we wake to see a gun on the floor between us and Makarov.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Price crawls towards the gun, but Makarov takes it from us and shoots Yuri dead. A fist fight follows in which we tie a cable around his neck and push him through the shattered glass floor, leaving him hanging at the top of the hotel. Price lands on a balcony, and in the absence of anyone to say a cool line to, silently lights a cigar. It’s over - World War III has been won.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many trilogy endings - notably &lt;em&gt;The Dark Night Rises&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare 3&lt;/em&gt; suffers in that the stakes are so high by this point that there’s a sense everything must be overly dramatic and extreme to make it worthy as a finale. I mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/18/call-of-duty-modern-warfare-2-retrospective&quot;&gt;my retrospective&lt;/a&gt; that parts of &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt; felt awkward in the context of recent real-world events, but there’s none of that here because everyone has been caricatured to the level of cartoonish heroes and villains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I understand that it was necessary to focus on strong leads because telling the story of a fictional WW3 at a macro level would be impossible, &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; really marks the point that &lt;em&gt;COD&lt;/em&gt; stopped trying to tell semi-respectful war stories and switched to worshipping a bunch of superheroes - most prominently Captain Price. You could say this strategy paid off in the long run, because flawless heroes undoubtedly sell more skins in the modern microtransaction-led world than nuanced characters would have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_10.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same trend is apparent in terms of the game’s settings. With perhaps the exception of the London Underground, the main difference between each locale is that each city’s most famous landmark is dropped on the horizon. The actual spaces you move through are fairly generic, without enough local flare to really generate any notable sense of place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, the game is near identical to &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt;. The core shooting has a satisfying weight, but the left trigger tap lock-on is sometimes overpowered. It can be frustrating when missions end due to friendly fire, since everyone wears quite similar armour and the AI doesn’t always keep them to two sides of an area, and for similar reasons it’s almost infuriating when an unseen enemy insta-kills you with a one-hit melee attack from behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your AI comrades do a decent job of keeping up the appearance of large-scale battles, but there are moments when everyone fires at a single enemy for a long time, waiting for the player to kill them so we can move on. Enemy AI is unremarkable, with difficulty increases largely down to the quantity of foes in an area, rather than any discernable change in their behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_11.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stealth sections return in force, likely due to the popularity of the All Ghillied Up mission in the original &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare&lt;/em&gt;, but they haven’t evolved at all. The player always follows directly behind an NPC (probably because the AI isn’t there for solo stealth), and in &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; they always reach a point where all hell breaks loose. Perhaps Infinity Ward was worried players wouldn’t have the attention span for a complete mission without a big firefight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all its flaws, the &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare&lt;/em&gt; trilogy is an important part of recent gaming history, and &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; does stand up well enough for a playthrough in the present day. In fact, I’d say the story is more coherent and interesting than &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt;, and with so much variety - there’s standard FPS shooting, stealth, on-rails sections, drone operation, car and boat chases, and so on - I can at least say for sure that you won’t be bored across its seven-hour span.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="call-of-duty" /><category term="shooters" /><summary type="html">With a bit more time on my hands this week, I decided to dust off my Xbox One and play through a game that I sunk many an hour into on the Xbox 360 about a decade ago (although it turns out not in the way I thought) - Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3. As the final game in the first-person shooter series’ most popular and iconic trilogy, this one had a lot to live up to. In November 2011, almost 11 years ago to the day at the time of writing, Activision released the Infinity Ward-developed Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3, marking the final instalment in a trilogy that set Call of Duty free from the confines of its traditional World War II setting, redefined online multiplayer, and elevated the series as a whole to become an instantly recognisable pillar of mainstream gaming and a reliable moneymaker for the publisher. With so much focus on the game’s multiplayer, the campaign is the topic of far less discussion. In fact, when I started playing it via the Xbox One’s backwards compatibility (sidenote - for some reason this required an 11GB game update, and it arguably would have been quicker to dig out my 360), I started earning achievements after the first couple of missions. Apparently the multiplayer, and in particular the co-op Special Ops, were such a distraction that I never completed MW3’s campaign back in the day.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">F1 22: How to choose the perfect difficulty and assists</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/04/f1-22-how-to-choose-perfect-difficulty-assists" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="F1 22&amp;#58; How to choose the perfect difficulty and assists" /><published>2022-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/04/f1-22-how-to-choose-perfect-difficulty</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/04/f1-22-how-to-choose-perfect-difficulty-assists">&lt;p&gt;Half of the enjoyment of any racing game comes from achieving the perfect balance between your own ability, the challenge of keeping the car under control at fast speeds, and the competition offered by your AI rivals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/f1-22-difficulty_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is no exception, and having &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/10/28/f1-22-better-than-internet-says&quot;&gt;recently purchased the game&lt;/a&gt;, I thought I’d share the process I went through to get all those sliders in the right places. And while the options referenced in the tips below are specific to Codemasters’ latest title, you could equally use the general principles to configure any sim or simcade racer to be as enjoyable as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;assists&quot;&gt;Assists&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forget AI opponents for a second and focus on your own car. You won’t be having any fun at all if you’re spinning the car every time you put your foot on the accelerator, but equally, racing games can feel like passively watching TV footage if the game is handling all the braking and steering for you.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/f1-22-difficulty_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my eyes, you’ll always want to turn &lt;strong&gt;Steering Assist&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Braking Assist&lt;/strong&gt; off. After all, aren’t those basic controls the whole reason you’re playing the game - to feel like you’re driving an F1 car? From there, the options have more subtle effects and are more down to personal preference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anti-Lock Brakes&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Traction Control&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Drift Assist&lt;/strong&gt; are all about stability, and you’ll want to experiment with them to find what feels best. I usually find the sweet spot to be somewhere in the middle, where the car is stable enough that the game isn’t completely frustrating, but loose enough that I still need to be careful when applying power coming out of corners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Dynamic Racing Line&lt;/strong&gt; settings are significant to your game experience. For a start, the racing line is &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; really needed on the straights, so you might as well at least go for Corners Only. After this point, I think whether you’ll turn it off entirely is largely down to how much time you have to learn the tracks. Racing is certainly more rewarding without it if you have the time to invest, and the 2D line is much less intrusive than the 3D one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pit Assist&lt;/strong&gt; settings I usually leave on to give my hands a little break when I stop, but if you’re seeking full immersion then it’s best to disable them. &lt;strong&gt;DRS Assist&lt;/strong&gt; should definitely be off, since opening that rear-wing window to blast past an opponent is one of the best feelings in the game. &lt;strong&gt;ERS Assist&lt;/strong&gt;, on the other hand, gives you another useful tool in your arsenal if turned off, but I can also understand that it might be a little too much to worry about while driving, and the game does a fair job of utilising the charge anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;simulation-settings&quot;&gt;Simulation settings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now, you should have the assists configured to a point where your car is a challenge to drive, but not so much so that you’re constantly spinning into walls. Now it’s time to adjust your opponents’ capabilities to match your speed and offer a consistent challenge in single player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/f1-22-difficulty_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike some other racing games, which offer proficiency and aggression sliders, &lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt; just has one bar named &lt;strong&gt;AI Difficulty&lt;/strong&gt;. In short, you want the AI to be about as fast as you in equal machinery. This will take some testing - if you’re easily pulling away from your teammate during races then you need to crank it up, while if you find cars forming a train behind you while the driver in front disappears into the distance, you need to turn it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Recovery Mode&lt;/strong&gt; setting allows you to turn off flashbacks, which let you rewind time and try again when things go wrong. I recommend leaving this on - some self-restraint will be required, but the AI in &lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt; is so aggressive that there will inevitably be collisions that aren’t your fault, for which you’ll need flashbacks to avoid race-ending damage and preserve your sanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Car Damage&lt;/strong&gt; settings are again personal preference. While some players aim to avoid all collisions and turn it off altogether, I normally leave damage on Reduced. This means that my major mistakes are appropriately punished, but I’m not left correcting the steering for the rest of the race because my front wing endplate grazed somebody’s tyre into Turn 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last important setting is &lt;strong&gt;Race Starts&lt;/strong&gt;. Assisted essentially allows you to simply hit the accelerator to move off the grid, while Manual requires you to hold the clutch in, apply some revs, and release it when the lights go out. The latter is much more engaging and adds some excitement to race starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are a few other settings, the sections above cover all the important ones. Once you’ve tweaked and tested them all, you’ll have a car that’s a decent challenge to drive and a group of opponents finely tuned to your own ability - then it’s finally time to go racing!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="racing" /><category term="formula-1" /><summary type="html">Half of the enjoyment of any racing game comes from achieving the perfect balance between your own ability, the challenge of keeping the car under control at fast speeds, and the competition offered by your AI rivals. F1 22 is no exception, and having recently purchased the game, I thought I’d share the process I went through to get all those sliders in the right places. And while the options referenced in the tips below are specific to Codemasters’ latest title, you could equally use the general principles to configure any sim or simcade racer to be as enjoyable as possible. Assists Forget AI opponents for a second and focus on your own car. You won’t be having any fun at all if you’re spinning the car every time you put your foot on the accelerator, but equally, racing games can feel like passively watching TV footage if the game is handling all the braking and steering for you.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/f1-22-difficulty_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/f1-22-difficulty_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>