<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-01-08T16:11:07+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What to expect from TSP in 2023</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/08/what-to-expect-tsp-2023" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What to expect from TSP in 2023" /><published>2023-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/08/what-to-expect-tsp-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/08/what-to-expect-tsp-2023">&lt;p&gt;It’s been quite a ride for &lt;em&gt;The Strat Pack&lt;/em&gt; since the site’s original soft launch in September 2021. More than a year later, after a site design upgrade and 76 articles, my musings on games and adjacent interests have amassed nearly 50,000 views, which is certainly more than I expected at the start. I appreciate everybody for taking the time to read them, and especially those who have emailed in to give their views and chat about their favourites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some articles have performed much as I’d have hoped - &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/02/19/newbies-guide-buying-formula-1-models&quot;&gt;my introduction to Formula 1 model collecting&lt;/a&gt; is the fourth most read article here, for example - but often there is a huge disconnect between the effort I expend writing an article (and how proud I am of it) and its reception, and that can be tough. A simple how-to guide can sometimes yield tens of thousands of views, while a sprawling retrospective can get nowhere near breaking into triple figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can add to that the pressure that I have put myself under to deliver weekly articles. This has a few knock-on effects, including the occasional rushed news or opinion piece when I run out of time, but the biggest consequence is forcing me to play games to a schedule. If I have a review or retrospective slated in for a specific date, I’ll sacrifice my evenings for the preceding week for play sessions to finish it, even if I’m not in the mood. But gaming is a longstanding hobby of mine, and it shouldn’t feel like a chore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I also feel like I’ve already covered most of the older games that immediately sprang to mind when I started the site, and there aren’t enough new titles I’m interested in to provide a consistent flow of content. When I paused work on posts over the Christmas break, I found myself playing a lot of endurance races in &lt;em&gt;Automobilista 2&lt;/em&gt;, and that wouldn’t be fertile ground for many articles without repeating myself a whole lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fear not - it may sound like I’m building up to shutting down the site, or at the very least going on hiatus, but what I actually want to say is that in 2023 I’ll be taking a more relaxed approach to &lt;em&gt;The Strat Pack&lt;/em&gt;. Articles will go up when I have something specific that I’m enthusiastic to write about - not on a fixed weekly basis - and I’ll open up the subject matter more often to films, television, music, and so on to accommodate this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome (I hope) is that although posts might be slightly less frequent, they’ll be of higher quality when they are published, and will be worth your time to read. It might sacrifice some numbers from algorithms that demand regular updates, but I think this approach will produce a site I can be more proud of, give me more time to play games I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to play, and be more accommodating to other changes in my life heading into the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for stopping by, and I hope you will continue to do so. Please &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thestratpack&quot;&gt;follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for updates regarding new articles, and I hope to connect with many more of you as the year goes on. All the best for 2023!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><summary type="html">It’s been quite a ride for The Strat Pack since the site’s original soft launch in September 2021. More than a year later, after a site design upgrade and 76 articles, my musings on games and adjacent interests have amassed nearly 50,000 views, which is certainly more than I expected at the start. I appreciate everybody for taking the time to read them, and especially those who have emailed in to give their views and chat about their favourites. Some articles have performed much as I’d have hoped - my introduction to Formula 1 model collecting is the fourth most read article here, for example - but often there is a huge disconnect between the effort I expend writing an article (and how proud I am of it) and its reception, and that can be tough. A simple how-to guide can sometimes yield tens of thousands of views, while a sprawling retrospective can get nowhere near breaking into triple figures. You can add to that the pressure that I have put myself under to deliver weekly articles. This has a few knock-on effects, including the occasional rushed news or opinion piece when I run out of time, but the biggest consequence is forcing me to play games to a schedule. If I have a review or retrospective slated in for a specific date, I’ll sacrifice my evenings for the preceding week for play sessions to finish it, even if I’m not in the mood. But gaming is a longstanding hobby of mine, and it shouldn’t feel like a chore. Furthermore, I also feel like I’ve already covered most of the older games that immediately sprang to mind when I started the site, and there aren’t enough new titles I’m interested in to provide a consistent flow of content. When I paused work on posts over the Christmas break, I found myself playing a lot of endurance races in Automobilista 2, and that wouldn’t be fertile ground for many articles without repeating myself a whole lot. Fear not - it may sound like I’m building up to shutting down the site, or at the very least going on hiatus, but what I actually want to say is that in 2023 I’ll be taking a more relaxed approach to The Strat Pack. Articles will go up when I have something specific that I’m enthusiastic to write about - not on a fixed weekly basis - and I’ll open up the subject matter more often to films, television, music, and so on to accommodate this. The outcome (I hope) is that although posts might be slightly less frequent, they’ll be of higher quality when they are published, and will be worth your time to read. It might sacrifice some numbers from algorithms that demand regular updates, but I think this approach will produce a site I can be more proud of, give me more time to play games I want to play, and be more accommodating to other changes in my life heading into the new year. Thanks for stopping by, and I hope you will continue to do so. Please follow me on Twitter for updates regarding new articles, and I hope to connect with many more of you as the year goes on. All the best for 2023!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – making history</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/25/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA 22 Career Mode&amp;#58; TSP United &amp;#8211; making history" /><published>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/25/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/25/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-4">&lt;p&gt;Last time out in my &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Career Mode series I was lucky to hold on to my job as TSP United manager after a disappointing 2026/27 season. Would I be able to handle the mounting pressure in England’s top flight with the board’s expectations ever increasing? Perhaps this photo might give you a clue…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a reminder, I’m playing this Career Mode campaign with special custom rules for some added challenge. I’m not to spend a penny on players (signing free agents is fine) and the focus is on &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players&quot;&gt;scouting and developing youth players&lt;/a&gt;. So my main source of new talent through this whole thing is to send a scout out around England occasionally and see what he brings back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this is the fourth instalment of my TSP United Career Mode series. Click here to catch up on the first six seasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/06/17/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-2&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – hitting the big time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/09/16/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-3&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – cup runs to remember&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202728---premier-league&quot;&gt;2027/28 - Premier League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a rough last season, I didn’t opt to make any signings heading into 2027/28, instead making some rearrangements as young players returned from loan. Notably, Gale took the spot between the sticks, relegating the inconsistent Parkin to the bench. Departures included former regular striker Prince, one of the few remaining original TSP United players.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were off the mark quickly and went on a frankly insane run of form considering our recent struggles, ending up top after ten games, having won 25 of the 30 available points. Gale was making saves well beyond his ability on paper, and by December I was wondering whether we might be on course to do a Leicester (who ironically were our closest title rivals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stumbled slightly over the Christmas period, lacking the squad depth to handle two games a week, but stayed on Leicester’s tail. As Chelsea took the top spot we were scraping victories, often coming back from steep deficits to win. But our form prevailed, and with five games left we inched ahead of the Blues. The fate of the league season was in our hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we beat Arsenal and Newcastle emphatically, Chelsea lost to City, putting us four points ahead. We had a chance to win the league in our penultimate game of the season at the Etihad, and didn’t let it go to waste. Pierre and Vaughan both netted braces, and the scoring was capped off by Goddard as we thrashed Pep Guardiola’s team and were crowned Premier League champions at the end of a truly improbable season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best player&lt;/strong&gt; - Annumanian, who broke Vaughan’s scoring record&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - N/A, because we made no signings&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Gale, who became the new first-choice GK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202829---premier-league&quot;&gt;2028/29 - Premier League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a league title under our belts, my sights were firmly set on a grand European finale to this Career Mode campaign. With most of our players improving, there was no need for huge squad changes, but I did bring Hunter into the first team at LM, moving the declining legend Willis to the bench.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We beat Man United in the Community Shield and made a strong start in the league despite losing Vaughan to a three-month injury. Our Champions League campaign was less smooth. We drew a tricky group, which featured both Inter and Bayern, and a defeat to the latter in the final group stage match saw us tumble out into the Europa League. The dream was over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unexpectedly, the Premier League became something of a saunter and we retained our title with a couple of games to go. Meanwhile, our Europa League run saw us face off with Manchester United, Villareal, and AC Milan, setting up a final date with a Liverpool team we’d smashed 4-0 just days before with a second-string lineup, on the final day of the league season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first team made no mistake on the big occasion. TSP United applied the early pressure before Pierre headed in a Hunter corner in the fifth minute. A fantastic Alisson performance kept Liverpool in the game, but goals from Annumanian and Vaughan meant we were four goals clear by half time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pierre got a fifth early in the second half, and when Neto was shown a red card we controlled the rest of the game. Proceedings were capped off by Willis, a late substitute, who grabbed the sixth and final goal in stoppage time with perhaps his last kick of a ball for TSP United. Maybe our Champions Leauge bid fell short, but we were European champions nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best player&lt;/strong&gt; - Annumanian, pushing the limits yet again&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - N/A, because we made no signings&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Hancock, straight in at CB on his loan return&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">Last time out in my FIFA 22 Career Mode series I was lucky to hold on to my job as TSP United manager after a disappointing 2026/27 season. Would I be able to handle the mounting pressure in England’s top flight with the board’s expectations ever increasing? Perhaps this photo might give you a clue… As a reminder, I’m playing this Career Mode campaign with special custom rules for some added challenge. I’m not to spend a penny on players (signing free agents is fine) and the focus is on scouting and developing youth players. So my main source of new talent through this whole thing is to send a scout out around England occasionally and see what he brings back. Note that this is the fourth instalment of my TSP United Career Mode series. Click here to catch up on the first six seasons: • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – hitting the big time • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – cup runs to remember 2027/28 - Premier League Despite a rough last season, I didn’t opt to make any signings heading into 2027/28, instead making some rearrangements as young players returned from loan. Notably, Gale took the spot between the sticks, relegating the inconsistent Parkin to the bench. Departures included former regular striker Prince, one of the few remaining original TSP United players.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Splinter Cell remake details on series’ 20th birthday</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/18/splinter-cell-20th-anniversary-remake" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Splinter Cell remake details on series' 20th birthday" /><published>2022-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/18/splinter-cell-20th-anniversary-remake</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/18/splinter-cell-20th-anniversary-remake">&lt;p&gt;Fans on the &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; subreddit were speculating recently about what Ubisoft might do for the series’ 20th anniversary. While &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/12/18/splinter-cell-remake&quot;&gt;the upcoming remake&lt;/a&gt; stoked some excitement, the publisher has been so neglectful of Sam Fisher and his pals in recent years that many expected nothing at all this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/splinter-cell-20th-anniversary-remake_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it turns out we did get something! &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XfJpSeit3zI&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The video uploaded to the Ubisoft YouTube account&lt;/a&gt; was as full of marketing fluff as you might expect, but it did include some interesting bits and pieces - including a look back at the series’ history and a very brief discussion of the upcoming game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-from-the-past&quot;&gt;Learning from the past&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part of the video focused on the past, and chiefly on the original &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt;, which was released in 2002. While there was some nostalgia to be enjoyed, watching a bunch of Ubisoft staffers sitting around a table and talking about their experiences as players wasn’t particularly interesting, and we didn’t get any worthwhile insight into the game’s development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the usual discussion of the series’ technical innovations (lighting, flowing drapes, fish tanks, and so on) there was a somewhat interesting discussion of Sam Fisher’s character, in which they pointed out how he was more human the usual video game lead character, speaking to enemies, defying orders to save people uninvolved in the mission, and so on.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this wasn’t groundbreaking stuff, it was nice to see that the people working on the remake appreciate this side of Sam’s character, as well as the slower, stealthier gameplay that made the first few titles what they were. Also interesting was that at one point they mentioned they had read &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1TaxVlnfcGVy56oQt4HHlCopUOAfAqATFF7IqT7zm5wM/edit&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the open letter fans wrote to Ubisoft&lt;/a&gt; pleading for a return to the series’ roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;news-on-the-future&quot;&gt;News on the future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us on nicely to the second half of the video, which was definitely the highlight, because this was the part where we were drip fed a few more precious details about the upcoming &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There will be more variance in the game’s AI - for example, standard security guards will respond to threats less adeptly than elite mercenaries, who will “behave like trained professionals”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio occlusion will form a part of the stealth, with sounds bouncing off of and being absorbed by different surfaces depending on material&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was some vague talk about a desire to make Sam’s movements more “immersive” as the player moves through the levels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The team were very clear that stealth is the priority, and they are working to ensure that zero-kill mission completion is possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The “harsh” three-strikes-and-you’re-out alarms from the early games will be scaled back, giving the player a chance to de-escalate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regarding the story, there was more allusion to changing “things that haven’t aged particularly well”, without any specifics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So along with &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/12/18/splinter-cell-remake&quot;&gt;the initial details&lt;/a&gt; there’s plenty to think about, even if concrete details are still thin on the ground. Unfortunately, the team ended the video with a warning that they would be “going dark for a while” to focus on development, so it’s anyone’s guess when we’ll get more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need something to keep you occupied in the meantime, head over to the Ubisoft Store, where the original &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; is free until 30th November.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="splinter-cell" /><category term="stealth" /><summary type="html">Fans on the Splinter Cell subreddit were speculating recently about what Ubisoft might do for the series’ 20th anniversary. While the upcoming remake stoked some excitement, the publisher has been so neglectful of Sam Fisher and his pals in recent years that many expected nothing at all this week. But it turns out we did get something! The video uploaded to the Ubisoft YouTube account was as full of marketing fluff as you might expect, but it did include some interesting bits and pieces - including a look back at the series’ history and a very brief discussion of the upcoming game. Learning from the past The first part of the video focused on the past, and chiefly on the original Splinter Cell, which was released in 2002. While there was some nostalgia to be enjoyed, watching a bunch of Ubisoft staffers sitting around a table and talking about their experiences as players wasn’t particularly interesting, and we didn’t get any worthwhile insight into the game’s development. As well as the usual discussion of the series’ technical innovations (lighting, flowing drapes, fish tanks, and so on) there was a somewhat interesting discussion of Sam Fisher’s character, in which they pointed out how he was more human the usual video game lead character, speaking to enemies, defying orders to save people uninvolved in the mission, and so on.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/splinter-cell-20th-anniversary-remake_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/splinter-cell-20th-anniversary-remake_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3 (Xbox 360) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/11/call-of-duty-modern-warfare-3-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Call of Duty&amp;#58; Modern Warfare 3 (Xbox 360) retrospective" /><published>2022-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/11/call-of-duty-modern-warfare-3-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/11/call-of-duty-modern-warfare-3-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;With a bit more time on my hands this week, I decided to dust off my Xbox One and play through a game that I sunk many an hour into on the Xbox 360 about a decade ago (although it turns out not in the way I thought) - &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3&lt;/em&gt;. As the final game in the first-person shooter series’ most popular and iconic trilogy, this one had a lot to live up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2011, almost 11 years ago to the day at the time of writing, Activision released the Infinity Ward-developed &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3&lt;/em&gt;, marking the final instalment in a trilogy that set &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/call-of-duty&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; free from the confines of its traditional World War II setting, redefined online multiplayer, and elevated the series as a whole to become an instantly recognisable pillar of mainstream gaming and a reliable moneymaker for the publisher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With so much focus on the game’s multiplayer, the campaign is the topic of far less discussion. In fact, when I started playing it via the Xbox One’s backwards compatibility (sidenote - for some reason this required an 11GB game update, and it arguably would have been quicker to dig out my 360), I started earning achievements after the first couple of missions. Apparently the multiplayer, and in particular the co-op Special Ops, were such a distraction that I never completed &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt;’s campaign back in the day.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setting-the-scene&quot;&gt;Setting the scene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jumping back into it in 2022, &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; picks up right after &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/18/call-of-duty-modern-warfare-2-retrospective&quot;&gt;the bizarre final events of &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, with Price and Nikolai rushing Soap to a safehouse for medical assistance. The logo on the title screen tells us what to expect, as “WW3” morphs into &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; - this game is set to tackle war on a huge scale, as Makarov-engineered Russian aggression targets states around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conveying this urgency, we’re thrown straight into a mission in New York, bypassing the usual &lt;em&gt;COD&lt;/em&gt; tutorial. We mount an assault to take back the New York Stock Exchange, board a Russian submarine, and a high-speed chase ensues through the harbour. Unusually for the series, this is about all we’ll see of the US, as most of the game’s action takes place in Europe (although oddly, and perhaps in an effort not to alienate a large part of the audience, most missions are still played from the perspective of US troops).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then play as Yuri, helping Captain Price evacuate the injured Soap (who after &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt; has apparently ascended to NPC legend status) as the safehouse comes under attack. We miss the extraction chopper and fall down a slope into a river, but Price rescues us - an instant reminder of what a guy he is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a series first, the next mission is played from a Russian perspective, as we fill the shoes of a guard on the president’s private jet. The plane is attacked by Makarov’s terrorists, and there are some cool zero-G moments during the shootouts as the plane plummets to the ground. We locate the president in the wreckage, but just as we’re about to extract him Makarov appears and kidnaps him. Before shooting us dead, he says Russia will take control of Europe even if it has to burn it to the ground in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;going-underground&quot;&gt;Going underground&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next is a stealth mission with Price and Soap as you investigate a tip that Makarov is transporting something to London. This features a challenging sniper segment, but all that good work is undone when you must fire mortar that is painfully slow and prevents you from moving to avoid hits. When you eventually reach your destination, you find the cargo is already gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shipment is in a warehouse in Tower Hamlets, which allows for a nice level visually, with the grimy industrial estate juxtaposed against the bright lights of Canary Wharf in the background. As with many missions in &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; this starts quiet before turning into an all-out firefight against hordes of enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad guys eventually jump into a random waiting Tube train, and I can forgive the questionable accuracy as we chase them through the tunnels on a truck just because the sequence is pretty cool, especially as the chase bursts through packed commuter platforms. The train derails at Westminster and you fight your way up through the station to surface level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A suspect van arrives and is shot down, but it’s not the only one. We’re whisked away to this game’s answer to &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt;’s No Russian - a wholly unnecessary segment where we play a camera-wielding dad filming his wife and little girl on holiday in London. A van pulls up, Russians in gas masks jump out, and we see our family killed in a chemical attack. The next cut scene tells us that similar attacks are taking place across Europe, paving the way for a Russian invasion, so why did this need to be playable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-european-tour&quot;&gt;A European tour&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US forces move in on Hamburg to rescue the vice president in a mission that plays out much more like classic &lt;em&gt;COD&lt;/em&gt;, with an opening that seems to be deliberately reminiscent of the D-Day beach landings and large-scale battles between opposing squads across vast areas. It’s perhaps telling in terms of the series’ direction that there’s not much else notable about this level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then play as Yuri once again, alternating between on-foot and chopper turret sections as he and the gang attempt to locate an arms dealer who has been working with Makarov. He tells us that his bomb maker, Volk, is headed for Paris. This mission is set apart by its finale, which sees you fight through a sandstorm. Everything turns orange and black, and the effects and lighting make this look very nice even by today’s standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next big set piece mission takes us to Paris, where the American squad are wearing gas masks because there is still toxic residue from the chemical attacks in the air. This is the first of several parts of &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; that feel like they’re paying homage to the &lt;em&gt;Wolfenstein&lt;/em&gt; games, as we drop down into creepily lit catacombs descorated with skulls and bones to find Volk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This culminates in a car chase with some on-rails shooting, ending in some seriously excessive ramming as we disable Volk’s vehicle and capture him. The last segment is a battle on a bridge, at the end of which an explosion causes the Eiffel Tower to topple into the Seine. They just couldn’t resist the visuals, which form a part of some of the game’s promotional images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;return-to-castle-makarov&quot;&gt;Return to Castle Makarov&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volk says Makarov is in Prague, so Yuri and co. are sent to infiltrate the city to get close to the castle in preparation. This is full-on &lt;em&gt;Wolfenstein&lt;/em&gt;, from the architecture to the black armour worn by the Russian soldiers. Soap mimics Price in Chernobyl mode - the flawless guide whose footsteps we must follow as we creep around in the shadows avoiding enemy patrols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is ripped straight from the original &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare&lt;/em&gt;, and there are some moments where the Russian soldiers must be straight-up blind not to see us, it is perhaps the best mission in the game simply because it has more character than most of the others. This is further elevated when it goes loud (as they all do) and we find ourselves helping the Czech resistance to take on the Russians in huge battles in the city’s streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hide out in a church that is serving as a resistance HQ until morning, planning to snipe Makarov when he arrives for a meeting. Our contact betrays us and blows us up, and when we wake we have to protect Price as he carries an injured Soap through the streets. Just before he dies, Soap finds the strength to tell Price that Makarov knows Yuri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Price punches us down some stairs to interrogate us, and in a flashback we see that Yuri did indeed previously work with Makarov, but that he was betrayed, turned good, and attempted to stop the No Russian massacre. Apparently this is enough to convince Price, but he won’t admit it because he just says he won’t kill us “for now” and it’s never mentioned again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more Price-led stealth as we infiltrate the castle - as in &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt;, this mostly consists of him doing all the cool stuff while we wait behind. Things are mixed up in an interesting way when he kills the lights in a prison area and we use our night vision to take out helpless enemies, but this lasts all of 20 seconds before they drop flares and can see again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_8.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learn the Russian president’s daughter is in Berlin and that he is likely to give up his nuclear codes to Makarov if she is located and taken hostage. The US team in Germany go after her, repeatedly disobeying orders to extract after the first team is destroyed by Russian forces, and we only catch a brief glimpse of her before she’s whisked away in a chopper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tying-up-the-loose-ends&quot;&gt;Tying up the loose ends&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With his daughter in enemy hands, Yuri and Price need to locate the Russian president in a Siberian diamond mine before he gives up the launch codes. Our fight through the mine ends in a bizarre vertical breach as we plant explosives on the floor and drop down to rescue the president. Yuri gets blown up but Price helps him to the chopper, which takes off and leaves US team leader Sandman (did I mention him before?) to his presumable death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US and Russia declare peace (European countries too, I hope, since they’ve been on the receiving end of invasions throughout the game) but Makarov is still at large, and Price can’t have that. We get to play as the legend himself for the first time as he and Yuri don juggernaut armour and launch an assault on the Dubai hotel where Makarov is staying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_9.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we reach the top, a chopper fires a rocket that leaves Yuri impaled. He tells us to leave him and go after Makarov, so we jump onto his helicopter as it takes off and fight the pilots. Somehow both of us surive the ensuing crash, and we wake to see a gun on the floor between us and Makarov.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Price crawls towards the gun, but Makarov takes it from us and shoots Yuri dead. A fist fight follows in which we tie a cable around his neck and push him through the shattered glass floor, leaving him hanging at the top of the hotel. Price lands on a balcony, and in the absence of anyone to say a cool line to, silently lights a cigar. It’s over - World War III has been won.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many trilogy endings - notably &lt;em&gt;The Dark Night Rises&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare 3&lt;/em&gt; suffers in that the stakes are so high by this point that there’s a sense everything must be overly dramatic and extreme to make it worthy as a finale. I mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/18/call-of-duty-modern-warfare-2-retrospective&quot;&gt;my retrospective&lt;/a&gt; that parts of &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt; felt awkward in the context of recent real-world events, but there’s none of that here because everyone has been caricatured to the level of cartoonish heroes and villains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I understand that it was necessary to focus on strong leads because telling the story of a fictional WW3 at a macro level would be impossible, &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; really marks the point that &lt;em&gt;COD&lt;/em&gt; stopped trying to tell semi-respectful war stories and switched to worshipping a bunch of superheroes - most prominently Captain Price. You could say this strategy paid off in the long run, because flawless heroes undoubtedly sell more skins in the modern microtransaction-led world than nuanced characters would have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_10.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same trend is apparent in terms of the game’s settings. With perhaps the exception of the London Underground, the main difference between each locale is that each city’s most famous landmark is dropped on the horizon. The actual spaces you move through are fairly generic, without enough local flare to really generate any notable sense of place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, the game is near identical to &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt;. The core shooting has a satisfying weight, but the left trigger tap lock-on is sometimes overpowered. It can be frustrating when missions end due to friendly fire, since everyone wears quite similar armour and the AI doesn’t always keep them to two sides of an area, and for similar reasons it’s almost infuriating when an unseen enemy insta-kills you with a one-hit melee attack from behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your AI comrades do a decent job of keeping up the appearance of large-scale battles, but there are moments when everyone fires at a single enemy for a long time, waiting for the player to kill them so we can move on. Enemy AI is unremarkable, with difficulty increases largely down to the quantity of foes in an area, rather than any discernable change in their behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_11.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stealth sections return in force, likely due to the popularity of the All Ghillied Up mission in the original &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare&lt;/em&gt;, but they haven’t evolved at all. The player always follows directly behind an NPC (probably because the AI isn’t there for solo stealth), and in &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; they always reach a point where all hell breaks loose. Perhaps Infinity Ward was worried players wouldn’t have the attention span for a complete mission without a big firefight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all its flaws, the &lt;em&gt;Modern Warfare&lt;/em&gt; trilogy is an important part of recent gaming history, and &lt;em&gt;MW3&lt;/em&gt; does stand up well enough for a playthrough in the present day. In fact, I’d say the story is more coherent and interesting than &lt;em&gt;MW2&lt;/em&gt;, and with so much variety - there’s standard FPS shooting, stealth, on-rails sections, drone operation, car and boat chases, and so on - I can at least say for sure that you won’t be bored across its seven-hour span.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="call-of-duty" /><category term="shooters" /><summary type="html">With a bit more time on my hands this week, I decided to dust off my Xbox One and play through a game that I sunk many an hour into on the Xbox 360 about a decade ago (although it turns out not in the way I thought) - Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3. As the final game in the first-person shooter series’ most popular and iconic trilogy, this one had a lot to live up to. In November 2011, almost 11 years ago to the day at the time of writing, Activision released the Infinity Ward-developed Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3, marking the final instalment in a trilogy that set Call of Duty free from the confines of its traditional World War II setting, redefined online multiplayer, and elevated the series as a whole to become an instantly recognisable pillar of mainstream gaming and a reliable moneymaker for the publisher. With so much focus on the game’s multiplayer, the campaign is the topic of far less discussion. In fact, when I started playing it via the Xbox One’s backwards compatibility (sidenote - for some reason this required an 11GB game update, and it arguably would have been quicker to dig out my 360), I started earning achievements after the first couple of missions. Apparently the multiplayer, and in particular the co-op Special Ops, were such a distraction that I never completed MW3’s campaign back in the day.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/cod-modern-warfare-3_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">F1 22: How to choose the perfect difficulty and assists</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/04/f1-22-how-to-choose-perfect-difficulty-assists" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="F1 22&amp;#58; How to choose the perfect difficulty and assists" /><published>2022-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/04/f1-22-how-to-choose-perfect-difficulty</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/04/f1-22-how-to-choose-perfect-difficulty-assists">&lt;p&gt;Half of the enjoyment of any racing game comes from achieving the perfect balance between your own ability, the challenge of keeping the car under control at fast speeds, and the competition offered by your AI rivals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/f1-22-difficulty_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is no exception, and having &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/10/28/f1-22-better-than-internet-says&quot;&gt;recently purchased the game&lt;/a&gt;, I thought I’d share the process I went through to get all those sliders in the right places. And while the options referenced in the tips below are specific to Codemasters’ latest title, you could equally use the general principles to configure any sim or simcade racer to be as enjoyable as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;assists&quot;&gt;Assists&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forget AI opponents for a second and focus on your own car. You won’t be having any fun at all if you’re spinning the car every time you put your foot on the accelerator, but equally, racing games can feel like passively watching TV footage if the game is handling all the braking and steering for you.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/f1-22-difficulty_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my eyes, you’ll always want to turn &lt;strong&gt;Steering Assist&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Braking Assist&lt;/strong&gt; off. After all, aren’t those basic controls the whole reason you’re playing the game - to feel like you’re driving an F1 car? From there, the options have more subtle effects and are more down to personal preference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anti-Lock Brakes&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Traction Control&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Drift Assist&lt;/strong&gt; are all about stability, and you’ll want to experiment with them to find what feels best. I usually find the sweet spot to be somewhere in the middle, where the car is stable enough that the game isn’t completely frustrating, but loose enough that I still need to be careful when applying power coming out of corners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Dynamic Racing Line&lt;/strong&gt; settings are significant to your game experience. For a start, the racing line is &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; really needed on the straights, so you might as well at least go for Corners Only. After this point, I think whether you’ll turn it off entirely is largely down to how much time you have to learn the tracks. Racing is certainly more rewarding without it if you have the time to invest, and the 2D line is much less intrusive than the 3D one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pit Assist&lt;/strong&gt; settings I usually leave on to give my hands a little break when I stop, but if you’re seeking full immersion then it’s best to disable them. &lt;strong&gt;DRS Assist&lt;/strong&gt; should definitely be off, since opening that rear-wing window to blast past an opponent is one of the best feelings in the game. &lt;strong&gt;ERS Assist&lt;/strong&gt;, on the other hand, gives you another useful tool in your arsenal if turned off, but I can also understand that it might be a little too much to worry about while driving, and the game does a fair job of utilising the charge anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;simulation-settings&quot;&gt;Simulation settings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now, you should have the assists configured to a point where your car is a challenge to drive, but not so much so that you’re constantly spinning into walls. Now it’s time to adjust your opponents’ capabilities to match your speed and offer a consistent challenge in single player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/f1-22-difficulty_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike some other racing games, which offer proficiency and aggression sliders, &lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt; just has one bar named &lt;strong&gt;AI Difficulty&lt;/strong&gt;. In short, you want the AI to be about as fast as you in equal machinery. This will take some testing - if you’re easily pulling away from your teammate during races then you need to crank it up, while if you find cars forming a train behind you while the driver in front disappears into the distance, you need to turn it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Recovery Mode&lt;/strong&gt; setting allows you to turn off flashbacks, which let you rewind time and try again when things go wrong. I recommend leaving this on - some self-restraint will be required, but the AI in &lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt; is so aggressive that there will inevitably be collisions that aren’t your fault, for which you’ll need flashbacks to avoid race-ending damage and preserve your sanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Car Damage&lt;/strong&gt; settings are again personal preference. While some players aim to avoid all collisions and turn it off altogether, I normally leave damage on Reduced. This means that my major mistakes are appropriately punished, but I’m not left correcting the steering for the rest of the race because my front wing endplate grazed somebody’s tyre into Turn 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last important setting is &lt;strong&gt;Race Starts&lt;/strong&gt;. Assisted essentially allows you to simply hit the accelerator to move off the grid, while Manual requires you to hold the clutch in, apply some revs, and release it when the lights go out. The latter is much more engaging and adds some excitement to race starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are a few other settings, the sections above cover all the important ones. Once you’ve tweaked and tested them all, you’ll have a car that’s a decent challenge to drive and a group of opponents finely tuned to your own ability - then it’s finally time to go racing!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="racing" /><category term="formula-1" /><summary type="html">Half of the enjoyment of any racing game comes from achieving the perfect balance between your own ability, the challenge of keeping the car under control at fast speeds, and the competition offered by your AI rivals. F1 22 is no exception, and having recently purchased the game, I thought I’d share the process I went through to get all those sliders in the right places. And while the options referenced in the tips below are specific to Codemasters’ latest title, you could equally use the general principles to configure any sim or simcade racer to be as enjoyable as possible. Assists Forget AI opponents for a second and focus on your own car. You won’t be having any fun at all if you’re spinning the car every time you put your foot on the accelerator, but equally, racing games can feel like passively watching TV footage if the game is handling all the braking and steering for you.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/f1-22-difficulty_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/f1-22-difficulty_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">F1 22 is better than the internet says</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/28/f1-22-better-than-internet-says" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="F1 22 is better than the internet says" /><published>2022-10-28T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-28T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/28/f1-22-better-than-internet-says</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/28/f1-22-better-than-internet-says">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt;’s free-to-play weekend came at a tough time for Codemasters and EA - at least as far as my evaluation was concerned. Coming hot off the heels of &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/10/21/formula-1-97-retrospective&quot;&gt;my retrospective on the PS1 classic &lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, they had their work cut out to impress me - but impress me they certainly did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/f1-22_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annual sports games have to put the work in to break free of the “last year’s game with this year’s stats” tag, and &lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt; didn’t get off to a good start. &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/22/f1-22-announcement-colossal-waste-of-time&quot;&gt;The April trailer&lt;/a&gt; didn’t showcase any notable gameplay features and raised concerns with its focus on F1 Life - a new game mode featuring supercars, clothing, and even sofas that all seemed perfect microtransaction territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your first few minutes with &lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt; will confirm it &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; been EA-ified to a much greater degree than its predecessor. Before doing anything else it wanted me to pick a supercar for my virtual luxury home, which didn’t bode well. But once I’d skipped through some dialogues and muted the overly loud EA Trax, it was possible to relegate the unnecessary additions to the background and focus on what is actually a solid step forward on the track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Online discussion around the game, including on &lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/F1Game/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the series subreddit&lt;/a&gt;, has been consistently negative. Some of that criticism concerned the new microtransaction-focused features, but just as much was about gameplay problems - bugs, handling issues, dodgy driving by the AI, and so on.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/f1-22_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the patches pushed out since July have done the trick, but I didn’t encounter any issues during what Steam tells me was a four-hour tryout across several races over the weekend. It’s possible the developers were helped out by the regulations overhaul for the 2022 season, but in my eyes &lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt; in its current state is a significant step up over &lt;em&gt;F1 2021&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my chosen configuration (mid traction control with most other assists turned off), the game is much more challenging than last year’s edition. The cars require more careful control, and the rear end can more easily step out mid-turn or on exit, meaning you need to be a lot more precise in your power application or risk spinning into the wall. This results in a far more rewarding experience when you do pull off a perfect lap or overtaking manoeuvre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graphics and performance have also seen some uplift. I was surprised when the game automatically set everything to Ultra and turned on ray tracing, and I expected a poor frame rate. But &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/07/15/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition-review&quot;&gt;my 3070 Ti&lt;/a&gt; was more than up to the job. The game seems to have increased fidelity and detail, but also runs better than &lt;em&gt;F1 2021&lt;/em&gt; on average, which is a fantastic combination to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, despite all the unnecessary surrounding distractions, it was &lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt;’s gameplay that won me over. I bought it while it was on offer and it’ll now be in my regular rotation. I’ll likely produce some articles along the lines of &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1&quot;&gt;my &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt; Career Mode series&lt;/a&gt; - I’m thinking a season-long campaign in search of the win that has eluded Mercedes in real life. Watch this space.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="racing" /><category term="formula-1" /><summary type="html">F1 22’s free-to-play weekend came at a tough time for Codemasters and EA - at least as far as my evaluation was concerned. Coming hot off the heels of my retrospective on the PS1 classic Formula 1 97, they had their work cut out to impress me - but impress me they certainly did. Annual sports games have to put the work in to break free of the “last year’s game with this year’s stats” tag, and F1 22 didn’t get off to a good start. The April trailer didn’t showcase any notable gameplay features and raised concerns with its focus on F1 Life - a new game mode featuring supercars, clothing, and even sofas that all seemed perfect microtransaction territory. Your first few minutes with F1 22 will confirm it has been EA-ified to a much greater degree than its predecessor. Before doing anything else it wanted me to pick a supercar for my virtual luxury home, which didn’t bode well. But once I’d skipped through some dialogues and muted the overly loud EA Trax, it was possible to relegate the unnecessary additions to the background and focus on what is actually a solid step forward on the track. Online discussion around the game, including on the series subreddit, has been consistently negative. Some of that criticism concerned the new microtransaction-focused features, but just as much was about gameplay problems - bugs, handling issues, dodgy driving by the AI, and so on.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/10/f1-22_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/10/f1-22_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Formula 1 97 (PS1) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/21/formula-1-97-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Formula 1 97 (PS1) retrospective" /><published>2022-10-21T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-21T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/21/formula-1-97-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/21/formula-1-97-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;I was shocked on multiple levels to find that one of my favourite childhood games recently celebrated its 25th birthday. Developed by Bizarre Creations, &lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt; was the official game of the 1997 Formula 1 championship, the follow-up to the 1995 original (which was simply titled &lt;em&gt;Formula 1&lt;/em&gt;), and a disc that span in my PlayStation’s drive for hundreds of hours back in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you would expect from a licensed sports game, &lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt; features all the teams and drivers from the 1997 season, with the notable exception of eventual champion Jacques Villeneuve, who was excluded for image rights reasons and is referred to simply as “the Canadian” or “Williams number one”. And as the game was released in September, the developers had time to tweak each team’s performance to match their actual performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;blocky-but-beautiful&quot;&gt;Blocky but beautiful&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt;’s graphics hold up surprisingly well for a game of its age. The backdrops do suffer from some pop-in, but that can be forgiven when the recreations of the circuits are faithful enough that (save for a tweaked corner or chicane here and there) I could drive them well based on my experience with their modern-day equivalents in recent racing games.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monaco is especially well rendered. While boxy, the detail in the surroundings is massive for a PS1 game. The love that went into these circuits is apparent in tiny additions that have no business appearing in a game of this fidelity – the little Ferrari flags in the crowd at Monza, for example. The tracks also feature true-to-life sponsors, although Fosters has been censored since 1995 and the Marlboro stand-in race car has been stripped of its chevron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attention to detail on the cars is just as impressive, and they do have notably different bodies based on their real-life counterparts, rather than just being different textures applied to a single model, as was the norm for similar games at the time. Using the reverse camera to take a closer look is a pleasure, with liveries almost looking like pixel art renditions of the real thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt; was also the first game in the series to include a cockpit view, which is of debateable utility given the draw distance, but is still a cool touch. Again, it’s the details that shine, with readable Goodyear branding on the tyres and glowing orange brake discs when you brake heavily. If you turn on tear-offs in the settings, the screen will also accumulate dirt until you hit the triangle button to rip off a visor layer – a bizarrely low-level addition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vroom-vroom&quot;&gt;Vroom vroom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the audio side of things, the Grand Prix mode is soundtracked by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F-2pZX-S0N4&amp;amp;list=PL8BF2B7D268626FEA&amp;amp;index=10&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;original rock songs&lt;/a&gt;. They don’t quite match &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CtCLKjhFgoU&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the original’s Joe Satriani menu track&lt;/a&gt;, but they do a good job of building tension and I’m not ashamed to say that at some point in the past I remember sitting down with a guitar to play along with a couple. While Grand Prix mode is the focus of this article, it’s worth noting here that the Arcade mode’s techno soundtrack is truly awful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you hit the track, the sound effects do a serviceable – if slightly drony – job of emulating the era’s V10 engines for your own car. Other cars for some reason operate at a higher pitch (perhaps to simulate perspective) and can sound like a swarm of bees at some points. Aside from that, you’ll mainly hear the cheering of the crowd and the mumble of announcers on the track speakers, but all that’s usually masked by the engine sounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The late great Murray Walker returns, this time joined by Martin Brundle. The commentary acts almost as a Formula 1 time capsule, as Murray gives a little intro to each circuit, noting what has changed for 1997. In-session chatter also covers regulation changes, like the implementation of a new rear crash structure, or drivers suffering from cramp due to the lower in-car position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coupled with the reactive clips for collisions and position changes, it usually does a good job of adding to the authenticity and excitement. Sometimes Murray’s clips will combine to comedic effect (“Beautiful! He’s just hit Verstappen!”), but it’s not too jarring because it somehow matches his personality. Brundle will chip in with technical perspectives, but is probably best known for responding to Walker’s remarks: “You’re right there, Murray.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also new for this game were race engineer radio calls. They usually occur after big collisions (“What was &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;?! Are you alright?”) or to guide you towards tyre changes when the weather turns. The distortion applied, likely to emulate the choppy radio of the time, means these are often incredibly loud, further adding to the adrenaline after a risky move goes wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hitting-the-apex&quot;&gt;Hitting the apex&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gameplay offers some solid arcade racing – “minutes to learn, lifetime to master” stuff. The digital controls for the accelerator and brake (these were the days before triggers) mean your laps will never be as smooth as in modern games, but with circuit knowledge and careful presses you can build a satisfying flow around some corners, just grazing the edges of the track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those memory skills are important because &lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt; has no HUD indicator for upcoming turns, and corners are not always visible prior to their braking zones. Interestingly, the game does offer the first implementation I can remember of a racing line, which can be set to “training” mode to highlight braking areas in red to help make things accessible for newbies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That isn’t to say the driving can’t be punishing. Even one tyre on the grass (and there was a lot more grass and gravel close to the track in the 90s) will often result in a spin, sending you plummeting through the positions and – on the higher difficulties, at least – ruining your chances of a win. Therefore it’s often more rewarding to keep the car on the tarmac at all costs rather than pushing the limits too much, even if the latter might be faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of interest, I looked up the real lap records for the 1997 races and compared them to my own fastest laps in the game. Generally, my laps were a few seconds quicker than the real drivers’ records. While I’d like to put that down to my immense skill, in reality it seems that the accuracy in the circuits and handling just wasn’t there yet at the time of the game’s release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;championship-rivals&quot;&gt;Championship rivals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Racing game AI was pretty unremarkable across the board in the PS1 era, and &lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt; was no exception. It does the job, but the computer-controlled cars will mainly follow the optimal racing line (or even beyond, taking shortcuts through the barriers in some parts of Monaco). They’ll pull alongside to make their own moves, but won’t react to the player’s lunges, meaning with any move there is a risk they will turn straight into you. It’s much safer to try to get past them on the straights than in the corners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cars are no longer immovable objects like they were in the 1995 edition, but it could be argued that Bizarre Creations went too far in the other direction. This game’s cars feel as light as a feather, leaping into the air under even moderate contact and spinning with ease – not helpful when the AI likes to behave as though you’re not even there when heading into turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all its weaknesses, the AI has at least improved when it comes to the subsequent traffic jams as cars stack up behind an incident. In the original Formula 1, everyone would wait patiently for the blockage to clear, while in &lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt; they weave on approach to give themselves a chance of getting through. This can lead to some wild final classifications if the leaders sit in the queue and get overtaken, adding to the entertainment factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_8.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pit stops are more of factor than before, not least because the game now has a variable weather setting, allowing for in-race transitions. Stops use a simple menu where you can choose which tyre compound to fit, which wings to repair, and how much fuel to load. Another nice little detail is that fresh tyres sport the white labels that were common at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tinkering-with-the-setup&quot;&gt;Tinkering with the setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of additional settings to tweak to your heart’s content. Flags introduce rules while racing (and yes, it is possible to get black flagged and disqualified), and the weather setting I previously mentioned can be set to sunny, rainy, random, or the most realistic option: variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_9.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty-related settings include the main difficulty slider (with five notches) and steering/braking assists, which I never see the point of in a racing game. If you’re not steering and braking yourself, what’s the point? If you’re into the endurance and strategy side of F1, you can also crank the race length all the way up to full distance, flick on the tyre wear and fuel depletion toggles, and test your mettle in an hour-and-a-half-long slog of an event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt; also gives you the option to add mechanical failures to the mix. Blown up engines were a lot more common back in the 1990s, and while it’s frustrating to lose your progress due to a random number generator, it’s rare and spectacular enough that I always liked to play with this on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the technically minded, there are also a few parts of the car setup that can be tweaked - the suspension, brake discs and bias, and front and rear downforce. Obviously the driving model isn’t detailed enough for this to have as realistic an effect as it would in, say, &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/project-cars&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project Cars&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but it’s nice that the extra depth is there as an option for those who want to tinker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_10.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Damage, on the other hand, is a different prospect. In the previous section I mentioned how difficult it is to avoid contact with other drivers, and it doesn’t take much of said contact at all to leave you limping around the rest of the lap missing your front wing. Realistic? Yes. But when most damage accrued isn’t your fault, it’s a much happier time to play with it turned off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also worth mentioning that the driver name customisation feature - likely included so fans could rectify the Villeneuve situation - also functions as a way to input cheats. Effects include the addition of bonus tracks, a mode with &lt;em&gt;Wipeout&lt;/em&gt;-style cars, a top-down helicopter camera, and little sprite versions of Walker and Brundle that sit at the bottom of the screen and move with the commentary. All of these are good fun to try out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to revisiting the past, video games suffer from issues that mediums like film and music don’t. While I can go back and listen to the Beatles’ songs or watch a Hitchcock movie and receive much the same experience as people would have at the time of their release, games are tied much more closely to the technology that delivers them, and therefore our modern sensibilities can render classics of yesteryear almost unplayable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hold up the late PS2 &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pro Evolution Soccer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; titles as potentially the best football games ever in terms of gameplay, but I must admit that despite their lack of recent innovation, the modern Codemasters &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;F1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; games are far superior to &lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt; both as entertainment products and as simulations of the complexities of what is a very technical and often convoluted sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_11.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while &lt;em&gt;F1 2010&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;F1 2022&lt;/em&gt; might feel relatively similar, what Bizarre Creations assembled in &lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt; is a slice of mid-90s Formula 1 that offers nostalgia not just for the game, but for the history of the sport. The arcade-style (by modern standards, at least) gameplay holds up just well enough to enable the game to serve as a sort of virtual history lesson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, between the details in the game (recreations of the cars, circuit layouts as they were prior to tweaks, Walker and Brundle’s comments on regulation changes) and things I Googled myself (videos of 1997 races to compare to the in-game tracks, info on long-forgotten drivers and teams, the purpose of tyre stickers), I feel like by diving back into &lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt; after years away I actually learnt more about a bygone era of motorsport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_12.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sights, sounds, and action of classic Formula 1 are all here, and any fan of a certain age will feel warm inside listening to Murray Walker’s voice as those big yellow graphics flash on the screen and the V10s drone on. And the gameplay to backs it up, pushing the game beyond the “YouTube video search” category and making a revisit an afternoon well spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the magic that the 1995 and 1997 editions delivered wasn’t long for this world, and development was handed to Visual Science for 1998’s game, which was widely considered inferior. Formula 1 then games entered a slump that arguably lasted until 2010. Even if there are better, more recent alternatives, I’d encourage F1 fans to at least try &lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt;. How many other sports games held the top spot for 13 years after release, after all?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="racing" /><category term="formula-1" /><summary type="html">I was shocked on multiple levels to find that one of my favourite childhood games recently celebrated its 25th birthday. Developed by Bizarre Creations, Formula 1 97 was the official game of the 1997 Formula 1 championship, the follow-up to the 1995 original (which was simply titled Formula 1), and a disc that span in my PlayStation’s drive for hundreds of hours back in the day. As you would expect from a licensed sports game, Formula 1 97 features all the teams and drivers from the 1997 season, with the notable exception of eventual champion Jacques Villeneuve, who was excluded for image rights reasons and is referred to simply as “the Canadian” or “Williams number one”. And as the game was released in September, the developers had time to tweak each team’s performance to match their actual performance. Blocky but beautiful Formula 1 97’s graphics hold up surprisingly well for a game of its age. The backdrops do suffer from some pop-in, but that can be forgiven when the recreations of the circuits are faithful enough that (save for a tweaked corner or chicane here and there) I could drive them well based on my experience with their modern-day equivalents in recent racing games.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/10/formula-1-97_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why is everything a live service?</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/14/why-is-everything-a-live-service" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why is everything a live service?" /><published>2022-10-14T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/14/why-is-everything-a-live-service</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/14/why-is-everything-a-live-service">&lt;p&gt;I caught a streamer I follow playing &lt;em&gt;Marauders&lt;/em&gt; recently and the game looks fantastic. For those who don’t know, it’s a sci-fi FPS that has players jumping between ships as space pirates in search of loot. Visually, it struck me as an interesting fusion of &lt;em&gt;No Man’s Sky&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Wolfenstein&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Fallout&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/marauders_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is the case in other shooters in its subgenre, during the raids you’re faced not only with AI-controlled bots, but also other players. The unpredictability lends an almost horror-like pacing to proceedings as you creep through the dark corridors wondering what might be lurking around the next corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the truth is that I’m just not that fussed about playing online. I don’t have hours per day to hone my skills in a particular game, and those who do will always blow me away. But &lt;em&gt;Marauders&lt;/em&gt; looked like fun, so I went searching on Steam to find out whether I can play it offline if I want to chill out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no mention of offline play on the store page, and every forum post I found on the topic suggested that it’s simply not possible. This was disappointing in the context of this game, but feels all the more alienating against the backdrop of wider changes in the games industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;everything-everywhere-all-online&quot;&gt;Everything, everywhere, all online&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; went online, and within a few years Ultimate Team was the main game mode. Since 2010 or thereabouts, changes to the match engine and Career Mode have been minor, with the developers’ focus clearly on raking in as much money as possible from players for digital trading cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same has happened to racing games. &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was unbalanced as a single player experience because the economy had to work on a global scale. Cars were riced at the equivalent of tens of hours of grinding in an attempt to push players towards microtransactions. And the &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;F1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; series is starting to follow a similar path, with an increased focus on the purchase of tangental items like race suits and victory radio messages.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even games that have no business connecting to the internet now enforce it. The &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/hitman&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; series might be fantastic in gameplay terms, but there was no excuse for it to require an internet connection to earn unlocks in single-player missions that have no online gameplay components at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps &lt;em&gt;Marauders&lt;/em&gt; can be forgiven a little for its online focus - it is an early access game after all, and it will need to receive updates as new features are added. But the question can still be asked: Why, when all the ingredients are there - environments, weapons, AI - can the game not be played offline?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lessons-from-the-past&quot;&gt;Lessons from the past&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put bluntly, forcing players online is making gaming a less enjoyable hobby overall. At best it’s inconvenient, and at worst a series like &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; goes from being an enjoyable, high-quality offline game to a product where the gameplay sometimes feels secondary to the publisher’s desire to extract additional money from you over and above the box price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other significant drawback to online-only games is that they become inaccessible once the developer deems they are no longer profitable to run. Even &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt; is patched to be properly playable offline someday, if I boot up my copy in 20 years once the PS4 servers are down and said patch is unavailable, I still won’t be able to play the full game from the disc alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By comparison, look at favourites from previous generations. &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pro Evolution Soccer 5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Formula 1 ‘97&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/10/gran-turismo-3-retrospective&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; were all standalone games, presented in their entirety on a single disc, and if I put that disc in a console in 2022 they run just as well as they did they day I bought them. While the downloadable bug fixes introduced during the Xbox 360 generation were a useful new tool, the modern trend towards games that don’t run - or are severely limited - without an internet connection is a step too far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I’m clinging to the past and the days of complete, offline games are numbered, but it’s consistently disappointing to see an interesting-looking game only to find out that it requires the internet to function and will die the moment the servers are shut off. Our only hope is that gamers wise up and vote with their wallets, but at present that doesn’t look very likely.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="industry" /><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">I caught a streamer I follow playing Marauders recently and the game looks fantastic. For those who don’t know, it’s a sci-fi FPS that has players jumping between ships as space pirates in search of loot. Visually, it struck me as an interesting fusion of No Man’s Sky, Wolfenstein, and Fallout. As is the case in other shooters in its subgenre, during the raids you’re faced not only with AI-controlled bots, but also other players. The unpredictability lends an almost horror-like pacing to proceedings as you creep through the dark corridors wondering what might be lurking around the next corner. But the truth is that I’m just not that fussed about playing online. I don’t have hours per day to hone my skills in a particular game, and those who do will always blow me away. But Marauders looked like fun, so I went searching on Steam to find out whether I can play it offline if I want to chill out. There was no mention of offline play on the store page, and every forum post I found on the topic suggested that it’s simply not possible. This was disappointing in the context of this game, but feels all the more alienating against the backdrop of wider changes in the games industry. Everything, everywhere, all online First FIFA went online, and within a few years Ultimate Team was the main game mode. Since 2010 or thereabouts, changes to the match engine and Career Mode have been minor, with the developers’ focus clearly on raking in as much money as possible from players for digital trading cards. The same has happened to racing games. Gran Turismo 7 was unbalanced as a single player experience because the economy had to work on a global scale. Cars were riced at the equivalent of tens of hours of grinding in an attempt to push players towards microtransactions. And the F1 series is starting to follow a similar path, with an increased focus on the purchase of tangental items like race suits and victory radio messages.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/10/marauders_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/10/marauders_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fable (PC) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/07/fable-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fable (PC) retrospective" /><published>2022-10-07T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-07T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/07/fable-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/07/fable-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;For my next retrospective, I decided to dive back into one of the most memorable games of my childhood: &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;. Released on the Xbox in 2004, the first title in Lionhead’s RPG series failed to live up to the unrealistic hype amassed through Peter Molyneux’s misguided media interviews, but still had plenty of substance to make it one of the notable releases of its generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BCXTmBAk5C0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;crank up the soundtrack&lt;/a&gt; and settle in as we head back to Albion and revisit the full story of the original game, along the way considering some of &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;’s standout mechanics and features and how they compared to its contemporaries, its successors, and the embellished previews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great-expectations&quot;&gt;Great expectations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I heard about &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; was in early 2004, from a very excited friend. “This game is going to be amazing,” he told me one day after school, showing me video game magazines full of what would later turn out to be exaggerated promises from designer Peter Molyneux. “You can do anything – even go to a town, kill the mayor, and sleep with his daughter!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was too young to realise that the Xbox wasn’t powerful enough to deliver on the level of freedom promised, and was very excited ahead of the game’s September release. My parents eventually agreed to buy me a copy as a reward for good exam results, and while &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; wasn’t the one-of-a-kind sandbox in Molyneux’s head, it had enough character and hints of that ambition to be one of the most memorable titles of its generation.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RPG’s opening moments drop the player into Oakvale as an oddly-proportioned young boy, tasked with completing small tasks around town to earn enough gold to buy our sister a birthday present. These serve as an introduction to the game’s quite simple morality system, and we earn good points by – for example – reporting a cheating man to his wife, or evil points for taking his bribe and keeping our mouth shut (although we learn there are still repercussions, as word quickly travels to the town guards anyway).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly as soon as we give Theresa her present, the town is overrun by bandits, who kill our father. Our mother and sister run off without us as we hide, and we are about to be killed too, before a mysterious stranger tells us to come with him if we want to live and teleports us to safety. This turns out to be the old hero Maze. He’s voiced by Peter Dickson, who does a lot of TV announcer work in the UK, and this is sometimes a little distracting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eye-of-the-tiger&quot;&gt;Eye of the tiger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our tutorial continues at the Heroes’ Guild, where the Guildmaster puts us through our paces in melee combat, archery, and will (magic) – &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;’s three main ability classes. We also meet Whisper, an annoyingly confrontational fellow student who tries to rile us up for some reason. Unfortunately, we’ll continue to encounter her throughout the game’s main story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a final test fight against a largely defenceless Maze, we’ve passed our training and are sent out into the world as a hero. At our graduation, the Guildmaster stresses that we can do good and evil and the world will change accordingly. This was a key theme of the series, and was certainly better realised in &lt;em&gt;Fable II&lt;/em&gt;, but it’s another indicator of the ambition of the game and even here leaves you wondering how far &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; will let you take it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our initial quests are fairly basic chores. As soon as we’re outside the guild it’s immediately obvious that the citizens of Albion are hapless morons who depend on heroes for everything, and as such we’re sent on insignificant errands like dealing with wasps and helping the incompetent guards defend a farm from bandits. Interestingly, there is an “evil” version of this quest where you attack the farm, and Whisper joins whichever side you don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We meet Maze in Bowerstone and he shares the news that our sister might still be alive, but doesn’t know where she is. Very helpful. Instead of dealing with that, we escort some traders through Darkwood, protecting them from balverines (werewolves). There’s a nice branching questline here where you can choose to bring along a bitten trader who eventually transforms, but the balverines themselves are tedious to fight, mostly due to their ability to jump off-screen for random periods of time after you get a few hits in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;linear-freedom&quot;&gt;Linear freedom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this time, you’re probably getting the sense that &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;’s open world is not too open after all. Sure, you can technically go anywhere and there are side quests and minigames to indulge in, but Albion essentially consists of a series of corridors with a few enemies and chests dotted here and there. Although the game does restock level-appropriate enemies if you revisit most areas, there’s very little reason to do so when your hero can teleport around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Albion does have going for it is character, and plenty of it. The &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; series is known for its British voice acting, and while the NPCs here are more stilted and repetitive than they would be in the Xbox 360 games, they are generally likable and often elicit a chuckle – even if that is sometimes due to their overblown gestures and the main character’s silence in cutscenes. Really, it’s testament to the writing and acting that the game is so charming and memorable when all the enemies and questlines are so cliched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One unfortunate design choice was to make the Heroes’ Guild the player’s hub of operations. Characters will frequently describe our next task, only to say they’ve left the quest card at the guild, meaning we need to teleport back to pick it up. The same holds true for levelling up our hero. These are all mechanics that are dealt with via menus in other games, and it quickly becomes grating that they require travel in &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;, even if it is near-instant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, the various design elements give an impression of a game that was delivered before its time. You can feel where Molyneux and his team probably wanted to do more, but the hardware limitations and design lexicon of the time meant each area &lt;em&gt;needed&lt;/em&gt; to have four enemies and a clearly identifiable chest containing an item. In 2004, games had to pick an approach and stick to it. &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; opts for accessibility over the depth of its contemporary &lt;em&gt;Morrowind&lt;/em&gt; – two philosophies that would be fused by the time of &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;going-undercover&quot;&gt;Going undercover&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the story, Maze tells us there is a blind seeress at a camp belonging to the bandit Twinblade who might be able to tell us something about our sister. After a rather janky stealth bit to get past the main gate, there’s a creative section where we are tasked with collecting and equipping bandit clothes to go undercover. At the end of the path we fight Twinblade, who offers a basic but satisfying pattern-based boss fight where we must dodge his blows and attack when he gets his blades stuck in the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out the seeress is none other than our sister Theresa, who was blinded during the siege and started running with Twinblade’s gang. Over the course of the next few unnoteworthy quests (which unfortunately involved many more balverines) she shares more information about our family. She thinks we’re descended from a bloodline that is capable of wielding a sword that is apparently so powerful that it can be used to rule the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we’ve amassed some renown (a separate stat running adjacent to the good/evil bar that represents how famous our hero is), we’re invited to fight at the Arena. This is a grind, featuring a round for each of eight enemy types, most with five waves each. Oddly, it was also my first introduction to some enemies I’d yet to face in the wild. The Arena exposes the weaknesses of the game’s AI, which will walk straight into a spinning blade if it is on a direct path to you, and I’m not sure if this was a bug, but the crowd was booing so loudly the whole time that I had to turn my headphones down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we defeat a giant scorpion, Jack of Blades makes an appearance and pits us against Whisper, who was our Arena comrade to this point. Whisper constantly cheats and is the worst fight in the game, teleporting behind you and jumping off-screen like a balverine, all with invulnerability. At the end of the fight you can choose to kill or spare her (I chose the latter). On our way to the exit, we learn that our mother was a former Arena champion, and Jack of Blades drops by to tell us that she lives in solitude somewhere and he wants to reunite us. Just don’t worry that he sounds like Darth Vader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fight-for-your-right&quot;&gt;Fight for your right&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably a good place to discuss &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;’s combat, which is a simple affair with one button assigned to melee, will, and archery respectively. Both the player and enemies can block, which adds a little depth as you’ll need to build up to a block-breaking flourish to do any damage. Some enemies will get knocked out mid-fight, introducing a decision as to whether to leave them where they are to focus on others, at a cost of their later resurgence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the opening couple of hours, where combat is entertaining enough as you work out how to fight properly, enemies can start to feel like sponges as they increase in health disproportionately to your own development. This makes some battles - particularly against enemies like balverines and trolls that take many hits to kill but offer fairly rare opportunities to get them in – long slogs that end in relief more than any feeling of triumph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, at least for melee-focused characters like my own, something clicks. You’ve levelled up at the guild and spent your gold on stronger weaponry and armour. Perhaps you’re even throwing a few spells into the mix – my personal favourite was multi-strike, which lets you hit enemies multiple times with a single swing of your sword. Suddenly low-level enemies are single-hit kills, and against even the more challenging variants you feel in control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d argue that the sense of progression from &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;’s levelling system and equipment upgrades feels better than those even in more modern RPGs like &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt;. Each upgrade, purchase, or augmentation feels like it makes a significant difference – aesthetically and in terms of gameplay – which makes for a far more satisfying gameplay experience than finding constant multiples of the same few items that are only good to sell to traders at rip-off rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one thing I can’t forgive &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;’s combat system for – and the reason I went firmly down the melee path – is the targeting system for ranged attacks. Although there is manual aim for the bow, you’ll mainly use your archery and will abilities by holding down the left trigger to target enemies. But it’s wildly unpredictable – in some cases spinning my hero 180 degrees to target traders downhill behind me rather than troll directly in front – and the time wasted made these combat styles almost unusable in many cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;breaking-out&quot;&gt;Breaking out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We meet our sister again and she says Jack of Blades is the one that burned down our home and cut out her eyes. Hmm, interesting… What could this guy possibly want to do with our family and our magical connection to this all-powerful sword? We’ll have to return to that mystery later, though, as Theresa tells us our mother is living in Bargate Prison these days, and apparently we’re going to break her out to reunite the family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we need to speak to the archaeologist, who knows a secret way into the prison, but he’s in the process of being kidnapped by Jack and his demonic minions. This is a tough new enemy type (I was glad I stocked up on health potions back at the Arena) that took me back into the hit sponge zone, and the arbitrary time limit placed on a fight against a huge group of these foes made this a quest I was glad to get out of the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secret passage starts in the graveyard, and to gain access we must please the dead Heroes’ Guild founder Nostro by gathering his equipment, which the oddball gravekeeper has hidden around the grounds. We must do this while fighting off a seemingly infinite number of undead enemies in an enjoyably gloomy atmosphere, which is a stark contrast to the usually bright, jolly, and colourful areas we encounter across the majority of Albion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We fight our way into the prison and save our mother. You’d assume that as a former Arena champion she’d be a great help, but she mainly stands around while we battle the waves of guards on the way out, occasionally remarking on how good we are at fighting now. Thanks, Mum. But it doesn’t matter, because Jack corners us inches from freedom and throws us back in a cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;breaking-out-again&quot;&gt;Breaking out (again)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prison segment mixes things up a little. Each year, the guards make us race around the compound, and the winner gets the privilege of listening to the warden recite his poetry in his office. While his back is turned you can sneak around to retrieve the combination to open one of three books, one of which contains the cell key. Pick the wrong one? Back to the cells for you, to rot until next year’s race. It’s a creative idea, and the growth of the hero’s hair and beard to show the passing of trime is a nice touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the key, we can now break out again with our mother and the other prisoners. At the end of the tunnels, in a chamber that was suspiciously empty on the way in, we fight a really cool enemy called a kraken, which is a kind of huge water dragon. It has phases involving whacking tentactles and a green laser that shoots from its face, and is generally an enjoyable fight - it’s just a shame the second phase requires archery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems we’re now firmly on the war path against Jack - not least because his minions kidnap our mother again nearly as soon as we get her back. We visit the Hook Coast, where dementor-like enemies are terrorising the local villagers, and discover Maze holding our sister hostage and performing a ritual that will give Jack of Blades the key for the sword. Jack runs off with the key, and we’re forced to fight the traitor in a tough battle to the death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we chase Jack through various parts of Albion as he activates the focus sites required to obtain the sword. In Oakwood, the Hobbe Caves, and Bowerstone Jail, we fight alongside other heroes and citizens against hordes of minions, just missing Jack each time as he teleports to the next location. The sky glows red and there’s a real sense we’re building to a finale as we chase Jack to the Heroes’ Guild for what promises to be the final showdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-final-showdown&quot;&gt;The final showdown&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the guild burning and the Guildmaster incapacitated (and very grouchy if we try to speak to him again), we chase Jack into a big, church-like room. He kills our mother before our eyes and brandishes the all-powerful sword he’s coveted all this time. It’s clear that only one of us is leaving alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_8.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final one-on-one is another two-phase fight. First, Jack comes directly at us for a melee and will duel. He still uses some slightly unfair tricks, but oddly wasn’t as frustrating as Whisper was earlier on. Then he floats in the air while he sends minions at us. I won’t say how long it took me to realise that fighting them is futile as they endlessly respawn, and that I needed to strafe to avoid them while firing arrows at Jack (sigh). After switching tactics, it wasn’t too much longer before Jack of Blades was defeated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, we’re faced with our final moral choice - do we kill our sister in order to wield the Sword of Aeons’ power for ourselves, or throw it into the vortex and destroy it forever? I chose to spare my sister’s life, but was disappointed when she just walked out without so much as a thank you, saying something about going travelling to find herself. And with that, our hero is sent back out into Albion to do side quests for eternity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; is a memorable and lovingly crafted game, even if it doesn’t deliver on the promises that were made during its development. There’s plenty that stuck with me over the last two decades, from the feel of the combat, to the intonation of certain lines of dialogue, and even the way the experience orbs float towards you &lt;em&gt;Galaga&lt;/em&gt;-style when you hold the right trigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s the smaller, more conditional details that really make &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; stand out. After making morally good decisions throughout the game (even if they are obvious and binary after the tutorial finishes) my hero sprouted a halo, and if you went in the opposite direction you’d grow devil horns. You can buy titles from vendors and characters will actually call you by them in dialogue. While perhaps not brand new, little customisations like these were extremely rare in 2004, especially in such a graphically vibrant game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_9.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, while the level of freedom Molyneux and his team strove to give the player was what made &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; unique, it also left some of the later parts of the story feeling tonally incongruous. Some sequences, like the final decision over the sword, offered options for both good and evil characters, but - for example - it felt plain wrong for my angelic hero to slaughter so many guards a few minutes before, even if he was wrongfully imprisoned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your mileage with &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; will probably depend on how much nostalgia you hold for it. I rode through much of the game on memories of how it blew me away 18 years ago, but I imagine it would be much less gripping for somebody raised on the luxuries of later RPGs like &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt;. The series still has enough of a unique atmosphere and charm to be worth playing for the first time, but - based on memory, at least - I think &lt;em&gt;Fable II&lt;/em&gt; would be the better place for newbies to start. I’ll confirm that when I get around to playing it again.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fable" /><category term="rpg" /><summary type="html">For my next retrospective, I decided to dive back into one of the most memorable games of my childhood: Fable. Released on the Xbox in 2004, the first title in Lionhead’s RPG series failed to live up to the unrealistic hype amassed through Peter Molyneux’s misguided media interviews, but still had plenty of substance to make it one of the notable releases of its generation. So crank up the soundtrack and settle in as we head back to Albion and revisit the full story of the original game, along the way considering some of Fable’s standout mechanics and features and how they compared to its contemporaries, its successors, and the embellished previews. Great expectations The first time I heard about Fable was in early 2004, from a very excited friend. “This game is going to be amazing,” he told me one day after school, showing me video game magazines full of what would later turn out to be exaggerated promises from designer Peter Molyneux. “You can do anything – even go to a town, kill the mayor, and sleep with his daughter!” I was too young to realise that the Xbox wasn’t powerful enough to deliver on the level of freedom promised, and was very excited ahead of the game’s September release. My parents eventually agreed to buy me a copy as a reward for good exam results, and while Fable wasn’t the one-of-a-kind sandbox in Molyneux’s head, it had enough character and hints of that ambition to be one of the most memorable titles of its generation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hitman 3 (PC) review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/30/hitman-3-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hitman 3 (PC) review" /><published>2022-09-30T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-30T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/30/hitman-3-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/30/hitman-3-review">&lt;p&gt;I finally gave into temptation and bought the final chapter of in one of my favourite series of recent years. &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt; takes Agent 47 to new locations and promises to wrap up the trilogy’s narrative - but given the behind-the-scenes turmoil at IO Interactive during its development, does it deliver the same level of quality as the previous games? Read on to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; Hitman 3 &lt;em&gt;sits in an awkward spot, right on the boundary between what I would call a review and a retrospective. Note that while this article is labelled “review”, it will contain some spoilers due to the age of the game.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iteration-on-excellence&quot;&gt;Iteration on excellence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the series’ reboot in 2016, &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt;’s World of Assassination has set a consistent high tide mark for what was a rather lucklustre console generation compared to its predecessor. There was - and still is - nothing quite like IO Interactive’s “social stealth” games, which task the player with assassinating targets not with firepower or button-mashing dexterity, but through careful observation, planning, and execution, all without leaving a trace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, each &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt; level sets the globetrotting Agent 47 loose in a new location - in &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt;’s case ranging from Dubai skyscrapers to English country houses and Argentinian vineyards. While the player does have access to guns, the fun is in quietly subduing carefully selected civilians to disguise yourself and gain access to restricted areas.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sandboxes themselves are a joy to explore, intricately detailed and full of interesting and funny dialogue to overhear. Curiosity is nearly always rewarded when discovering new areas, and the levels are presented with such gorgeous graphics that the game sometimes feels almost like a window into how the other half live, in much the same way that the &lt;em&gt;Assassin’s Creed&lt;/em&gt; games can be used as a sort of historical sightseeing tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the complexity of the levels, the AI doesn’t always get things right (it’s still remarkably good - it’s just unreasonable to ask it to understand every possible context it could be presented with), but for the most part the game’s humourous - sometimes borderline slapstick - approach to stealth and action helps to paper over the cracks and avoid breaking immersion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the killings themselves, &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt; does what all my favourite games do. It gives the player the tools and lets them choose what happens next. You are free to walk up to each target and shoot or strangle them, but it’s much more rewarding to scout the level and find opportunities to set up elaborate “accidents” - even more so if you turn off the on-screen prompts, which can make this feel a little bit like painting by numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the amount of time you spend blending in and observing, the pacing of the gameplay is almost like &lt;em&gt;Paranormal Activity&lt;/em&gt;’s approach to horror - a long, slow build-up while you try to pretend everything is normal and put the pieces in place, followed by those crucial, adrenaline-pumping seconds as you execute your plan, and hopefully the target, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;seeing-the-sights&quot;&gt;Seeing the sights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agent 47 begins his 2021 world tour at the opening of a &lt;strong&gt;Dubai&lt;/strong&gt; skyscraper. The sprawling level spans the upper floors of the building and is perhaps the game’s most beautiful, the sun beaming in across the ornate interior. My first target was tragically electrocuted by his own art exhibit, while my favourite assassination option here was to steal some security keycards, sabotage my second target’s parachute, and trigger an evacuation of the penthouse where he was holed up to send him tumbling to his death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second mission takes us to a country house in &lt;strong&gt;Dartmoor&lt;/strong&gt;. There’s an acclaimed murder mystery-style story to be explored here, but being dumped outside a restricted compound immediately put me in &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/splinter-cell&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; mode. I went full stealth, infiltrating the grounds and climbing the drainpipes to the top floor, where I eliminated the target as she screamed into a pillow in a secret room and solved a simple puzzle to steal some files from her safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Berlin&lt;/strong&gt; required a similar approach, slipping quietly into a warehouse rave. The twist here is that the player must identify five ICA agents by exploring and listening in to conversations before eliminating them. I stumbled into enough agents and killed most of them with a pistol shot from distance, with the club music helping to cover up any commotion. This was one of my least favourite &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt; missions, but one I will probably revisit and try to approach more methodically now I know roughly where I’m going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, Agent 47 is tasked with killing two targets and deleting data from a server at a secret underground ICA facility in &lt;strong&gt;Chongqing&lt;/strong&gt;, China. This was an enjoyable level, and again very pretty, the rainy city draped with neon lights in a way that reminded me of &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/07/29/stray-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This was the first time &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt; lined me up with a viable sniper shot, taking a target out through a distant window, before I disguised myself as an ICA analyst to go underground and find my second victim. The ICA area suffers from some awful voice acting for several critical characters, but this one will still certainly be worth a replay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also where the game first strays from its winning formula and tries to introduce more of a narrative to the gameplay. Deleting data from the ICA server puts the facility on red alert, and Agent 47 must escape by sneaking past tens of patrolling guards. I’m in two minds about this - on one hand it certainly provides an adrenaline-pumping mission finale, but on the other it was more scripted than anything in a &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt; sandbox should be, and denied me the usual satisfaction of completing a mission undetected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unearned-gravitas&quot;&gt;Unearned gravitas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Mendoza&lt;/strong&gt; vineyard mission is also story-driven as the game attempts to push the series’ narrative towards its denouement. This time Diana Burnwood - the mostly disembodied voice of Agent 47’s handler for the earlier games - is in attendance, and wants him to kill one of her rivals for the position of Constant (don’t ask - it’s a long story), as well as the owner of the winery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latter is fairly straightforward (I visited his house disguised as his lawyer and strangled him), but it’s clear the game is cranking up the difficulty with Diana’s rival Tamara Vidal. Diana herself is rarely more than a metre from her, ruling out any kind of explosive elimination, while even a silenced shot sets every guard in the place on 47. In the end I located a bottle of her favourite wine and posed as a waiter to serve her a poisoned glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s almost the end of the game, as far as I’m concerned. Nothing from this point plays like a &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt; game, and while it serves to tie up all of the story’s loose ends, I don’t know anybody who plays these games for the narrative and it was somewhat underwhelming that the final location turned out not to be another sandbox but a much more linear level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I’m getting ahead of myself. First, after Diana administers him a nerve agent, 47 has a strange dream sequence where we’re brought face to face with all of the targets we’ve killed through the trilogy. It’s nice that the developers tried to add some fanfare to the finale, but the tone is very serious and feels as though we’re expected to feel some guilt over their deaths, which falls a bit flat in a game that’s all about creative killing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;47 wakes up in a lab where scientists are researching a memory-wiping serum he was given as a child, and on opening the door we realise that we are on a train hurtling through &lt;strong&gt;Romania&lt;/strong&gt;. The last mission of the series sees Agent 47 making his way to the head of the train, travelling through, over, and around carriages in a way was reminiscent of &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell: Pandora Tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;’s train level - just with added disguises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose the trilogy had to have an ending, but the final mission isn’t one I’d ever go back and play. You get to use all of Agent 47’s tricks, but they take on a more simplistic light when working in such confined spaces where there there’s normally only one realistic option to progress laid on a plate (like exactly the right outfit sitting just inside the carriage door). Eventually we reach the front and take care of the main baddie - ironically, by injecting him with the serum - and it’s all over, albeit in a very understated way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;off-field-issues&quot;&gt;Off-field issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On gameplay alone, &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt; would be one of very few games to earn my maximum five-star rating, but &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review&quot;&gt;as always seems to be the case these days&lt;/a&gt;, it falls short for several business-related reasons. These won’t necessarily ruin your enjoyment of the game - especially if you can get it for a reduced price, like I did - but it’s only fair that they’re taken into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first (and most publicised) of these is that this is a single-player game that essentially must be played online. There’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/HiTMAN/comments/l45so8/a_list_of_things_not_available_offline_in_hitman/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a full list of what’s missing if you play offline&lt;/a&gt; on Reddit, but put simply you’ll have access to the main missions and not much else. Additionally, any games you saved while playing online are inaccessible, and you will be unable to earn the challenge-based unlocks for the levels. It’s a baffling decision for a game with no multiplayer - especially when the online leaderboards are full of apparent cheaters who completed every mission in less than a minute anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly - and more importantly in the game’s current, supported state - is &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt;’s value proposition. Both &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Hitman 2&lt;/em&gt; featured at least six “proper” missions and locations by my count, while &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt; - excluding the very linear train level - provides just five. Again, not a fatal shortcoming, but a little disappointing for such an unusually expensive title, and I’d have felt short changed if I had paid full price for the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, warnings aside, is &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt; worth it? Totally. From exploring the five new sprawling locations to revisting old missions in the updated engine, there are hours of fun and challenge to be found here, and the beauty of the series’ gameplay is that each level offers a ton of replay value to try new routes, disguises, equipment, and assassination options. This is must-play stuff, so my advice would be to pick it up on an offer when you can - just make sure you put aside enough time, because &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt; is very addictive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4/5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="hitman" /><category term="stealth" /><summary type="html">I finally gave into temptation and bought the final chapter of in one of my favourite series of recent years. Hitman 3 takes Agent 47 to new locations and promises to wrap up the trilogy’s narrative - but given the behind-the-scenes turmoil at IO Interactive during its development, does it deliver the same level of quality as the previous games? Read on to find out. Note: Hitman 3 sits in an awkward spot, right on the boundary between what I would call a review and a retrospective. Note that while this article is labelled “review”, it will contain some spoilers due to the age of the game. Iteration on excellence Since the series’ reboot in 2016, Hitman’s World of Assassination has set a consistent high tide mark for what was a rather lucklustre console generation compared to its predecessor. There was - and still is - nothing quite like IO Interactive’s “social stealth” games, which task the player with assassinating targets not with firepower or button-mashing dexterity, but through careful observation, planning, and execution, all without leaving a trace. For the uninitiated, each Hitman level sets the globetrotting Agent 47 loose in a new location - in Hitman 3’s case ranging from Dubai skyscrapers to English country houses and Argentinian vineyards. While the player does have access to guns, the fun is in quietly subduing carefully selected civilians to disguise yourself and gain access to restricted areas.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>