<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-10-07T19:16:30+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Fable (PC) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/07/fable-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fable (PC) retrospective" /><published>2022-10-07T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-07T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/07/fable-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/10/07/fable-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;For my next retrospective, I decided to dive back into one of the most memorable games of my childhood: &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;. Released on the Xbox in 2004, the first title in Lionhead’s RPG series failed to live up to the unrealistic hype amassed through Peter Molyneux’s misguided media interviews, but still had plenty of substance to make it one of the notable releases of its generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BCXTmBAk5C0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;crank up the soundtrack&lt;/a&gt; and settle in as we head back to Albion and revisit the full story of the original game, along the way considering some of &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;’s standout mechanics and features and how they compared to its contemporaries, its successors, and the embellished previews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great-expectations&quot;&gt;Great expectations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I heard about &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; was in early 2004, from a very excited friend. “This game is going to be amazing,” he told me one day after school, showing me video game magazines full of what would later turn out to be exaggerated promises from designer Peter Molyneux. “You can do anything – even go to a town, kill the mayor, and sleep with his daughter!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was too young to realise that the Xbox wasn’t powerful enough to deliver on the level of freedom promised, and was very excited ahead of the game’s September release. My parents eventually agreed to buy me a copy as a reward for good exam results, and while &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; wasn’t the one-of-a-kind sandbox in Molyneux’s head, it had enough character and hints of that ambition to be one of the most memorable titles of its generation.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RPG’s opening moments drop the player into Oakvale as an oddly-proportioned young boy, tasked with completing small tasks around town to earn enough gold to buy our sister a birthday present. These serve as an introduction to the game’s quite simple morality system, and we earn good points by – for example – reporting a cheating man to his wife, or evil points for taking his bribe and keeping our mouth shut (although we learn there are still repercussions, as word quickly travels to the town guards anyway).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly as soon as we give Theresa her present, the town is overrun by bandits, who kill our father. Our mother and sister run off without us as we hide, and we are about to be killed too, before a mysterious stranger tells us to come with him if we want to live and teleports us to safety. This turns out to be the old hero Maze. He’s voiced by Peter Dickson, who does a lot of TV announcer work in the UK, and this is sometimes a little distracting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eye-of-the-tiger&quot;&gt;Eye of the tiger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our tutorial continues at the Heroes’ Guild, where the Guildmaster puts us through our paces in melee combat, archery, and will (magic) – &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;’s three main ability classes. We also meet Whisper, an annoyingly confrontational fellow student who tries to rile us up for some reason. Unfortunately, we’ll continue to encounter her throughout the game’s main story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a final test fight against a largely defenceless Maze, we’ve passed our training and are sent out into the world as a hero. At our graduation, the Guildmaster stresses that we can do good and evil and the world will change accordingly. This was a key theme of the series, and was certainly better realised in &lt;em&gt;Fable II&lt;/em&gt;, but it’s another indicator of the ambition of the game and even here leaves you wondering how far &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; will let you take it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our initial quests are fairly basic chores. As soon as we’re outside the guild it’s immediately obvious that the citizens of Albion are hapless morons who depend on heroes for everything, and as such we’re sent on insignificant errands like dealing with wasps and helping the incompetent guards defend a farm from bandits. Interestingly, there is an “evil” version of this quest where you attack the farm, and Whisper joins whichever side you don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We meet Maze in Bowerstone and he shares the news that our sister might still be alive, but doesn’t know where she is. Very helpful. Instead of dealing with that, we escort some traders through Darkwood, protecting them from balverines (werewolves). There’s a nice branching questline here where you can choose to bring along a bitten trader who eventually transforms, but the balverines themselves are tedious to fight, mostly due to their ability to jump off-screen for random periods of time after you get a few hits in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;linear-freedom&quot;&gt;Linear freedom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this time, you’re probably getting the sense that &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;’s open world is not too open after all. Sure, you can technically go anywhere and there are side quests and minigames to indulge in, but Albion essentially consists of a series of corridors with a few enemies and chests dotted here and there. Although the game does restock level-appropriate enemies if you revisit most areas, there’s very little reason to do so when your hero can teleport around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Albion does have going for it is character, and plenty of it. The &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; series is known for its British voice acting, and while the NPCs here are more stilted and repetitive than they would be in the Xbox 360 games, they are generally likable and often elicit a chuckle – even if that is sometimes due to their overblown gestures and the main character’s silence in cutscenes. Really, it’s testament to the writing and acting that the game is so charming and memorable when all the enemies and questlines are so cliched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One unfortunate design choice was to make the Heroes’ Guild the player’s hub of operations. Characters will frequently describe our next task, only to say they’ve left the quest card at the guild, meaning we need to teleport back to pick it up. The same holds true for levelling up our hero. These are all mechanics that are dealt with via menus in other games, and it quickly becomes grating that they require travel in &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;, even if it is near-instant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, the various design elements give an impression of a game that was delivered before its time. You can feel where Molyneux and his team probably wanted to do more, but the hardware limitations and design lexicon of the time meant each area &lt;em&gt;needed&lt;/em&gt; to have four enemies and a clearly identifiable chest containing an item. In 2004, games had to pick an approach and stick to it. &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; opts for accessibility over the depth of its contemporary &lt;em&gt;Morrowind&lt;/em&gt; – two philosophies that would be fused by the time of &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;going-undercover&quot;&gt;Going undercover&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the story, Maze tells us there is a blind seeress at a camp belonging to the bandit Twinblade who might be able to tell us something about our sister. After a rather janky stealth bit to get past the main gate, there’s a creative section where we are tasked with collecting and equipping bandit clothes to go undercover. At the end of the path we fight Twinblade, who offers a basic but satisfying pattern-based boss fight where we must dodge his blows and attack when he gets his blades stuck in the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out the seeress is none other than our sister Theresa, who was blinded during the siege and started running with Twinblade’s gang. Over the course of the next few unnoteworthy quests (which unfortunately involved many more balverines) she shares more information about our family. She thinks we’re descended from a bloodline that is capable of wielding a sword that is apparently so powerful that it can be used to rule the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we’ve amassed some renown (a separate stat running adjacent to the good/evil bar that represents how famous our hero is), we’re invited to fight at the Arena. This is a grind, featuring a round for each of eight enemy types, most with five waves each. Oddly, it was also my first introduction to some enemies I’d yet to face in the wild. The Arena exposes the weaknesses of the game’s AI, which will walk straight into a spinning blade if it is on a direct path to you, and I’m not sure if this was a bug, but the crowd was booing so loudly the whole time that I had to turn my headphones down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we defeat a giant scorpion, Jack of Blades makes an appearance and pits us against Whisper, who was our Arena comrade to this point. Whisper constantly cheats and is the worst fight in the game, teleporting behind you and jumping off-screen like a balverine, all with invulnerability. At the end of the fight you can choose to kill or spare her (I chose the latter). On our way to the exit, we learn that our mother was a former Arena champion, and Jack of Blades drops by to tell us that she lives in solitude somewhere and he wants to reunite us. Just don’t worry that he sounds like Darth Vader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fight-for-your-right&quot;&gt;Fight for your right&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably a good place to discuss &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;’s combat, which is a simple affair with one button assigned to melee, will, and archery respectively. Both the player and enemies can block, which adds a little depth as you’ll need to build up to a block-breaking flourish to do any damage. Some enemies will get knocked out mid-fight, introducing a decision as to whether to leave them where they are to focus on others, at a cost of their later resurgence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the opening couple of hours, where combat is entertaining enough as you work out how to fight properly, enemies can start to feel like sponges as they increase in health disproportionately to your own development. This makes some battles - particularly against enemies like balverines and trolls that take many hits to kill but offer fairly rare opportunities to get them in – long slogs that end in relief more than any feeling of triumph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, at least for melee-focused characters like my own, something clicks. You’ve levelled up at the guild and spent your gold on stronger weaponry and armour. Perhaps you’re even throwing a few spells into the mix – my personal favourite was multi-strike, which lets you hit enemies multiple times with a single swing of your sword. Suddenly low-level enemies are single-hit kills, and against even the more challenging variants you feel in control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d argue that the sense of progression from &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;’s levelling system and equipment upgrades feels better than those even in more modern RPGs like &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt;. Each upgrade, purchase, or augmentation feels like it makes a significant difference – aesthetically and in terms of gameplay – which makes for a far more satisfying gameplay experience than finding constant multiples of the same few items that are only good to sell to traders at rip-off rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one thing I can’t forgive &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt;’s combat system for – and the reason I went firmly down the melee path – is the targeting system for ranged attacks. Although there is manual aim for the bow, you’ll mainly use your archery and will abilities by holding down the left trigger to target enemies. But it’s wildly unpredictable – in some cases spinning my hero 180 degrees to target traders downhill behind me rather than troll directly in front – and the time wasted made these combat styles almost unusable in many cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;breaking-out&quot;&gt;Breaking out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We meet our sister again and she says Jack of Blades is the one that burned down our home and cut out her eyes. Hmm, interesting… What could this guy possibly want to do with our family and our magical connection to this all-powerful sword? We’ll have to return to that mystery later, though, as Theresa tells us our mother is living in Bargate Prison these days, and apparently we’re going to break her out to reunite the family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we need to speak to the archaeologist, who knows a secret way into the prison, but he’s in the process of being kidnapped by Jack and his demonic minions. This is a tough new enemy type (I was glad I stocked up on health potions back at the Arena) that took me back into the hit sponge zone, and the arbitrary time limit placed on a fight against a huge group of these foes made this a quest I was glad to get out of the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secret passage starts in the graveyard, and to gain access we must please the dead Heroes’ Guild founder Nostro by gathering his equipment, which the oddball gravekeeper has hidden around the grounds. We must do this while fighting off a seemingly infinite number of undead enemies in an enjoyably gloomy atmosphere, which is a stark contrast to the usually bright, jolly, and colourful areas we encounter across the majority of Albion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We fight our way into the prison and save our mother. You’d assume that as a former Arena champion she’d be a great help, but she mainly stands around while we battle the waves of guards on the way out, occasionally remarking on how good we are at fighting now. Thanks, Mum. But it doesn’t matter, because Jack corners us inches from freedom and throws us back in a cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;breaking-out-again&quot;&gt;Breaking out (again)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prison segment mixes things up a little. Each year, the guards make us race around the compound, and the winner gets the privilege of listening to the warden recite his poetry in his office. While his back is turned you can sneak around to retrieve the combination to open one of three books, one of which contains the cell key. Pick the wrong one? Back to the cells for you, to rot until next year’s race. It’s a creative idea, and the growth of the hero’s hair and beard to show the passing of trime is a nice touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the key, we can now break out again with our mother and the other prisoners. At the end of the tunnels, in a chamber that was suspiciously empty on the way in, we fight a really cool enemy called a kraken, which is a kind of huge water dragon. It has phases involving whacking tentactles and a green laser that shoots from its face, and is generally an enjoyable fight - it’s just a shame the second phase requires archery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems we’re now firmly on the war path against Jack - not least because his minions kidnap our mother again nearly as soon as we get her back. We visit the Hook Coast, where dementor-like enemies are terrorising the local villagers, and discover Maze holding our sister hostage and performing a ritual that will give Jack of Blades the key for the sword. Jack runs off with the key, and we’re forced to fight the traitor in a tough battle to the death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we chase Jack through various parts of Albion as he activates the focus sites required to obtain the sword. In Oakwood, the Hobbe Caves, and Bowerstone Jail, we fight alongside other heroes and citizens against hordes of minions, just missing Jack each time as he teleports to the next location. The sky glows red and there’s a real sense we’re building to a finale as we chase Jack to the Heroes’ Guild for what promises to be the final showdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-final-showdown&quot;&gt;The final showdown&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the guild burning and the Guildmaster incapacitated (and very grouchy if we try to speak to him again), we chase Jack into a big, church-like room. He kills our mother before our eyes and brandishes the all-powerful sword he’s coveted all this time. It’s clear that only one of us is leaving alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_8.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final one-on-one is another two-phase fight. First, Jack comes directly at us for a melee and will duel. He still uses some slightly unfair tricks, but oddly wasn’t as frustrating as Whisper was earlier on. Then he floats in the air while he sends minions at us. I won’t say how long it took me to realise that fighting them is futile as they endlessly respawn, and that I needed to strafe to avoid them while firing arrows at Jack (sigh). After switching tactics, it wasn’t too much longer before Jack of Blades was defeated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, we’re faced with our final moral choice - do we kill our sister in order to wield the Sword of Aeons’ power for ourselves, or throw it into the vortex and destroy it forever? I chose to spare my sister’s life, but was disappointed when she just walked out without so much as a thank you, saying something about going travelling to find herself. And with that, our hero is sent back out into Albion to do side quests for eternity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; is a memorable and lovingly crafted game, even if it doesn’t deliver on the promises that were made during its development. There’s plenty that stuck with me over the last two decades, from the feel of the combat, to the intonation of certain lines of dialogue, and even the way the experience orbs float towards you &lt;em&gt;Galaga&lt;/em&gt;-style when you hold the right trigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s the smaller, more conditional details that really make &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; stand out. After making morally good decisions throughout the game (even if they are obvious and binary after the tutorial finishes) my hero sprouted a halo, and if you went in the opposite direction you’d grow devil horns. You can buy titles from vendors and characters will actually call you by them in dialogue. While perhaps not brand new, little customisations like these were extremely rare in 2004, especially in such a graphically vibrant game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_9.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, while the level of freedom Molyneux and his team strove to give the player was what made &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; unique, it also left some of the later parts of the story feeling tonally incongruous. Some sequences, like the final decision over the sword, offered options for both good and evil characters, but - for example - it felt plain wrong for my angelic hero to slaughter so many guards a few minutes before, even if he was wrongfully imprisoned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your mileage with &lt;em&gt;Fable&lt;/em&gt; will probably depend on how much nostalgia you hold for it. I rode through much of the game on memories of how it blew me away 18 years ago, but I imagine it would be much less gripping for somebody raised on the luxuries of later RPGs like &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt;. The series still has enough of a unique atmosphere and charm to be worth playing for the first time, but - based on memory, at least - I think &lt;em&gt;Fable II&lt;/em&gt; would be the better place for newbies to start. I’ll confirm that when I get around to playing it again.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fable" /><category term="rpg" /><summary type="html">For my next retrospective, I decided to dive back into one of the most memorable games of my childhood: Fable. Released on the Xbox in 2004, the first title in Lionhead’s RPG series failed to live up to the unrealistic hype amassed through Peter Molyneux’s misguided media interviews, but still had plenty of substance to make it one of the notable releases of its generation. So crank up the soundtrack and settle in as we head back to Albion and revisit the full story of the original game, along the way considering some of Fable’s standout mechanics and features and how they compared to its contemporaries, its successors, and the embellished previews. Great expectations The first time I heard about Fable was in early 2004, from a very excited friend. “This game is going to be amazing,” he told me one day after school, showing me video game magazines full of what would later turn out to be exaggerated promises from designer Peter Molyneux. “You can do anything – even go to a town, kill the mayor, and sleep with his daughter!” I was too young to realise that the Xbox wasn’t powerful enough to deliver on the level of freedom promised, and was very excited ahead of the game’s September release. My parents eventually agreed to buy me a copy as a reward for good exam results, and while Fable wasn’t the one-of-a-kind sandbox in Molyneux’s head, it had enough character and hints of that ambition to be one of the most memorable titles of its generation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/10/fable_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hitman 3 (PC) review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/30/hitman-3-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hitman 3 (PC) review" /><published>2022-09-30T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-30T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/30/hitman-3-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/30/hitman-3-review">&lt;p&gt;I finally gave into temptation and bought the final chapter of in one of my favourite series of recent years. &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt; takes Agent 47 to new locations and promises to wrap up the trilogy’s narrative - but given the behind-the-scenes turmoil at IO Interactive during its development, does it deliver the same level of quality as the previous games? Read on to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; Hitman 3 &lt;em&gt;sits in an awkward spot, right on the boundary between what I would call a review and a retrospective. Note that while this article is labelled “review”, it will contain some spoilers due to the age of the game.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iteration-on-excellence&quot;&gt;Iteration on excellence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the series’ reboot in 2016, &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt;’s World of Assassination has set a consistent high tide mark for what was a rather lucklustre console generation compared to its predecessor. There was - and still is - nothing quite like IO Interactive’s “social stealth” games, which task the player with assassinating targets not with firepower or button-mashing dexterity, but through careful observation, planning, and execution, all without leaving a trace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, each &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt; level sets the globetrotting Agent 47 loose in a new location - in &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt;’s case ranging from Dubai skyscrapers to English country houses and Argentinian vineyards. While the player does have access to guns, the fun is in quietly subduing carefully selected civilians to disguise yourself and gain access to restricted areas.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sandboxes themselves are a joy to explore, intricately detailed and full of interesting and funny dialogue to overhear. Curiosity is nearly always rewarded when discovering new areas, and the levels are presented with such gorgeous graphics that the game sometimes feels almost like a window into how the other half live, in much the same way that the &lt;em&gt;Assassin’s Creed&lt;/em&gt; games can be used as a sort of historical sightseeing tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the complexity of the levels, the AI doesn’t always get things right (it’s still remarkably good - it’s just unreasonable to ask it to understand every possible context it could be presented with), but for the most part the game’s humourous - sometimes borderline slapstick - approach to stealth and action helps to paper over the cracks and avoid breaking immersion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the killings themselves, &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt; does what all my favourite games do. It gives the player the tools and lets them choose what happens next. You are free to walk up to each target and shoot or strangle them, but it’s much more rewarding to scout the level and find opportunities to set up elaborate “accidents” - even more so if you turn off the on-screen prompts, which can make this feel a little bit like painting by numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the amount of time you spend blending in and observing, the pacing of the gameplay is almost like &lt;em&gt;Paranormal Activity&lt;/em&gt;’s approach to horror - a long, slow build-up while you try to pretend everything is normal and put the pieces in place, followed by those crucial, adrenaline-pumping seconds as you execute your plan, and hopefully the target, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;seeing-the-sights&quot;&gt;Seeing the sights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agent 47 begins his 2021 world tour at the opening of a &lt;strong&gt;Dubai&lt;/strong&gt; skyscraper. The sprawling level spans the upper floors of the building and is perhaps the game’s most beautiful, the sun beaming in across the ornate interior. My first target was tragically electrocuted by his own art exhibit, while my favourite assassination option here was to steal some security keycards, sabotage my second target’s parachute, and trigger an evacuation of the penthouse where he was holed up to send him tumbling to his death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second mission takes us to a country house in &lt;strong&gt;Dartmoor&lt;/strong&gt;. There’s an acclaimed murder mystery-style story to be explored here, but being dumped outside a restricted compound immediately put me in &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/splinter-cell&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; mode. I went full stealth, infiltrating the grounds and climbing the drainpipes to the top floor, where I eliminated the target as she screamed into a pillow in a secret room and solved a simple puzzle to steal some files from her safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Berlin&lt;/strong&gt; required a similar approach, slipping quietly into a warehouse rave. The twist here is that the player must identify five ICA agents by exploring and listening in to conversations before eliminating them. I stumbled into enough agents and killed most of them with a pistol shot from distance, with the club music helping to cover up any commotion. This was one of my least favourite &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt; missions, but one I will probably revisit and try to approach more methodically now I know roughly where I’m going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, Agent 47 is tasked with killing two targets and deleting data from a server at a secret underground ICA facility in &lt;strong&gt;Chongqing&lt;/strong&gt;, China. This was an enjoyable level, and again very pretty, the rainy city draped with neon lights in a way that reminded me of &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/07/29/stray-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This was the first time &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt; lined me up with a viable sniper shot, taking a target out through a distant window, before I disguised myself as an ICA analyst to go underground and find my second victim. The ICA area suffers from some awful voice acting for several critical characters, but this one will still certainly be worth a replay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also where the game first strays from its winning formula and tries to introduce more of a narrative to the gameplay. Deleting data from the ICA server puts the facility on red alert, and Agent 47 must escape by sneaking past tens of patrolling guards. I’m in two minds about this - on one hand it certainly provides an adrenaline-pumping mission finale, but on the other it was more scripted than anything in a &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt; sandbox should be, and denied me the usual satisfaction of completing a mission undetected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unearned-gravitas&quot;&gt;Unearned gravitas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Mendoza&lt;/strong&gt; vineyard mission is also story-driven as the game attempts to push the series’ narrative towards its denouement. This time Diana Burnwood - the mostly disembodied voice of Agent 47’s handler for the earlier games - is in attendance, and wants him to kill one of her rivals for the position of Constant (don’t ask - it’s a long story), as well as the owner of the winery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latter is fairly straightforward (I visited his house disguised as his lawyer and strangled him), but it’s clear the game is cranking up the difficulty with Diana’s rival Tamara Vidal. Diana herself is rarely more than a metre from her, ruling out any kind of explosive elimination, while even a silenced shot sets every guard in the place on 47. In the end I located a bottle of her favourite wine and posed as a waiter to serve her a poisoned glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s almost the end of the game, as far as I’m concerned. Nothing from this point plays like a &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt; game, and while it serves to tie up all of the story’s loose ends, I don’t know anybody who plays these games for the narrative and it was somewhat underwhelming that the final location turned out not to be another sandbox but a much more linear level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I’m getting ahead of myself. First, after Diana administers him a nerve agent, 47 has a strange dream sequence where we’re brought face to face with all of the targets we’ve killed through the trilogy. It’s nice that the developers tried to add some fanfare to the finale, but the tone is very serious and feels as though we’re expected to feel some guilt over their deaths, which falls a bit flat in a game that’s all about creative killing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;47 wakes up in a lab where scientists are researching a memory-wiping serum he was given as a child, and on opening the door we realise that we are on a train hurtling through &lt;strong&gt;Romania&lt;/strong&gt;. The last mission of the series sees Agent 47 making his way to the head of the train, travelling through, over, and around carriages in a way was reminiscent of &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell: Pandora Tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;’s train level - just with added disguises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose the trilogy had to have an ending, but the final mission isn’t one I’d ever go back and play. You get to use all of Agent 47’s tricks, but they take on a more simplistic light when working in such confined spaces where there there’s normally only one realistic option to progress laid on a plate (like exactly the right outfit sitting just inside the carriage door). Eventually we reach the front and take care of the main baddie - ironically, by injecting him with the serum - and it’s all over, albeit in a very understated way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;off-field-issues&quot;&gt;Off-field issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On gameplay alone, &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt; would be one of very few games to earn my maximum five-star rating, but &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review&quot;&gt;as always seems to be the case these days&lt;/a&gt;, it falls short for several business-related reasons. These won’t necessarily ruin your enjoyment of the game - especially if you can get it for a reduced price, like I did - but it’s only fair that they’re taken into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first (and most publicised) of these is that this is a single-player game that essentially must be played online. There’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/HiTMAN/comments/l45so8/a_list_of_things_not_available_offline_in_hitman/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a full list of what’s missing if you play offline&lt;/a&gt; on Reddit, but put simply you’ll have access to the main missions and not much else. Additionally, any games you saved while playing online are inaccessible, and you will be unable to earn the challenge-based unlocks for the levels. It’s a baffling decision for a game with no multiplayer - especially when the online leaderboards are full of apparent cheaters who completed every mission in less than a minute anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly - and more importantly in the game’s current, supported state - is &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt;’s value proposition. Both &lt;em&gt;Hitman&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Hitman 2&lt;/em&gt; featured at least six “proper” missions and locations by my count, while &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt; - excluding the very linear train level - provides just five. Again, not a fatal shortcoming, but a little disappointing for such an unusually expensive title, and I’d have felt short changed if I had paid full price for the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, warnings aside, is &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt; worth it? Totally. From exploring the five new sprawling locations to revisting old missions in the updated engine, there are hours of fun and challenge to be found here, and the beauty of the series’ gameplay is that each level offers a ton of replay value to try new routes, disguises, equipment, and assassination options. This is must-play stuff, so my advice would be to pick it up on an offer when you can - just make sure you put aside enough time, because &lt;em&gt;Hitman 3&lt;/em&gt; is very addictive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4/5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="hitman" /><category term="stealth" /><summary type="html">I finally gave into temptation and bought the final chapter of in one of my favourite series of recent years. Hitman 3 takes Agent 47 to new locations and promises to wrap up the trilogy’s narrative - but given the behind-the-scenes turmoil at IO Interactive during its development, does it deliver the same level of quality as the previous games? Read on to find out. Note: Hitman 3 sits in an awkward spot, right on the boundary between what I would call a review and a retrospective. Note that while this article is labelled “review”, it will contain some spoilers due to the age of the game. Iteration on excellence Since the series’ reboot in 2016, Hitman’s World of Assassination has set a consistent high tide mark for what was a rather lucklustre console generation compared to its predecessor. There was - and still is - nothing quite like IO Interactive’s “social stealth” games, which task the player with assassinating targets not with firepower or button-mashing dexterity, but through careful observation, planning, and execution, all without leaving a trace. For the uninitiated, each Hitman level sets the globetrotting Agent 47 loose in a new location - in Hitman 3’s case ranging from Dubai skyscrapers to English country houses and Argentinian vineyards. While the player does have access to guns, the fun is in quietly subduing carefully selected civilians to disguise yourself and gain access to restricted areas.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hitman-3_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GTA VI leak: Beyond the videos</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/23/gta-vi-leak-beyond-the-videos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTA VI leak&amp;#58; Beyond the videos" /><published>2022-09-23T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-23T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/23/gta-vi-leak-beyond-the-videos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/23/gta-vi-leak-beyond-the-videos">&lt;p&gt;We saw one of the biggest leaks in video game history last Sunday as a hacker uploaded a huge number of videos and images from Rockstar’s upcoming &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/grand-theft-auto&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto VI&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to the internet, and it’s safe to say online discussion around this unexpected sneak peek has been a complete mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gta-vi_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The early footage shows several interesting locations, features, and segments of dialogue that give us clues about what we can expect on the game’s release, which is likely years away. However, most of the comments I’ve seen on social media have completely ignored the big picture to focus on rough edges that are extremely unlikely to be present in the final game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching all of this, I felt compelled to delay my planned article this week and write about &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt; instead. I’ll stress that I have no special inside knowledge about the leak or the game itself, but I hope I can at least offer some more considered thoughts than those currently spewed across the web. In brief, the whole debacle has taught me three things…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-people-know-nothing-about-hacking&quot;&gt;1. People know nothing about hacking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“[X Rockstar employee] is going to be in trouble” was a common theme on Reddit, as wannabe cybersecurity experts offered rundowns of exactly how the person whose name appeared in some of the videos was outwitted by a social engineering attack that gave the attacker access. Others were sure that online messages indicated this was the work of a disgruntled employee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that there are two things that we know about the incident - at least since &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RockstarGames/status/1571849091860029455&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rockstar confirmed there was a “network intrusion” on Monday&lt;/a&gt;. Firstly, we know that a hacker gained access to &lt;em&gt;some Rockstar systems&lt;/em&gt; (not even necessarily their network, since so much happens on cloud services these days). Secondly, we know that they were able to download some videos and images created &lt;em&gt;at some point in the game’s development&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. We don’t know if they phished someone, we don’t know if they used some ultra-sophisticated zero-day vulnerability, and we don’t know if a storage platform was improperly configured and allowed them access. We don’t know what happened, and Rockstar is probably still piecing it together itself, so there’s no point in blindly speculating - especially when that speculation involves pointing the finger at individual employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that point - sure, somebody’s name appears on screen in some of the videos, but if a hacker steals files from a shared location they could have &lt;em&gt;anybody’s&lt;/em&gt; name on them, regardless of how they got in. That person just &lt;em&gt;recorded&lt;/em&gt; the videos. Confidently asserting that they were the cause of the breach is at best foolish, and at worst borderline slander.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-people-know-nothing-about-development&quot;&gt;2. People know nothing about development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d have thought that in 2022’s tech-driven society, with all the developer blogs and behind-the-scenes footage we’re treated to, that people would have a rough idea of what goes into making a video game. Unfortunately not, it appears, as Sunday’s discussion threads were jammed with complaints about &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt;’s graphics, despite the game being years off release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It looks nearly the same as &lt;em&gt;GTA V&lt;/em&gt;,” people whined. &lt;em&gt;Of course it does&lt;/em&gt;. The footage is obviously from a very early version of the game - likely borrowing a lot from the last entry - where the developers are testing out systems to see what works and laying the groundwork for later, more polished versions. There are going to be rough edges, and for all we know they could no longer exist, since we don’t know when the videos were captured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rockstar was evidently concerned about this reaction too, as evidenced in the statement it tweeted earlier this week:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We are extremely disappointed to have any details of our next game shared with you all in this way. Our work on the next &lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto&lt;/em&gt; game will continue as planned and we remain as committed as ever to delivering and experience to you, our players, that truly exceeds your expectations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: Stop judging our game on janky alpha footage that was never meant to be made public, you idiots. It’s also clear that many of the clips may have been recorded &lt;em&gt;specifically to inform bug fixes&lt;/em&gt;, as the creator seems to focus attention on issues like clipping and AI mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you watch the videos with a curious eye, rather than a critical one, they actually offer an inside view of game development that we rarely get to see. For example, the pop-ups that litter the screen during the restaurant robbery (like HOSTAGE_POLICE_ARRIVAL, GENERIC_CURSE_TO_SELF, and CALL_FOR_SUPPORT_RESPONSE) are a fascinating glimpse of how AI reactions, animations, and sound clips are handled behind the scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-rockstar-might-actually-deliver-on-gta-vi&quot;&gt;3. Rockstar might actually deliver on &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of August I wrote about &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/08/05/gta-vi-first-details-scepticism&quot;&gt;how skeptical I am about &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Early details suggested that the series might be moving in the direction of live services following the success of &lt;em&gt;GTA Online&lt;/em&gt;, and given that this is the first &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; game to be released since Rockstar worked out how to print free money, I’m concerned about what that might mean for the single-player experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a few leaked clips haven’t completely allayed my fears, what they have done is reassured me that the minutiae and attention to detail that Rockstar is known for are still there. Beyond the debug messages, clipping, and placeholder textures, there are already signs of some real touches of class - the fluidity of new female lead character’s walking animations, for example, or the two NPCs discussing Lifeinvader conspiracy theories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between that and the obstructed views of Vice City in the background, I’m feeling much more confident that the detail that makes &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt;’s worlds so much fun to explore will still be present. And then there’s the restaurant robbery, complete with the second main character controlled by AI to back you up. It could be a Story Mode set piece, but I’m crossing my fingers that this means more ad hoc interactivity with the world and NPCs than in previous games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, despite the fact that they certainly would have liked to introduce us to the game in a more controlled fashion, the &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt; leak shows enough potential that it should really have been a net positive for Rockstar in my opinion. Instead, they’ve needed to engage in damage limitation because the internet is stupid and expects a game with years of development left to go to look like a finished AAA product - or at least that’s my two cents.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="grand-theft-auto" /><category term="industry" /><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">We saw one of the biggest leaks in video game history last Sunday as a hacker uploaded a huge number of videos and images from Rockstar’s upcoming Grand Theft Auto VI to the internet, and it’s safe to say online discussion around this unexpected sneak peek has been a complete mess. The early footage shows several interesting locations, features, and segments of dialogue that give us clues about what we can expect on the game’s release, which is likely years away. However, most of the comments I’ve seen on social media have completely ignored the big picture to focus on rough edges that are extremely unlikely to be present in the final game. Watching all of this, I felt compelled to delay my planned article this week and write about GTA VI instead. I’ll stress that I have no special inside knowledge about the leak or the game itself, but I hope I can at least offer some more considered thoughts than those currently spewed across the web. In brief, the whole debacle has taught me three things… 1. People know nothing about hacking “[X Rockstar employee] is going to be in trouble” was a common theme on Reddit, as wannabe cybersecurity experts offered rundowns of exactly how the person whose name appeared in some of the videos was outwitted by a social engineering attack that gave the attacker access. Others were sure that online messages indicated this was the work of a disgruntled employee. The truth is that there are two things that we know about the incident - at least since Rockstar confirmed there was a “network intrusion” on Monday. Firstly, we know that a hacker gained access to some Rockstar systems (not even necessarily their network, since so much happens on cloud services these days). Secondly, we know that they were able to download some videos and images created at some point in the game’s development.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gta-vi_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gta-vi_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – cup runs to remember</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/16/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-3" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA 22 Career Mode&amp;#58; TSP United &amp;#8211; cup runs to remember" /><published>2022-09-16T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/16/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/16/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-3">&lt;p&gt;The years are flying by in my &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Career Mode series, and after surviving our first season in the top flight, the fans are now expecting TSP United to push on and improve their standing amongst England’s best clubs in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a reminder, I’m playing this Career Mode campaign with special custom rules for some added challenge. I’m not to spend a penny on players (signing free agents is fine) and the focus is on &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players&quot;&gt;scouting and developing youth players&lt;/a&gt;. So my main source of new talent through this whole thing is to send a scout out around England occasionally and see what he brings back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this is the third instalment of my TSP United Career Mode series. Click here to catch up on the first four seasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/06/17/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-2&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – hitting the big time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202526---premier-league&quot;&gt;2025/26 - Premier League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a top-flight season under our belts, it was time to cement our place in the Premier League, and that meant strengthening in some key areas. Free agent centre backs Adhoum and Alba came in to provide some depth, Anami was retrained to join them in defence, and I signed a clubless left midfielder named Albanese now that Annumanian was playing up front.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a slow start, but some good form towards the end of 2025 meant we crept into the top half at the start of the new year. The goal of the season undoubtedly came from club legend Willis against Liverpool, cutting in from the wing and rounding Allison to give TSP United an early lead at Anfield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the issues started. Annumanian suffered an injury around the 25-game mark (luckily, he’d return in scoring form before May) and Aguerre’s poor form gave me no choice but to give the youngster Parkin more chances in goal. In better news, academy product Hunter was steadily developing as a right-wing understudy to Pierre, and Green stepped in at left back to replace a declining Marcos Alonso, who would retire at the end of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the league campaign ended in mid-table mediocrity, our FA Cup run culminated in a dramatic triumph against Arsenal at Wembley. After going 2-0 down in the early stages, we dragged ourselves back to 2-2, before going in 3-2 down at the break. Arsenal had a man sent off in the second half, and a late equaliser from Pierre took the game to extra time, where Annumanian wrote himself into the TSP United history books with the winning goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best original player&lt;/strong&gt; - Willis/Hutton, the two survivors from League 2&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - Alba, providing much-needed depth at CB&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Green, earning his first-team spot&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202627---premier-league&quot;&gt;2026/27 - Premier League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With our FA Cup victory came a Europa League spot, and with the hectic schedule that European football brings incoming, we once again needed to strengthen the squad. Club legend Johnson left, opting for a move elsewhere due to a lack of playing time. The pickings were slim, but we signed another free agent named Aguirre - this time at right back - and sent the scouts back out to England and Scotland to top up the academy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our efforts were rewarded with what I consider to be an impressive first run in the Europa League. With games coming fast, our youngsters took to the pitch, with striker Goddard the standout, scoring a hat trick as we beat group leaders AZ 3-2 in the final game to secure our progression. After destroying Young Boys in the first knockout round, we didn’t have enough to beat Atalanta in the Round of 16 and tumbled out of the competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The board were expecting us to qualify for the Europa League via the league this year, but our mixed fortunes early on gave way to the most dire run of form of my managerial career so far. In the end we finished tenth, well short of the board’s expectations, largely due to poor performances from Parkin and his defence. Vaughan broke the Premier League season scoring record, which should give you an idea of what a disaster it was at the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With nothing to write home about from the domestic cup runs and the league season ending in disappointment, the highlight of 2026/27 was without doubt our first European campaign - not only because of how far we progressed, but because it was mainly down to our next generation of players. The future of TSP United looks bright, but having missed out on most of my objectives I can only hope I’m around long enough to see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best original player&lt;/strong&gt; - Willis, still going strong at LM after six years&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - Aguirre, who made some exciting runs from RB&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Goddard, back with 18 goals in 31 apps&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">The years are flying by in my FIFA 22 Career Mode series, and after surviving our first season in the top flight, the fans are now expecting TSP United to push on and improve their standing amongst England’s best clubs in 2025. As a reminder, I’m playing this Career Mode campaign with special custom rules for some added challenge. I’m not to spend a penny on players (signing free agents is fine) and the focus is on scouting and developing youth players. So my main source of new talent through this whole thing is to send a scout out around England occasionally and see what he brings back. Note that this is the third instalment of my TSP United Career Mode series. Click here to catch up on the first four seasons: • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – hitting the big time 2025/26 - Premier League With a top-flight season under our belts, it was time to cement our place in the Premier League, and that meant strengthening in some key areas. Free agent centre backs Adhoum and Alba came in to provide some depth, Anami was retrained to join them in defence, and I signed a clubless left midfielder named Albanese now that Annumanian was playing up front.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to run a half marathon</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/09/how-to-run-half-marathon" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to run a half marathon" /><published>2022-09-09T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-09T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/09/how-to-run-half-marathon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/09/how-to-run-half-marathon">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/running&quot;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt; on and off for years, but I was in two minds when I first considered signing up to a half marathon earlier this year. Towards the end of 2021 I’d completed &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/10/running-formula-1-for-your-feet&quot;&gt;a one-hour event&lt;/a&gt;, but a half marathon was double the distance, a whole new level of commitment, and a step into the unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/half-marathon_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spoiler alert - I finished the race. I didn’t do it in quite the way I’d hoped, but I’m happy with what I achieved and plan to go back stronger and better prepared next year. In that spirit, I thought that while everything was fresh in my mind it would be a good time to share what I’ve learnt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-for-a-half-marathon&quot;&gt;Training for a half marathon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first things you need in order to run a half marathon are time to train, somewhere to run (the streets are your best bet), good running shoes, and light and comfortable clothes to run in. The important thing here is to pick an outfit and stick to it - don’t buy a new shirt and save it for the main event, because you won’t know whether it chafes until it’s too late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started training properly in March, six months ahead of the event in September. Prior to that I’d been running about 5km twice a week, so I started to ramp that up. My midweek run started at 5km and eventually became 7.5km, while my long weekend run slowly scaled up until I ran my first half marathon distance in July. Given that I was running up and down hills and the event course would be flat, I thought I was well set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two moments that turned out to be crucial came towards the end of my training. Firstly, one day the tread of my trusty running shoes fell off while I was out running the streets of my neighbourhood. I thought I chose the replacements well, but over time I started to feel complaints from my knees and the outside of my right foot, and it only got worse. When I did my final preparation run it took a week for them to feel somewhat normal again.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second stroke of bad luck came about a month before the race, when I ended up looking after somebody who came down with COVID. Fortunately I didn’t catch it myself (that might have been game over completely), but it did keep me off the streets for two weeks. In the end, I managed only four more runs - two short, two long - before the event itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;running-a-half-marathon&quot;&gt;Running a half marathon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the day came, everything was set. I had run a non-stop half marathon distance the week before and my knees had mostly recovered, and the forecasted rain disappeared, leaving a morning that was dry but not too hot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first mistake was arriving at the time suggested by the event organisers. I ended up queueing for nearly an hour to use a toilet before the race and missed my start time by 20 minutes. Aside from the boredom and discomfort, starting three hours after my usual running time meant it was considerably warmer than I was used to when I crossed the start line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first mile was a breeze, with an early challenge emerging only as I entered a tunnel. I had plenty in the tank to deal with the slope, but the underground section was unexpectedly hot, and I could feel the sweat dripping down my forehead. Although I felt fine, this was when the first doubts started to creep in over whether I could keep this up for 21km.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My pace slipped slightly over the next few miles, but I still felt strong. The only nagging concern was over my knees, which had started to give the first indications that there was a painful journey ahead. This was exacerbated by a section where I had to traverse some cobbled streets, where I needed to watch every step to avoid slipping or folding an ankle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit that by the seventh mile I was starting to lag, with stitches forming on either side of my stomach. I endured the pain for a while longer, but by the time I hit the eight-mile mark it was too much. I pulled to the side of the road and tried to keep up a brisk walk, swigging from the sports drink I’d brought along and praying for recovery and a second wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never regained the same level of energy I enjoyed at the beginning, but after about a mile I did force myself to start running again. I could see my knees were red, and every step hurt more and more until I was worried something would snap at some point. Passing strewn-out runners being tended to by paramedics wasn’t exactly reassuring, but I remained determined to keep going, even if progress was slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/half-marathon_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the final kilometre or so the streets were lined with spectators, which helped me to muster enough for a final push. When I checked my split times later, the was a noticeable increase in my pace as I drew closer to the finish, and I finally made it across the line after about two hours and 20 minutes - not quite what I was aiming for, but an achievement nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-i-learnt&quot;&gt;What I learnt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I finished the race, the half marathon didn’t &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; go to plan. In the days since, I’ve thought carefully about how things played out and have identified some key areas to improve on for next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Running shoes&lt;/strong&gt; - Do you remember how I mentioned that you shouldn’t switch out your equipment shortly before a race? My forced change of running shoes was a prime example, as I didn’t have time to realise the damage they were doing to my feet and legs. My top priority is to buy a better quality pair that I can train in throughout my next attempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water&lt;/strong&gt; - I opted to take a sports drink with me for the race, thinking that replacing my lost sugar and salt would give me an extra burst of energy. But its thick, sugary taste was almost nauseating when running, and discouraged me from drinking. Next time I’ll stick to water, and perhaps try the energy sachets that many of the other runners were using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pace&lt;/strong&gt; - I started out ambitious, aiming for the two-hour mark, and it blew up in my face after about two thirds of the race distance. Next time I’ll set out at a more comfortable pace, because running slightly slower throughout is better overall than starting quickly and running out of steam later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there you have it. That’s everything I know about how to run a half marathon, and also what I’ve learnt about how &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to run a half marathon. I hope this article is useful if you’re preparing for your own race, and if you have any tips for my second attempt next year, please let me know.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="running" /><summary type="html">I’ve been running on and off for years, but I was in two minds when I first considered signing up to a half marathon earlier this year. Towards the end of 2021 I’d completed a one-hour event, but a half marathon was double the distance, a whole new level of commitment, and a step into the unknown. Spoiler alert - I finished the race. I didn’t do it in quite the way I’d hoped, but I’m happy with what I achieved and plan to go back stronger and better prepared next year. In that spirit, I thought that while everything was fresh in my mind it would be a good time to share what I’ve learnt. Training for a half marathon The first things you need in order to run a half marathon are time to train, somewhere to run (the streets are your best bet), good running shoes, and light and comfortable clothes to run in. The important thing here is to pick an outfit and stick to it - don’t buy a new shirt and save it for the main event, because you won’t know whether it chafes until it’s too late. I started training properly in March, six months ahead of the event in September. Prior to that I’d been running about 5km twice a week, so I started to ramp that up. My midweek run started at 5km and eventually became 7.5km, while my long weekend run slowly scaled up until I ran my first half marathon distance in July. Given that I was running up and down hills and the event course would be flat, I thought I was well set. Two moments that turned out to be crucial came towards the end of my training. Firstly, one day the tread of my trusty running shoes fell off while I was out running the streets of my neighbourhood. I thought I chose the replacements well, but over time I started to feel complaints from my knees and the outside of my right foot, and it only got worse. When I did my final preparation run it took a week for them to feel somewhat normal again.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/half-marathon_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/half-marathon_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">F1 Manager 2022 is like a revival of old movie games</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/02/f1-manager-2022-movie-game-revival" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="F1 Manager 2022 is like a revival of old movie games" /><published>2022-09-02T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/02/f1-manager-2022-movie-game-revival</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/02/f1-manager-2022-movie-game-revival">&lt;p&gt;There was a time, certainly in the 2000s but also arguably as early as the 1980s - I’m looking at you, &lt;em&gt;ET&lt;/em&gt; - when most video games based on films were disappointments. There were some notable exceptions, like the excellent &lt;em&gt;Spider-Man 2&lt;/em&gt;, but all too often movie tie-ins were dull, mediocre games with recognisable textures and voices copied and pasted into the right places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f1-manager-2022_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sports game have largely avoided the same fate - perhaps because their real-life counterparts translate more easily into a video game format. &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/pro-evolution-soccer&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; have always given us enjoyable recreations of professional football, there have been countless iterations on golf, and across the pond &lt;em&gt;Madden&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;NBA&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;MLB&lt;/em&gt; are all long-running series. For those who want on-brand motorsport, &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-1&quot;&gt;Codemasters’ &lt;em&gt;F1&lt;/em&gt; series&lt;/a&gt; has done a consistent job of providing entertaining racing since its first true edition surfaced in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year there’s a new face on the scene - &lt;em&gt;F1 Manager 2022&lt;/em&gt;, developed by Frontier. From the very beginning it’s been promoted on its presentation, with early screenshots compared favourably to Codemasters’ graphics. Official teams and drivers were expected of a licensed game, and when early access opened we also saw that it features the flashy F1 race intro sequence, radio audio from the real drivers, and commentary from Crofty at key in-race moments. With all that on its side, what could go wrong?&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f1-manager-2022_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, for a start, the racing is not as impressive in motion as it was in still images. Like &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/football-manager&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the game’s simulation is obviously based on a series of strategic calculations rather than a physics model, and it suffers from the same mismatch with its 3D representation. Drivers take odd racing lines and steer erratically, for example, leaving you on edge when watching onboard cameras as they always look like they’re about to spin out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That would be forgivable for a management game - it certainly is for &lt;em&gt;FM&lt;/em&gt;’s unnatural-looking players - but for &lt;em&gt;F1 Manager 2022&lt;/em&gt; the visual disconnect just helps to highlight other shortcomings. When you sell realism, players expect realism, and the reaction to the game’s launch has given me a new appreciation for the way &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/08/27/motorsport-manager-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Motorsport Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; cleverly streamlined the complexities of motorsport into a sort of cartoonish card game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f1-manager-2022_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/F1Manager/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;F1 Manager&lt;/em&gt;’s subreddit&lt;/a&gt; is full of complaints of game-breaking issues. Players are frustrated at the limited instructions they can issue to drivers, simple and repetitive practice sessions, drivers cutting across the racing line and blocking their cars’ fast laps, and intermediate tyres that they say perform better than slicks in the dry. And it doesn’t seem there’s much challenge to be found amongst the chaos, either - even players managing backmarkers like Haas and Williams are finding they can be championship contenders by the second season if they optimise their cars’ development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To Frontier’s credit, they appear to be engaging with players more than most developers have historically in similar situations, and seem to be keen to gather feedback. Hopefully most of the bugs can be fixed fairly quickly, but it remains to be seen whether the balance and missing detail will be rectified in this year’s game. For now, however, it looks like &lt;em&gt;F1 Manager 2022&lt;/em&gt; is a revival of the classic movie game - a title that relies on licences and familiar faces to sell, but lacks substance beyond its slick presentation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="f1-manager" /><category term="formula-1" /><category term="racing" /><category term="management" /><summary type="html">There was a time, certainly in the 2000s but also arguably as early as the 1980s - I’m looking at you, ET - when most video games based on films were disappointments. There were some notable exceptions, like the excellent Spider-Man 2, but all too often movie tie-ins were dull, mediocre games with recognisable textures and voices copied and pasted into the right places. Sports game have largely avoided the same fate - perhaps because their real-life counterparts translate more easily into a video game format. FIFA and PES have always given us enjoyable recreations of professional football, there have been countless iterations on golf, and across the pond Madden, NBA, and MLB are all long-running series. For those who want on-brand motorsport, Codemasters’ F1 series has done a consistent job of providing entertaining racing since its first true edition surfaced in 2010. This year there’s a new face on the scene - F1 Manager 2022, developed by Frontier. From the very beginning it’s been promoted on its presentation, with early screenshots compared favourably to Codemasters’ graphics. Official teams and drivers were expected of a licensed game, and when early access opened we also saw that it features the flashy F1 race intro sequence, radio audio from the real drivers, and commentary from Crofty at key in-race moments. With all that on its side, what could go wrong?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f1-manager-2022_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f1-manager-2022_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Muse – Will Of The People review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/08/26/muse-will-of-the-people-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Muse &amp;#8211; Will Of The People review" /><published>2022-08-26T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-26T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/08/26/muse-will-of-the-people-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/08/26/muse-will-of-the-people-review">&lt;p&gt;I’m back after a longer-than-expected break for COVID-related reasons, and have returned just in time for Muse’s first new album in nearly four years, &lt;em&gt;Will Of The People&lt;/em&gt;. While &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/music&quot;&gt;it’s relatively rare for me to discuss music&lt;/a&gt; on this blog, I’ve been a huge Muse fan since I was a teenager, so I thought I’d jot down some notes from my initial listens to share with you all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/muse-will-of-the-people_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months leading up to its release, Muse frontman Matt Bellamy billed &lt;em&gt;Will Of The People&lt;/em&gt; as “a greatest hits album of new songs”, revisiting the styles of the band’s previous eight studio albums across its ten tracks. It’s unsurprising, then, that what he and his bandmates delivered is an eclectic collection of songs that range from heavy metal to emotional piano ballads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the quality? Opinions on individual tracks will vary depending on your tastes for different Muse eras, but for me heavy rocker Kill Or Be Killed sits with their very best, there are a couple of decent guitar-heavy songs, and much of the record is B-tier pop-rock. The lows - there are &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; lows - are nowhere near as dismal as the worst tracks on some of their other albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you enjoy &lt;em&gt;Will Of The People&lt;/em&gt; will depend on what you’re expecting. We can almost say for certain now that the Muse that delivered &lt;em&gt;Origin of Symmetry&lt;/em&gt; is gone for good, but if you’re open to enjoying their more playful, overblown side - and not averse to some quite significant shifts in sound and theme - then the album provides nod-along pop, heavy guitar riffs, and surprisingly emotional moments in almost equal measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the very least, it’s a definite step up from 2018’s disappointing, synth-heavy effort &lt;em&gt;Simulation Theory&lt;/em&gt;. At best, you could make an argument that this is Muse’s best album since &lt;em&gt;The 2nd Law&lt;/em&gt; or even &lt;em&gt;The Resistance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;track-by-track&quot;&gt;Track by track&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Will Of The People&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Catchy pop-rock track that works fantastically as a set opener at live gigs. Doesn’t outstay its welcome like previous songs in this category (Psycho) and has more lyrical depth than some reviewers give it credit for. While it’s often written off as another Muse call for revolution, in reality it transforms during the second verse into a warning about those who seek positive change but go too far and “throw the baby out with the bath water”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Compliance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Another misunderstood song, sometimes mistaken as an anti-mask/vaccine track, but actually in my view provides some quite thoughful commentary on how directionless individuals are swept up by ideologically-fuelled online movements in a bid to find purpose. Musically, eerie verses and some very funky bass make Compliance enjoyable despite its heavy pop leanings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Liberation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Musically reminiscent of the tail end of The Globalist with similar lyrical themes to Defector, with the Queen-style harmonies of United States of Eurasia thrown in for good measure. Varied enough to be engaging, but the “thank you” segment always feels disappointing because everything to that point feels like it’s building to something. But as the first time we’ve heard Matt Bellamy properly break out his piano since 2015, I’ll take it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Won’t Stand Down&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The verses feel very Imagine Dragons and often jar with the breakdowns and chorus, but when it gains momentum it’s hard not to move too. Ascending, synth-backed choruses get the adrenaline pumping, and everything past the two-minute mark is heavier than we’ve heard Muse in years. Delivers the guitar riffs Muse fans endlessly hope for, but not the classical elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Ghosts (How Can I Move On)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Bellamy takes to the stage alone with this piano ballad, which would feel right at home on his solo Record Store Day 2021 LP &lt;em&gt;Cryosleep&lt;/em&gt;. The lyrics sometimes stumble over themselves a little, but the composition, themes, and longing vocals are enough to make this a surprisingly welcome interlude. Along with Euphoria, this marks the emotional high of the album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. You Make Me Feel Like It’s Halloween&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It’s hard to argue in favour of Halloween, especially when it comes right after a track as heartfelt as Ghosts. It’s fun and groovy, but between the organ, the title, and the B-movie horror sound effects, it sticks out as an oddity on the album and feels more like a Halloween novelty track than something that belongs on a mainline Muse record. It does earn a few bonus points for the guitar solo, however, which is far better than it has any right to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Kill Or Be Killed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Without a doubt the best song on the album, and perhaps the best track Muse have delivered in a decade - maybe even 15 years. Kill Or Be Killed is some of the heaviest rock the trio have ever recorded, taking a similar tone to fan favourite &lt;em&gt;Absolution&lt;/em&gt; bonus track Fury, but with added punch. The lyrics, chord progressions, and general feeling all scream “classic Muse”, and one can only hope that we’re treated to more music like this in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Verona&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In my opinion this is &lt;em&gt;WOTP&lt;/em&gt;’s weakest track, and not just because it lives in Kill Or Be Killed’s shadow. Verona is a synthy love song with shades of U2, which is a side of modern Muse that is often bemoaned. It builds up nicely, but ultimately does little to earn its place as the album’s second-longest song, and is the only one I’ve found myself occasionally skipping already. It has heart, but there’s nothing particularly Musey about it - I can imagine myself checking my watch as a support band plays something very similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Euphoria&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It took a few listens, but Euphoria has quickly become one of my favourites. I’m not big on the almost shouted verses, but there’s something to the chords and sustain-heavy guitar solos that takes me back to the early-to-mid-2000s when I first discovered Muse and felt all their songs deeply. It’s upbeat, it has probably the best guitar solo on the album, and there’s more desperation to the melodies than I thought the band could muster in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. We Are Fucking Fucked&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If &lt;em&gt;WOTP&lt;/em&gt; is a greatest hits-style tour of Muse’s previous work, the verses here are as close as we get to &lt;em&gt;Showbiz&lt;/em&gt;. I’m split on the song in general - it’s lively, but the chorus where Bellamy lists bad things in the world feels basic, and there’s a point near the end where he just yells “fuck off” a couple of times. Luckily, the guitar work is enough to keep pushing through it, and it only increases in intensity as the album comes to a close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4/5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="muse" /><category term="guitar" /><summary type="html">I’m back after a longer-than-expected break for COVID-related reasons, and have returned just in time for Muse’s first new album in nearly four years, Will Of The People. While it’s relatively rare for me to discuss music on this blog, I’ve been a huge Muse fan since I was a teenager, so I thought I’d jot down some notes from my initial listens to share with you all. In the months leading up to its release, Muse frontman Matt Bellamy billed Will Of The People as “a greatest hits album of new songs”, revisiting the styles of the band’s previous eight studio albums across its ten tracks. It’s unsurprising, then, that what he and his bandmates delivered is an eclectic collection of songs that range from heavy metal to emotional piano ballads. As for the quality? Opinions on individual tracks will vary depending on your tastes for different Muse eras, but for me heavy rocker Kill Or Be Killed sits with their very best, there are a couple of decent guitar-heavy songs, and much of the record is B-tier pop-rock. The lows - there are some lows - are nowhere near as dismal as the worst tracks on some of their other albums. Whether you enjoy Will Of The People will depend on what you’re expecting. We can almost say for certain now that the Muse that delivered Origin of Symmetry is gone for good, but if you’re open to enjoying their more playful, overblown side - and not averse to some quite significant shifts in sound and theme - then the album provides nod-along pop, heavy guitar riffs, and surprisingly emotional moments in almost equal measure. At the very least, it’s a definite step up from 2018’s disappointing, synth-heavy effort Simulation Theory. At best, you could make an argument that this is Muse’s best album since The 2nd Law or even The Resistance.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/08/muse-will-of-the-people_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/08/muse-will-of-the-people_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GTA VI: First details leave plenty of room for scepticism</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/08/05/gta-vi-first-details-scepticism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTA VI&amp;#58; First details leave plenty of room for scepticism" /><published>2022-08-05T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-05T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/08/05/gta-vi-first-details-scepticism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/08/05/gta-vi-first-details-scepticism">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gta-vi_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was last week, nearly nine whole years after the release of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/grand-theft-auto&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2022-07-27/gta-6-release-date-rockstar-cleans-up-image-after-employee-backlash&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;an article by &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt;’s Jason Schreier&lt;/a&gt; finally provided some concrete information on its sequel - at least if you believe his ex-Rockstar sources. The piece focused mainly on how progressive Rockstar is apparently now trying to be, but we did get some interesting details on &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt; has been in development since 2014, but insiders predict the release date is still at least two years away&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game will feature a playable female protagonist, who will be one half of a Bonnie and Clyde-inspired duo who are the stars of the story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is codenamed &lt;em&gt;Project Americas&lt;/em&gt;, and was originally meant to cover large parts of North and South America, but was cut down to a fictional Miami (presumably Vice City) to keep the scope manageable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There will be more building interiors than in previous &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; games, and Rockstar plans to add new missions and cities on a regular basis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the online reaction to the article consisted of misguided complaints about the female character, and perhaps-not-so-misguided concerns about how the tone of the game will be affected by the shift in its developer’s culture. But for me, the thing that set the alarm bells ringing was the line about &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt;’s setting and how the game will be extended after launch.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;early-red-flags&quot;&gt;Early red flags&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would happily play a game as a female character, and I could &lt;em&gt;tolerate&lt;/em&gt; a &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; game with blunted satire (it’s been going downhill since the peak that was &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/02/12/gta-iv-immersive-mechanics-lost-forever&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;GTA IV&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, anyway), but what would be harder to stomach is a sequel that doesn’t stand on its own two feet as a quality &lt;em&gt;game&lt;/em&gt;, and instead seeks to establish a platform to keep people spending for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rockstar stumbled upon this model with &lt;em&gt;GTA V&lt;/em&gt;. The main game released in 2013, and as players completed the story and moved on to &lt;em&gt;GTA Online&lt;/em&gt; the company pivoted, realising that it could make more money by having players pay real money to buy imaginary, multiplayer-only cars and yachts, only otherwise obtainable through endless hours of grinding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lines in the article that stood out to me the most were about the scope and roadmap for the project. If Schreier’s sources are correct, the game will release with a Vice City setting but extra missions and cities will be added later. He praises this as a way to avoid development crunch, but my worry is about what this model means for players and the game overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;approach-with-caution&quot;&gt;Approach with caution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Games companies have realised in recent years that they can make a lot of money from live service games, and titles that would have previously been almost certain single-player classics - think &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Diablo Immortal&lt;/em&gt;, for example - have been ruined by the model, prioritising microtransactions over completeness and - y’know - &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible for a title to have online and add-on elements &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; be a good game, but I guess what I’m saying is that I don’t trust modern Rockstar to deliver an experience that I will enjoy as much as previous &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; games. The company’s trademark used to be top-tier single player titles, but it seems that &lt;em&gt;GTA Online&lt;/em&gt;’s popularity has changed all that, with the company even going so far as to cancel planned single-player expansions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still have 2018’s &lt;em&gt;Red Dead Redemption 2&lt;/em&gt; as proof of what Rockstar can achieve in the single player arena, but the few details we have been given on &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt; don’t sound all that appealing. It’s early days, and it could still turn out to be the sequel we’re all dreaming of, but while any &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; game used to be a slam-dunk preorder, I think I’ll be waiting for far more information - maybe even reviews - before spending my hard-earned cash on this one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="grand-theft-auto" /><category term="industry" /><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">It was last week, nearly nine whole years after the release of Grand Theft Auto V, that an article by Bloomberg’s Jason Schreier finally provided some concrete information on its sequel - at least if you believe his ex-Rockstar sources. The piece focused mainly on how progressive Rockstar is apparently now trying to be, but we did get some interesting details on GTA VI: GTA VI has been in development since 2014, but insiders predict the release date is still at least two years away The game will feature a playable female protagonist, who will be one half of a Bonnie and Clyde-inspired duo who are the stars of the story It is codenamed Project Americas, and was originally meant to cover large parts of North and South America, but was cut down to a fictional Miami (presumably Vice City) to keep the scope manageable There will be more building interiors than in previous GTA games, and Rockstar plans to add new missions and cities on a regular basis Much of the online reaction to the article consisted of misguided complaints about the female character, and perhaps-not-so-misguided concerns about how the tone of the game will be affected by the shift in its developer’s culture. But for me, the thing that set the alarm bells ringing was the line about GTA VI’s setting and how the game will be extended after launch.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gta-vi_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gta-vi_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Stray (PC) review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/29/stray-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stray (PC) review" /><published>2022-07-29T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-29T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/29/stray-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/29/stray-review">&lt;p&gt;Just in case you hadn’t already heard, &lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt; is a game where you play as a cat. Ever since it was shown off at a PlayStation event in 2020, the internet has been abuzz with talk about it, but mostly from the memey cat angle rather than any discussion of the actual game. Intrigued, I picked up a copy when it was finally released last week so I could find out for myself whether it was a compelling experience or just popular due to its feline protagonist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/stray_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;into-the-depths&quot;&gt;Into the depths&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt;’s opening moments are peaceful. Waking up with your cat buddies, you run as a pack through an overgrown passage, taking their lead as you learn to navigate the environment on four feet. But tragedy strikes and the cat misses a jump, sliding into a pit where you’re unable to reach your pals. You limp through a door and enter a cyberpunk city full of neon and robots whose heads look like the old Apple error icon. From there, the rest of the game concerns your quest to find a way back to the fabled Outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right away, you’ll notice that this is a beautiful game. The cat animation is very well done, from general movement right down to the little ear twitches, and nearly every environment looks like it could be ripped straight from the concept art. While the plaudits will go to the neon-draped streets, I’m a particular fan of some of the robots’ living quarters, which are stacked high with books and 90s computing equipment. I hope BlueTwelve Studio will find the time to add a photo mode later, because the camera angles, the cat’s poses, and the on-screen prompts obstruct some fantastic frames.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/stray_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically speaking, the bulk of &lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt; consists of simple 3D platforming. With a rough knowledge of where you’re going, you’ll need to scramble up pipes, signs, and air conditioning units to find a path above the city to reach your destination. Sometimes you’ll need to evade snappy little headcrab-like enemies called Zurks, and at others there are simple puzzles that involve rolling barrels around or finding and inserting plugs into computers. Some of my favourites utilised cat-specific mechanics – walking on a keyboard to send a message, or scratching a blind to reveal the window behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-cats-best-friend&quot;&gt;A cat’s best friend&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the scope of the game would be somewhat limited if you spent its entirety alone as a cat. The robots talk to the cat as though it has human-level intelligence, but it can’t speak back, and can only carry small objects. Luckily, fairly early on you meet a robot named B-12 who acts as a conduit between the cat and the world, translating dialogue and grabbing items on your behalf. I won’t go into the reasons in this mostly spoiler-free review, but by the end of the game you could make a strong argument that B-12 is the real main character, and that the whole show exists to tell his story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of said story you’ll see a variety of areas, from slums and sewers to city streets and canals, and – with a little help from B-12 and his superior dexterity – there’s a surprising mechanical variety for a game about a cat. While the game’s bread and butter is the humble item fetch quest – the type where you’ll stumble on the solution if  you just explore the area enough – there are also parts involving fast-paced pursuits, some slightly clunky stealth sections, and even third-person shooter elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/stray_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stray might be fairly simple in terms of gameplay, but its charm and atmosphere pull it through. Although the city is more threatening than the initial natural area, it is still backed by a light, synthwave-style soundtrack that both matches its environs and delivers a relaxing experience that very much feels like you are exploring the city districts with the innocence and curiosity of a cat. This is despite some fairly high stakes in the story, which spans about five hours and has some quite touching moments (quite an achievement when you consider there is no spoken dialogue in the game).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;understandable-limitations&quot;&gt;Understandable limitations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that topic, this is a game by a small studio, and it does show. I’m not as concerned as others about the length of the game – it has a dense enough concentration of detail and quality that it still feels like a good proposition – but there are some elements where it’s clear money had to be saved. For example, whenever a character needs to put on an item of clothing during the story, the screen fades to black and when we return they are magically wearing it. It’s forgivable in the circumstances, but that extra animation or two would have gone a long way to maintain the player’s immersion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt; also doesn’t seem to be incredibly well optimised for PC play. It’s not game breaking – for 95 per cent of my play time performance was flawless, even while exploring some of the more dense and beautiful environments I previously mentioned – but there were certain areas where the frame rate suffered somewhat, even running on &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/07/15/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition-review&quot;&gt;my new 3070 Ti&lt;/a&gt;. It also crashed once fairly early on, although that may have been because I Alt-tabbed to my notes at a time it didn’t like, because thankfully the issue didn’t reoccur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/stray_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s &lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt; in a nutshell. I wouldn’t exactly call it groundbreaking, but BlueTwelve have built a charming, atmospheric, and pretty world for you to lose a few hours in. The game may be a little short for some people’s tastes, but at about a third of the release price of a AAA game, I’m not complaining. &lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt; is enjoyable, original, and a game I might return to as a sort of comfort play once enough time has elapsed for me to have forgotten the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4/5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="platformer" /><summary type="html">Just in case you hadn’t already heard, Stray is a game where you play as a cat. Ever since it was shown off at a PlayStation event in 2020, the internet has been abuzz with talk about it, but mostly from the memey cat angle rather than any discussion of the actual game. Intrigued, I picked up a copy when it was finally released last week so I could find out for myself whether it was a compelling experience or just popular due to its feline protagonist. Into the depths Stray’s opening moments are peaceful. Waking up with your cat buddies, you run as a pack through an overgrown passage, taking their lead as you learn to navigate the environment on four feet. But tragedy strikes and the cat misses a jump, sliding into a pit where you’re unable to reach your pals. You limp through a door and enter a cyberpunk city full of neon and robots whose heads look like the old Apple error icon. From there, the rest of the game concerns your quest to find a way back to the fabled Outside. Right away, you’ll notice that this is a beautiful game. The cat animation is very well done, from general movement right down to the little ear twitches, and nearly every environment looks like it could be ripped straight from the concept art. While the plaudits will go to the neon-draped streets, I’m a particular fan of some of the robots’ living quarters, which are stacked high with books and 90s computing equipment. I hope BlueTwelve Studio will find the time to add a photo mode later, because the camera angles, the cat’s poses, and the on-screen prompts obstruct some fantastic frames.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/stray_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/stray_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Portal 2 (PC) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/22/portal-2-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portal 2 (PC) retrospective" /><published>2022-07-22T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-22T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/22/portal-2-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/22/portal-2-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;There was a time, way back in 2007, when Valve was a company that made video games, and released a little collection called &lt;em&gt;The Orange Box&lt;/em&gt;. Having already completed &lt;em&gt;Half-Life 2&lt;/em&gt; on PC by that point, I had the most fun with a new title tacked onto the end of the compendium named &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt;, which presented a unique blend of the first-person shooter and puzzle genres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; tasks the player with solving various challenges using a portal gun. This tool can fire two portals – orange and blue – which appear as large ovals on the walls. Walk through one and you’ll come out of the other, and the same holds true for various objects you’ll use to complete the levels. This innovative gameplay mechanic, plus some sarcastic, fourth wall-breaking dialogue, earnt &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; a place in many gamers’ hearts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Valve published &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt;, which made many of the era’s “best of” lists, but for one reason or another never joined my game library. Curious, I picked up a copy for the grand sum of £1.43 in a recent Steam sale, in the hope that it still stands up 11 years later. After an eight-hour playthrough of the sequel, I can say that &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; tries to do much more than the original, and while it is successful in some respects, in my view it fails in others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thinking-with-portals&quot;&gt;Thinking with portals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; begins with the player waking up in a room at Aperture Laboratories, and it doesn’t take long for its signature tone to show as we’re instructed to complete our mandatory time staring at a painting on the wall to feel “mentally reinvigorated”. With that complete, we go back to bed, but apparently we sleep for too long because when we wake the dormitory building is ruined and there’s someone pounding on the door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This turns out to be Wheatley, a hapless but well-intentioned floating eye robot voiced by Stephen Merchant. There’s a clever bit here where the game asks us to press A to speak, but that button just makes us jump, which Wheatley points out. Now we’ve familiarised ourselves with the controls and met our new companion, Wheatley rips our bedroom from the building and whisks us off to the main facility for some “emergency testing”.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the test lab, we start working with portals. As in the first &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; game, each puzzle is essentially a self-enclosed cell with an entry and an exit, beyond which there is a lift to reset everything and take us to the next level. Between the player and their escape can lie any combination of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•  &lt;strong&gt;Weighted cubes&lt;/strong&gt; - usually need to be placed on buttons&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Light-refracting cubes&lt;/strong&gt; - can be used to divert lasers to receptors&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Lasers&lt;/strong&gt; - deal damage, but activate devices when pointed the right way&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Turrets&lt;/strong&gt; - monitor for the player and kill them near-instantly on firing&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Gravity rays&lt;/strong&gt; - push and pull objects, including the player&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Various gels and gel dispensers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re getting ahead of ourselves a little here. The first puzzles are relatively simple – initially we’re only allowed to use portals provided to us, and then eventually we’re allowed to fire blue portals. This introductory section was obviously required to bring new players up to speed with the series’ mechanics, but it won’t be too challenging to anyone who played the first game. &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; wants to do more than this, however…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dude-wheres-my-cake&quot;&gt;Dude, where’s my cake?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valve had something of a problem coming into &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt;. The standout character of the original &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; was GLaDOS – the robotic, yet sassy host putting us through all these tests. But we killed her at the end of the game. So to ensure she could return and deliver more of the wisecracks we all love, they contrived a way for the clumsy Wheatley to accidentally flip all her switches, bringing her back to life. She takes us to the heart of the test centre, we get the orange portal gun, and the real fun begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GLaDOS says she wants to test with us forever, but she’s obviously still harbouring some resentment about the whole killing her thing. “Well done,” she says after another completed puzzle. “Here are the test results: You are a horrible person. We weren’t even testing for that.” Wheatley pops in from time to time, telling us he’s working on a way to break us out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, he sets us free through a hatch in the test chamber wall, and we’re dashing through the service passages of the testing facility past production lines manufacturing cubes and turrets, on the run from GLaDOS. It’s neat to use portals in a non-testing environment, although it does come with some difficulties, which I’ll discuss in more detail later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all very fast-paced, but this is where Wheatley started to grate on me a bit. I like Stephen Merchant, and have enjoyed some of his other work – especially his role as Ricky Gervais’s agent in &lt;em&gt;Extras&lt;/em&gt; – but Wheatley just does not stop providing irritating commentary on everything that we do, and it becomes especially annoying when he starts nagging you to get a move on when you’re trying to figure out what the game wants you to do to move to the next area. Admittedly there are some funny jokes in there, but compared to GLaDOS’s cold delivery it’s all a bit overdone and obnoxious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, GLaDOS captures us in a cell, but she uses some faulty turrets we and Wheatley produced, which break the glass. Wheatley shows up and we plug him in and transfer his consciousness into GLaDOS’s body to end her reign over the testing centre. But somewhat predictably, Wheatley is less keen to escape once he realises his newfound power. Instead, he condemns GLaDOS to life inside a potato battery and becomes evermore suspicious of us, eventually punting us both down to the pits of the facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-from-the-past&quot;&gt;Learning from the past&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is probably the best segment of the game in terms of both story and gameplay. We end up in a decrepit Aperture testing facility, which has a &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/bioshock&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-esque vibe with its decaying mid-century furnishings. The voice guiding us through this area is that of Cave Johnson, the founder of Aperture Science. Since he’s dead and can’t be there in person, we are played recordings he prepared for candidates as they reached each test chamber, which feels more akin to the dialogue in the original &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The puzzles are more challenging here, and while they do make use of old-fashioned versions of the modern testing equipment, the historic test centre also has its own tricks up its sleeve. These tricks, it turns out, come mostly in the form of the aforementioned gels and dispensers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•  &lt;strong&gt;Blue gel&lt;/strong&gt; – lets you bounce higher to reach new areas&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Orange gel&lt;/strong&gt; – lets you sprint at super speed and build momentum&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;White gel&lt;/strong&gt; – moon rock-based (remember that), makes surfaces portalable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are used in conjunction with each other to create some great puzzles that really freshen up the formula. By the end of this segment you’ll be placing portals under dispensers to distribute gel where it’s needed before executing elaborate combinations of sprints, jumps, bounces, and portal shots to reach your destination. The most satisfying parts of &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; are those that make you feel super smart for thinking in more than three dimensions to solve a chamber, and these puzzles certainly deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We eventually find GLaDOS in her potato form and begin to make our way through the 70s-era areas, and then those from the 1980s. Along the way we’re met with the “startling” revelation (it’s actually signposted as much, if not more than, Wheatley’s turn to the dark side) that GLaDOS is actually the digitised form of Johnson’s personal assistant Caroline, who was put in charge of the facility when he died. GLaDOS has a vague recollection of this, which serves as her motivation to kill Wheatley and regain control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;taking-back-control&quot;&gt;Taking back control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forming an unlikely partnership, we fight our way to the surface to deal with Wheatley. We find that he’s already making his mark on the test centre, and has apparently been crossbreeding cubes and turrets to produce limping, non-functional offspring. When he learns of our presence he wants to test us, but his chambers are far too easy, so he steals GLaDOS’s designs. This is where the gravity beams come into play, again adding a challenging twist as we now need to try to direct objects – and ourselves – through the air. As the thrill of watching us test wears off, Wheatley grows slowly more insane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For once in a game with an unusual central mechanic, the final boss fight is actually very well done. Wheatley floats around in the middle of the arena and fires missiles at you, which you must send through portals at various angles to circumvent his shields and hit him. GLaDOS throws corrupted cores to you at various intervals, which you attach to Wheatley to gradually weaken him. Once enough of these are connected, we’re directed to press the same “stalemate button” we used to defeat GLaDOS earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the game’s final masterstroke. Wheatley has rigged the button to explode, which damages the testing centre and blows a hole in the roof. There it is, staring right at you: the moon. You remember that the white gel that made surfaces portalable was made of moon rocks, and take a chance. You fire a portal directly at the moon, and the vacuum of space tears Wheatley apart. It’s rare that a game’s final moments are my favourite, but this was a great callback and ups the stakes while so well while maintaining mechanical consistency that it may be the exception to the rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GLaDOS, now in control, pulls us back through the portal as Wheatley spirals off into space. Back on Earth, she decides that the least problematic option is just to let us go. We ascend to the surface past a bizarre choir of dancing turrets (I have no idea how that idea got any further than the brainstorming whiteboard) and step outside into the sunlight. The end credits are set to another song – this time sung by GLaDOS – about how happy she is to finally be rid of us, and we get a final scene of Wheatley drifting through space expressing his remorse before everything fades to black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;straying-from-the-formula&quot;&gt;Straying from the formula&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were parts of &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; I loved, and elements I didn’t see the need for at all. Despite its first-person perspective, Portal is a puzzle game, and it works best when it’s challenging the player to use the tools at their disposal to escape the cell the testing centre has built for them. There’s something immensely satisfying about the Checkoff’s gun-ness of it all – you know everything there must be used, but how? At the game’s strongest it follows an enhanced version of this format, and you’re forced to think not just in portals but also according to the effects of gels and gravity rays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in trying to make &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; bigger and better than its predecessor, Valve had to break it out of that bright white box. Beyond the testing chamber, it’s unclear what’s part of the puzzle and what’s just scenery. The most jarring moments were when the game seemed to be guiding me down a path, only for me to realise after much retreading that it was expecting me to have shot a portal at a tiny grey dot a mile away in the previous area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; is often brought up in “game of the generation” conversations, but honestly I prefer the far more concise and focused original. That said, there are still plenty of enjoyable puzzles in the various testing centres you explore over its eight-hour span, and even if Wheatley gets quite annoying early on, there is a lot of content that subverts the player’s expectations in amusing and surprising ways. If you didn’t play &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; back in 2011 then by all means go back for a playthrough – just don’t expect the earth-shattering experience some talk it up to be, and don’t overlook the original.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="portal" /><category term="puzzle" /><summary type="html">There was a time, way back in 2007, when Valve was a company that made video games, and released a little collection called The Orange Box. Having already completed Half-Life 2 on PC by that point, I had the most fun with a new title tacked onto the end of the compendium named Portal, which presented a unique blend of the first-person shooter and puzzle genres. For the uninitiated, Portal tasks the player with solving various challenges using a portal gun. This tool can fire two portals – orange and blue – which appear as large ovals on the walls. Walk through one and you’ll come out of the other, and the same holds true for various objects you’ll use to complete the levels. This innovative gameplay mechanic, plus some sarcastic, fourth wall-breaking dialogue, earnt Portal a place in many gamers’ hearts. In 2011, Valve published Portal 2, which made many of the era’s “best of” lists, but for one reason or another never joined my game library. Curious, I picked up a copy for the grand sum of £1.43 in a recent Steam sale, in the hope that it still stands up 11 years later. After an eight-hour playthrough of the sequel, I can say that Portal 2 tries to do much more than the original, and while it is successful in some respects, in my view it fails in others. Thinking with portals Portal 2 begins with the player waking up in a room at Aperture Laboratories, and it doesn’t take long for its signature tone to show as we’re instructed to complete our mandatory time staring at a painting on the wall to feel “mentally reinvigorated”. With that complete, we go back to bed, but apparently we sleep for too long because when we wake the dormitory building is ruined and there’s someone pounding on the door. This turns out to be Wheatley, a hapless but well-intentioned floating eye robot voiced by Stephen Merchant. There’s a clever bit here where the game asks us to press A to speak, but that button just makes us jump, which Wheatley points out. Now we’ve familiarised ourselves with the controls and met our new companion, Wheatley rips our bedroom from the building and whisks us off to the main facility for some “emergency testing”.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>