<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-09-23T11:28:08+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Transport Fever 2 review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/30/transport-fever-2-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transport Fever 2 review" /><published>2021-09-22T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-22T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/08/30/transport-fever-2-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/30/transport-fever-2-review">&lt;p&gt;Let’s face the facts: &lt;em&gt;Transport Fever 2&lt;/em&gt; is a lot like &lt;em&gt;Transport Tycoon&lt;/em&gt;. You’re dropped into a map dotted with small towns, resources, and factories and tasked with building the road, rail, sea, and air infrastructure that connects them to help the world’s economy to develop. With the same scenario and toolset, it’s a comparison that would inevitably be drawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a dangerous game for Urban Games to play with the original &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/transport-fever.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transport Fever&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. With &lt;em&gt;Transport Tycoon&lt;/em&gt; so beloved and its upgraded iteration &lt;em&gt;OpenTTD&lt;/em&gt; compatible with modern PCs, anything short of brilliance would be met with indifference. That’s not to mention that this is a fully 3D game. How many classic series have stuttered when moving to the third dimension? I’m looking at you, &lt;em&gt;RollerCoaster Tycoon&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all this in mind, I approached &lt;em&gt;Transport Fever 2&lt;/em&gt; with caution, ready to be let down. But I’m happy to say that I was pleasantly surprised. While this latest outing in the transport management genre is far from perfect, it has provided me with many hours of enjoyment, and - at least in its best moments - can be as satisfying as anything that came before it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-challenge&quot;&gt;The challenge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After selecting a map seed you’re happy with, your new transport company is established, given a loan, and left to link the various cities and industries on a map with passenger and cargo lines. The latter is generally a more reliable income source and can be used to level up cities by providing them with goods they have demand for. However, it also requires complex supply chains - the city requires food, the food factory requires grain, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge lies in doing this while generating a profit. Is it better to focus on passengers or cargo? Should you upgrade your existing line or build a new one? Would a new bus route bring more passengers to the train station? The choices you make - especially in the early game - will be the difference between success and failure.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that sounds a bit simple, it’s also worth noting that the creators over on the Steam Workshop have done a great job with modding the game beyond its vanilla setup. There are all sorts to choose from, but I’d especially recommend Realistic Town Growth, which removes the game’s arbitrary limit on how large any individual town can grow and lets you encourage some huge metropolises to grow by boosting industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there’s plenty of fun to be had with the base game. While the core challenge of building a network and generating a profit is fairly straightforward, committed players will find plenty to occupy themselves with, whether that involves imposing your own limitations, specialising in particular vehicles or industries, encouraging cities to grow in picturesque ways, or efficiently using your infrastructure for multiple lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-toolset&quot;&gt;The toolset&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help you achieve all this, &lt;em&gt;Transport Fever 2&lt;/em&gt; provides tools to build transport networks across four domains: road, rail, sea, and air. Within each category, the tools provided generally include tracks/roads of varying speeds, passenger and cargo stations, vehicle depots, signals, and waypoints (which can be used to direct vehicles to particular places without using stations - useful for implementing one-way systems and the like). These tools are generally reliable and an improvement on previous titles in the genre, although they can be slightly finnicky at times - espcially when it comes to elevation, bridges, and merging different tracks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the infrastructure is down, the next step is to purchase some vehicles. The available vehicles depend on the region you chose when starting the game (Europe, America, or Asia) and the in-game year. Over a span of more than a century, technology will progress from the horse and cart to the latest high-speed trains and aircraft. On purchasing a vehicle, you must assign it to a line, which tells it which stations to visit, which goods to pick up or drop off, how long to wait for a load, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll want to run a test game to start with to figure all this out, as the most efficient ways to solve problems are not always immediately obvious (more on this later). But once you’ve got the hang of it, it can be immensely satisfying to construct and configure complex networks for passengers and goods. Once you’ve got high-speed passenger trains seamlessly sharing lines with assorted cargo trains, you’ll waste plenty of time just sitting back and watching it all work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also worth noting that alongside all the usual tools, the game also gives you close control over progression. While the normal three-speed time control is present, &lt;em&gt;Transport Fever 2&lt;/em&gt; also has a slider for date speed. This means that if, like me, you find the eras pass a bit too quickly, you can slow down the calendar at any time to give you a bit more time to develop your network before you need to upgrade vehicles and infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-difficulty&quot;&gt;The difficulty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is often the case in this genre, the most difficult part of &lt;em&gt;Transport Fever 2&lt;/em&gt; is getting started. Your new transport is automatically granted a $5m loan, and your early decisions will play a huge part in determining whether this investment is used to generate huge profit or send your firm tumbling further into debt. Much of the early game is spent balancing network expansion with loan repayments (which come in $500k increments) and it’s a satisfying moment when your loan debt reaches zero and you know that from there on there is no more interest to pay and all your profit is yours to keep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the midpoint, you’ll find yourself choosing between tactical construction and upgrades. Take that passenger line you built in the 1890s, for example - would it be more profitable to extend it with an extra station or to invest in more modern trains that cater to more passengers and travel more quickly? The bottom toolbar displays a constant counter of how much money you’re making, and you’ll be looking to boost this figure as much as possible to propel yourself into the realm of airports and shinkansen later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The late game is either a cruise or an exercise in firefighting, depending on how much planning you put in earlier on. If you played it smart, this is where you get to play with all the fancy toys like the high-speed planes, aircraft, and container ships. If you were less tactical when building your empire, there’ll probably be a lot of remediation on your plate as your infrastructure groans under the weight of the additional demand of expanding city populations and industry output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the vanilla game with the default difficulty, it’s not exactly difficult to work yourself into a situation where you’re raking in tens of millions per month and are basically free to build whatever you wish. Maybe that sounds like a dream to you if you just want to build to your heart’s content (and the game does also offer a complete sandbox mode with unlimited money), but if you’re looking for a bigger challenge then there’s always hard mode and the aforementioned mods if you want to mix things up for more of a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-vibe&quot;&gt;The vibe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you even get to enjoying the game, prepare for some pretty hefty load times. That may sound like an exaggeration, but seriously, if you want to get a coffee, load up the game first. Although there are no loading screens during the game, the initial one takes so long that I’ve written this paragraph and checked my takeaway delivery status in the time it has taken the game to load in. Seriously, it may even be the longest I’ve ever encountered in a game - and that includes &lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto Online&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll quickly notice that the game is very pretty to look at with a level of detail that is rare for a strategy game. Many of the screenshots included with this review aren’t representative of the zoom level where you’ll spend most of your time, but that’s because the cities look so good at street level and the vehicles are so detailed up close that I needed to show them off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, the game has funky music with some truly jazzy guitar. At its best, it channels something between &lt;em&gt;Sim City 2000&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Better Call Saul&lt;/em&gt;, but over time it can become grating. I say “by default” because I prompty turned it off, but hey, maybe it’s your kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the only other thing to mention is to be prepared to be frustrated from time to time. Electric train won’t leave the depot? It could be that the depot itself is not electrified and must be demolished and rebuilt (and to demolish it, you’ll need to sell your new train). Ship won’t join your new route? There’s an accessibility issue somewhere - maybe the water isn’t deep enough at some points or there’s not a suitable dock - but the game won’t tell you what.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is frequently the case with production, shipment, and transportation metrics when working with industry. A facility will stop producing a certain material and you’ll be left to work backwards to understand why. Months of in-game time and millions of dollars later, it’ll turn out that you accidentally demolished ten metres of road that took a factory out of range of a truck stop. You’ll get used to running these kinds of diagnostics in the end, but it can be very confusing as a new player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-judgement&quot;&gt;The judgement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transport Fever 2&lt;/em&gt; does what many games before it have failed at - transferring a classic 2D game format into 3D while keeping things both practical and aesthetically pleasing. By the time you reach the 21st century, you’ll have constructed a sprawling network of buses, trams, trains, ships, and planes, and the game’s graphics are good enough to let you sit back and admire it like the prettiest of virtual model train sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the systems and tooling is a little rough around the edges. While the complexity of roads and tracks allows for a little leeway on their construction tools, it would be nice if the developers provided the player with more information about why certain lines and industries aren’t working when problems arise. That said, you’ll slowly learn the language of the game and the key things to look out for, so this isn’t a gamebreaker for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you get bored with whatever you’re currently working on, there’s always another line to build, a more challenging map to generate, a new region to try, or a railway spaghetti junction to reconfigure, so running out of content is not a concern - and that’s without mentioning all the mods out there that add new systems, vehicles, and more to keep things fresh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transport Fever 2&lt;/em&gt; lacks some of the charm of &lt;em&gt;Transport Tycoon&lt;/em&gt;, but we’re not talking about the chasm between &lt;em&gt;RollerCoaster Tycoon&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Planet Coaster&lt;/em&gt;. The core gameplay loop that made Chris Sawyer’s classic so addictive is still there. So if you’re looking to scratch that itch, I’d definitely recommend this game - just expect a few minor frustrations along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4/5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="transport-fever" /><category term="management" /><summary type="html">Let’s face the facts: Transport Fever 2 is a lot like Transport Tycoon. You’re dropped into a map dotted with small towns, resources, and factories and tasked with building the road, rail, sea, and air infrastructure that connects them to help the world’s economy to develop. With the same scenario and toolset, it’s a comparison that would inevitably be drawn. This was a dangerous game for Urban Games to play with the original Transport Fever. With Transport Tycoon so beloved and its upgraded iteration OpenTTD compatible with modern PCs, anything short of brilliance would be met with indifference. That’s not to mention that this is a fully 3D game. How many classic series have stuttered when moving to the third dimension? I’m looking at you, RollerCoaster Tycoon. With all this in mind, I approached Transport Fever 2 with caution, ready to be let down. But I’m happy to say that I was pleasantly surprised. While this latest outing in the transport management genre is far from perfect, it has provided me with many hours of enjoyment, and - at least in its best moments - can be as satisfying as anything that came before it. The challenge After selecting a map seed you’re happy with, your new transport company is established, given a loan, and left to link the various cities and industries on a map with passenger and cargo lines. The latter is generally a more reliable income source and can be used to level up cities by providing them with goods they have demand for. However, it also requires complex supply chains - the city requires food, the food factory requires grain, and so on. The challenge lies in doing this while generating a profit. Is it better to focus on passengers or cargo? Should you upgrade your existing line or build a new one? Would a new bus route bring more passengers to the train station? The choices you make - especially in the early game - will be the difference between success and failure.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_4.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_4.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What if Football Manager was a tabletop game?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/07/eleven-football-management-tabletop-game/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What if Football Manager was a tabletop game?" /><published>2021-09-07T18:30:36+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-07T18:30:36+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/07/eleven-football-manager-tabletop-game</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/07/eleven-football-management-tabletop-game/">&lt;p&gt;What if &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/football-manager.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; wasn’t a computer game you play alone in front of a screen until the early hours of the morning, but a physical product you could reach out an touch with your hands? Maybe even an activity you could do - dare I say it - &lt;em&gt;with friends&lt;/em&gt;? No, I hadn’t considered it until now either, but it turns out that’s exactly what &lt;em&gt;Eleven&lt;/em&gt; is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polish developer Portal Games’s football management tabletop &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://gamefound.com/projects/portalgames/eleven-football-manager-board-game&quot;&gt;has just opened for funding on Gamefound&lt;/a&gt;, and at the time of writing it’s sitting pretty at 500 per cent of its funding target (about €150,000) with 19 days remaining. So it seems that while &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; had never thought of playing &lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt; with dice and cards, it’s an experience people are hungry for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/eleven_football_manager.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eleven&lt;/em&gt; describes itself as “an economic strategy board game”, which is an elaborate way of describing a game that lets you roleplay as a football manager. You and up to three friends will be bringing in players, choosing tactics, developing stadiums, signing up sponsors, and all that are typical of the coach-come-CEO role that only exists in gaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The base game comes in at €60, which is &lt;em&gt;fairly&lt;/em&gt; reasonable given the number of pieces it looks like it comes with. What I was surprised at, however, is that the game is already launching with a range of five expansions, all priced at €20, which feels a little bit like the monetisation tactics of a cash-in mobile game, or what Konami is trying to do with &lt;em&gt;eFootball&lt;/em&gt;. I just ordered the Solo Campaign expansion because my friends aren’t really into football so I’ll mainly be playing alone, but if you want everything the game has to offer on release day you’re looking at a €128 outlay (plus postage).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is &lt;em&gt;Eleven&lt;/em&gt; any good? Well, the YouTubers on the campaign page seemed to enjoy their preview copies enough, but of course they would. The rest of us will have to wait a year to find out - the expected release date is September 2022. When it lands on my doorstep I’ll try it out and post a review.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="tabletop" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">What if Football Manager wasn’t a computer game you play alone in front of a screen until the early hours of the morning, but a physical product you could reach out an touch with your hands? Maybe even an activity you could do - dare I say it - with friends? No, I hadn’t considered it until now either, but it turns out that’s exactly what Eleven is. Polish developer Portal Games’s football management tabletop has just opened for funding on Gamefound, and at the time of writing it’s sitting pretty at 500 per cent of its funding target (about €150,000) with 19 days remaining. So it seems that while I had never thought of playing Football Manager with dice and cards, it’s an experience people are hungry for. Eleven describes itself as “an economic strategy board game”, which is an elaborate way of describing a game that lets you roleplay as a football manager. You and up to three friends will be bringing in players, choosing tactics, developing stadiums, signing up sponsors, and all that are typical of the coach-come-CEO role that only exists in gaming. The base game comes in at €60, which is fairly reasonable given the number of pieces it looks like it comes with. What I was surprised at, however, is that the game is already launching with a range of five expansions, all priced at €20, which feels a little bit like the monetisation tactics of a cash-in mobile game, or what Konami is trying to do with eFootball. I just ordered the Solo Campaign expansion because my friends aren’t really into football so I’ll mainly be playing alone, but if you want everything the game has to offer on release day you’re looking at a €128 outlay (plus postage). Is Eleven any good? Well, the YouTubers on the campaign page seemed to enjoy their preview copies enough, but of course they would. The rest of us will have to wait a year to find out - the expected release date is September 2022. When it lands on my doorstep I’ll try it out and post a review.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/eleven_football_manager.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/eleven_football_manager.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Transport Fever 2&amp;amp;colon; What Production, Shipment, and Transport really mean</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/28/transport-fever-2-industry-production-shipment-transport/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transport Fever 2&amp;colon; What Production, Shipment, and Transport really mean" /><published>2021-08-29T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-29T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/08/28/transport-fever-2-industry-production-supply-transport</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/28/transport-fever-2-industry-production-shipment-transport/">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/08/30/transport-fever-2-review&quot;&gt;my &lt;em&gt;Transport Fever 2&lt;/em&gt; review&lt;/a&gt; I wrote about the how the game sometimes frustrates by leaving you guessing as to why a line isn’t working or a factory isn’t producing goods. Three key metrics - Production, Shipment, and Transport - are the root cause of many of these annoying issues, and my goal with this article is to explain exactly what they are to help anyone who is also stuck staring at them and wondering why they won’t increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter which of these figures you’re having trouble with, one key thing to remember is that they can take a little while to ramp up, even when you’ve solved the problem that was holding your industry back. So don’t expect the metrics to shoot up as soon as you make a change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we jump into the nitty gritty of these numbers, a note on factory levels: If you can keep production, shipment, and transport in the section at the right-hand end of the counters, the Level bar will start to move up. When it crosses the next threshold, the factory will expand. It will require more resources, but if supplied with adequate materials it will also produce a greater volume of goods. This can be an effective way of satisfying demand without building additional transportation infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_industry_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;production&quot;&gt;Production&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Production, as the name would suggest, indicates how many units of a certain product a facility is &lt;em&gt;producing&lt;/em&gt;. The food processing plant in the example above produces one food unit for every two units of grain it receives, and is operating at a production level of 190/200.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Counterintuitively, product is driven by supply and not demand. To increase food production to 200, all I would need to do is supply more grain, perhaps by sourcing it from additional farms. This is true regardless of whether there are onward transport links to consumers. For example, if you were to supply a completely isolated food factory with grain, it would pay to receive the materials and produce food - that food would just disappear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shipment&quot;&gt;Shipment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shipment indicates how many units of a particular product are &lt;em&gt;shipped&lt;/em&gt; from the facility. This is reflective of how much demand there is for these goods at the destination city, and is also capped by the current level of production. This complexity makes it slightly more difficult to troubleshoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the screenshot, shipment is 91. Production is 190, so we know it’s not being capped by the input. The city receiving the food is Kobe, and by opening the city dialogue box we can see that its food supply is currently 105/97. This explains our shipment figure - the amount of food required by the destination city is only a fraction of what the factory is able to produce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_industry_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the city demand looks fine, it’s worth checking your transport links. Shipment levels will fall if there is no route from the producing facility to the destination. I once saw oil production and shipment fall off a cliff because I had accidentally deleted a road that made the drop-off truck stop accessible to the refinery. Rebuilding 10m of road saved an entire industry!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;transport&quot;&gt;Transport&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Transport is the percentage of the shipped units that make it to their destination. Ideally, this should always be 100 per cent - if it’s not, you’ve got a problem somewhere along the line holding things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, it’s rare to see a low Transport figure on an established line, and if there were issues then you’d likely have spotted them already because, well, the whole game is about transportation! One scenario that may catch you out, however, is if a factory levels up or a city’s demand increases due to growth and more goods are shipped than the line was originally designed for. In this case, you might need to introduce additional vehicles, or increase the capacity of those that are already running.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="transport-fever" /><category term="management" /><summary type="html">In my Transport Fever 2 review I wrote about the how the game sometimes frustrates by leaving you guessing as to why a line isn’t working or a factory isn’t producing goods. Three key metrics - Production, Shipment, and Transport - are the root cause of many of these annoying issues, and my goal with this article is to explain exactly what they are to help anyone who is also stuck staring at them and wondering why they won’t increase. No matter which of these figures you’re having trouble with, one key thing to remember is that they can take a little while to ramp up, even when you’ve solved the problem that was holding your industry back. So don’t expect the metrics to shoot up as soon as you make a change. Before we jump into the nitty gritty of these numbers, a note on factory levels: If you can keep production, shipment, and transport in the section at the right-hand end of the counters, the Level bar will start to move up. When it crosses the next threshold, the factory will expand. It will require more resources, but if supplied with adequate materials it will also produce a greater volume of goods. This can be an effective way of satisfying demand without building additional transportation infrastructure. Production Production, as the name would suggest, indicates how many units of a certain product a facility is producing. The food processing plant in the example above produces one food unit for every two units of grain it receives, and is operating at a production level of 190/200.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_industry_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_industry_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Visiting Thruxton for BTCC and Formula 4</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/29/btcc-formula-4-thruxton/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visiting Thruxton for BTCC and Formula 4" /><published>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/08/29/btcc-formula-4-thruxton</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/29/btcc-formula-4-thruxton/">&lt;p&gt;With the effect of the COVID-19 pandemic somewhat reduced thanks to the UK’s vaccination programme, I decided to make the most of the last of the summer sun and head down to Thruxton to see some racing, see some family, and generally just do something that didn’t involve sitting in front of my desk or TV all day. I’ve had enough of that since 2020, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/thruxton_1.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Saturday I visited, the main event was qualifying for the British Touring Car Championship, with support series including Formula 4 filling out the programme for the day. This essentially amounted to back-to-back sessions from 9am to past 6pm with the exception of an hour-long lunch break, which I say is pretty good value for the £14 entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thruxton itself is an entirely different circuit to &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/10/26/exploring-brands-hatch-at-the-formula-ford-festival/&quot;&gt;Brands Hatch&lt;/a&gt;. Sitting just outside of Andover, the track forms a large loop around the outside of an airfield. Spectators are permitted along the pit straight, the outside of Turn 1, and up to the Campbell-Cobb chicane, leaving maybe three quarters of the lap that’s only visible in the distance across the field. There are grass verges around all the viewing areas, providing plenty of space to set up camp with good views of the track even on busy days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/thruxton_2.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best viewing was to be had from the two grandstands at the Club chicane. As well as providing the best views of the more remote regions of the circuit, the section of track between Woodham and the chicane itself was host to most of the racing action, including many overtakes and several crashes. On the day I visited, a seat in the grandstand would set you back a reasonable £6, bringing my total admission spend to £20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite Saturday not being the main racing day, the cars on display provided solid entertainment with a few notable incidents. There was a big crash involving several cars at the end of the second Mini Challenge race, and a Formula 4 race was won by a car that controversially took the lead by skipping the chicane on the last lap (&lt;a href=&quot;http://fiaformula4.com/zagazeta-appeal-dismissed-gray-declared-winner-of-round-16/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;which was later penalised&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/thruxton_3.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was particularly interesting to see up close was the way the BTCC cars took some of the kerbs, hitting the strips so aggressively that cars often bounced up onto two wheels temporarily. Watching the race on the TV the next day, the commentators mentioned that this was discouraged by the tyre manufacturers and may have been responsible for some of the failures we saw, but it certainly added to the spectacle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I’d say Thruxton was definitely worth the trip. The circuit doesn’t give you as many viewing angles as Brands Hatch and doesn’t feel quite so “interactive”, but the track - and in particular the Club chicane - certainly made for some exciting racing and provided an enjoyable and affordable day out. I’ll absolutely be visiting again at some point in future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="motorsport" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="formula-4" /><summary type="html">With the effect of the COVID-19 pandemic somewhat reduced thanks to the UK’s vaccination programme, I decided to make the most of the last of the summer sun and head down to Thruxton to see some racing, see some family, and generally just do something that didn’t involve sitting in front of my desk or TV all day. I’ve had enough of that since 2020, after all. On the Saturday I visited, the main event was qualifying for the British Touring Car Championship, with support series including Formula 4 filling out the programme for the day. This essentially amounted to back-to-back sessions from 9am to past 6pm with the exception of an hour-long lunch break, which I say is pretty good value for the £14 entry. Thruxton itself is an entirely different circuit to Brands Hatch. Sitting just outside of Andover, the track forms a large loop around the outside of an airfield. Spectators are permitted along the pit straight, the outside of Turn 1, and up to the Campbell-Cobb chicane, leaving maybe three quarters of the lap that’s only visible in the distance across the field. There are grass verges around all the viewing areas, providing plenty of space to set up camp with good views of the track even on busy days. The best viewing was to be had from the two grandstands at the Club chicane. As well as providing the best views of the more remote regions of the circuit, the section of track between Woodham and the chicane itself was host to most of the racing action, including many overtakes and several crashes. On the day I visited, a seat in the grandstand would set you back a reasonable £6, bringing my total admission spend to £20. Despite Saturday not being the main racing day, the cars on display provided solid entertainment with a few notable incidents. There was a big crash involving several cars at the end of the second Mini Challenge race, and a Formula 4 race was won by a car that controversially took the lead by skipping the chicane on the last lap (which was later penalised). What was particularly interesting to see up close was the way the BTCC cars took some of the kerbs, hitting the strips so aggressively that cars often bounced up onto two wheels temporarily. Watching the race on the TV the next day, the commentators mentioned that this was discouraged by the tyre manufacturers and may have been responsible for some of the failures we saw, but it certainly added to the spectacle. All in all, I’d say Thruxton was definitely worth the trip. The circuit doesn’t give you as many viewing angles as Brands Hatch and doesn’t feel quite so “interactive”, but the track - and in particular the Club chicane - certainly made for some exciting racing and provided an enjoyable and affordable day out. I’ll absolutely be visiting again at some point in future.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/thruxton_1.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/thruxton_1.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Transport Fever 2&amp;amp;colon; How to fix a broken shipping line</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/28/transport-fever-2-broken-shipping-line/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transport Fever 2&amp;colon; How to fix a broken shipping line" /><published>2021-08-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/08/28/transport-fever-2-broken-shipping-line</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/28/transport-fever-2-broken-shipping-line/">&lt;p&gt;If you’ve read &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/08/30/transport-fever-2-review&quot;&gt;my review of &lt;em&gt;Transport Fever 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll know that one of the most frustrating parts of the game is when there’s a problem but it doesn’t tell you what’s wrong or how to fix it. And none of these is more frustrating than when you find yourself unable to assign a ship to a new sea line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chances are if you’ve stumbled across this article, you’ve been presented with the an error when trying to put the infrastructure in place to transport passengers or cargo across water. The messages vary, but will usually say something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_shipping_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Unable to find path to stop (no path for big ships). A path has been found, but only small ships are allowed on this path. Consider using small ships or large docks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This caused a fair bit of confusion when I first encountered it. What was this mysterious issue? Over time, I’ve found that this error can be caused by any of the following factors…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-waters-are-not-navigable&quot;&gt;The waters are not navigable&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the solution can be as simple as checking that the water along your route is deep enough for the ship to travel through. That said, despite my initial suspicions, I don’t think this will often be the issue. After some testing, is appears that the game considers any depth at all navigable, even if I create an artifical, jagged seabed sits just below the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to double-check is to use the Navigable Waters layer. Click the layers button in the top left and choose the icon that looks like waves. The game will colour all water that ships can travel through green, and this will help you to identify any trouble spots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theres-a-bridge-in-the-way&quot;&gt;There’s a bridge in the way&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Low road and rail bridges can also present an obstruction to ships. Again, the easiest way to check this is by using the Navigable Waters layer. If your bridge has a blue area around it, you’ll need to demolish it and reconstruct it at a greater height in order to allow ships to pass underneath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_shipping_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theres-no-suitable-dock&quot;&gt;There’s no suitable dock&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final reason why your route might be failing, and the one that caught me out first time round, is if you don’t have suitable docks at your ports for your ship to arrive and depart from. Ships come in two flavours in &lt;em&gt;Transport Fever 2&lt;/em&gt; - large and small - and there are docks to match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add a large dock for your large ship, click on the port, choose Configure, and select the large dock under either Passenger or Cargo. Place the dock, and then switch to the Landing tab and add the appropriate landing next to the dock. This should look something like the image below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_shipping_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, make sure that your line is now using the correct landing. Open the Line Manager, look at the relevant port’s entry in the route, and click on the waves with the dock number next to them. Use the dropdown to select your new large dock and youi should be good to go!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="transport-fever" /><category term="management" /><summary type="html">If you’ve read my review of Transport Fever 2, you’ll know that one of the most frustrating parts of the game is when there’s a problem but it doesn’t tell you what’s wrong or how to fix it. And none of these is more frustrating than when you find yourself unable to assign a ship to a new sea line. Chances are if you’ve stumbled across this article, you’ve been presented with the an error when trying to put the infrastructure in place to transport passengers or cargo across water. The messages vary, but will usually say something like this: “Unable to find path to stop (no path for big ships). A path has been found, but only small ships are allowed on this path. Consider using small ships or large docks.” This caused a fair bit of confusion when I first encountered it. What was this mysterious issue? Over time, I’ve found that this error can be caused by any of the following factors… The waters are not navigable Sometimes the solution can be as simple as checking that the water along your route is deep enough for the ship to travel through. That said, despite my initial suspicions, I don’t think this will often be the issue. After some testing, is appears that the game considers any depth at all navigable, even if I create an artifical, jagged seabed sits just below the surface. The easiest way to double-check is to use the Navigable Waters layer. Click the layers button in the top left and choose the icon that looks like waves. The game will colour all water that ships can travel through green, and this will help you to identify any trouble spots. There’s a bridge in the way Low road and rail bridges can also present an obstruction to ships. Again, the easiest way to check this is by using the Navigable Waters layer. If your bridge has a blue area around it, you’ll need to demolish it and reconstruct it at a greater height in order to allow ships to pass underneath. There’s no suitable dock The final reason why your route might be failing, and the one that caught me out first time round, is if you don’t have suitable docks at your ports for your ship to arrive and depart from. Ships come in two flavours in Transport Fever 2 - large and small - and there are docks to match. To add a large dock for your large ship, click on the port, choose Configure, and select the large dock under either Passenger or Cargo. Place the dock, and then switch to the Landing tab and add the appropriate landing next to the dock. This should look something like the image below. Finally, make sure that your line is now using the correct landing. Open the Line Manager, look at the relevant port’s entry in the route, and click on the waves with the dock number next to them. Use the dropdown to select your new large dock and youi should be good to go!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_shipping_3.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/tf2_shipping_3.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Motorsport Manager review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/27/motorsport-manager-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Motorsport Manager review" /><published>2021-08-27T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-27T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/08/27/motorsport-manager-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/27/motorsport-manager-review">&lt;p&gt;I’m a little off the pace with &lt;em&gt;Motorsport Manager&lt;/em&gt;. Playsport Games’ Formula 1 management game (it’s unlicensed and includes other series, but that’s basically what it is) was first released on mobile in 2014, before moving to PC in 2016. It frequently pops up in Steam sales and Humble Bundles, but despite having a copy sitting in my library for years, it’s only now, a full five years since it came out, that I’ve actually gotten around to playing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/motorsport_manager_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a big Formula 1 fan, I was both quite excited to get going and somewhat skeptical. Motorsport is about much more than on-track racing, but even the flagship Codemasters &lt;em&gt;F1&lt;/em&gt; series gets the strategic side of things horribly wrong, forcing the player to make suboptimal decisions to ensure the AI stay competitive - especially when the weather changes. Would a small studio fare any better in this area? The answer, as we’ll see in this article, is yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’re wondering about the screenshots, there are some great mods out there for this game. The one I’m using is called Formula 1 Manager 2021, and adds all the teams and drivers for the current season, as well as real life media personalities, sponsors, team principals, and even designers and mechanics. Since the game always starts in 2016, this can lead to some funny situations. For example, my team TSP Racing scouted and signed Yuki Tsunoda when he was just 14 years old in-game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-challenge&quot;&gt;The challenge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably don’t need me to tell you how motorsport works, but just in case… &lt;em&gt;Motorsport Manager&lt;/em&gt; puts you in the shoes of the team principal of a racing team (existing or new). Said team competes in a series of race weekends over the course of each season, and your job is to try to win races and - ultimately - the drivers’ and constructors’ championships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/motorsport_manager_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, you must recruit and/or develop the best drivers, design new parts for your cars and improve their performance and reliability, recruit and organise your pit crew, sign up sponsors and keep them happy, and slowly expand your team’s HQ, all while balancing the books, keeping the team owner happy, and making those all-important strategy calls at the track. Basically, think &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/football-manager.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; but for Formula 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-toolset&quot;&gt;The toolset&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you achieve all this? Off the track, one of your major activities will be developing the car. There are two main ways to do this, and the first is to develop new parts. To make things interesting you must choose from a series of perks and tradeoffs - for example, a certain type of new front wing might make the car better at slow corners, but reduce its reliability. Some parts also employ a creative interpretation of the governing body’s rules, which adds a risk of penalties if discovered during post-race scrutineering. The second way to improve the car is to improve existing parts, asking your team to boost their performance and reliability within set limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your other administrative duties include staff management. Drivers, race mechanics, and designers are all fairly detailed, with various skill ratings and perks - for example, a particular designer might reduce the number of days it takes to develop parts. Then there’s the pit crew, who all have ratings across the different pit stop roles. Your responsibilities here are hiring and firing to improve the quality of the crew, and rotating team members in and out between races, balancing ability with fatigue to reduce the risk of time-consuming mistakes during pit stops that could cost you positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/motorsport_manager_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there are the commercials. You must balance car development, staff expenditure, HQ development, and other running costs with income. What’s an F1 team’s main revenue source? Sponsorship. Different companies will approach you with offers to slap their logos on your car, each offering varying initial and per-race payments for the privilege. The game here is to consider the money offered against the length of the contracts. If you expect to rapidly improve your team’s standing (and therefore marketability), you might not want to lock a sponsor in on a low-paying multi-year deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the most important part of &lt;em&gt;Motorsport Manager&lt;/em&gt; is what happens on track. Your race weekend will begin with a practice session. By running practice programmes, you can earn knowledge perks (Hard Tyres Level 1, Race Trim Level 3, etc.) to equip during later sessions. The other half of this is car setup, where there are three metrics - downforce, handling, and speed balance - that can be indirectly affected by adjusting various parts. You begin with a vague window for each area recommended by the mechanic, and your drivers provide feedback after each stint to narrow this range and allow you to improve the balance ready for the rest of the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qualifying and the race are much more about executing and adjusting your strategy as conditions change and events unfold. You’ll go into each session with an idea of how to manage your limited sets of tyres and fuel (you do this by telling your drivers when to change engine modes and drive more or less aggressively). But as in real F1, this can all change at the drop of a hat. Sudden changes to the weather, crashes bringing out the safety car, and component failures can all force you to think quickly about the right next move. The catch with the weather is that unlike real teams, your weather radar only shows conditions a few laps into the future. When you get it wrong it your race can be instantly ruined, but gaining positions by telling your drivers to conserve those softs long enough to switch to inters &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; as the first drops of rain start to fall is immensely satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/motorsport_manager_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other interesting mechanic is regular voting on rule changes. You and the other team principals will periodically vote on potential rule changes for the following season, and from time to time the president himself will ask if you’d like to propose a change yourself… for a fee. Proposals include things like longer or shorter sessions, reintroducing refuelling, awarding points for qualifying, and reverse grid races. These all have pros and cons for different teams with different strengths and weaknesses, which makes the vote an interesting political mini-game. The rule modifications themselves are also a nice mechanic for making each season different and preventing your team from becoming too comfortable later in the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-difficulty&quot;&gt;The difficulty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you start a new team like I did, you’ll begin at the back of the grid - &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; at the back. You are a new Haas behind Haas. Your team HQ is a shed, your drivers don’t deserve their seats in the world’s premier motorsport series, and not only are all your car parts low-spec stock components, but they’ll also have terrible reliability, frequently setting back your progress mid-race when you need to spend crucial seconds repairing them during pit stops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that note, you better be patient, because in the early game you will lose &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt;. For at least the first half of your first season, the only time you’ll finish above 19th is when other drivers crash out. It’s just not possible to gain and retain places in an awful car that adds 30 seconds or more to every pit stop for repairs. This makes it slightly difficult to get into a rhythm with the game initially, but it really makes you appreciate those moments when your strategy propels one of your cars into Q2 or snatches 15th place in a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/motorsport_manager_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, it doesn’t take &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; long to make some significant improvements to your team. By the latter stages of the first season I was already developing Average parts, had signed Tsunoda, and had a couple of top ten finishes under my belt (albeit in topsy-turvy races). However, modest improvements like these and winning championships are two different matters entirely, so don’t expect to be lifting any silverware in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, you’ll fare better in &lt;em&gt;Motorsport Manager&lt;/em&gt; if you watch real life racing. Team management and car development is fairly standard fare for a strategy game, but come race weekend there’s certain knowledge that will really help. What kind of programmes do teams run during practice sessions? Is it better to start the race on hard or soft tyres? Should we pit when the safety car comes out? Although you could work some of this out in-game, knowing what real teams would typically do will serve you well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a note on the AI, which is actually probably the best I’ve seen in a racing game for strategy. It is unphased by rapid weather changes, and it actually outshines the big-budget Codemasters &lt;em&gt;F1&lt;/em&gt; series both in this respect and in terms of strategic variance between AI teams. Opposing strategists also sometimes look rather far ahead on the weather radar - at one point I scoffed when Red Bull put Perez on wets when everyone else was coming off of inters, but a couple of laps later it bucketed it down. Intelligent stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-vibe&quot;&gt;The vibe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this adds up to an experience that feels more like a tabletop game based on Formula 1 than a motorsport simulation, but for the most part this is balanced in a way that feels pretty natural. Maybe there are some players who would like to spend hours poring over practice session telemetry in a &lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;-esque way to construct intricate setups, but representing knowledge gained from practice stints via driver feedback, and perks for the qualifying and race, works well and helps to keep the action moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/motorsport_manager_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the game for you if you’re hungry for on-track action. Strategy is the name of the game here, and the cars don’t race realistically, instead adopting slot car-like lines when in close proximity. The satisfaction to be gained from &lt;em&gt;Motorsport Manager&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t come from the amazing overtaking moves you’d expect in a game like &lt;em&gt;Assetto Corsa&lt;/em&gt;, it comes from managing pace, tyres, and part condition over the course of the race to push your drivers as high up the field as possible in the face of changing conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tone of the game is also greatly improved by the colourful emails, media stories, and social media posts that pop up between sessions and races. This effect is amplified with the F1 2021 mod, and frequently raised a smile when Martin Brundle reported that Wolff and Horner have been at it again, a fan berated Haas’s performances on Twitter, or Jean Todt reprimanded TSP Racing for disgracing the sport by running an illegal rear wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-judgement&quot;&gt;The judgement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Motorsport Manager&lt;/em&gt;’s complexity and difficulty curve makes it hard to recommend unconditionally. You certainly need to sink a lot of time into the game before you’re familiar enough with the systems to know whether you’re enjoying yourself or not. That said, with the game so often discounted it’s not a massive risk to take, and there’s certainly a lot of love for the little details of Formula 1 here that fans will appreciate regardless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I think your enjoyment of &lt;em&gt;Motorport Manager&lt;/em&gt; will depend on what type of motorsport fan you are. If you’re part of the new generation of F1 fans that Liberty Media has been courting, one of those who lives for 15-second Instagram videos of crashes and angry radio messages, there’s not much here for you. If you’re what the Super League’s attempted founders would call a “legacy fan”, you’ll likely find great enjoyment in all the intricacies of resource management and stategy on offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4/5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="motorsport-manager" /><category term="racing" /><summary type="html">I’m a little off the pace with Motorsport Manager. Playsport Games’ Formula 1 management game (it’s unlicensed and includes other series, but that’s basically what it is) was first released on mobile in 2014, before moving to PC in 2016. It frequently pops up in Steam sales and Humble Bundles, but despite having a copy sitting in my library for years, it’s only now, a full five years since it came out, that I’ve actually gotten around to playing it. As a big Formula 1 fan, I was both quite excited to get going and somewhat skeptical. Motorsport is about much more than on-track racing, but even the flagship Codemasters F1 series gets the strategic side of things horribly wrong, forcing the player to make suboptimal decisions to ensure the AI stay competitive - especially when the weather changes. Would a small studio fare any better in this area? The answer, as we’ll see in this article, is yes. In case you’re wondering about the screenshots, there are some great mods out there for this game. The one I’m using is called Formula 1 Manager 2021, and adds all the teams and drivers for the current season, as well as real life media personalities, sponsors, team principals, and even designers and mechanics. Since the game always starts in 2016, this can lead to some funny situations. For example, my team TSP Racing scouted and signed Yuki Tsunoda when he was just 14 years old in-game. The challenge You probably don’t need me to tell you how motorsport works, but just in case… Motorsport Manager puts you in the shoes of the team principal of a racing team (existing or new). Said team competes in a series of race weekends over the course of each season, and your job is to try to win races and - ultimately - the drivers’ and constructors’ championships. To do this, you must recruit and/or develop the best drivers, design new parts for your cars and improve their performance and reliability, recruit and organise your pit crew, sign up sponsors and keep them happy, and slowly expand your team’s HQ, all while balancing the books, keeping the team owner happy, and making those all-important strategy calls at the track. Basically, think Football Manager but for Formula 1. The toolset How do you achieve all this? Off the track, one of your major activities will be developing the car. There are two main ways to do this, and the first is to develop new parts. To make things interesting you must choose from a series of perks and tradeoffs - for example, a certain type of new front wing might make the car better at slow corners, but reduce its reliability. Some parts also employ a creative interpretation of the governing body’s rules, which adds a risk of penalties if discovered during post-race scrutineering. The second way to improve the car is to improve existing parts, asking your team to boost their performance and reliability within set limits. Your other administrative duties include staff management. Drivers, race mechanics, and designers are all fairly detailed, with various skill ratings and perks - for example, a particular designer might reduce the number of days it takes to develop parts. Then there’s the pit crew, who all have ratings across the different pit stop roles. Your responsibilities here are hiring and firing to improve the quality of the crew, and rotating team members in and out between races, balancing ability with fatigue to reduce the risk of time-consuming mistakes during pit stops that could cost you positions. Then there are the commercials. You must balance car development, staff expenditure, HQ development, and other running costs with income. What’s an F1 team’s main revenue source? Sponsorship. Different companies will approach you with offers to slap their logos on your car, each offering varying initial and per-race payments for the privilege. The game here is to consider the money offered against the length of the contracts. If you expect to rapidly improve your team’s standing (and therefore marketability), you might not want to lock a sponsor in on a low-paying multi-year deal. Of course, the most important part of Motorsport Manager is what happens on track. Your race weekend will begin with a practice session. By running practice programmes, you can earn knowledge perks (Hard Tyres Level 1, Race Trim Level 3, etc.) to equip during later sessions. The other half of this is car setup, where there are three metrics - downforce, handling, and speed balance - that can be indirectly affected by adjusting various parts. You begin with a vague window for each area recommended by the mechanic, and your drivers provide feedback after each stint to narrow this range and allow you to improve the balance ready for the rest of the weekend. Qualifying and the race are much more about executing and adjusting your strategy as conditions change and events unfold. You’ll go into each session with an idea of how to manage your limited sets of tyres and fuel (you do this by telling your drivers when to change engine modes and drive more or less aggressively). But as in real F1, this can all change at the drop of a hat. Sudden changes to the weather, crashes bringing out the safety car, and component failures can all force you to think quickly about the right next move. The catch with the weather is that unlike real teams, your weather radar only shows conditions a few laps into the future. When you get it wrong it your race can be instantly ruined, but gaining positions by telling your drivers to conserve those softs long enough to switch to inters just as the first drops of rain start to fall is immensely satisfying. One other interesting mechanic is regular voting on rule changes. You and the other team principals will periodically vote on potential rule changes for the following season, and from time to time the president himself will ask if you’d like to propose a change yourself… for a fee. Proposals include things like longer or shorter sessions, reintroducing refuelling, awarding points for qualifying, and reverse grid races. These all have pros and cons for different teams with different strengths and weaknesses, which makes the vote an interesting political mini-game. The rule modifications themselves are also a nice mechanic for making each season different and preventing your team from becoming too comfortable later in the game. The difficulty If you start a new team like I did, you’ll begin at the back of the grid - way at the back. You are a new Haas behind Haas. Your team HQ is a shed, your drivers don’t deserve their seats in the world’s premier motorsport series, and not only are all your car parts low-spec stock components, but they’ll also have terrible reliability, frequently setting back your progress mid-race when you need to spend crucial seconds repairing them during pit stops. On that note, you better be patient, because in the early game you will lose a lot. For at least the first half of your first season, the only time you’ll finish above 19th is when other drivers crash out. It’s just not possible to gain and retain places in an awful car that adds 30 seconds or more to every pit stop for repairs. This makes it slightly difficult to get into a rhythm with the game initially, but it really makes you appreciate those moments when your strategy propels one of your cars into Q2 or snatches 15th place in a race. That said, it doesn’t take too long to make some significant improvements to your team. By the latter stages of the first season I was already developing Average parts, had signed Tsunoda, and had a couple of top ten finishes under my belt (albeit in topsy-turvy races). However, modest improvements like these and winning championships are two different matters entirely, so don’t expect to be lifting any silverware in the near future. In general, you’ll fare better in Motorsport Manager if you watch real life racing. Team management and car development is fairly standard fare for a strategy game, but come race weekend there’s certain knowledge that will really help. What kind of programmes do teams run during practice sessions? Is it better to start the race on hard or soft tyres? Should we pit when the safety car comes out? Although you could work some of this out in-game, knowing what real teams would typically do will serve you well. Also a note on the AI, which is actually probably the best I’ve seen in a racing game for strategy. It is unphased by rapid weather changes, and it actually outshines the big-budget Codemasters F1 series both in this respect and in terms of strategic variance between AI teams. Opposing strategists also sometimes look rather far ahead on the weather radar - at one point I scoffed when Red Bull put Perez on wets when everyone else was coming off of inters, but a couple of laps later it bucketed it down. Intelligent stuff. The vibe All of this adds up to an experience that feels more like a tabletop game based on Formula 1 than a motorsport simulation, but for the most part this is balanced in a way that feels pretty natural. Maybe there are some players who would like to spend hours poring over practice session telemetry in a Football Manager-esque way to construct intricate setups, but representing knowledge gained from practice stints via driver feedback, and perks for the qualifying and race, works well and helps to keep the action moving. This is not the game for you if you’re hungry for on-track action. Strategy is the name of the game here, and the cars don’t race realistically, instead adopting slot car-like lines when in close proximity. The satisfaction to be gained from Motorsport Manager doesn’t come from the amazing overtaking moves you’d expect in a game like Assetto Corsa, it comes from managing pace, tyres, and part condition over the course of the race to push your drivers as high up the field as possible in the face of changing conditions. The tone of the game is also greatly improved by the colourful emails, media stories, and social media posts that pop up between sessions and races. This effect is amplified with the F1 2021 mod, and frequently raised a smile when Martin Brundle reported that Wolff and Horner have been at it again, a fan berated Haas’s performances on Twitter, or Jean Todt reprimanded TSP Racing for disgracing the sport by running an illegal rear wing. The judgement Motorsport Manager’s complexity and difficulty curve makes it hard to recommend unconditionally. You certainly need to sink a lot of time into the game before you’re familiar enough with the systems to know whether you’re enjoying yourself or not. That said, with the game so often discounted it’s not a massive risk to take, and there’s certainly a lot of love for the little details of Formula 1 here that fans will appreciate regardless. All in all, I think your enjoyment of Motorport Manager will depend on what type of motorsport fan you are. If you’re part of the new generation of F1 fans that Liberty Media has been courting, one of those who lives for 15-second Instagram videos of crashes and angry radio messages, there’s not much here for you. If you’re what the Super League’s attempted founders would call a “legacy fan”, you’ll likely find great enjoyment in all the intricacies of resource management and stategy on offer. 4/5</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/motorsport_manager_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/motorsport_manager_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Gran Turismo 7 could be the racing game I’ve been waiting for</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/21/gran-turismo-7-campaign-mode/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gran Turismo 7 could be the racing game I've been waiting for" /><published>2021-08-20T18:30:36+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-20T18:30:36+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/21/looking-forward-gran-turismo-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/21/gran-turismo-7-campaign-mode/">&lt;p&gt;Remember the Sony PlayStation 5 games showcase in June 2020? I wouldn’t be surprised if the combination of a next-gen console launch and pandemic lockdowns meant it had the biggest ever audience for such an event. It seemed to go on forever and featured dozens of new games, but in amongst them all there was one that stood out above the rest: &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/gran_turismo_7_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the day, I played the first three &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/gran-turismo.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; games to death. There was something addictive about starting with a miniscule number of credits and buying a bland street car, only to slowly juice it up, swap it out for sexier models, and win a lot of races along the way. It was kind of like the motorsport equivalent of a &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/football-manager.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; journeyman save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the PS2/Xbox generation I switched to the green team. Over the next decade the excellent early entries in the &lt;em&gt;Forza Motorsport&lt;/em&gt; series provided me with my racing fix, but there was still some niche itch instilled by &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; that &lt;em&gt;Forza&lt;/em&gt; just couldn’t scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the PlayStation 4 came around I switched back, and one of the things I was most excited about was a new next-gen &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; game. So I waited… and waited, and waited… and it never came. Sure, we got &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo Sport&lt;/em&gt;, which had the cars, tracks, and handling, but its multiplayer-first focus and the lack of a single-player campaign meant it had nothing to offer me that &lt;em&gt;Assetto Corsa&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/project-cars.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project CARS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; couldn’t provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why during the &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; announcement trailer, it wasn’t the shiny next-gen cars or on-track action that got me excited for a new entry in the series - it was a flash of this screen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/gran_turismo_7_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forget the fact that Sarah looks like one of those annoying marketing bots that asks if you need assistance on companies’ websites - campaign mode is back! And with &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; set to be released on both PS4 and PS5, I won’t need to buy an expensive (and elusive) new console to play it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as a glimpse of some competitions and tracks, we were also briefly shown the Tuning Shop, providing confirmation that you’ll still be able to craft your starter Honda Civic into a racing machine capable of challenging ever stronger opponents in the mode’s racing series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/gran_turismo_7_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game has since been delayed to 2022, but to be honest at this point it’s probably the upcoming release that I’m most excited about, so I can deal with that. It’s quite rare these days that I buy a game at full price on release, but this could be one of those occasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More hardcore simulators like &lt;em&gt;Assetto Corsa&lt;/em&gt; (or &lt;em&gt;iRacing&lt;/em&gt; for those with stacked wallets and too much time) are where the real racing is at, but they demand full concentration, and sometimes I want a game that sits nicely between arcade and simulation that I can throw on at the end of a busy work day and relax with, with just a little more depth than something like &lt;em&gt;Need for Speed&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;GRID&lt;/em&gt;. I’m hoping &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; can be that game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;UPDATE: We got another peek at&lt;/em&gt; Gran Turismo 7 &lt;em&gt;on the most recent PlayStation Showcase, which only got me more excited about this game! Brief glimpses were shown of some more Career Mode screens, but more than anything the new trailer showed off just how pretty the cars are (at least on PS5). The release is now slated for March 2022 and I can’t wait!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="gran-turismo" /><category term="racing" /><summary type="html">Remember the Sony PlayStation 5 games showcase in June 2020? I wouldn’t be surprised if the combination of a next-gen console launch and pandemic lockdowns meant it had the biggest ever audience for such an event. It seemed to go on forever and featured dozens of new games, but in amongst them all there was one that stood out above the rest: Gran Turismo 7. Back in the day, I played the first three Gran Turismo games to death. There was something addictive about starting with a miniscule number of credits and buying a bland street car, only to slowly juice it up, swap it out for sexier models, and win a lot of races along the way. It was kind of like the motorsport equivalent of a Football Manager journeyman save. During the PS2/Xbox generation I switched to the green team. Over the next decade the excellent early entries in the Forza Motorsport series provided me with my racing fix, but there was still some niche itch instilled by Gran Turismo that Forza just couldn’t scratch. When the PlayStation 4 came around I switched back, and one of the things I was most excited about was a new next-gen Gran Turismo game. So I waited… and waited, and waited… and it never came. Sure, we got Gran Turismo Sport, which had the cars, tracks, and handling, but its multiplayer-first focus and the lack of a single-player campaign meant it had nothing to offer me that Assetto Corsa or Project CARS couldn’t provide. That’s why during the Gran Turismo 7 announcement trailer, it wasn’t the shiny next-gen cars or on-track action that got me excited for a new entry in the series - it was a flash of this screen: Forget the fact that Sarah looks like one of those annoying marketing bots that asks if you need assistance on companies’ websites - campaign mode is back! And with Gran Turismo 7 set to be released on both PS4 and PS5, I won’t need to buy an expensive (and elusive) new console to play it! As well as a glimpse of some competitions and tracks, we were also briefly shown the Tuning Shop, providing confirmation that you’ll still be able to craft your starter Honda Civic into a racing machine capable of challenging ever stronger opponents in the mode’s racing series. The game has since been delayed to 2022, but to be honest at this point it’s probably the upcoming release that I’m most excited about, so I can deal with that. It’s quite rare these days that I buy a game at full price on release, but this could be one of those occasions. More hardcore simulators like Assetto Corsa (or iRacing for those with stacked wallets and too much time) are where the real racing is at, but they demand full concentration, and sometimes I want a game that sits nicely between arcade and simulation that I can throw on at the end of a busy work day and relax with, with just a little more depth than something like Need for Speed or GRID. I’m hoping Gran Turismo 7 can be that game. UPDATE: We got another peek at Gran Turismo 7 on the most recent PlayStation Showcase, which only got me more excited about this game! Brief glimpses were shown of some more Career Mode screens, but more than anything the new trailer showed off just how pretty the cars are (at least on PS5). The release is now slated for March 2022 and I can’t wait!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/gran_turismo_7_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/gran_turismo_7_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">PES 5 Master League retrospective ‐ balancing realism and gameplay</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PES 5 Master League retrospective &amp;#8208; balancing realism and gameplay" /><published>2021-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pro Evolution Soccer 5&lt;/em&gt; has always been an all-time favourite of mine, but it is only now, 15 years after its initial release, that I have found the inspiration to do it justice in words. Of course, there are many reviews out there from 2005 that cover its gameplay, features, and so on, but in this post I have attempted to capture what made it so perfectly balanced and special to many fans. I hope that at the very least this will stir up some nostalgia that inspire others to dig out their copies for a match or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/pes-5-1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like everyone else, I didn’t have a normal Christmas holiday this year. In my efforts to stave off boredom in the gap between Christmas and the new year, I installed an emulator and grabbed a copy of &lt;em&gt;Pro Evolution Soccer 5&lt;/em&gt; to play. I wasted a huge number of hours playing this game as a teenager, and wanted to see how it held up 15 years and three console generations later. To my surprise, I once again became addicted, and played Master League matches on a daily basis for the rest of the break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some nostalgia involved here, of course – both for the game and the 2005/06 football season – but there are so many things that should have driven me away: the graphics are rough round the edges, the game mechanics are unrefined, and the emulator stutters and occasionally refuses to let me run right until I reconnect my controller. With all these inconveniences, what kept me playing? And why didn’t I fire up my PlayStation 4 or PC and play one of the football games from 2020 instead?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the answer says a lot about design, both in football games and video games in general. I’d always considered &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt;, or more generally the period between &lt;em&gt;Pro Evolution Soccer 4&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Pro Evolution Soccer 6&lt;/em&gt; on PlayStation 2 and Xbox, to be a high tide mark for football games. But even with this in mind when playing more modern games, I could never really pinpoint why. Returning to &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt; in 2020 with fresh eyes has given me the perspective I needed to put this X factor into words.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-i-the-master-league&quot;&gt;Part I: The Master League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons for &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt;’s superiority lie both on and off the pitch. I’ll begin with the latter, which I believe is a masterstroke that is key to the game’s overall addictiveness. The Master League is Konami’s answer to FIFA’s Career Mode – a multi-season campaign that puts the player in charge of a club with financial responsibilities and the freedom to make transfers. However, there are some important differences that lean away from realism and integrate systems more often seen in other video game genres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/pes-5-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-sense-of-ownership&quot;&gt;A sense of ownership&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first important difference is that the Master League’s focus is on the club, not the manager’s career. The player can either select or create a team at the beginning of the Master League, and cannot switch to another team at any point. If they choose the latter option, they choose the team’s name, design kits (which integrate with the game world better than similar features in other games due to the range of design options and general lack of licences), and select other attributes like a stadium and crowd colours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “real” way to play the Master League is to begin with the default squad, rather than the team’s real-life players. This team, which includes fictional players like Castolo, Minanda, Stremer, and Ivarov, is largely useless in terms of ability. They take touches metres ahead of themselves, hit shots wildly off-target unless directly facing the goal at walking pace, and are outmuscled by even the smallest opponents. This means there is a natural siege mentality for the first couple of seasons, and scraping a point feels like a victory. Unlike &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt;, where selecting Chelsea will mean Champions League matches in your first year in charge, it is not even possible to reach continental competition in the Master League until at least the third season, and even that is unlikely given the players initially at your disposal. This adds to the sense of progression as the player – and by extension their club – earns their place in the footballing world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/pes-5-3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this means the player has a far greater sense of ownership than they do in other games’ career modes, where they can take over a successful team of competent players assembled by a real-world manager. This is your club, and as the seasons progress and you slowly bring in talent during the transfer windows, each player in the squad reflects a decision you have made. It’s less realistic, but makes for a far more engaging game – something that will become a recurring theme through this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-football-rpg&quot;&gt;A football RPG&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This culminates in a mode structured more like a football role-playing game (RPG) than a sports game. The squad is akin the player’s party, the matches are battles, and the time between is spent managing resources and organising the party in a way that increases the success rate, including keeping track of players’ development and signing new personnel where required. To help them on their way, &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt; tracks and makes available quite a bit more data than even the most recent football games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/pes-5-4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important aspect of this is that transfers are straightforward, and are far more about affordability than negotiation, which is rarely done well in games. In this respect, the player’s focus is always on their points balance (more on that later) and earning enough to upgrade. They aren’t forced to sit through lengthy office cut scenes, playing a guessing game with an inconsistent AI to agree on a price, and being unable to sign the best players even in the cash-rich end game because of their value to their current clubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scouting players to sign is also more rewarding than in modern &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt;. Players in both current games have an Overall rating, which often reduces comparison to a single statistic and makes choosing between two players, whether for a transfer or a starting position, a one-dimensional affair. &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt; does not have this statistic, and the player must instead scan each player’s full attributes to gain an impression of their ability. Overlapping star diagrams like the one pictured above allow the player to directly compare six attributes when switching players, sometimes forcing an informed decision – for example, do I choose a full-back who is pacey and attacking, or powerful and defensive? It also helps that the full list of attributes is smaller than in modern games, making it easier to review them in full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/pes-5-5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exaggerated speed and visibility with which these attributes improve also adds to the RPG-like sense of narrative and progression. After each match, the player is taken to a screen where progression points for each attribute stack up for the players that took to the pitch, and it’s hugely satisfying to see your signings’ attributes increase. It’s difficult to compare them exactly, but I believe the progression in &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt; is also quicker than in games like the modern &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; series, where a player will join with an Overall rating in the 50s and take a decade to reach full potential. Once again, this is a compromise on realism for the sake of gameplay, increasing the investment that the player has in their squad and club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;extreme-focus&quot;&gt;Extreme focus&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most important part of the Master League, and I believe has been lost in every current career mode, is the fact that it keeps the player extremely focused on a simple task: survival and development. There is no fan sentiment to monitor, no board waiting to sack you, and no possibility of a move to another club. It’s you and your created team against the world, and if they fail, you may be forced to start another game (something that once happened to me, when I foolishly signed Steven Pienaar and saved myself into a corner, ensuring bankruptcy). The risk level is comparable to that of classic arcade games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points are the currency in PES 5, and the only number that matters is your bank account balance. You earn points by getting results: 1,000 for a win and 500 for a draw, with bonus points for each goal scored. Your players are paid an annual salary, and if you don’t have enough points to cover the wage bill at the end of the season, it’s game over. Any leftover funds can be used to sign new players, leading to something of a gamble on a mental risk-reward calculation when signing players during the mid-season transfer window – will the added talent be enough to secure the results necessary to pay the wages at the end of the season? Or will your ambition be the cause of your downfall?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/pes-5-6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus on points and the wage bill adds real tension to the Master League, which is something that isn’t recreated in career modes with separate wage budgets. The stakes of each individual match are raised – especially towards the end of a subpar season – and while the board won’t be on your back for being knocked out of the cup, the number of matches and therefore your chance of winning points is reduced. This can lead to an intense scramble to scrape results in the last few fixtures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The points system also has the added effect of tying Master League difficulty directly to match difficulty. A greater challenge on the pitch means a lower chance of amassing points and signing star players. As a result, the focus is always on the football and never on dialogue trees, objectives, or working out how to please unseen and unpredictable parties that could cut your tenure short. This makes sense in the big picture, because no &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; game will ever be &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/01/25/football-manager-addictive-spreadsheet/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so they shouldn’t try to be. Perhaps the Master League economy is a byproduct of development limitations, but accidental or not, it is a beautifully concise system that could be discussed alongside some of history’s best gameplay loops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-ii-core-gameplay&quot;&gt;Part II: Core gameplay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what of the gameplay on the pitch, where the player spends most of their time? I remember marvelling at the realism of &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt; back in 2005, but in retrospect it is nothing of the sort. Quick passes fly about effortlessly, players’ movements follow robotic paths, and pinball-like deflections between bodies produce some truly comedic spells of play. These issues may have been the due to the hardware of the time – there’s only so much Konami could do with physics and AI on a PlayStation 2, after all - but these compromises in the representation of real-life football also serve to make the game more fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/pes-5-7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-beautiful-game&quot;&gt;The beautiful game&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No football game before &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt; – and arguably no game since – flows as fantastically as Konami’s masterpiece. Its gameplay mechanics are designed for fast, end-to-end action, with passes pinging between players with pinpoint accuracy, but ball control that is heavy enough that any attempt to break into a packed penalty area carries a real risk of losing possession without creating an opportunity. This means shooting from distance is just as viable an option, and it is possible to score some real 30-yard screamers with the more talented players of the time like Frank Lampard and Steven Gerrard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game’s attacking balance is unmatched – you’re just as likely to score or miss with a long shot, a run through the middle, or a cross into the box – and this variety is catalysed by the aforementioned element of randomness. All those different shot types, deflections, mistakes, and rebounds add an organic unpredictability that means that even after hundreds of hours of play, players still see new situations emerge. This stops attacking and defending, even against the AI, from falling into the predictable patterns seen in many football games (like some &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; editions’ six-yard box square-pass-and-shoot goals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ai-and-momentum&quot;&gt;AI and momentum&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also worth taking a moment to discuss the AI, which you’ll be seeing a lot of if you choose to play the Master League mode. Simply put, &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt;’s AI is a bigger challenge than any modern football game’s equivalent. Three seasons into my new campaign, I was just about winning consistently on four stars, and that still left me with the five-star mode (and the six-star mode, unlockable via the PES Shop) to take on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe a lack of predictability is again what makes the AI work so well – it seems to have a random element, and also encounters all the scraps and deflections that you do, which stops the player from learning that opponents will always pass in a certain direction or pattern. Perhaps this generation of football games was also slightly easier to develop AI for, in that the game engine itself was simpler, and there were fewer mechanics for the AI to have to interpret and choose between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt; matches also benefit from being left to run their course naturally. In 2021, football game forums are rife with complaints about alleged “momentum” mechanics – the idea that the game “wants” a certain result for entertainment value, and makes a losing team more likely to score a last-minute equaliser or pits a dominant player’s championship challengers against a team fighting relegation who seem to gain superhuman powers if the player has won too many matches recently. While I remember reading some initial murmurings about momentum at the time, &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt; seems to largely let the game flow, free from artficial drama. The bulk of the “momentum” you’ll find here is in the commentary (particularly from Trevor Brooking, who seems obsessed with the word, especially following goals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/pes-5-10.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;party-on-the-pitch&quot;&gt;Party on the pitch&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier, I discussed the Master League mode’s RPG-like elements, and these are also present as you take to the pitch, with the game adjusting noticeably to players’ attributes and engineering situations for them to take effect. Starting a player with less fatigue and better form is often more beneficial than starting a jaded superstar, and some abilities like the famous lofted through ball are essentially locked off until you have skilled enough players. These limitations initially led me to believe the game was much more basic than I remembered when I first picked it up, but as I acquired more talented players and began to see the effects on the pitch, I began to realise that this was just another facet of its complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a similar way, a game of &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt; includes several subtle, and sometimes slightly frustrating, gameplay features that digress from real football in the name of playability. Low-skill players take huge touches when controlling even the simplest pass, for example, and players almost always stumble when tackled, making it impossible to instantly win the ball back. This also seems to be the reason for one of the most often criticised occurrences, when the ball will occasionally pass through a player’s leg. This was criticised and branded unrealistic at the time – particularly by fans of the rival &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; series – but it’s really Konami rolling the D20 once more, and the attacker’s ability and luck totalling more than the defender’s (or vice versa). It can be visually jarring, but it’s the kind of nuanced feature that keeps the game flowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;straightforward-set-pieces&quot;&gt;Straightforward set pieces&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever a new iteration of a football game is at the drawing board, the developers need to make a decision on set pieces, and in the 2000s we saw a huge variety of systems employed. In my opinion, &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt; strikes the balance better than any, again bringing player attributes to the forefront. Rather than a complicated system of giant arrows, ball contact diagrams, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cGd5qVouoCY&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;stop-the-slider mini games&lt;/a&gt;, Konami gave us three means of influencing free kicks: the initial angle, a power bar, and the application of curl with the D-pad. The result leaves the player feeling far more connected to the action – free kicks are fast, direct, and satisfying when they hit the top corner, and (as is the case with all good game design) when the player fails, they always feel as though they might do better next time with a slight change of technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Penalties benefit from being even more straightforward. Both the player and the goalkeeper select one of nine directions – that’s it. No power bar, no stuttering run-ups or star jumps on the line, and no fancy chips down the centre. What happens next is a combination of luck and player attributes – even if the goalkeeper dives the right way, they might not keep the shot out if their skills don’t match the striker’s, and the taker always stands a chance of hitting the post or missing entirely. The way the outcome is calculated feels fair, balanced, and in sync with the rest of the match engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/pes-5-9.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;an-imperfect-masterpiece&quot;&gt;An imperfect masterpiece&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this isn’t to say that &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt;’s interpretation of football is perfect. Referees in particular could have used some refinement. After noticing them constantly blowing for soft fouls, sometimes nowhere near the ball, I initially held back on tackling, fearing that I’d gather bookings just as easily. But despite being massively strict on minor infringements, they seem to have no sense of whether a foul was committed by the last man. A deliberate but minor foul on a player through on goal will usually yield no card – the AI does it to me, I do it to the AI, and it essentially becomes another fair gameplay tactic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advantage rule is also massively inconsistent, and is something modern football games undoubtedly do better. The main issue here is that the period that the referee plays advantage for tends to be very short. If an opposing player fouls my attacker and the ball happens to fall to his strike partner, the advantage icon disappears almost as soon as he controls it, meaning no free kick is awarded even if he is being tightly marked and is immediately dispossessed. There are also many times where the referee stops play when playing on would have given the attacking team a chance on goal. The advantage rule was a feature introduced in &lt;em&gt;PES 3&lt;/em&gt;, but even two editions later it was in desperate need of improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, despite the flowing gameplay and organic deflections, the players themselves aren’t always the quickest to react to unexpected passages of play. Generally this isn’t an issue, but it can be frustrating to see a deflected clearance apparently fall into your star forward’s path, only for him to refuse to approach the ball, letting a more distant defender get there first and clean up the mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-iii-the-future-of-gaming&quot;&gt;Part III: The future of gaming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what does this analysis of a 15-year-old football game tell us about video games more broadly? I think the key message is that a compromise between realism and gameplay, which used to be forced upon developers by the PlayStation 2’s limited hardware, is essential to creating a more playable game. The conversation around sports games always seems to be around which title more closely resembles the real game, but perhaps the focus would be better placed on which is more fun instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this post has examined &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt;, the same is true of games in other genres. Looking at another Konami series, &lt;em&gt;Metal Gear Solid&lt;/em&gt; evolved in a similar way. &lt;em&gt;Metal Gear Solid 2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;3&lt;/em&gt; were arguably the series’ peak, when gameplay was constrained to small areas that presented controlled, isolated challenges, and a large amount of effort was spent adding colour, story, and character. Fast forward to &lt;em&gt;Metal Gear Solid 5&lt;/em&gt; and emphasis is squarely on open-world gameplay, with few cut scenes and little memorable dialogue. Anybody from the mid-2000s would be stunned at the gameplay features, but the game loses its focus, both thematically and in terms of the gameplay – there are any number of situations the developers did not account for where the player can engineer situations that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uxjnMR2CupA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;confuse the AI&lt;/a&gt;, either exposing bugs (and breaking immersion) or lowering the difficulty. It is a game in desperate need of focus, both in terms of the player experience and where development time was allocated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gameplay-over-realism&quot;&gt;Gameplay over realism&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A niche more commonly explored by mid-level and indie developers is the game that has fairly simple mechanics (or at least features that have been relatively stable for years) and modern graphics. This section of the gaming market is wide-ranging, but I would point to examples like &lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;, the rebooted &lt;em&gt;Hitman series&lt;/em&gt;, and the modern &lt;em&gt;Wolfenstein&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Doom&lt;/em&gt; games. These games follow almost the same core gameplay formula that similar titles did 15 years ago, but the developers have used the extra power at their disposal to make them prettier, refine mechanics, and improve their AI, rather than adding additional complexity unnecessarily or targeting hyperrealism at the expense of player enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the football genre in particular, I suspect there are many disenfranchised players out there who like me would jump at the chance to play a game similar to the classic &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; titles, but with minor improvements (for example, updated graphics, better referees, and more consistent player control) rather than additional features that increase realism but make the game more of a chore to play (slower, heavier gameplay; player complaints and conversations, press conferences and negotiation cut scenes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; has improved somewhat during the PS4/Xbox One generation, but it definitely isn’t as fast or addictive as it was previously, and the Master League has been diluted massively in pursuit of &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt;’s Career Mode. With the focus on cash-generating online services like FIFA Ultimate Team and MyClub, gameplay has remained relatively consistent for a while now, but perhaps there’s a small developer out there that could make take a chance on a simpler, more arcadey title that resembles a refined classic &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until then, I’m hooked once more on the classic &lt;em&gt;Pro Evolution Soccer&lt;/em&gt; formula, and at least for the foreseeable future, &lt;em&gt;PES 5&lt;/em&gt; is going to remain my football game of choice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="pro-evolution-soccer" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">Pro Evolution Soccer 5 has always been an all-time favourite of mine, but it is only now, 15 years after its initial release, that I have found the inspiration to do it justice in words. Of course, there are many reviews out there from 2005 that cover its gameplay, features, and so on, but in this post I have attempted to capture what made it so perfectly balanced and special to many fans. I hope that at the very least this will stir up some nostalgia that inspire others to dig out their copies for a match or two. Like everyone else, I didn’t have a normal Christmas holiday this year. In my efforts to stave off boredom in the gap between Christmas and the new year, I installed an emulator and grabbed a copy of Pro Evolution Soccer 5 to play. I wasted a huge number of hours playing this game as a teenager, and wanted to see how it held up 15 years and three console generations later. To my surprise, I once again became addicted, and played Master League matches on a daily basis for the rest of the break. There is some nostalgia involved here, of course – both for the game and the 2005/06 football season – but there are so many things that should have driven me away: the graphics are rough round the edges, the game mechanics are unrefined, and the emulator stutters and occasionally refuses to let me run right until I reconnect my controller. With all these inconveniences, what kept me playing? And why didn’t I fire up my PlayStation 4 or PC and play one of the football games from 2020 instead? I believe the answer says a lot about design, both in football games and video games in general. I’d always considered PES 5, or more generally the period between Pro Evolution Soccer 4 and Pro Evolution Soccer 6 on PlayStation 2 and Xbox, to be a high tide mark for football games. But even with this in mind when playing more modern games, I could never really pinpoint why. Returning to PES 5 in 2020 with fresh eyes has given me the perspective I needed to put this X factor into words.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/pes-5-1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/pes-5-1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Football Manager is the most addictive spreadsheet ever designed</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/25/football-manager-addictive-spreadsheet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Football Manager is the most addictive spreadsheet ever designed" /><published>2019-01-25T17:30:36+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-25T17:30:36+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/25/football-manager-addictive-spreadsheet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/25/football-manager-addictive-spreadsheet/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/football-manager.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This month’s off-topic post delves into the world of &lt;em&gt;Football Manager &lt;/em&gt;– a game I’ve found myself playing again in the last couple of weeks. Here I attempt to explain why the much-loved series has always been greater than the sum of its parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve previously read even a couple of posts on this blog you’ll be well aware that I’m quite into data analysis and manipulation. It should come as no surprise, then, that I’m currently engrossed in a game that’s little more than a glorified spreadsheet. That’s right – I’m back into &lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-history-infootball-manager&quot;&gt;A history in &lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were others before it, but the first football management game I really clicked with was &lt;em&gt;Football Manager 2006&lt;/em&gt;. I was given the game for Christmas in 2005 and can remember spending the following days and weeks managing my team while eating the chocolate I’d received and listening to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=04m2zffCX_w&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Franz Ferdinand’s &lt;em&gt;You Could Have It So Much Better&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. A small group of my school friends were enamoured with the game and we’d trade tactics and stories at any opportunity we were given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At university one of my flatmates was obsessed with &lt;em&gt;Football Manager 2011&lt;/em&gt;. Any time he was home I could hear the music coming from his room, where he’d prop the door open and settle in for long sessions guiding a non-league club to glory. I’d occasionally play a little bit myself – I think I had the 2008 or 2009 edition at that point – but the amassing pressures of exams, job hunting, and the world of work (and, let’s be honest, the more dip-in, dip-out gameplay of &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt;) meant _FM _took a back seat.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That continued until 2017, when I had a lot of free time with little money to go out and do things. When I saw &lt;em&gt;Football Manager 2017&lt;/em&gt; on offer on Steam I picked it up and sank many hours into a save that saw my Bournemouth side make the Champions League places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On starting a new job, I once again abandoned the game until I spotted it in my library and sped through a couple of seasons at the redeveloped Bournemouth Stadium. While I might not be able to sink the hours I used to into the game, I’ve certainly caught the bug again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/fm2017-1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/fm2017-1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ingredients-for-success&quot;&gt;Ingredients for success&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game has changed somewhat over the years as features have come and gone, but there are some key, ever-present elements that make the _Football Manager _series as engrossing as it is for fans, despite the fact that it’s basically a spreadsheet of teams and footballers wrapped up in a nice GUI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. The stats&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Seasoned players pride themselves on knowing not the content of the database, but &lt;em&gt;how to read it&lt;/em&gt;. Your scout’s perception of a player’s ability might be way off &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.passion4fm.com/how-to-find-best-scouts-football-manager/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;if he’s got poor judgement&lt;/a&gt;, and your £15 million wonderkid might be destined for a life on the bench &lt;a href=&quot;https://fminside.net/youth-development-internal-factors/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;if you can’t boost his determination&lt;/a&gt;. The mystery around reading the game is only heightened by the fact that Sports Interactive has never fully revealed what goes on under the hood to decide who wins and who loses on the pitch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. The unpredictability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Your job is never done in &lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;. All those numbers working behind the scenes can turn your title winners into mid-table fodder or your relegation battlers into giant killers quicker than you might think. There’s always another challenge to take on and another crisis to deal with – usually a key player deciding he wants to leave for Bayern Munich just a few hours before the end of the transfer window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. The narratives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Probably the biggest factor in this list. Whether it’s your own managerial career, the rise of your current club, or a player’s development &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.guidetofm.com/squad/development&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;from hot prospect to key player&lt;/a&gt;, the storylines that emerge in every _Football Manager _save are what keeps fans hooked. The effect is compounded by the small details the developers drop in here and there – when the in-game journalists ask questions about landmark appearances, for example. Some players even report &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.footballmanagerblog.org/2014/04/how-to-get-son-in-football-manager-2014.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;taking on their own sons as youth recruits&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. The community&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From my group of school friends 14 years ago to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/footballmanagergames/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;the meme-happy &lt;em&gt;Football Manager &lt;/em&gt;subreddit&lt;/a&gt; today, the most fun you’ll have with the game is sharing stories and arguing about what makes the game tick. It is possible to play a network game of &lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;, but the real value the internet adds is the expanded community of players. The tales, challenges, and debates are what keep people coming back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/fm2017-2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/fm2017-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few games out there that pay off in the long run like _Football Manager _does when you stick with a club, mould it to your vision, and bring through your own generation of players. And the summary screen above is only the tip of the iceberg of data on your reign for you to dig through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these factors combined are what makes _Football Manager _more than the sum of its parts, and definitely more than the database the whole game is built on. Hopefully all of this sounds familiar to anyone who has played the series, and I hope I’ve also done a good enough job to explain the game to people who have never really understood what all the fuss is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But no, I won’t tell you how many hours I’ve logged on &lt;em&gt;Football Manager 2017&lt;/em&gt; on my Steam account.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="football-manager" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">This month’s off-topic post delves into the world of Football Manager – a game I’ve found myself playing again in the last couple of weeks. Here I attempt to explain why the much-loved series has always been greater than the sum of its parts. If you’ve previously read even a couple of posts on this blog you’ll be well aware that I’m quite into data analysis and manipulation. It should come as no surprise, then, that I’m currently engrossed in a game that’s little more than a glorified spreadsheet. That’s right – I’m back into Football Manager. A history in Football Manager There were others before it, but the first football management game I really clicked with was Football Manager 2006. I was given the game for Christmas in 2005 and can remember spending the following days and weeks managing my team while eating the chocolate I’d received and listening to Franz Ferdinand’s You Could Have It So Much Better. A small group of my school friends were enamoured with the game and we’d trade tactics and stories at any opportunity we were given. At university one of my flatmates was obsessed with Football Manager 2011. Any time he was home I could hear the music coming from his room, where he’d prop the door open and settle in for long sessions guiding a non-league club to glory. I’d occasionally play a little bit myself – I think I had the 2008 or 2009 edition at that point – but the amassing pressures of exams, job hunting, and the world of work (and, let’s be honest, the more dip-in, dip-out gameplay of FIFA) meant _FM _took a back seat.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/football-manager.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/football-manager.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring Brands Hatch at the Formula Ford Festival</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/10/26/exploring-brands-hatch-at-the-formula-ford-festival/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring Brands Hatch at the Formula Ford Festival" /><published>2018-10-26T18:00:46+01:00</published><updated>2018-10-26T18:00:46+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/10/26/exploring-brands-hatch-at-the-formula-ford-festival-2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/10/26/exploring-brands-hatch-at-the-formula-ford-festival/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/brandshatch7.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been meaning to visit Brands Hatch for a long time, so since I’d just passed my GCFE exam I thought I’d head down to Kent for a relaxing day of racing at the Formula Ford Festival.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that hit me is how modern the facilities at Brands Hatch look. I’d expected an experience similar to my local football club, but from the moment I stepped off the bus it was clear the management hadn’t been skimping on maintenance, with signage that looked almost brand new. Even the bathrooms were clean and modern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing that stood out on seeing the circuit in the flesh for the first time was the large change in elevation over the course of the lap. Brands Hatch essentially spans two hills and the valley between them, and from the Paddock Hill Grandstand (which was free to sit in on the day I attended) you could see almost every inch, from Druids to Clark Curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/brandshatch4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, it was a bright autumn day, and having squinted into the sun from Paddock Hill for a while I went to try some different viewpoints. You’re able to roam pretty much wherever you like at Brands Hatch, and through the day I wandered practically the entire track, watching from Paddock Hill Bend, Hailwoods Hill, and Clearways at various points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite place of them all, however, was the inside track at Druids. By standing right on the inside of the curve you can get a great up-close look at the cars and see the fine detail of some of the on-track battles. There’s also a tree stump that makes a great spot to sit and watch the cars speed up Hailwoods Hill, under the bridge, and towards the hairpin. You can look in any direction for a different view and see most of the circuit without moving, making it possible to track interesting tussles as cars head down to Graham Hill Bend.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Brands Hatch itself was an interesting, modern, and often picturesque venue, but what about the actual racing? It was… actually better than I was probably expecting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Formula Ford, which has served as a stepping stone for big Formula 1 names like Jenson Button, features open-wheeled, wingless cars that can reach speeds of 130mph. I attended the Saturday running of the annual Formula Ford Festival, for which several qualifying sessions and races were scheduled, along with sessions involving a few other classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The action was back-to-back throughout the day, meaning there was always something to watch. During the morning qualifying sessions I was still familiarising myself with the circuit, watching from different perspectives and taking some photos. For the afternoon, I settled in inside of the track at Druids and really started to focus on the racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the inside of the hairpin I saw some nice, neat passes executed up close – especially during a particularly close race that saw the top four runners separated by a fraction of a second for the full 15 laps. Fans weren’t disappointed in terms of incidents, either, with a few scrapes, several cars stuck in the gravel, and a couple of rather odd comings together: one between a frontrunner and back marker under blue flags, and one when the safety car was deployed and several drivers collided as the cars bunched up behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/brandshatch3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this was made all the more enthralling by the fact that I was so close to the action. You can hear the squeal of the tyres, smell the fumes, and see the rear right wheel of the cars struggle to cling to the tarmac as they take the downhill right of Paddock Hill Bend. Even after several hours sitting and watching the racing, you just can’t take your eyes off it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll definitely be returning to Brands Hatch – when it can be comfortably reached within an hour from London Victoria, it’s too close not to – but my day at the Formula Ford Festival has also whet my appetite for live racing. We’re about to head into the winter break, but come 2019 I can see myself travelling around the UK to visit a few more circuits…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="motorsport" /><category term="formula-ford" /><summary type="html">I’ve been meaning to visit Brands Hatch for a long time, so since I’d just passed my GCFE exam I thought I’d head down to Kent for a relaxing day of racing at the Formula Ford Festival.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/brandshatch7.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/brandshatch7.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>