<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-07-22T18:59:22+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Portal 2 (PC) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/22/portal-2-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portal 2 (PC) retrospective" /><published>2022-07-22T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-22T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/22/portal-2-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/22/portal-2-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;There was a time, way back in 2007, when Valve was a company that made video games, and released a little collection called &lt;em&gt;The Orange Box&lt;/em&gt;. Having already completed &lt;em&gt;Half-Life 2&lt;/em&gt; on PC by that point, I had the most fun with a new title tacked onto the end of the compendium named &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt;, which presented a unique blend of the first-person shooter and puzzle genres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; tasks the player with solving various challenges using a portal gun. This tool can fire two portals – orange and blue – which appear as large ovals on the walls. Walk through one and you’ll come out of the other, and the same holds true for various objects you’ll use to complete the levels. This innovative gameplay mechanic, plus some sarcastic, fourth wall-breaking dialogue, earnt &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; a place in many gamers’ hearts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Valve published &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt;, which made many of the era’s “best of” lists, but for one reason or another never joined my game library. Curious, I picked up a copy for the grand sum of £1.43 in a recent Steam sale, in the hope that it still stands up 11 years later. After an eight-hour playthrough of the sequel, I can say that &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; tries to do much more than the original, and while it is successful in some respects, in my view it fails in others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thinking-with-portals&quot;&gt;Thinking with portals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; begins with the player waking up in a room at Aperture Laboratories, and it doesn’t take long for its signature tone to show as we’re instructed to complete our mandatory time staring at a painting on the wall to feel “mentally reinvigorated”. With that complete, we go back to bed, but apparently we sleep for too long because when we wake the dormitory building is ruined and there’s someone pounding on the door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This turns out to be Wheatley, a hapless but well-intentioned floating eye robot voiced by Stephen Merchant. There’s a clever bit here where the game asks us to press A to speak, but that button just makes us jump, which Wheatley points out. Now we’ve familiarised ourselves with the controls and met our new companion, Wheatley rips our bedroom from the building and whisks us off to the main facility for some “emergency testing”.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the test lab, we start working with portals. As in the first &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; game, each puzzle is essentially a self-enclosed cell with an entry and an exit, beyond which there is a lift to reset everything and take us to the next level. Between the player and their escape can lie any combination of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•  &lt;strong&gt;Weighted cubes&lt;/strong&gt; - usually need to be placed on buttons&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Light-refracting cubes&lt;/strong&gt; - can be used to divert lasers to receptors&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Lasers&lt;/strong&gt; - deal damage, but activate devices when pointed the right way&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Turrets&lt;/strong&gt; - monitor for the player and kill them near-instantly on firing&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Gravity rays&lt;/strong&gt; - push and pull objects, including the player&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Various gels and gel dispensers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re getting ahead of ourselves a little here. The first puzzles are relatively simple – initially we’re only allowed to use portals provided to us, and then eventually we’re allowed to fire blue portals. This introductory section was obviously required to bring new players up to speed with the series’ mechanics, but it won’t be too challenging to anyone who played the first game. &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; wants to do more than this, however…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dude-wheres-my-cake&quot;&gt;Dude, where’s my cake?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valve had something of a problem coming into &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt;. The standout character of the original &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; was GLaDOS – the robotic, yet sassy host putting us through all these tests. But we killed her at the end of the game. So to ensure she could return and deliver more of the wisecracks we all love, they contrived a way for the clumsy Wheatley to accidentally flip all her switches, bringing her back to life. She takes us to the heart of the test centre, we get the orange portal gun, and the real fun begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GLaDOS says she wants to test with us forever, but she’s obviously still harbouring some resentment about the whole killing her thing. “Well done,” she says after another completed puzzle. “Here are the test results: You are a horrible person. We weren’t even testing for that.” Wheatley pops in from time to time, telling us he’s working on a way to break us out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, he sets us free through a hatch in the test chamber wall, and we’re dashing through the service passages of the testing facility past production lines manufacturing cubes and turrets, on the run from GLaDOS. It’s neat to use portals in a non-testing environment, although it does come with some difficulties, which I’ll discuss in more detail later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all very fast-paced, but this is where Wheatley started to grate on me a bit. I like Stephen Merchant, and have enjoyed some of his other work – especially his role as Ricky Gervais’s agent in &lt;em&gt;Extras&lt;/em&gt; – but Wheatley just does not stop providing irritating commentary on everything that we do, and it becomes especially annoying when he starts nagging you to get a move on when you’re trying to figure out what the game wants you to do to move to the next area. Admittedly there are some funny jokes in there, but compared to GLaDOS’s cold delivery it’s all a bit overdone and obnoxious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, GLaDOS captures us in a cell, but she uses some faulty turrets we and Wheatley produced, which break the glass. Wheatley shows up and we plug him in and transfer his consciousness into GLaDOS’s body to end her reign over the testing centre. But somewhat predictably, Wheatley is less keen to escape once he realises his newfound power. Instead, he condemns GLaDOS to life inside a potato battery and becomes evermore suspicious of us, eventually punting us both down to the pits of the facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-from-the-past&quot;&gt;Learning from the past&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is probably the best segment of the game in terms of both story and gameplay. We end up in a decrepit Aperture testing facility, which has a &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/bioshock&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-esque vibe with its decaying mid-century furnishings. The voice guiding us through this area is that of Cave Johnson, the founder of Aperture Science. Since he’s dead and can’t be there in person, we are played recordings he prepared for candidates as they reached each test chamber, which feels more akin to the dialogue in the original &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The puzzles are more challenging here, and while they do make use of old-fashioned versions of the modern testing equipment, the historic test centre also has its own tricks up its sleeve. These tricks, it turns out, come mostly in the form of the aforementioned gels and dispensers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•  &lt;strong&gt;Blue gel&lt;/strong&gt; – lets you bounce higher to reach new areas&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Orange gel&lt;/strong&gt; – lets you sprint at super speed and build momentum&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;White gel&lt;/strong&gt; – moon rock-based (remember that), makes surfaces portalable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are used in conjunction with each other to create some great puzzles that really freshen up the formula. By the end of this segment you’ll be placing portals under dispensers to distribute gel where it’s needed before executing elaborate combinations of sprints, jumps, bounces, and portal shots to reach your destination. The most satisfying parts of &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; are those that make you feel super smart for thinking in more than three dimensions to solve a chamber, and these puzzles certainly deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We eventually find GLaDOS in her potato form and begin to make our way through the 70s-era areas, and then those from the 1980s. Along the way we’re met with the “startling” revelation (it’s actually signposted as much, if not more than, Wheatley’s turn to the dark side) that GLaDOS is actually the digitised form of Johnson’s personal assistant Caroline, who was put in charge of the facility when he died. GLaDOS has a vague recollection of this, which serves as her motivation to kill Wheatley and regain control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;taking-back-control&quot;&gt;Taking back control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forming an unlikely partnership, we fight our way to the surface to deal with Wheatley. We find that he’s already making his mark on the test centre, and has apparently been crossbreeding cubes and turrets to produce limping, non-functional offspring. When he learns of our presence he wants to test us, but his chambers are far too easy, so he steals GLaDOS’s designs. This is where the gravity beams come into play, again adding a challenging twist as we now need to try to direct objects – and ourselves – through the air. As the thrill of watching us test wears off, Wheatley grows slowly more insane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For once in a game with an unusual central mechanic, the final boss fight is actually very well done. Wheatley floats around in the middle of the arena and fires missiles at you, which you must send through portals at various angles to circumvent his shields and hit him. GLaDOS throws corrupted cores to you at various intervals, which you attach to Wheatley to gradually weaken him. Once enough of these are connected, we’re directed to press the same “stalemate button” we used to defeat GLaDOS earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the game’s final masterstroke. Wheatley has rigged the button to explode, which damages the testing centre and blows a hole in the roof. There it is, staring right at you: the moon. You remember that the white gel that made surfaces portalable was made of moon rocks, and take a chance. You fire a portal directly at the moon, and the vacuum of space tears Wheatley apart. It’s rare that a game’s final moments are my favourite, but this was a great callback and ups the stakes while so well while maintaining mechanical consistency that it may be the exception to the rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GLaDOS, now in control, pulls us back through the portal as Wheatley spirals off into space. Back on Earth, she decides that the least problematic option is just to let us go. We ascend to the surface past a bizarre choir of dancing turrets (I have no idea how that idea got any further than the brainstorming whiteboard) and step outside into the sunlight. The end credits are set to another song – this time sung by GLaDOS – about how happy she is to finally be rid of us, and we get a final scene of Wheatley drifting through space expressing his remorse before everything fades to black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;straying-from-the-formula&quot;&gt;Straying from the formula&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were parts of &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; I loved, and elements I didn’t see the need for at all. Despite its first-person perspective, Portal is a puzzle game, and it works best when it’s challenging the player to use the tools at their disposal to escape the cell the testing centre has built for them. There’s something immensely satisfying about the Checkoff’s gun-ness of it all – you know everything there must be used, but how? At the game’s strongest it follows an enhanced version of this format, and you’re forced to think not just in portals but also according to the effects of gels and gravity rays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in trying to make &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; bigger and better than its predecessor, Valve had to break it out of that bright white box. Beyond the testing chamber, it’s unclear what’s part of the puzzle and what’s just scenery. The most jarring moments were when the game seemed to be guiding me down a path, only for me to realise after much retreading that it was expecting me to have shot a portal at a tiny grey dot a mile away in the previous area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; is often brought up in “game of the generation” conversations, but honestly I prefer the far more concise and focused original. That said, there are still plenty of enjoyable puzzles in the various testing centres you explore over its eight-hour span, and even if Wheatley gets quite annoying early on, there is a lot of content that subverts the player’s expectations in amusing and surprising ways. If you didn’t play &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; back in 2011 then by all means go back for a playthrough – just don’t expect the earth-shattering experience some talk it up to be, and don’t overlook the original.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="portal" /><category term="puzzle" /><summary type="html">There was a time, way back in 2007, when Valve was a company that made video games, and released a little collection called The Orange Box. Having already completed Half-Life 2 on PC by that point, I had the most fun with a new title tacked onto the end of the compendium named Portal, which presented a unique blend of the first-person shooter and puzzle genres. For the uninitiated, Portal tasks the player with solving various challenges using a portal gun. This tool can fire two portals – orange and blue – which appear as large ovals on the walls. Walk through one and you’ll come out of the other, and the same holds true for various objects you’ll use to complete the levels. This innovative gameplay mechanic, plus some sarcastic, fourth wall-breaking dialogue, earnt Portal a place in many gamers’ hearts. In 2011, Valve published Portal 2, which made many of the era’s “best of” lists, but for one reason or another never joined my game library. Curious, I picked up a copy for the grand sum of £1.43 in a recent Steam sale, in the hope that it still stands up 11 years later. After an eight-hour playthrough of the sequel, I can say that Portal 2 tries to do much more than the original, and while it is successful in some respects, in my view it fails in others. Thinking with portals Portal 2 begins with the player waking up in a room at Aperture Laboratories, and it doesn’t take long for its signature tone to show as we’re instructed to complete our mandatory time staring at a painting on the wall to feel “mentally reinvigorated”. With that complete, we go back to bed, but apparently we sleep for too long because when we wake the dormitory building is ruined and there’s someone pounding on the door. This turns out to be Wheatley, a hapless but well-intentioned floating eye robot voiced by Stephen Merchant. There’s a clever bit here where the game asks us to press A to speak, but that button just makes us jump, which Wheatley points out. Now we’ve familiarised ourselves with the controls and met our new companion, Wheatley rips our bedroom from the building and whisks us off to the main facility for some “emergency testing”.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/15/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition review" /><published>2022-07-15T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-15T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/15/nvidia-3070-ti-founders-edition-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/15/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition-review">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been watching the price of Nvidia 30 series graphics cards for years with a view to upgrading from my modest but reliable &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/09/01/asus-geforce-dual-gtx1060-o6g-review/&quot;&gt;Asus GeForce Dual GTX 1060 O6G&lt;/a&gt;. With cryptocurrency prices crashing and hardware finally coming back into stock at reasonable(ish) prices, I finally pulled the trigger and made the outlay for a Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was giddy with excitement as I installed the new card inside my PC. I was no longer playing catch-up - here I was holding a glossy box containing a flagship component anyone would want to add to their rig. So did it fulfil my high-end gaming dreams? Well… Kind of. Read on to hear all about the hype, the perks, and the tribulations of 3070 Ti ownership…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unboxing-installation-and-troubleshooting&quot;&gt;Unboxing, installation, and troubleshooting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition came in a slick little package, as you’d expect from a premium product. The card was snugly nestled in foam inside a sturdy box, with a little cavity underneath for the quick start booklet and the special power adapter required to hook it up to your system. The set is incredibly photogenic, as you can see above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slid my 1060 out of the case and replaced it with the 3070 Ti with minimal fuss. I’d been a little wary of the fit, but it actually turned out to be slightly narrower than my previous card. This generation of cards demands a lot of power, and you must plug two cables from your power supply into Nvidia’s adapter, which connects to your card. A lesson from experience here - use two separate cables for this, not two connectors on the same wire.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While my old graphics card was essentially plug and play, the 3070 Ti turned out to be very fiddly to get working properly. Over the first day or two I was seeing poor performance in games and even the occasional unscheduled PC restart. Through trial, error, and a lot of Googling, I ended up making the following changes, which seem to have stabilised things somewhat:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•  Swapped to two separate power cables to the card&lt;br /&gt;
•  Reinstalled the drivers from scratch with Display Driver Uninstaller&lt;br /&gt;
•  Cut my minimum processor state to 10 percent in my power plan&lt;br /&gt;
•  Switched to a RAM Extreme Memory Profile (XMP) in the BIOS&lt;br /&gt;
•  Adjusted some Nvidia Control Panel settings for specific games&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d already upgraded to a 750W power supply ahead of time, but after spotting rising temperatures I also installed three more fans in my case to keep things cool. The 3070 Ti is working much better now, but I still don’t think it’s &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; at peak performance, and in the medium term I plan to install faster memory to eliminate any further bottlenecking by other components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gaming-performance&quot;&gt;Gaming performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With card installed and functional (kind of - some of the above took days’ worth of tinkering alongside some of the tests I’m about to describe), I did what any sane person would do: I loaded up some of my games and cranked all the settings up to the maximum to see what the 3070 Ti could do. For what it’s worth, all this is running on a monitor capable of 1440p at 75Hz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll start with &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; because it was by far the clunkiest game to configure. EA give you a grand total of five graphics settings to play around with (helpfully, this is only possible outside of the game menus), and it initially seemed like no matter what I did the game would stutter horribly or be plagued by screen tearing after installing the 3070 Ti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the point at which I switched to an XMP profile in my BIOS, before turning to the Nvidia Control Panel for some finetuning. Configuring the V-sync setting to Adaptive seemed to do the trick, and &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt; now runs smoothly, looking sharper than before and especially slick during close-ups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transitioning to the 3070 Ti with &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-1&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;F1 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was absolutely painless, and it’s one of the games with the most impressive graphical upgrades. Codemasters’ simcade racer is capable of ray tracing, which means you have a choice between silky smooth gameplay or losing a few frames for nicer shadows and reflections. I usually choose the former for top-end performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tag/call-of-duty&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Call of Duty: Warzone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was also easy to configure and required the least tinkering. I essentially just turned everything up to max settings - including ray tracing - and limited the frame rate to the 75 FPS that my monitor is capable of. The game runs flawlessly, and I’m looking forward to getting stuck in with some friends in the near future with the improved fidelity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s a slightly older game, I was impressed by the step up in &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/grand-theft-auto&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;GTA V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s performance when I ran it with the 3070 Ti under the hood. The extra power allowed me to turn on the game’s more elaborate visual effects and more detailed textures, and cruising around Los Santos - particularly against the orange and pink skies at dusk - has never looked better or smoother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I’ll give &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/cities-skylines&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a mention because I’ve been playing it again recently. Paradox’s city builder was released in 2015 and lacks the fancy graphical features and settings of some of the other games on this list, but the 3070 Ti does a good job of improving performance, sharpening some of the previously rough edges and providing a consistent frame rate, which sometimes creaked along a little bit in more built-up areas on my 1060.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I’d liken an upgrade to the Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition to an upgrade to a PlayStation 5 or &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/xbox&quot;&gt;Xbox Series X&lt;/a&gt; - you’ll see a noticable improvement to your gaming experience, but the difference won’t be black and white like the day you plugged in an Xbox 360 and saw games in HD for the first time. These days it’s all in the little details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would advise against the upgrade if you’re either not very technical or not prepared to commit the time and money needed to ensure the card can perform at its best. You won’t know for sure until you have the card up and running how many fiddly little settings you’ll need to tinker with or which other components might need an upgrade to keep up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you’re into your PC gaming and in this for the long run, the 3070 Ti does deliver on what it promises - at least after some configuration and troubleshooting. Nvidia’s flagship graphics card series has given my game collection a nice facelift, and I’m certainly looking forward to diving into some titles that were built for this generation of cards and their new features.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="hardware" /><category term="graphics-cards" /><summary type="html">I’ve been watching the price of Nvidia 30 series graphics cards for years with a view to upgrading from my modest but reliable Asus GeForce Dual GTX 1060 O6G. With cryptocurrency prices crashing and hardware finally coming back into stock at reasonable(ish) prices, I finally pulled the trigger and made the outlay for a Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition. I was giddy with excitement as I installed the new card inside my PC. I was no longer playing catch-up - here I was holding a glossy box containing a flagship component anyone would want to add to their rig. So did it fulfil my high-end gaming dreams? Well… Kind of. Read on to hear all about the hype, the perks, and the tribulations of 3070 Ti ownership… Unboxing, installation, and troubleshooting The Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition came in a slick little package, as you’d expect from a premium product. The card was snugly nestled in foam inside a sturdy box, with a little cavity underneath for the quick start booklet and the special power adapter required to hook it up to your system. The set is incredibly photogenic, as you can see above. I slid my 1060 out of the case and replaced it with the 3070 Ti with minimal fuss. I’d been a little wary of the fit, but it actually turned out to be slightly narrower than my previous card. This generation of cards demands a lot of power, and you must plug two cables from your power supply into Nvidia’s adapter, which connects to your card. A lesson from experience here - use two separate cables for this, not two connectors on the same wire.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cities: Skylines: A guide to schools, universities, and education</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/08/cities-skylines-education-guide" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cities&amp;#58; Skylines&amp;#58; A guide to schools, universities, and education" /><published>2022-07-08T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-08T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/08/cities-skylines-education-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/08/cities-skylines-education-guide">&lt;p&gt;Planning and managing a growing city in &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt; is a lot like building a house of cards. Every individual element is connected, and they must all progress in unison, maintaining a careful balance. Once one part falls away - perhaps through a power cut or a health crisis, for example - it is very easy for everything to fall apart. Your city is constantly on the edge of chaos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/cities-skylines-education_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently jumped back into the game after a years-long hiatus, having splurged on a Humble Bundle with many of the expansions, and the problem I was met with concerned my citizens’ education. I didn’t want a sprawling industrial complex in my city, but the fancy office buildings that were popping up were complaining they didn’t have enough educated workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My subsequent investigation into the &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt; education system led to the article that follows, which attempts to explain how it all fits together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;education-levels&quot;&gt;Education levels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt; uses four levels to describe citizens’ education: uneducated, educated, well educated, and highly educated. These correspond to the most advanced educational institution that each citizen has graduated from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Citizens who have completed no education are &lt;strong&gt;uneducated&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
• Citizens who have graduated from elementary school are &lt;strong&gt;educated&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
• Citizens who have graduated from high school are &lt;strong&gt;well educated&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
• Citizens who have graduated from university are &lt;strong&gt;highly educated&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to note that citizens must attend the relevant educational institution at the corresponding life stage - for example, a young adult who did not attend high school cannot then go to university. This means that as you develop your education system (which we’ll cover in a moment) it will take time for new youngsters to filter up through the ranks.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/cities-skylines-education_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check on your citizens’ current education levels in a few different ways. First, you can see education levels for residents of a particular building by clicking on it. Most usefully, however, you can view a summary of the entire city’s education levels by clicking on the education icon on the toolbar and reviewing the pie chart in the pane that appears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-do-we-need-educated-citizens&quot;&gt;Why do we need educated citizens?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: Educating your citizens will help your city develop. This manifests in several different but interconnected ways across all three main zoning types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the simplest level, certain education standards are required for certain jobs. If you click a commercial or industrial building, you’ll see a summary of the jobs offered by level. If you don’t have enough educated workers, jobs at the higher end will go unfilled, either limiting that employer’s growth or - in the worst case scenario - even causing the business to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/cities-skylines-education_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But educated residents don’t just improve their workplaces - they also give their homes a boost. Residential blocks are more likely to level up when the people who live inside are better educated, assuming you’ve also put the work in to raise the land value far enough to make it possible. Interestingly, there’s also an in-game tip that says educated citizens produce less rubbish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-educate-citizens&quot;&gt;How to educate citizens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might expect, if you want to accelerate your citizens’ education then the first step is ensuring that the right schools and universities are available to them. &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt; has a US-style education system and you’ll want to build from the bottom up, making slow but steady progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;strong&gt;elementary school&lt;/strong&gt; is the first stop for your young citizens. Then you’ll want to make sure they can secure a place at a &lt;strong&gt;high school&lt;/strong&gt; (or &lt;strong&gt;institute of creative arts&lt;/strong&gt;). Finally, well educated young adults can go to &lt;strong&gt;university&lt;/strong&gt; (or a &lt;strong&gt;community college&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;modern technology institute&lt;/strong&gt;) to take the final step and become highly educated model citizens ready for office jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/cities-skylines-education_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first consideration when building this infrastructure is quantity. The tabs on the Education pane show the availablility of places at each institution, and you’ll want to make sure that their capacity is well clear of the number of eligible students to ensure that everybody who wants to can attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accessibility is just as important. When you’re placing a building, the nearby roads will turn green to show which residences can easily attend, but you should also provide schools and universities with strong public transport links to enable citizens from further afield to make their way in, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;extra-encouragement&quot;&gt;Extra encouragement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you put the above plan into action, you’ll see your citizens’ education levels increase dramatically over the next few generations, but there are also a few more changes you can make to give things a little extra push.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the &lt;strong&gt;public library&lt;/strong&gt; is an anomaly when it comes to educational buildings. Libraries mostly provide entertainment, but they do provide a very small educational boost for citizens, particularly at the lower end of the education hierarchy - just don’t expect overwhelming results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final weapons in your arsenal are education-related policies, which can be applied to either your entire city or to individual areas as required. &lt;strong&gt;Education Boost&lt;/strong&gt; is your best friend here, providing a 25 percent budget increase and making citizens more likely to choose education over work. &lt;strong&gt;Educational Blimps&lt;/strong&gt; is another winner, providing a small boost at no cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, you should avoid some of the other policies. In particular, &lt;strong&gt;School’s Out&lt;/strong&gt; will push citizens into work over university, and &lt;strong&gt;For-Profit Education&lt;/strong&gt; will force them to pay to learn, to the exclusion of less well-off residents. So make sure these aren’t checked to avoid putting extra hurdles in the way of your citizens’ quest for knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="cities-skylines" /><category term="management" /><summary type="html">Planning and managing a growing city in Cities: Skylines is a lot like building a house of cards. Every individual element is connected, and they must all progress in unison, maintaining a careful balance. Once one part falls away - perhaps through a power cut or a health crisis, for example - it is very easy for everything to fall apart. Your city is constantly on the edge of chaos. I recently jumped back into the game after a years-long hiatus, having splurged on a Humble Bundle with many of the expansions, and the problem I was met with concerned my citizens’ education. I didn’t want a sprawling industrial complex in my city, but the fancy office buildings that were popping up were complaining they didn’t have enough educated workers. My subsequent investigation into the Cities: Skylines education system led to the article that follows, which attempts to explain how it all fits together. Education levels Cities: Skylines uses four levels to describe citizens’ education: uneducated, educated, well educated, and highly educated. These correspond to the most advanced educational institution that each citizen has graduated from. • Citizens who have completed no education are uneducated. • Citizens who have graduated from elementary school are educated. • Citizens who have graduated from high school are well educated. • Citizens who have graduated from university are highly educated. It’s important to note that citizens must attend the relevant educational institution at the corresponding life stage - for example, a young adult who did not attend high school cannot then go to university. This means that as you develop your education system (which we’ll cover in a moment) it will take time for new youngsters to filter up through the ranks.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/cities-skylines-education_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/cities-skylines-education_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">BioShock Infinite: Burial at Sea (PC) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/24/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BioShock Infinite&amp;#58; Burial at Sea (PC) retrospective" /><published>2022-06-24T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-06-24T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/24/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/24/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;I rarely bother with downloadable content. Most of the time I’m ready to put a game down by the time I finish the main story, and paying half the price for a fraction of the content doesn’t appeal to me. But when I heard that &lt;em&gt;BioShock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; had a two-part supplement to its story that took players back into Rapture, I couldn’t resist giving &lt;em&gt;Burial at Sea&lt;/em&gt; a go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote in &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/06/10/bioshock-infinite-retrospective&quot;&gt;my &lt;em&gt;BioShock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; retrospective&lt;/a&gt; that if the first two games were about the city of Rapture, the trilogy’s conclusion was about the individuals connected to Columbia. This allowed for a more character-driven story, but I felt that overall the game lost part of what &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt; was, leaving behind the allure of Andrew Ryan’s city and the horror elements that kept you on edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up came &lt;em&gt;Burial at Sea&lt;/em&gt;, a downloadable add-on campaign for &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt; that was released in two parts between 2013 and 2014. This new extension continues the story of Booker DeWitt and Elizabeth “Comstock”, but takes place predominantly in Rapture. And while it is not successful at everything it tries to do, by transplanting the more engaging characters of &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt; into the creepy corridors of an underwater metropolis on the brink provides some of the best &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt; segments ever, at least in short bursts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;humble-beginnings&quot;&gt;Humble beginnings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Episode One&lt;/em&gt; is the lesser of the two in terms of both length and quality, and begins on New Year’s Eve in 1958. DeWitt, a private investigator, is hired by Elizabeth to find a girl named Sally. We exit our office, and we get something I’d always wanted – a chance to explore Rapture in the kind of thriving splendour that Columbia displayed for most of the main game.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game guides us past some familiar elements in their fully functional forms, which until this point we’ve only ever heard stories of. We use a fire plasmid to light Elizabeth’s cigarette, Little Sisters are being trained to do their grim jobs, and a waiter teleports around a bar like a Houdini splicer to take patrons’ orders. It really is fascinating to see how Rapture worked at its peak, blending mid-century style with its ominous superhuman technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highlight of our time in mainstream Rapture is an encounter with the neurotic artist Sander Cohen, who we’re told might know where Sally is. He says he’ll help if we dance so he can paint us, but when we do he shocks us and we wake up in a bathysphere on our way down to Fontaine’s department store, which Ryan has separated from the rest of the city and sunk to serve as a prison for Fontaine and his followers. Cohen tells us over the capsule’s radio that we will find Sally in the houseware department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rapid-decay&quot;&gt;Rapid decay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the moment we land in the lobby, this feels more like the Rapture we know. The store is decaying and creepy, and is populated by splicers. They aren’t quite as crazy as they will eventually be, and much of their speech parrots libertarian messages from Ryan’s propaganda. The sounds of the city are back too – from the demented dialogue enemies spout as they roam around to the Circus of Values vending machine jingle. It’s enough to keep you on your toes, peeking around each corner as you proceed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After picking up a new ice plasmid named Old Man Winter (located amongst some really nice store promotional displays), we see Sally climb into a vent in housewares. Splicers are trying to lure her out to harvest her ADAM, so after closing all but one of the exits Booker insists that we turn up the heat to flush her out. We do so, despite Elizabeth’s protests, but when she comes out of the exhaust we see that Sally has transformed into a Little Sister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sally calls for Mr Bubbles, her Big Daddy, to help. The fight that ensues is as prominent a collision of the two worlds as we get, with a particular favourite moment coming when I pitted the subnautical beast against a Motorised Patriot summoned through a tear by Elizabeth. Eventually the Big Daddy falls lifeless to the ground and we can turn our attention to Sally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here, at the finale of &lt;em&gt;Episode One&lt;/em&gt;, comes &lt;em&gt;Burial at Sea&lt;/em&gt;’s first big twist. When DeWitt tries to pull Sally out of the vent, he remembers his struggle with Anna at the tear - but from the wrong side. At this moment, Elizabeth calls us Comstock and berates us for trying to snatch Sally as we took her previously. On the bombshell that we’ve been playing as a post-Comstock DeWitt all this time, we’re impaled by a Big Daddy’s drill, and the first part ends as we fall to the ground and the screen fades to black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mixing-it-up&quot;&gt;Mixing it up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Episode Two&lt;/em&gt; begins in an idyllic Paris. We’re now playing as Elizabeth, and everyone says hello and offers compliments as we explore the streets. Then we catch a glimpse of Sally, and as we chase her everything falls apart. The city falls to ruins, and when we enter a door with Booker’s name on it we come face-to-face with the thermostat we used to crank up the heat on Sally. We turn around to &lt;em&gt;Burial at Sea&lt;/em&gt;’s first jump scare – she’s right behind us in her creepy Little Sister form. It’s clear Elizabeth is wracked with guilt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wake to see Fontaine (as Atlas) and his men pulling Sally from the vent. A vision of Booker tells us to say we can get Fontaine back to Rapture, which suddenly gets his attention. On DeWitt’s advice we tell him that we are Suchong’s lab assistant and we can get him something valuable, so he lets us go. As we leave the Big Daddy fight arena we move some rubble to see our own corpse – Elizabeth was killed in the fight. The version of her we now play as has all her fingers and cannot open tears between worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We leave and explore the Ryan the Lion Preparatory Academy, which is basically porn for &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt; fans. It’s full of material teaching children about the perils of communism and “parasites”, even to a level where there are boards encouraging them to identify freeloaders they’ve met, all led by the titular lion character, who is never seen without a cigarette in his mouth. The anti-nationalism and anti-religion messages stand in stark contrast to Columbia’s founding values, which we were surrounded by in the main game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s immediately clear that &lt;em&gt;Burial at Sea&lt;/em&gt; wants us to change our tactics. &lt;em&gt;Episode One&lt;/em&gt; played much the same as &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt;, but Elizabeth is a lot weaker than Booker and must stick to the shadows to survive. She has guns, but ammo is scarce and one-hit stealth kills are more efficient. We pick up a little crossbow, and later we’ll get access to some nice toys like tranquiliser and gas darts and the Peeping Tom plasmid, which allows us to see enemies’ locations through walls and turn invisible for short periods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combined with environmental considerations (water in particular is noisy to walk through and prone to attracting attention - unfortunate in Rapture’s more run down areas), this produces some truly tense moments. It is greatly satisfying to perfectly time an approach – either by hiding behind a box or using the Sky-Hook to drop down behind your enemy – and clobber a splicer. Irrational Games has clearly gone to great lengths to differentiate Elizabeth from the series’ other player characters, and it pays off in abundance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;taking-to-the-skies&quot;&gt;Taking to the skies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We creep around Rapture some more – including through a smutty theatre, which is a great location but gets very limited use – and eventually find our way to the lab belonging to Suchong, the developer of plasmids and the Big Daddy. He has a tear machine that’s broken, so we do some fetch quests to find the items required to repair it. We get confirmation here of how this fits into &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt;’s narrative, as we get one part from the heart of Fontaine’s operation, where his army of splicers talk about crashing New Year’s Eve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the machine running, we open a tear to Columbia. Our goal is to acquire a special particle used to keep the city afloat, which we can use to lift the sunken department store to Rapture’s level and set Fontaine loose. Our travels through Comstock’s city yield some interesting tidbits – for example, we see that Jeremiah Fink and Suchong had been collaborating on their science projects, sharing notes on Big Daddies and Songbird, and see some evidence of Fink’s failed attempts to have it bond with a young Elizabeth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But my biggest groan during &lt;em&gt;Burial at Sea&lt;/em&gt; also came in this section, when we overhear the Lutece twins instructing Vox Populi leader Daisy Fitzroy to give Elizabeth no other choice but to kill her. “She must arrive a girl and leave a woman,” they say, promising this will be critical to the overall success of the uprising. This was hugely disappointing. &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/06/10/bioshock-infinite-retrospective#reading-between-the-lines&quot;&gt;I previously praised Fitzroy&lt;/a&gt; as one of a very few &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt; characters with some genuine complexity and moral ambiguity, and this moment retconned all of that away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get the particle and a hair sample (our own) that Suchong wanted, then return to Rapture. But just as Suchong is about to fulfil his end of the deal, Andrew Ryan intervenes. There’s a fantastically tense moment as he counts down the 60 seconds until his goons enter the room to deal with Elizabeth, and I really felt the terror of a vulnerable young woman about to face down an army. My only slight grievance here is that these are tough enemies, and you have to listen to his whole speech again every time you die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coming-full-circle&quot;&gt;Coming full circle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All hell is breaking loose outside as Fontaine’s uprising starts to gain momentum. We reach his office and use the particle to lift the building, which means Fontaine has his escape and needs to keep his end of the deal by handing over Sally. Unsurprisingly, he doesn’t, and instead drops his Atlas accent and tortures us to find out where his “ace in the hole” is. When he begins to threaten Sally, we have a vision of Booker and realise it is in Suchong’s lab, so it’s back out into Rapture for us to save Sally’s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea_8.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a neat moment here where our path is blocked by an injured Big Daddy and his two worried Little Sisters. We learn from Suchong’s notes that he’s been struggling to build a bond between the two, but deduce that we can give their relationship a shot in the arm by having the Little Sisters give him ADAM. This in turn leads to Suchong’s death as the Big Daddy turns on him when he abuses the girls. This was unexpected and it was fantastic to see the world’s rules put to such clever use in the narrative when the designers could easily have just beefed up Suchong for another boss fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We grab the ace in the hole – a piece of paper – and deliver it to Fontaine, who promptly hits us over the head. As we drift back into consciousness he’s telling us that he doesn’t understand it. Our eyes focus on the page and we decrypt Suchong’s code, revealing three words: “Would you kindly”. Elizabeth has just delivered the phrase that will allow Atlas to order &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt;’s Jack around and swing the revolution in his favour – now he just needs to get him to Rapture. Sally, useless, is now set free, but before Fontaine departs he issues one more blow to Elizabeth, who dies slumped against the glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea_9.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Burial at Sea&lt;/em&gt; started slow, but by the end I felt it had done enough both in terms of story and narrative to deserve its place as the last piece of the &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt; saga. &lt;em&gt;Episode One&lt;/em&gt; meandered somewhat, but &lt;em&gt;Episode Two&lt;/em&gt; did an excellent job – Fitzroy moment aside – of tying up the trilogy’s narrative in a way the was arguably needed after the slightly disjointed addition of &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also worth reiterating on how different &lt;em&gt;Episode Two&lt;/em&gt; was in terms of gameplay. If you’re going to make significant changes to your beloved series’ formula then the latter half of the final expansion is a brave place to do it, but putting the player in the shoes of the more fragile but lighter-footed Elizabeth was an inspired move that really leant into the first two &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt; games’ horror tendencies. This was missing from &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt;’s main campaign, but I was on edge for large parts of &lt;em&gt;Burial at Sea&lt;/em&gt; as I snuck around Rapture’s shadowy corners trying to avoid detection by splicers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt; fan and, like me, your excitement for story-based games tends to tail off before the downloadable content arrives, I implore you to go back and play &lt;em&gt;Burial at Sea&lt;/em&gt;. As well as a return to the creepy subnautical world of Rapture, it offers a satisfying denouement to the saga’s storyline and some of the trilogy’s best and most refined gameplay to boot.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="bioshock" /><category term="shooters" /><summary type="html">I rarely bother with downloadable content. Most of the time I’m ready to put a game down by the time I finish the main story, and paying half the price for a fraction of the content doesn’t appeal to me. But when I heard that BioShock Infinite had a two-part supplement to its story that took players back into Rapture, I couldn’t resist giving Burial at Sea a go. I wrote in my BioShock Infinite retrospective that if the first two games were about the city of Rapture, the trilogy’s conclusion was about the individuals connected to Columbia. This allowed for a more character-driven story, but I felt that overall the game lost part of what BioShock was, leaving behind the allure of Andrew Ryan’s city and the horror elements that kept you on edge. Next up came Burial at Sea, a downloadable add-on campaign for Infinite that was released in two parts between 2013 and 2014. This new extension continues the story of Booker DeWitt and Elizabeth “Comstock”, but takes place predominantly in Rapture. And while it is not successful at everything it tries to do, by transplanting the more engaging characters of Infinite into the creepy corridors of an underwater metropolis on the brink provides some of the best BioShock segments ever, at least in short bursts. Humble beginnings Episode One is the lesser of the two in terms of both length and quality, and begins on New Year’s Eve in 1958. DeWitt, a private investigator, is hired by Elizabeth to find a girl named Sally. We exit our office, and we get something I’d always wanted – a chance to explore Rapture in the kind of thriving splendour that Columbia displayed for most of the main game.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite-burial-at-sea_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – hitting the big time</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/17/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA 22 Career Mode&amp;#58; TSP United &amp;#8211; hitting the big time" /><published>2022-06-16T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-06-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/17/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/17/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-2">&lt;p&gt;When we last left my TSP United &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt; Career Mode series, we had just made it into the Championship as League One champions. Did the lads from the Stratosphere have what it takes to handle the giddy heights of England’s second tier? Read on to find out how we fared in the following seasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a reminder, I’m playing this Career Mode campaign with special custom rules for some added challenge. I’m not to spend a penny on players (signing free agents is fine) and the focus is on &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players&quot;&gt;scouting and developing youth players&lt;/a&gt;. So my main source of new talent through this whole thing is to send a scout out around England occasionally and see what he brings back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this is the second instalment of my TSP United Career Mode series. Click here to catch up on the first two seasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202324---the-championship&quot;&gt;2023/24 - The Championship&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made a couple of decent signings heading into the Championship. Late-career goalkeeper Aguerre arrived, while young Japanese central midfielder Anami joined the side. The latter turned out to be a solid addition, becoming a regular fixture in the midfield and grabbing a few goals, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A less successful signing was an ageing Marcos Alonso, who joined at left back after Chelsea declined to renew his contract. He got himself sent off conceding a penalty 20 minutes into his debut and never got much better, spending two months on the sidelines with an injury from October. At the very least, the Stratosphere did get to see one of his trademark free kick goals in his comeback game against Swansea City.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/fifa-22-career-mode_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TSP United had a stable start to the season, but by Christmas we were sitting in the play-off places, 12 points behind runaway league leaders Bournemouth. Somehow we closed the gap, and the season culminated in a tense three-way title race, with Watford joining the fray. All three were dropping points, but we developed of an unfortunate habit of losing to our title rivals, which did not help our chances of lifting any silverware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In amongst all this, club legend Johnson came into goalscoring form, while for the first time his strike partner Prince dropped off a bit, eventually losing his starting place to the impressive youngster Vaughan. Prince eventually got another chance when Johnson got injured in January and was out for the rest of the season, joining the academy product up front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/fifa-22-career-mode_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watford hit late form and won the league with a game to go. This left us to a tense showdown with Huddersfield on the final day, where due to a packed schedule and a miscalculation most of the first team wasn’t fit. TSP United went 2-0 up through Goddard and Smyth, but collapsed to a 2-3 deficit. A late equaliser from Groves earned a point, and after a tense wait we learnt that Millwall had beaten Bournemouth, securing automatic promotion for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as earning our place in the Premier League, TSP United went on a little bit of a run in the FA Cup. A 4-3 win over Southampton, with all the goals coming from academy graduates, was a particular highlight. But it all fell apart in a dismal 5-1 quarter-final defeat to Chelsea, which was a warning as to how difficult things would become next season…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best original player&lt;/strong&gt; - Johnson, knocking them in until his injury&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - Anami, although Alonso didn’t offer much competition&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Vaughan, earning a first-team place up front&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202425---premier-league&quot;&gt;2024/25 - Premier League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was it. TSP United had finally hit the big time. To avoid sliding straight back down to where we came from we needed to strengthen at the back, so as well as promoting some youth players we signed a free agent centre-back named Aguirre to bolster the defence. He quickly became one of the first names on the teamsheet and provided some much-needed height and stability at the back, even grabbing a few goals from corners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/fifa-22-career-mode_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was immediately clear it would be a tough season. The spins and turns that served us so well in getting past Championship defences were shrugged off by their Premier League counterparts, and goals were hard to come by. Club legends Prince and Johnson weren’t cutting it up front and it was obvious we’d need reinforcements come the January transfer window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first win came away at Brighton thanks to a Hutton hat trick and we found ourselves on a short run of form that petered out somewhat as Christmas approached. The best-case scenario at this point was for TSP United to cling to our place in the top flight for another year and consolidate as much as we could. With the strikers struggling and a long-term injury to Prince, we used the mid-season window to sign an young, unattached winger named Annumanian, who slotted in up front beside Vaughan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/fifa-22-career-mode_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere in the team, when Anami went off the boil in midfield I decided to give Groves some more game time to help him towards reaching his potential. The Japanese player got a chance to redeem himself later when Perry got injured. With a lack of depth at centre-back, I tried playing Anami alongside Aguirre in the middle, and the two formed a fairly solid partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes had the desired effect, with a trickle of goals coming through from Vaughan and Annumanian and the new-look defence not looking &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; so vulnerable. In the end, we secured safety with a couple of games left to play. Heading into the summer it was certainly time to build on the squad with the goal of making the next season a bit more comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best original player&lt;/strong&gt; - Hutton, keeping things ticking in midfield&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - Aguirre, solid at the back with some headed goals&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Groves, squeezing into the first team&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">When we last left my TSP United FIFA 22 Career Mode series, we had just made it into the Championship as League One champions. Did the lads from the Stratosphere have what it takes to handle the giddy heights of England’s second tier? Read on to find out how we fared in the following seasons. As a reminder, I’m playing this Career Mode campaign with special custom rules for some added challenge. I’m not to spend a penny on players (signing free agents is fine) and the focus is on scouting and developing youth players. So my main source of new talent through this whole thing is to send a scout out around England occasionally and see what he brings back. Note that this is the second instalment of my TSP United Career Mode series. Click here to catch up on the first two seasons: • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues 2023/24 - The Championship We made a couple of decent signings heading into the Championship. Late-career goalkeeper Aguerre arrived, while young Japanese central midfielder Anami joined the side. The latter turned out to be a solid addition, becoming a regular fixture in the midfield and grabbing a few goals, too. A less successful signing was an ageing Marcos Alonso, who joined at left back after Chelsea declined to renew his contract. He got himself sent off conceding a penalty 20 minutes into his debut and never got much better, spending two months on the sidelines with an injury from October. At the very least, the Stratosphere did get to see one of his trademark free kick goals in his comeback game against Swansea City.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/06/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/06/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">BioShock Infinite (PC) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/10/bioshock-infinite-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BioShock Infinite (PC) retrospective" /><published>2022-06-10T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-06-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/10/bioshock-infinite-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/10/bioshock-infinite-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;I’m on the war path in 2022, finally playing through all sorts of games that I probably &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have completed years ago, but for one reason or another passed me by. Next in line is &lt;em&gt;BioShock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; - the 2013 follow-up to two fantastic games that I hold among my all-time favourites. The switch from my beloved Rapture to Columbia demoted this one to my “to play” list, and once the initial hype died down so did any urgency I had to pick it up - until, that is, it went free on the Epic Games store a few weeks ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;BioShock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; is a game that can certainly be described as interesting on several levels. The core premise and story itself is interesting, including how it entwines itself with the series’ universe. The potential readings into what the designers and writers meant by it all are interesting. And at its most fundamental level, as a piece of video gaming entertainment, it’s interesting to notice the ways in which the &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt; formula has been tweaked to paper over some of the shortcomings and criticism of the first two games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-tale-of-two-timelines&quot;&gt;A tale of two timelines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most fundamental difference between &lt;em&gt;BioShock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; and the two games that came before it is that the iconic underwater city of Rapture is no more. This time out, our setting is Columbia – a flying city of interconnecting platforms that was established by Father Comstock, a religious leader who is seen as the ultimate authority and God’s right-hand man. The brief opening sees you take a row boat to a lighthouse, and essentially only fills you in that you’re a man named Booker DeWitt who has travelled from New York to settle his gambling debts. Then it launches you into the clouds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parts of Columbia you are shown carefully construct your impression of the city over the first hour or two. Unlike Rapture, the city is thriving when you arrive, and it initially seems rather idyllic until you begin to notice certain undercurrents. These eventually come to the surface when DeWitt wins a raffle, the prize for which is presented by “the loveliest white girl in Columbia”. Your reward, it turns out, is a chance to hurl a ball at a pair of lower-class citizens in stocks, but before you can do anything DeWitt is recognised as the “false shepherd”. From that moment, you’re on the run.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A switch is flicked here, and the game becomes a lot more violent both literally and figuratively. The shooting begins and the racism bubbles to the surface as your travels take you through areas branded with slogans like “Protecting our Race”. I was a bit worried at this point that the sum of the game’s story would be a lazy “religion is bad and racist”, but &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt; has more up its sleeve yet. Things get properly interesting when we run across Elizabeth – the girl DeWitt’s debtors have apparently been demanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Held captive and under observation by Comstock, Elizabeth is quickly established as having a supernatural power to open “tears” to other worlds. We break her out of her tower and – after some convincing that killing so many people is a necessity that doesn’t make us evil – she joins us in a failed escape attempt. We’re knocked out, and when we wake up we’re introduced to the Vox Populi – a rebel group attempting to start an uprising and overthrow Comstock. They’ll help us if we provide weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elizabeth is enamoured with the Vox and their promise of a better and fairer life for the people of Columbia, but when she brings us into a world where their revolution is in full throw it is clear that they are bent on tearing the city apart and killing even the most insignificant citizens. In this timeline DeWitt is their martyr, and the Vox turn on us because a living Booker “complicates the narrative”. Even Elizabeth steps in when the Vox leader Daisy is about to kill an industrialist’s child, and stabs her in the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A face-off with the spirit of Lady Comstock yields a twist – until now we’ve been led to believe that Elizabeth is Comstock’s daughter, but this is thrown into doubt. When Songbird – a giant, mechanical brute of a bird that guarded her tower – tracks us down, she sacrifices herself into captivity to save DeWitt’s life. Another jump between worlds leads us into a mental asylum, where we see glimpses of Elizabeth’s “rehabilitation” by Comstock’s regime, and a further switch enables a brief conversation with an elderly Elizabeth in 1984, set against the backdrop of Columbia invading New York. She hands us what will later turn out to be the key to stopping Songbird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot happens from here on out as the game culminates in a fight through Comstock’s airship to kill the man himself. We have a final (and long) battle with the Vox on the top deck, using the new intel to harness Songbird to our advantage before we lose control of him and Elizabeth is forced to transfer us into another world… and we end up in Rapture. It turns out Columbia and Rapture exist in parallel worlds. When we surface, there are lighthouses as far as the eye can see, and Elizabeth explains that there is “always a man, always a city” - an infinite number of alternate timelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learn a lot through some muddled scenes here, but the overall gist is this: Elizabeth is DeWitt’s daughter Anna, who he was forced to hand over to Comstock to settle his gambling debts. Comstock himself was rendered impotent due to inter-world travel via tears, but wanted Elizabeth to be his heiress and take over Columbia when he stepped down or died. Hearing this, DeWitt wants to go back in time and kill Comstock so none of this can happen, but realises that Comstock is in fact another version of &lt;em&gt;himself&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeWitt was offered a chance to be baptised and absolved of his sins when he returned from war, but turned the priest down. In a parallel timeline, he accepted the baptism and became religious, eventually transforming into Father Comstock and founding Columbia. As Elizabeths from various worlds converge on DeWitt in the lake where this took place, he allows them to drown him to keep her from the harm that would otherwise be inflicted by Comstock. The screen fades to black, and the game ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reading-between-the-lines&quot;&gt;Reading between the lines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a high level, &lt;em&gt;BioShock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; can be read as a warning about extremism on both sides of politics. Father Comstock’s regime is authoritarian, with slogans on the billboards, police in military uniforms on the street corners, and a horribly mistreated underclass of workers and ethnic minorities. But when the Vox Populi rise up, they too commit atrocities, with indiscriminate killings of anybody they deem to be part of the establishment – even children. It’s a cautionary tale about how easy it is for anyone to convince themselves they are “the good guys” and justified in undertaking horrible acts because they think their cause is worthy enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is supported by a few segments that offer commentary on the gulf that sometimes exists between the stories we tell ourselves and reality. Notably, Elizabeth is thoroughly convinced by just a few lines from the Vox Populi about how they’ll make Columbia a better place. Later, we see the priority the revolutionary group places on the narrative it has built. Although he is also fighting against Comstock, a dead DeWitt is more useful to Daisy Fitzroy because if he is living then he loses his martyr status, which is a cornerstone of their propaganda. Building a polarising story is more important to them than their integrity. &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt; shows the power of blind adherence to ideology to corrupt, even when a movement started with worthy intentions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an important and relevant message for the real world, but it doesn’t &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; work in-game because Comstock’s regime is so cartoonishly evil that you could make an argument that just about anything else would have been preferable. In fact, everyone in &lt;em&gt;BioShock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; is a hopeless caricature – Comstock as the insane cult leader and industrial tycoon Albert Fink as the capitalist without morals, for example. Daisy herself is a rare example of a character with some ambiguity – initially seeking justice before power pushes her over the ethical edge – far more interesting than all-out good or evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting here that all this is conveyed in a much more engaging way than the themes of the first two &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt; titles. This is possible because Columbia is alive around us, and there are NPCs we can listen to and interact with who aren’t just manic splicers rambling nonsense – ranging from major characters like Comstock and Daisy Fitzroy to enemies and random citizens. In &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt;, most exposition came though audio logs dotted around the ruins of Rapture. They still exist in &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt; and supplement the story with some colour, but the bulk of the main narrative is absorbed through experience – conversations with characters and observation of the city in motion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also points, especially early on, where Elizabeth expresses her dismay at DeWitt’s killing. This is a theme more akin to that of the original &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt;, which questioned gamers’ ability to make their own decisions. This is a first-person shooter, and we simply accept that shoot is what we must do in every situation where the game will let us. Elizabeth, on the other hand, is new to this world, and shocked at the carnage we leave in our wake. It’s not explored as consistently as it could have been, but this thread at least comes to a head when she turns to violence herself later on, stabbing Daisy in the back to spare the young boy she’s about to kill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take this a step further, Elizabeth and her character development could also be read as an analogy for the naivety of youth in general. She leaves captivity having read about the world in her library (akin to school) and is shocked at the reality outside. Her idealistic pacifism is eventually shattered, as I mentioned above. And she is impressionable enough to be won over quickly and completely by the Vox Populi’s promises, only realising her mistake when she sees what their revolution really looks like. The course of Infinite’s story is an education in practicality and critical thinking for her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;playing-the-game&quot;&gt;Playing the game&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt; series lends itself to discussions of story and themes, gaming is an interactive medium, and ultimately none of it would stand up if the gameplay experience was no good. What we get with &lt;em&gt;BioShock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; is a steady refinement of what came before in the first two games. The series’ shooting has never been the best. Unlike something responsive and weighty like &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/call-of-duty&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, combat in this game is a lot more about wearing down enemies’ health bars over time using the tools at your disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And those tools are as varied as any game’s. The selection of guns is what you’d expect from a modern FPS, but the “vigors” – powers embedded in your hand which replace plasmids this time around - are where the designers really got creative. These range from classics like lightning and fire to some that are really out there. My favourite was Murder of Crows, which allows you to throw a nest at your enemies’ feet so that birds attack them. Vigors are what sets &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt; apart, and my only complaint is that the game didn’t make it clearer that while two vigors sit in your quick-use slots for easy access, you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; still access them all at any time via a radial menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elizabeth is unique as a companion. While most sidekicks are annoying at best and game over machines at worst, Elizabeth is invulnerable to damage and serves instead as a tool to enhance the player’s experience. She picks locks to helps you progress, and often runs ahead, helping to guide you in the right direction. She throws items like ammo and money to Booker, and even her tears become a gameplay mechanic – you can shout to her to fabricate cover, weapons, health, turrets, and more. It’s so rare for a companion to be so genuinely useful that I found this directly contributed to the weight of the story, and you miss her when she’s taken away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Columbia itself also offers a chance for Irrational Games to add some variety to the series’ gameplay. Gone are the claustrophobic corridors of Rapture, which have been replaced in large part by open outdoor areas. The difference is night and day, and you’re much more likely to be engaged in ranged combat than in even the most expansive parts of Andrew Ryan’s underwater city. Staying on brand as a flying city, Columbia is full of Sky-Line rails, which enable DeWitt to slide around on a grappling hook-style device and drop down on enemies from above when the opportunity arises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foes range from standard foot soldiers (melee, pistol, machine gun, RPG, sniper, etc.) to  specialists. Firemen blast you with flames, and raven-themed warriors can teleport and hack at you with a sword, for example. The largest and most challenging enemy type is the Handyman, which benefits from great speed, extended reach, and the ability to take a large amount of your health if it hits you. The best of the lot, however, was the Motorised Patriot – robots modelled after the US Founding Fathers who storm into battle in a hail of bullets, shouting patriotic slogans as they join the fray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt;’s most memorable sequences are when the game decides to mix things up. Lady Comstock provides one of the more interesting fights, summoning ghost soldiers to do her bidding in a way that reminded me of Clifford Unger in &lt;em&gt;Death Stranding&lt;/em&gt;. I thought the battle was fairly short at first, but she returns several times in different arenas. Mechanically, it’s a nice change of pace to be forced to balance fighting the boss herself with dealing with her henchmen as they advance on your position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another notable mention goes to the mental asylum where Elizabeth is held later in the game. This features surprisingly good stealth gameplay, where if you are caught by a rotating sentry’s torch you are ambushed by a group of tough inmate enemies in creepy masks. The section culminates in a huge jump scare, where you pull a lever and turn around to find one of the sentries, which you’ve been tiptoeing around all along, right behind you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no regrets about taking the time to play &lt;em&gt;BioShock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; after nine years. There were elements I enjoyed – the opening chapel, the Motorised Patriots, and some of the grander spaces will all stick with me – but I felt Columbia was less atmospheric than Rapture, held back by the little details. The vending machines, for example, were just as creepy as Rapture’s, but their voices felt like imitations of the old ones (which can be explained by the parallel worlds plot point, but still). Maybe it’s also because I missed Rapture’s claustrophobia and the horror elements that the first two games employed, but it also seemed like the sub-nautical state had more of a story to tell as a city, while &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt;’s tale was much more about the individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_8.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that sounds like I’m being negative, I’m not. &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt; was still a fantastic game, head and shoulders above most other titles out there – particularly in &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/shooters&quot;&gt;the FPS genre&lt;/a&gt; – and it was clear that Irrational Games had spent a lot of time working out how they could act on some of the criticism directed at the first two games in the trilogy while still maintaining its character. While the transition to a new city was a mixed success, the gameplay is a definite step up, especially with Elizabeth and her tears to keep you company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There aren’t many games with enough depth to be worth a 2,500-word retrospective, but &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt; has pulled it off again. &lt;em&gt;BioShock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; is a mesh of complex ideas, some of which work better than others, but the underlying message about the perils of blind adherence to ideologies on all sides of the political spectrum is if anything more relevant now than it was back in 2013. If politics and philosophy aren’t your thing, there’s also a compelling personal story about DeWitt, Comstock, and Elizabeth to unpick. And if you don’t care about that… Well, there’s quite an enjoyable video game here, too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="bioshock" /><category term="shooters" /><summary type="html">I’m on the war path in 2022, finally playing through all sorts of games that I probably should have completed years ago, but for one reason or another passed me by. Next in line is BioShock Infinite - the 2013 follow-up to two fantastic games that I hold among my all-time favourites. The switch from my beloved Rapture to Columbia demoted this one to my “to play” list, and once the initial hype died down so did any urgency I had to pick it up - until, that is, it went free on the Epic Games store a few weeks ago. BioShock Infinite is a game that can certainly be described as interesting on several levels. The core premise and story itself is interesting, including how it entwines itself with the series’ universe. The potential readings into what the designers and writers meant by it all are interesting. And at its most fundamental level, as a piece of video gaming entertainment, it’s interesting to notice the ways in which the BioShock formula has been tweaked to paper over some of the shortcomings and criticism of the first two games. A tale of two timelines The most fundamental difference between BioShock Infinite and the two games that came before it is that the iconic underwater city of Rapture is no more. This time out, our setting is Columbia – a flying city of interconnecting platforms that was established by Father Comstock, a religious leader who is seen as the ultimate authority and God’s right-hand man. The brief opening sees you take a row boat to a lighthouse, and essentially only fills you in that you’re a man named Booker DeWitt who has travelled from New York to settle his gambling debts. Then it launches you into the clouds. The parts of Columbia you are shown carefully construct your impression of the city over the first hour or two. Unlike Rapture, the city is thriving when you arrive, and it initially seems rather idyllic until you begin to notice certain undercurrents. These eventually come to the surface when DeWitt wins a raffle, the prize for which is presented by “the loveliest white girl in Columbia”. Your reward, it turns out, is a chance to hurl a ball at a pair of lower-class citizens in stocks, but before you can do anything DeWitt is recognised as the “false shepherd”. From that moment, you’re on the run.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting the full Martin Brundle experience at Thruxton</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/03/btcc-formula-4-thruxton-2022" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting the full Martin Brundle experience at Thruxton" /><published>2022-06-03T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-06-03T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/03/btcc-formula-4-thruxton-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/03/btcc-formula-4-thruxton-2022">&lt;p&gt;I got back to Thruxton last week after nine months away, travelling down to Andover to watch the British Touring Car Championship, Formula 4, and other support races. It was a gorgeous day (so much so that I felt its effects for days to come) - perfect for sitting out in the fresh air and watching some racing from the grass banks at one of the country’s fastest circuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/thruxton-btcc-formula-4-2022_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time I visited the track the action came mainly from the racing - notably &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/08/29/btcc-formula-4-thruxton/&quot;&gt;a particularly incident-packed Mini Challenge race&lt;/a&gt;. The drivers seemed a bit more chilled out this year, however, and while there was some good jostling for position, the racing was friendly enough that the only DNF we saw was a Mini whose front left wheel simply gave way coming out of the Club chicane behind the safety car - a rather bizarre incident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I still maintain that &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/31/brands-hatch-best-views-uk-motorsport&quot;&gt;Brands Hatch has the best views in the country&lt;/a&gt;, Thruxton’s grandstands at Club give a good angle on the action, and its banked viewing areas mean you can see well no matter when you arrive or how much you move around. This year I explored a bit further than before, moving past Campbell and Cobb and around towards Segrave and Noble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/thruxton-btcc-formula-4-2022_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching Formula 4 cars navigate the Campbell-Cobb chicane from just behind the barriers was quite something. The angle reminded me of the segments in Sky’s Formula 1 practice coverage where Martin Brundle stands at different points on the track, observing the variations between drivers’ approaches and watching the weight shift across the wheels as they turn in.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The northmost viewing area is set up on a hill on the exit of Segrave and running down towards Noble. Therefore it doesn’t offer quite as much action as the complex itself, but it does provide a nice, clear space to catch the cars running at speed for any budding motorsport photographers, and was well worth the climb to see the cars from the slightly different perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/thruxton-btcc-formula-4-2022_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another area I visited for the first time this year was the paddock. Accessible via a pedestrian tunnel on the home straight, it extends out towards the airfield and is fully open to spectators, at least on BTCC weekend. Of particular interest to me were the Formula 4 team tents, where some of the cars were stripped down for all sorts of work, with panels missing to expose their front suspensions, engines, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, it was another successful day out. I feel like Thruxton isn’t often mentioned in the same conversations as more famous circuits like Silverstone and Brands Hatch that have hosted Formula 1 grands prix, but it should certainly be high on your list if you live in the south of England and you want to watch some exciting motor racing on a very fast track.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="motorsport" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="formula-4" /><summary type="html">I got back to Thruxton last week after nine months away, travelling down to Andover to watch the British Touring Car Championship, Formula 4, and other support races. It was a gorgeous day (so much so that I felt its effects for days to come) - perfect for sitting out in the fresh air and watching some racing from the grass banks at one of the country’s fastest circuits. Last time I visited the track the action came mainly from the racing - notably a particularly incident-packed Mini Challenge race. The drivers seemed a bit more chilled out this year, however, and while there was some good jostling for position, the racing was friendly enough that the only DNF we saw was a Mini whose front left wheel simply gave way coming out of the Club chicane behind the safety car - a rather bizarre incident. While I still maintain that Brands Hatch has the best views in the country, Thruxton’s grandstands at Club give a good angle on the action, and its banked viewing areas mean you can see well no matter when you arrive or how much you move around. This year I explored a bit further than before, moving past Campbell and Cobb and around towards Segrave and Noble. Watching Formula 4 cars navigate the Campbell-Cobb chicane from just behind the barriers was quite something. The angle reminded me of the segments in Sky’s Formula 1 practice coverage where Martin Brundle stands at different points on the track, observing the variations between drivers’ approaches and watching the weight shift across the wheels as they turn in.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/06/thruxton-btcc-formula-4-2022_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/06/thruxton-btcc-formula-4-2022_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Resident Evil 2 Remake (PS4) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/27/resident-evil-2-remake-ps4-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Resident Evil 2 Remake (PS4) retrospective" /><published>2022-05-27T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-27T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/27/resident-evil-2-remake-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/27/resident-evil-2-remake-ps4-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;My journey through the &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/resident-evil&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; universe continued this month as I picked up 2019’s &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil 2 Remake&lt;/em&gt; on PlayStation 4. There were a lot of these on the shelf at my local preowned video game shop, which I thought was an ominous sign, but I’m pleased to report that Capcom have done a sterling job of extracting the best bits from the 1998 original and bringing them into the 21st century in a very slick package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we get started, you might be wondering - is a long article about a three year-old remake of a 24 year-old game &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; a true retrospective? The label isn’t super important to me, but it’s certainly too late in the day to call this a review, and enough of the soul of the original &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil 2&lt;/em&gt; has been retained to give this piece a retro vibe. If you can think of a better name, let me know. Seriously, I spent way too much time thinking about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;welcome-to-raccoon-city&quot;&gt;Welcome to Raccoon City&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/06/resident-evil-hd-remaster-retrospective&quot;&gt;recently completed the first game&lt;/a&gt;, that was my natural comparison point going in, and some big differences were immediately clear. First, this is a full remake, and it shows. The graphics are up there with the best modern games and we get full cinematic cut scenes that don’t just look like PS2 models with HD textures applied. The flip side of this is that the first game’s gorgeous static backgrounds are gone – but hey, you can’t have everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of static cameras, we now look over the main characters’ shoulders in third person, and oh the things we see from this new perspective. The increased graphical fidelity makes much more gore possible this time out, and the game revels in it, with close-ups of bodies being ripped apart and bits of zombies’ faces being blown off as you shoot them. I don’t think it’s an exaggeration to say this could be the most violent video game I’ve ever played in terms of the detail and volume of blood and guts on display.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remarked that &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; felt like a puzzle game in horror dressing, but its sequel strays further towards the scary end of the spectrum, combining both jump scares and psychological horror. Much of the game is spent exploring dark areas with a torch, dreading whatever might be lurking around the next corner. Hidden zombies will startle you, not least because grabs are harder to avoid, but some of the game’s most effective mechanics - which we’ll cover later - are the ones that build a quiet and persistent sense of dread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-places-and-new-faces&quot;&gt;New places and new faces&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resident Evil 2&lt;/em&gt; gives you the choice of playing as pretty boy police rookie Leon Kennedy (who I chose), or Claire Redfield, younger sister of Chris from the first game. This once again gives you two campaigns that are broadly similar with some different story content. The voice acting is a definite step up from the previous game, but it still has some awkward moments - for example, telling a guy to “hang in there” as the bottom half of his body is ripped off, or the famous delivery of the “horrible things I’ve seen” line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game lacks the original’s unity of place, but has a similar overall structure that has you exploring areas, solving puzzles, and unlocking new rooms to progress, with the occasional boss peppered in. Things start with a semi-tutorial at a petrol station before you move to the police station, which is a substitute for the first game’s mansion. You’ll spend the bulk of the game retracing your steps there before the later game descends into the sewer and the Umbrella lab. It all culminates in an epic final chase with fire and enemies on all sides as you race to escape the self-destructing facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we’re covering the story, Ada Wong is a character worth mentioning. She pops up fairly early on and tells you she’s with the FBI, and is a big presence from there on in - you even play a small gameplay segment as her. She’s consistently cold to Leon, begrudgingly cooperating with him to kill zombies, but then she suddenly kisses him and can’t bear to shoot him when she’s revealed to be a traitor. I’m really not skipping over too much there, either. The sudden changes in their relationship are just plain jarring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fights-with-freaks&quot;&gt;Fights with freaks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, you encounter a variety of enemies along the way, ranging from standard zombies to more agile variants that crawl the ceilings, plant mutants, dogs, and so on. I found even the regular zombies more challenging than in the first game, taking quite a few bullets to down and even then sometimes getting back up or crawling towards me. The move to full 3D means we now get free aim, which adds to the frantic nature of encounters as you line up your shots, and means the terror comes from your own skill and not panic about whether the auto-aim will do what you’re hoping for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also applies to bosses, who are scarier and more difficult to beat than in &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt;. You’ll quickly become well acquainted with the G-virus mutant Birkin, who you’ll fight no fewer than three times over the course of the game. These are generally satisfying battles as you target the orange eyes on his ever-strengthening body. The exception is the Type 2 fight, which traps you with the boss on a tiny platform. No matter what you do, he &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be defeated with a swinging shipping container, which takes an age to arrive after you press the button and kills you instantly if you get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Type 2 is the low point for &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil 2&lt;/em&gt;’s bosses, Mr X is certainly the peak. After a certain point, this unkillable brute roams the police station, drawn to the noise you make by running, shooting zombies, or bursting through doors. When I first encountered him I ran, and it was downright terrifying as it slowly dawned on me that the thudding I was hearing was the sound of his footsteps as he tracked me down. Trying to fly through puzzles while he got closer and closer, aware that he could smash into the room at any moment, is one of those gaming memories that will stay with me forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-icing-on-the-cake&quot;&gt;The icing on the cake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this comes wrapped up in a package that includes exactly the quality of life improvements I was longing for when playing through &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/06/resident-evil-hd-remaster-retrospective&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resident Evil HD Remaster&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. One huge change is the ability to drop items anywhere, which reduces the pain of limited inventory space when you come across a critical item with no slots remaining. Typewriters return as the save mechanism, but you no longer need to collect and spend ribbon, which means you’re not punished for changing your mind about your loadout after you save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From these additions to the beautiful graphics, the detailed 3D environments to the plentiful journals and notes that litter the areas and provide additional backstory, it’s clear that this remake of the second game in the series was put together by people who really cared about what they were making. This even shows in the implementation of features that might seem like gimmicks in lesser titles - for example, the use of the DualShock 4’s built-in speaker for certain actions like unlocking doors is a nice touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resident Evil 2 Remake&lt;/em&gt; is a glossy and carefully constructed game that has earnt a place in my list of favourites. The story and acting can be cheesy, and if hardcore &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; fans’ accounts are to be believed then it’s not entirely consistent with canon, but it’s a well-made rollercoaster ride of a game that you should play just for the experience itself. The tone of the series has certainly shifted towards action-horror here, and it will be intriguing to see where it goes next if and when I pick up the sequel.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="resident-evil" /><category term="horror" /><category term="survival" /><summary type="html">My journey through the Resident Evil universe continued this month as I picked up 2019’s Resident Evil 2 Remake on PlayStation 4. There were a lot of these on the shelf at my local preowned video game shop, which I thought was an ominous sign, but I’m pleased to report that Capcom have done a sterling job of extracting the best bits from the 1998 original and bringing them into the 21st century in a very slick package. Before we get started, you might be wondering - is a long article about a three year-old remake of a 24 year-old game really a true retrospective? The label isn’t super important to me, but it’s certainly too late in the day to call this a review, and enough of the soul of the original Resident Evil 2 has been retained to give this piece a retro vibe. If you can think of a better name, let me know. Seriously, I spent way too much time thinking about this. Welcome to Raccoon City Having recently completed the first game, that was my natural comparison point going in, and some big differences were immediately clear. First, this is a full remake, and it shows. The graphics are up there with the best modern games and we get full cinematic cut scenes that don’t just look like PS2 models with HD textures applied. The flip side of this is that the first game’s gorgeous static backgrounds are gone – but hey, you can’t have everything. Instead of static cameras, we now look over the main characters’ shoulders in third person, and oh the things we see from this new perspective. The increased graphical fidelity makes much more gore possible this time out, and the game revels in it, with close-ups of bodies being ripped apart and bits of zombies’ faces being blown off as you shoot them. I don’t think it’s an exaggeration to say this could be the most violent video game I’ve ever played in terms of the detail and volume of blood and guts on display.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Warzone’s Godzilla v Kong event is better than it sounds</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/20/call-of-duty-warzone-godzilla-v-kong" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Warzone's Godzilla v Kong event is better than it sounds" /><published>2022-05-19T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-19T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/20/call-of-duty-warzone-godzilla-v-kong</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/20/call-of-duty-warzone-godzilla-v-kong">&lt;p&gt;Any semi-regular reader of this blog will know that I’m a fairly frequent critic of &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review&quot;&gt;live services&lt;/a&gt; and games that make their money with microtransactions, so it may come as a surprise that this week’s article is about &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty: Warzone&lt;/em&gt; - and it’s simply about how much fun I’m having.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/warzone-godzilla-v-kong_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compounding my apprehension about the new &lt;em&gt;Godzilla v Kong&lt;/em&gt; event was the skepticism over video games based on films that has been drilled into gamers over decades. More often than not, these games are some of the most generic titles out there, relying on character recognition to recoup their development costs. Put simply, they’re not usually very good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe Operation Monarch’s strength, therefore, is that it’s not a standalone &lt;em&gt;Godzilla v Kong&lt;/em&gt; game. Instead of a quickly thrown together full title, it’s a separate game mode that retains &lt;em&gt;Warzone&lt;/em&gt;’s core gameplay and adds some extra excitement on top by setting two “titans” loose on the map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the off, Godzilla and Kong roam Caldera doing their thing and generally looking scarier than your human enemies. Kong throws rocks and imposes his “wrath”, jumping up and stomping down on anything in his path. Godzilla’s signature attack is his heat ray (it’s coloured more like an ice beam, but whatever), which is equally devastating to anything directly in front of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/warzone-godzilla-v-kong_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s quite fun just to have the titans on the map. They’re constantly roaring, threatening to disrupt your plans with their destructive powers, and just generally looking quite cool on the horizon. And although it’s tangental to your main goals, it feels super cool (and very unlike &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/em&gt;) to pilot a plane and circle them in the air, peppering them with bullets.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are objectives here. Players can collect “intel” by dealing damage to the titans, opening crates, and killing other operators. The intel gives you perks, ranging from familiar items like gas masks and armour vests all the way to something called a “SCREAM device”, which allows you to direct the titans’ signature moves towards any point on the map you wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you couldn’t care less about Godzilla and Kong, the beauty of the event is that it adds some extra spice to the &lt;em&gt;Warzone&lt;/em&gt; formula. Everyone has their own tactics when things get towards the final circle, but the best laid plans can quickly go out the window when you see an incoming ground pound or heat ray barrage pop up on the map right on your location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/warzone-godzilla-v-kong_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The added randomness keeps you on your toes and leads to situations you wouldn’t usually encounter, adding more of a frantic feel as you’re attacked from all angles by the titans and other competing squads. It also means that even if a team secures a building right in the middle of the final circle, they still might not be safe if they have to flee Kong’s wrath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operation Monarch is &lt;em&gt;Warzone&lt;/em&gt; on steroids. It’s a whole lot of fun, and I’d recommend making the most of it before it disappears on 25th May. If you looked at the promotions and shrugged like I did, give it a go - at the very least you’ll come away from a few games with a smile on your face.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="call-of-duty" /><category term="shooters" /><summary type="html">Any semi-regular reader of this blog will know that I’m a fairly frequent critic of live services and games that make their money with microtransactions, so it may come as a surprise that this week’s article is about Call of Duty: Warzone - and it’s simply about how much fun I’m having. Compounding my apprehension about the new Godzilla v Kong event was the skepticism over video games based on films that has been drilled into gamers over decades. More often than not, these games are some of the most generic titles out there, relying on character recognition to recoup their development costs. Put simply, they’re not usually very good. Maybe Operation Monarch’s strength, therefore, is that it’s not a standalone Godzilla v Kong game. Instead of a quickly thrown together full title, it’s a separate game mode that retains Warzone’s core gameplay and adds some extra excitement on top by setting two “titans” loose on the map. From the off, Godzilla and Kong roam Caldera doing their thing and generally looking scarier than your human enemies. Kong throws rocks and imposes his “wrath”, jumping up and stomping down on anything in his path. Godzilla’s signature attack is his heat ray (it’s coloured more like an ice beam, but whatever), which is equally devastating to anything directly in front of him. It’s quite fun just to have the titans on the map. They’re constantly roaring, threatening to disrupt your plans with their destructive powers, and just generally looking quite cool on the horizon. And although it’s tangental to your main goals, it feels super cool (and very unlike Call of Duty) to pilot a plane and circle them in the air, peppering them with bullets.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/warzone-godzilla-v-kong_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/warzone-godzilla-v-kong_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIFA 22 Career Mode: How to scout and develop youth players</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA 22 Career Mode&amp;#58; How to scout and develop youth players" /><published>2022-05-13T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-13T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players">&lt;p&gt;There are different ways to tackle &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;’s Career Mode. Some players prefer to take the Paris Saint-Germain approach and build out a squad of the best players in the world, spending hundreds of millions to secure the top talent. In fact, you might even say that’s what EA seems to encourage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some - myself included - prefer a slower-paced challenge, finding young players with potential and nurturing them through carefully-timed promotion to the senior squad and ample game time with the first team. There’s a lot more going on with this sort of approach, so I’ve put this article together to run through the basics that you need to know to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;refining-your-youth-setup&quot;&gt;Refining your youth setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing you’ll want to do is address the top of your youth academy funnel and hire a decent scout. Head to the youth staff page and assess your current options. The most important factors are their experience rating (as far as I can decipher, this reflects how likely they are to find players) and judgement (how accurate their assessments of players’ abilities are).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/fifa-22-youth-development_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your current scouts are no good, you can always spend some of your transfer budget on a new one. When you’re satisfied with their skills, you need to send them to set up a scouting network. You can choose which country they’re searching in, how long they’re out there for, and select specific traits you want them to look for in a young player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1&quot;&gt;My Career Mode game&lt;/a&gt; is focused on young English players, so I usually send my scout out on long-term assignments in England and leave him to it. If you have different priorities then you might want to mix things up with shorter searches in different countries and with different parameters.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scouting-out-fresh-talent&quot;&gt;Scouting out fresh talent&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a short set-up period, your scouts will begin to deliver monthly updates to your inbox. These reports consist of a list of players with rough estimations of their current and potential abilities (at this point you’re probably seeing why the scout’s judgement rating was so important earlier).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/fifa-22-youth-development_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To filter this list down, I normally start with a baseline potential OVR rating - usually 80 if I’m managing a Premier League side. If a player has no chance of exceeding this lower limit then it’s very unlikely that they’ll ever feature in my first team even if they develop perfectly, so I send them on their way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the upper bounds of a player’s potential are above my threshold then I turn my attention to their minimum potential. If it’s also quite high - say in the mid-70s - then I’ll recruit the youngster right away to see how they develop in my academy. If it’s lower and there’s a risk they’ll be a dud, I’ll leave them on the report so my scout can take a closer look and return with a more accurate assessment of their potential ability next month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;managing-your-youth-squad&quot;&gt;Managing your youth squad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with scouting, you’ll receive monthly updates on your youth squad and over time their OVR will improve and their potential ability will become more accurate. The main use for this report is to check who falls short - if one of your recruits’ potential OVR falls below your minimum threshold, don’t be afraid to let them go and free up space in your youth academy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/fifa-22-youth-development_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a player progresses to an acceptable OVR and plays in a position where he’s likely to get game time, it may be time for a promotion to the senior team to optimise his development. Beware, however, that once a player leaves the youth squad you will lose visibility of his potential, so try not to promote players while their potential OVR range is too wide if you can help it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally a player will essentially force you to promote him. You’ll recieve an email telling you that he’s unsettled, and you face a choice between adding him to your main squad or losing him. If a player is still in my academy then he usually has decent potential (otherwise he’d have been dropped), so my approach is usually to give him a professional contract and then loan him out if he’s not quite good enough to play alongside the first team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;breaking-into-the-first-team&quot;&gt;Breaking into the first team&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the time finally comes, either through judgement or through coercion, make sure that your young players get some decent game time in the first team so they can reach their full potential. I normally treat them as though they have a few more OVR points than they do, filling my bench with youngsters and subbing them on whenever a match is looking stable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/fifa-22-youth-development_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cup matches, which are arguably less important and are more likely to be against lower-level opposition, should be a big opportunity for young players. Consider starting some young talent in the cup - particularly goalkeepers, who aren’t likely candidates to be subbed on during other games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when you try your best, circumstances (or just the sheer number of youth players you’re farming) don’t always allow for everyone to get the minutes they need on the pitch. If a player isn’t playing regularly then don’t be afraid to send them out on loan. The offers that come in always seem to be for loans with the option to buy and the other club will walk away if you try to negotiate, but don’t be put off by this bug - delegating the response to your director of football will allow you to renegotiate a standard loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow this pattern, exposing young players to first-team football via the bench, cup starts, and loans. You should see their OVR increase by a few points per season (you can check exactly how much on the Squad Hub screen). Eventually some will develop enough to earn starting places in your lineup, and maybe - if you’re lucky - in a few seasons’ time a new world superstar will drop out of the bottom end of your youth academy funnel.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">There are different ways to tackle FIFA 22’s Career Mode. Some players prefer to take the Paris Saint-Germain approach and build out a squad of the best players in the world, spending hundreds of millions to secure the top talent. In fact, you might even say that’s what EA seems to encourage. But some - myself included - prefer a slower-paced challenge, finding young players with potential and nurturing them through carefully-timed promotion to the senior squad and ample game time with the first team. There’s a lot more going on with this sort of approach, so I’ve put this article together to run through the basics that you need to know to get started. Refining your youth setup The first thing you’ll want to do is address the top of your youth academy funnel and hire a decent scout. Head to the youth staff page and assess your current options. The most important factors are their experience rating (as far as I can decipher, this reflects how likely they are to find players) and judgement (how accurate their assessments of players’ abilities are). If your current scouts are no good, you can always spend some of your transfer budget on a new one. When you’re satisfied with their skills, you need to send them to set up a scouting network. You can choose which country they’re searching in, how long they’re out there for, and select specific traits you want them to look for in a young player. My Career Mode game is focused on young English players, so I usually send my scout out on long-term assignments in England and leave him to it. If you have different priorities then you might want to mix things up with shorter searches in different countries and with different parameters.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/fifa-22-youth-development_2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/fifa-22-youth-development_2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>