<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-06-18T11:57:46+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Are you saving too much money?</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/18/are-you-saving-too-much-money" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are you saving too much money?" /><published>2023-06-17T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-06-17T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/18/are-you-saving-too-much-money</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/18/are-you-saving-too-much-money">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to money, I’m something like a squirrel. I receive it and I tuck it away for later use, ensuring a more pleasurable future. But I recently heard a convincing argument for spending more in the present to avoid missing out on experiences that may not be possible later on, and thought that was worth exploring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;delaying-gratification-for-too-long&quot;&gt;Delaying gratification for too long&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pdst.fm/e/chrt.fm/track/G454/traffic.megaphone.fm/SIXMSB5490111876.mp3?updated=1686753558&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;This weekend’s episode of Modern Wisdom&lt;/a&gt; featured trader and hedge fund manager Bill Perkins, who was on the podcast to discuss his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Die-Zero-Getting-Your-Money/dp/0358099765/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Die With Zero&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He essentially gave a warning against saving too much money for too long, instead advising listeners to use the resources of health, wealth, and time together to maximise the number of positive life experiences you get to enjoy before you die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His logic here was that by focusing on your bank balance and waiting for retirement to start spending and really enjoying life, you’ll miss out on irreplaceable experiences in the meantime. You’re unlikely to be able to do physically demanding things when you’re old, you can’t do hedonistic things when you’re married with kids, and your kids won’t want you to read bedtime stories to them when they’re teenagers, so you need to prioritise the right things at the right times in your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue, Perkins said, is that many people have blockers to spending money. Either their egos are tied to their wealth, or the habit of saving becomes so ingrained that they lose the mental connection between hard work and subsequent enjoyment, and become drones working jobs they don’t enjoy on the promise of a future reward somewhere over the horizon that may never become a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His advice was to instead treat life like a game of &lt;em&gt;Tetris&lt;/em&gt;, not only selecting the experiences you’d like to live out but also slotting them into the right places where you have the money, time, endurance, and flexibility to make the most of them. Memories pay dividends, he added - living is not just about the moment, but enjoyment in the years afterwards recalling experiences and telling stories.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-money-saving-instinct&quot;&gt;The money saving instinct&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on my own life, I think there is a natural tendency to save every penny that some people have to overcome more than others. I was never poor growing up, but I did come from a working class town, and when I first moved to London I was just about scraping by, considering every purchase in detail and lucky if I had anything left to transfer to my savings account at the end of each month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I got my first corporate job, I suddenly had disposable income, but my instinct was to save as much as I could rather than paying for any luxuries. What if I lost my job? Or I reached a point where my wage stagnated for years? While building some form of financial cushion was undoubtedly a good move, I took this to an extreme and missed out on a lot of experiences in my 20s as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, just as I reached a level of income where I felt comfortable to loosen the purse strings somewhat, the COVID pandemic hit and I was stuck at home in lockdown. I developed anxiety during the long isolation, so even when I started to emerge more in 2022, mundane things like train journeys were absolute ordeals and I really had to push myself to get back out there with everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My struggles in the last few years have given me an increased appreciation of the variety of experiences life has to offer, and since then I’ve been doing my best to say yes to as much as possible. I’ve visited Greece and &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/05/14/lesson-curiosity-japan&quot;&gt;Japan&lt;/a&gt;, and accepted invitations I might have turned down to eat different foods and play new sports and games. This has meant exposing myself to potential public embarrassment - something my anxiety never would have allowed at last year’s levels - but helps me to grow more resilient and generates new memories with my friends and colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;finding-the-golden-mean&quot;&gt;Finding the golden mean&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this relates to one of Aristotle’s ideas, which he explained in &lt;em&gt;The Nicomachean Ethics&lt;/em&gt;. He argued that all possible traits exist along a spectrum, with deficiency and excess at either end and an ideal golden mean in the middle - essentially a more complex version of the saying, “All things in moderation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saving all excess income leads to missed opportunities and experiences, and spending everything you earn on experiences means a less stable future. With that in mind, I intend to hover near the golden mean, maintaining a baseline level of savings, but continuing to embrace chances to try new things as they arrive. As Perkins said, if I don’t live life now, then I may never have a second shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you haven’t already done so, I’d very much recommend listening to &lt;a href=&quot;https://pdst.fm/e/chrt.fm/track/G454/traffic.megaphone.fm/SIXMSB5490111876.mp3?updated=1686753558&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the full episode of Modern Wisdom&lt;/a&gt; featuring Bill Perkins, in which he explains his philosophy on life and approach to balancing health, wealth, and time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="money" /><category term="philosophy" /><summary type="html">When it comes to money, I’m something like a squirrel. I receive it and I tuck it away for later use, ensuring a more pleasurable future. But I recently heard a convincing argument for spending more in the present to avoid missing out on experiences that may not be possible later on, and thought that was worth exploring. Delaying gratification for too long This weekend’s episode of Modern Wisdom featured trader and hedge fund manager Bill Perkins, who was on the podcast to discuss his book Die With Zero. He essentially gave a warning against saving too much money for too long, instead advising listeners to use the resources of health, wealth, and time together to maximise the number of positive life experiences you get to enjoy before you die. His logic here was that by focusing on your bank balance and waiting for retirement to start spending and really enjoying life, you’ll miss out on irreplaceable experiences in the meantime. You’re unlikely to be able to do physically demanding things when you’re old, you can’t do hedonistic things when you’re married with kids, and your kids won’t want you to read bedtime stories to them when they’re teenagers, so you need to prioritise the right things at the right times in your life. The issue, Perkins said, is that many people have blockers to spending money. Either their egos are tied to their wealth, or the habit of saving becomes so ingrained that they lose the mental connection between hard work and subsequent enjoyment, and become drones working jobs they don’t enjoy on the promise of a future reward somewhere over the horizon that may never become a reality. His advice was to instead treat life like a game of Tetris, not only selecting the experiences you’d like to live out but also slotting them into the right places where you have the money, time, endurance, and flexibility to make the most of them. Memories pay dividends, he added - living is not just about the moment, but enjoyment in the years afterwards recalling experiences and telling stories.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Starfield could be the fix for The Outer Worlds… and Fallout 4</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/14/starfield-fix-the-outer-worlds-fallout-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starfield could be the fix for The Outer Worlds... and Fallout 4" /><published>2023-06-14T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-06-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/14/starfield-fix-the-outer-worlds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/14/starfield-fix-the-outer-worlds-fallout-4">&lt;p&gt;There was a time in about 2018 when I thought &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/the-outer-worlds&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Outer Worlds&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; would be the fix for &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fallout&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fallout 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That doesn’t mean that I &lt;em&gt;hated&lt;/em&gt; Bethesda’s most recent “proper” game - I completed two lengthy playthroughs, one on release and one during the COVID pandemic - but for whatever reason it just didn’t grab me in the same way that old RPGs like &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/elder-scrolls&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oblivion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;watered-down-wasteland&quot;&gt;Watered-down wasteland&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, as I read more analysis, I began to understand why that was. While &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/elder-scrolls&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fallout&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fallout 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and other games had left me to forge my own way through their worlds, &lt;em&gt;Fallout 4&lt;/em&gt; let me craft my character’s &lt;em&gt;appearance&lt;/em&gt;, but didn’t offer half of their flexibility when it came to their &lt;em&gt;story&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/starfield_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt; also suffered from this issue to a degree, of course, casting the player as the “chosen one” Dragonborn, but it was much easier to ignore. &lt;em&gt;Fallout 4&lt;/em&gt; not only had a character-defining main quest, but featured worse side quest writing, and mismatched dialogue menu options and response tones, and in voicing the main character presented them as a much more developed individual in-game, leaving little to the player’s imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the main quest stole a lot of the focus away from the world. Not only did it seem there were fewer side quests, but they were less remarkable in their content than those in previous games, and there was less potential for interesting stories since most quests focused on gunplay, rather than talking your way out of trouble. It was enough to make you yearn for the richness of the Mojave Wasteland (sans nuclear winter).&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-pale-imitation&quot;&gt;A pale imitation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when Obsidian, the developer behind &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fallout&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fallout: New Vegas&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, announced that it was working on a new &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/rpg&quot;&gt;RPG&lt;/a&gt;, my excitement hit fever pitch. Their prior work included once of the most roleplay-friendly games and immersive worlds of all time, so surely a game of their own would restore all the features we loved and blow the watered-down &lt;em&gt;Fallout&lt;/em&gt; out of the water?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer was… not really. &lt;em&gt;The Outer Worlds&lt;/em&gt; was a game of above-average quality, but it never really captured my attention and I didn’t get anywhere close to completing the story. The structure - a series of hubs on different planets - obstructed any chance of recapturing the “man against the world”, choose-your-own-adventure feel of its predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest issue for me, however, was the tone. &lt;em&gt;The Outer Worlds&lt;/em&gt; felt like it was written by a sixth-form politics student, a game-shaped manifestation of the Twitter accounts that repeatedly yell “Isn’t capitalism bad?” without acknowledging any of its benefits or offering a viable alternative. This also meant that most quest decision points offered only saintly good or comically bad options, with no moral grey area or tough dilemmas to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining third of &lt;em&gt;The Outer Worlds&lt;/em&gt;’ personality was… quirkiness, to a degree never seen before in Bethesda games, despite their occasional oddball moments. Somehow Obsidian managed to crank this up to eleven while also sanitising it was far as possible, culminating in a bland, jokey atmosphere reminiscent of the modern Marvel movie formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-ray-of-hope&quot;&gt;A ray of hope&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;em&gt;Starfield&lt;/em&gt;. I know it’s a marketing cliche at this point, but watching the preview at the weekend I really felt that thrill of old Bethesda games again, like I could really go anywhere and do anything in this game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonally, the new game looks to be just what you’d expect from the makers of &lt;em&gt;The Elder Scrolls&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Fallout&lt;/em&gt;. That is, it’s primarily set in a serious world with serious characters, with just the occasional quirky beat on the side - the return of the Adoring Fan as an optional trait-based follower, for example. This helps massively with immersion, as unless I choose to see humorous content it looks like I can count on &lt;em&gt;Starfield&lt;/em&gt; to play it straight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Size and freedom is always an issue with space games, as the nature of space exploration means areas must be broken up between planets. How can you provide enough planets to simulate a region of space without them being procedurally generated and empty? The jury will be out in September, but somehow Bethesda appears to found a happy middle ground between the sparse vastness of &lt;em&gt;No Man’s Sky&lt;/em&gt; and the tightly-packed &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt; map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will the gunplay be like? Will planets feel repetitive? What exactly will the ratio of hand-built content to algorithmically generated areas be? How cumbersome will travel between planets feel? There are a lot of open questions ahead of &lt;em&gt;Starfield&lt;/em&gt;’s launch, but I’m hoping Bethesda has combined its experience with fan feedback on recent games and produced that rare special RPG - after all, with the increasingly casual changes introduced in &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Fallout 4&lt;/em&gt;, it may be the last chance many players give it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-future-is-bright-hopefully&quot;&gt;The future is bright (hopefully)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Todd Howard so enthusiastically reminded us during &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uMOPoAq5vIA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the &lt;em&gt;Starfield&lt;/em&gt; deep dive&lt;/a&gt;, this is the first new world Bethesda has created in decades, and a new subgenre for the studio, so even beyond the usual launch bugs that come with a game so complex, there’s a lot that could go wrong. But from what we’ve seen, it feels like some lessons have been learnt and the balance is there, so I’m cautiously optimistic ahead of 6th September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More generally, this is the most enthusiastic I’ve been about gaming for years. Between &lt;em&gt;Starfield&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;Metal Gear Solid 3&lt;/em&gt; remake, and some of the smaller games shown off over trailer season, it feels like there’s a healthier vein of larger studios and publishers shrugging off &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/10/14/why-is-everything-a-live-service&quot;&gt;the live service-obsessed, microtransaction-filled, multiplayer-first trend&lt;/a&gt; of recent years and investing in the high-quality single-player games we’ve all been waiting for.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="starfield" /><category term="rpg" /><category term="the-outer-worlds" /><category term="fallout" /><category term="elder-scrolls" /><summary type="html">There was a time in about 2018 when I thought The Outer Worlds would be the fix for Fallout 4. That doesn’t mean that I hated Bethesda’s most recent “proper” game - I completed two lengthy playthroughs, one on release and one during the COVID pandemic - but for whatever reason it just didn’t grab me in the same way that old RPGs like Oblivion did. Watered-down wasteland Over time, as I read more analysis, I began to understand why that was. While Skyrim, Fallout 3, and other games had left me to forge my own way through their worlds, Fallout 4 let me craft my character’s appearance, but didn’t offer half of their flexibility when it came to their story. Skyrim also suffered from this issue to a degree, of course, casting the player as the “chosen one” Dragonborn, but it was much easier to ignore. Fallout 4 not only had a character-defining main quest, but featured worse side quest writing, and mismatched dialogue menu options and response tones, and in voicing the main character presented them as a much more developed individual in-game, leaving little to the player’s imagination. Additionally, the main quest stole a lot of the focus away from the world. Not only did it seem there were fewer side quests, but they were less remarkable in their content than those in previous games, and there was less potential for interesting stories since most quests focused on gunplay, rather than talking your way out of trouble. It was enough to make you yearn for the richness of the Mojave Wasteland (sans nuclear winter).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/06/starfield_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/06/starfield_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why do we believe morality is in decline?</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/10/why-we-believe-morality-in-decline" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why do we believe morality is in decline?" /><published>2023-06-10T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-06-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/10/why-we-think-morality-in-decline</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/10/why-we-believe-morality-in-decline">&lt;p&gt;It’s a little embarrassing to admit it publicly, but I sometimes suffer from the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/lewronggeneration/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;le wrong generation&lt;/a&gt;” syndrome that seems to plague online comments sections. A little nostalgia is healthy, but occasionally I bring myself down with the thought that I could have lived in a generally more friendly and pleasant era than the one I inhabit, which isn’t productive at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;are-things-really-getting-worse&quot;&gt;Are things really getting worse?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine my intrigue then, when I stumbled across an article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.experimental-history.com/p/the-illusion-of-moral-decline&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the illusion of moral decline&lt;/a&gt; by Adam Mastroianni this week. In it, he provides the figures that show that people believe morality is in decline, people have &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; believed that morality is in decline, and that by objective measures morality hasn’t actually declined at all - if anything, it may have improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This begs the question: If things are getting better, why do we always think they’re getting worse? Mastroianni’s article offers several possible reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People just say that morality is in decline when asked because they think it makes them look more moral personally&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People are nicer to you when you’re a kid and therefore seem to get meaner when you grow up and they treat you like an adult&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People hear cherry-picked stories about how lovely the past was from relatives, television series, and films&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People think younger generations are less moral than they were because they are biased to forget immoral things they did when young&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main theory put forward in the article is that people pay more attention to negative information, but memories of positive things last longer. Therefore the present seems worse than it is, and the past seems better than it was, misleading us to believe morality is in decline.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;additional-factors&quot;&gt;Additional factors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with Mastrianni’s points (as I should - he’s a proper social psychologist with statistics to back him up and everything), but his article also got me thinking about additional elements that might be contributing. While natural biases certainly play a big part, I also think there are environmental factors in the modern world that amplify the effect of our tendency to believe the present is worse than it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;were-shown-more-immorality&quot;&gt;We’re shown more immorality&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From real-life horrors to disturbing fiction, it’s a lot easier to come into contact with immoral content in 2023. It’s not unusual to encounter terrifying or gory images on social media, the 24/7 news cycle is always hungry for new negative stories, and there are any number serial killer documentaries available on demand on your favourite streaming site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the realm of the arts, we now casually watch series that would never get made decades ago. I can turn on &lt;em&gt;Yellowjackets&lt;/em&gt; and see people doing horrific things (no spoilers), &lt;em&gt;Breaking Bad&lt;/em&gt; was about a brutal drug lord, and Netflix even made a series about Jeffrey Dahmer. I’ve been reading St Augustine’s &lt;em&gt;Confessions&lt;/em&gt;, and even back in the fourth century he was writing about how he felt he absorbed negativity from drama into his soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even taking a step back down the morality scale, it’s easy to see how the internet could turn us all into pessimists. At one time porn would have meant a dirty video or magazine your friend found - now it’s thousands of women flaunting themselves on social media to advertise their OnlyFans accounts. And how many arguments would you see or get into in the 1990s? In 2023, I can open my phone at any time and read a Twitter dispute that the participants would like never have in real life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;we-believe-more-things-are-immoral&quot;&gt;We believe more things are immoral&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I dive in, there’s a point to be made around the word “immoral”. Somebody answering a survey might not necessarily have to believe that people have become more sinful or evil to respond that morality is in decline. They could also have fewer positive experiences with others, or see others express more views that they personally disagree with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, increasing polarisation in politics (and other arenas) is a likely contributor to the impression of immorality - and this looks to be supported by a spike after 2016 in some of Mastrianni’s graphs. Speaking in US terms, Democrats and Republicans used to be respectful rivals - now they both see each other as a “threat to democracy” and their country itself, to a level where it’s almost become a meme for social media users not to be able to endure a Thanksgiving dinner with relatives from the opposing camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US has always been split almost 50/50 politically, so even if you believe one party to be immoral, the level of immorality hasn’t really changed - it just seems the rhetoric has reached a level where people are much more sensitive to others who have views incompatible with theirs, and therefore might be more likely to &lt;em&gt;view&lt;/em&gt; (and report) them as immoral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;more-immoral-people-are-getting-caught&quot;&gt;More immoral people are getting caught&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decades ago, it was easier to be invisibly immoral. Without CCTV and DNA analysis, it is likely that a greater number of criminals went undetected. Without the internet, the widest reach anybody’s unsavoury views could muster depended on how loudly they could yell in the town square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty standard example of the need to consider the causes &lt;em&gt;behind&lt;/em&gt; statistics. If more murderers are going to jail, that &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; mean there are more murders, but it could also mean there is more justice being dealt. If more people seem to be saying objectionable things, that &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; mean there are more people with these beliefs, or it could just mean they have an easier way to reach more people - and get called out - than before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we’re &lt;em&gt;seeing&lt;/em&gt; more people get caught. Once upon a time, a local murderer’s arrest would be reported in the newspaper, and if you missed that day’s issue or television bulletin then you’d likely miss the story. Now these news stories are run 24/7 on television, go viral on social media, are pushed to our phones as notifications, and are available forever online - so it’s easy to feel like there are more of these stories around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you’ve made it this far without doing so, I’d really recommend you take the time to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.experimental-history.com/p/the-illusion-of-moral-decline&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;read the original article&lt;/a&gt;. It’s far better researched and more scientifically backed than my two cents are.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="philosophy" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">It’s a little embarrassing to admit it publicly, but I sometimes suffer from the “le wrong generation” syndrome that seems to plague online comments sections. A little nostalgia is healthy, but occasionally I bring myself down with the thought that I could have lived in a generally more friendly and pleasant era than the one I inhabit, which isn’t productive at all. Are things really getting worse? Imagine my intrigue then, when I stumbled across an article on the illusion of moral decline by Adam Mastroianni this week. In it, he provides the figures that show that people believe morality is in decline, people have always believed that morality is in decline, and that by objective measures morality hasn’t actually declined at all - if anything, it may have improved. This begs the question: If things are getting better, why do we always think they’re getting worse? Mastroianni’s article offers several possible reasons: People just say that morality is in decline when asked because they think it makes them look more moral personally People are nicer to you when you’re a kid and therefore seem to get meaner when you grow up and they treat you like an adult People hear cherry-picked stories about how lovely the past was from relatives, television series, and films People think younger generations are less moral than they were because they are biased to forget immoral things they did when young The main theory put forward in the article is that people pay more attention to negative information, but memories of positive things last longer. Therefore the present seems worse than it is, and the past seems better than it was, misleading us to believe morality is in decline.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A lesson in curiosity from Japan</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/05/14/lesson-curiosity-japan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A lesson in curiosity from Japan" /><published>2023-05-14T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-05-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/05/14/lesson-curiosity-japan</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/05/14/lesson-curiosity-japan">&lt;p&gt;I recently returned from a couple of weeks out in Japan, and while I saw and experienced some amazing places, sights, and foods, I think the thing that will stay with me from this trip is more of an attitude I hope I will be able to retain long after the end of my holiday and absorb into my own life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/japan.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that always strikes me when I visit Japan is the level of curiosity on display for niche subjects. One example of this can be seen on TV every day - each area of the country has its own specialties, and on any channel you can find presenters visiting little local restaurants, cafes, shops, and so on to try them and speak to their creators about how they are made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;positivity-personified&quot;&gt;Positivity personified&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my most recent visit, I was lucky enough to see this outlook personified. In the buildup to my trip, I’d asked if a friend of a friend could help me get tickets to an event. As it turned out, he didn’t just buy a ticket, but also came with me and invited me to hang out with this friends the day before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We couldn’t communicate fluently (my Japanese and his English are both very basic) but we had a great time together. I think more than anything he was delighted that I’d taken an interest in one of his passions, and as we departed he gave me a very sentimental goodbye gift with a handwritten thank you message, which was more touching than I’d been expecting.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially it made me smile, but over time I considered it more deeply, thinking about the place it had come from, and realised how jaded modern life has made me. Especially since the dawn of the internet, life has me on high alert, always wary of being taken advantage of, and always conscious that no matter what I do, there will always be somebody better out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when I was on the receiving end of such kindness in Japan, my main concern was worry about whether my reactions might seem rude or ungrateful. It’s like the anxiety instilled in me by all those online horror stories, arguments, and comparisons has adjusted my natural response to focus on damage control, rather than gratitude or pure enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-have-control&quot;&gt;You have control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, one of the podcast episodes waiting in my queue when I got home was the dating expert Matthew Hussey &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dR-plImpf_8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;speaking on Modern Wisdom&lt;/a&gt;. In a discussion about dating trends, he shared a poignant message that can essentially be summed up as: “Your actions dictate your life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a part with relevance spanning well beyond dating, Hussey discouraged listeners from focusing on macro-level issues. An obsession with politics and global trends will affect your outlook and hold you back, when in fact your personal outcomes might be entirely different. And even if things do turn out the way the statistics suggest, you have more control than you think, and adjusting your actions can help to bring about different results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His advice was to approach life with curiosity, asking questions like “How can this work out?”, “How can I be impressed by this person?”, and “What can I learn here?” Having read many books to overcome (or at least heavily reduce) anxiety in the last year, it immediately struck me that these questions all seek the positive, rather than fearing negative outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps there’s some confirmation bias at play here, but to me, this seems to match what I learnt from my new friend. His gift now sits on a shelf in my flat, and I hope that long after the aura of my holiday as faded away it will still serve as a reminder in my daily life to stay grateful and curious.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="travel" /><category term="japan" /><category term="philosophy" /><summary type="html">I recently returned from a couple of weeks out in Japan, and while I saw and experienced some amazing places, sights, and foods, I think the thing that will stay with me from this trip is more of an attitude I hope I will be able to retain long after the end of my holiday and absorb into my own life. One thing that always strikes me when I visit Japan is the level of curiosity on display for niche subjects. One example of this can be seen on TV every day - each area of the country has its own specialties, and on any channel you can find presenters visiting little local restaurants, cafes, shops, and so on to try them and speak to their creators about how they are made. Positivity personified On my most recent visit, I was lucky enough to see this outlook personified. In the buildup to my trip, I’d asked if a friend of a friend could help me get tickets to an event. As it turned out, he didn’t just buy a ticket, but also came with me and invited me to hang out with this friends the day before. We couldn’t communicate fluently (my Japanese and his English are both very basic) but we had a great time together. I think more than anything he was delighted that I’d taken an interest in one of his passions, and as we departed he gave me a very sentimental goodbye gift with a handwritten thank you message, which was more touching than I’d been expecting.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/05/japan.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/05/japan.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Panic! at the Disco – Viva Las Vengeance review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/04/23/panic-at-the-disco-viva-las-vengeance-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Panic! at the Disco &amp;#8211; Viva Las Vengeance review" /><published>2023-04-23T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-23T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/04/23/viva-las-vengeance-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/04/23/panic-at-the-disco-viva-las-vengeance-review">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viva Las Vengeance&lt;/em&gt; is perhaps the greatest album ever to have almost completely passed me by, and I don’t think I’m alone in that. It was only via a coincidental search that I caught the titular single and Middle of a Breakup on Panic! at the Disco’s YouTube channel, and there seemed to be very little fanfare in the buildup to the album’s August 2022 release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/viva-las-vengeance_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I did realise the record was out, I listened through it exactly once on Spotify, my expectations fairly low given the more pop-focused direction of its predecessor, &lt;em&gt;Pray for the Wicked&lt;/em&gt;. Maybe I was in the wrong mood or too distracted, but I didn’t think much of it, and skipped on tickets for the tour when I saw Brandon Urie was playing the album in full at gigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How foolish I was. In mid-April 2023, I spotted an article from earlier in the year that said that Panic! at the Disco were no more, with Urie having wound down the project to focus on his family. In a mournful mood (&lt;em&gt;Pretty. Odd.&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Death of a Bachelor&lt;/em&gt; are two of my favourite albums), I revisited &lt;em&gt;Viva Las Vengeance&lt;/em&gt; to see if anything clicked, or if I could piece together anything about his state of mind when writing and recording it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I got beyond the two opening singles, I was entranced. Far from the last record’s bland pop, &lt;em&gt;Viva Las Vengeance&lt;/em&gt; is deliberately recorded as a tribute to 1970s rock, and in that sense almost serves as a sequel to &lt;em&gt;Pretty. Odd.&lt;/em&gt;’s 1960s tones. While there’s plenty of variety, these influences are most apparent in the Queen-style harmonies and Brian May-inspired solos.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the benefit of hindsight, lyrics about sex and partners begin to look more like metaphors for Urie’s relationship with fame, the music industry, and Panic! itself. Look below the surface and there are allusions to his love-hate feelings for his station in life and ponderings about what might have been had he never been thrust into the limelight. If you think this sounds like self-pity, sometimes it is, but it never outstays its welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, &lt;em&gt;Viva Las Vengeance&lt;/em&gt; is a grower. What at first appears to be surface-level showmanship and derivative composition shows greater depth the more you listen. If this does turn out to be Panic! at the Disco’s last album - and it appears it will be, at least for the moment - then we should be thankful that the final release expanded their top two to a top three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;track-by-track&quot;&gt;Track by track&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Viva Las Vengeance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The opener sets the mood for the album, with a feeling that Urie is resigned to giving in to the pressures on him (“shut up and go to bed”). He’s not going out without a bang, though, as referenced by both the song’s final lyrics and the screaming falsetto with which they’re delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Middle of a Breakup&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Energetic, catchy, and the pick of the album’s singles for me. My theory is that what initially felt like a typical Panic! sexual theme (“make-up sex in the middle of a breakup”) may actually be referring to the joy of performing shows for fans even while falling out of love with the music industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Don’t Let the Light Go Out&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As slow and emotional as the album gets, with Urie expressing his gratitude for a partner that challenges him in all the right ways. Heartfelt, with a nice buildup, although the “heavy machinery” line is a little clunky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Local God&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Probably the most interesting song on the album lyrically, as Urie appears to imagine what his life might have been like if he hadn’t become famous. A pleasant change of pace with some nice guitar work in the middle eight as he wholesomely muses on “teaching little kids how to rock and roll”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Star Spangled Banner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A stadium anthem with a chant-like chorus and jazzy, uptempo verses telling stories that seem to hark back to Urie’s teenage years. This nostalgic reflection on his and the band’s beginnings will be a recurring theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. God Killed Rock and Roll&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If the album’s Queen influences weren’t obvious enough elsewhere, Panic! really hit the nail on the head here with some piano sections that sound like they’re ripped straight from Bohemian Rhapsody. Urie’s voice once again steals the show with the refrain, full of rock history references.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Say It Louder&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Feels like an interlude between two halves of the album, and serves as a flip side to Local God as Urie takes a moment to revel in Panic!’s success. In retrospect, the slow middle section about committing a rock show to memory reads like a mourning of the parts of the lifestyle he does enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Sugar Soaker&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lifts the mood as probably the most fun song on the record, even if it lacks the depth of many others. This upbeat, riff-based track has call-and-response verses before hitting a lively, catchy chorus that show off Urie’s vocal acumen with a clever chord switchout the second time round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Something About Maggie&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This track almost feels like a little tribute to &lt;em&gt;Pretty. Odd.&lt;/em&gt; in the middle of the album, complete with some familiar-sounding horns in the latter stages. Some lyrics in the verses could potentially be read as an acknowledgment of long-time fans’ criticisms of Panic!’s last, poppier album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Sad Clown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Almost certainly evidence that Urie knew he was quitting well before the public announcement. “Leave me alone,” he screams, amongst lyrics alluding to disillusionment with endless performances and online criticism. The verse melody and It’s My Life-style riff are personal highlights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11. All By Yourself&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A slower number that I think deserved to be the final, farewell song. The lyrics speak to the universal experience of feeling down and locking yourself in your room to listen to a record, feeling that the artist is speaking directly to you and inspiring you to get back on your feet and achieve something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12. Do It to Death&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If I were to point to a weak point on the album, it’s probably this last song, which is just a little too repetitive for my tastes. The verses the most interesting segments, but make up on a small fraction of the track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5/5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="panic-at-the-disco" /><category term="guitar" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">Viva Las Vengeance is perhaps the greatest album ever to have almost completely passed me by, and I don’t think I’m alone in that. It was only via a coincidental search that I caught the titular single and Middle of a Breakup on Panic! at the Disco’s YouTube channel, and there seemed to be very little fanfare in the buildup to the album’s August 2022 release. When I did realise the record was out, I listened through it exactly once on Spotify, my expectations fairly low given the more pop-focused direction of its predecessor, Pray for the Wicked. Maybe I was in the wrong mood or too distracted, but I didn’t think much of it, and skipped on tickets for the tour when I saw Brandon Urie was playing the album in full at gigs. How foolish I was. In mid-April 2023, I spotted an article from earlier in the year that said that Panic! at the Disco were no more, with Urie having wound down the project to focus on his family. In a mournful mood (Pretty. Odd. and Death of a Bachelor are two of my favourite albums), I revisited Viva Las Vengeance to see if anything clicked, or if I could piece together anything about his state of mind when writing and recording it. Once I got beyond the two opening singles, I was entranced. Far from the last record’s bland pop, Viva Las Vengeance is deliberately recorded as a tribute to 1970s rock, and in that sense almost serves as a sequel to Pretty. Odd.’s 1960s tones. While there’s plenty of variety, these influences are most apparent in the Queen-style harmonies and Brian May-inspired solos.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/04/viva-las-vengeance_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/04/viva-las-vengeance_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Menu review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/03/18/the-menu-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Menu review" /><published>2023-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/03/18/the-menu-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/03/18/the-menu-review">&lt;p&gt;I’m very glad I didn’t go to see &lt;em&gt;The Menu&lt;/em&gt; at the cinema. Not because it’s a bad film, but because as somebody who suffers from intermittent anxiety,  visiting a restaurant can sometimes be quite a tense experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/the-menu_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will I like the food? If I don’t, should I eat it anyway? Will I seem uncultured if I don’t recognise the more exotic menu items? Are the waiting staff secretly judging me based on our brief interactions or overheard comments? &lt;em&gt;The Menu&lt;/em&gt; takes these anxieties, which I’m sure are common to some degree amongst much of the population, and cranks the dial up to 11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dinner-is-served&quot;&gt;Dinner is served&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relatively mundane opening sees a group of customers pay $1,250 a head to visit an exclusive restaurant on an island, but even as they tuck in to their first courses, there are glances and comments that set off those internal alarm bells. It really makes for quite uncomfortable viewing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the guests are an obsessive foodie and his date, a restaurant critic, an actor, and a group of fintech bros. It feels like a very &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/01/13/glass-onion-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; kind of group. For the first third of the film we watch them tour the island and eat, with a looming sense of dread (owed to an expertly creepy performance from Hong Chau as the maitre d’, Elsa) and some very sharp comedic writing.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, like &lt;em&gt;Triangle of Sadness&lt;/em&gt; (which at some point I’ll see if I remember enough of to write a review), &lt;em&gt;The Menu&lt;/em&gt; takes a lavish, exclusive experience that most people could only dream of enjoying and takes it completely off the rails. To its credit, &lt;em&gt;unlike&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Triangle of Sadness&lt;/em&gt;, the writing maintains its edge after this point and the second half is not entirely predictable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;threading-the-needle&quot;&gt;Threading the needle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trailer made it look like the film would end in simple bloodshed, but although there is some action and slashing involved, I can assure you that it retains its expertise in making you shift awkwardly in your seat throughout. In fact, it takes a huge amount of skill to blend psychological horror and dining cringe to such a degree while maintaining a natural pacing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particular credit goes to Ralph Fiennes, whose character Julian Slowik teeters on the border between gentleman and madman, having quite reasonable conversations with his guests one moment and asking the unthinkable of them the next. In many ways, he makes the film, balancing the needle at just the right point between comedy and thriller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing &lt;em&gt;The Menu&lt;/em&gt; has a knack for is giving you hope before snatching it away - with a dash of wit to stop the mood from feeling too sinister. Just when it appears to be heading for a ridiculous ending - and the eventual denouement is still its weakest element - it changes course yet again. A classic? Maybe not. But &lt;em&gt;The Menu&lt;/em&gt; is well worth two hours of your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;4/5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="films" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">I’m very glad I didn’t go to see The Menu at the cinema. Not because it’s a bad film, but because as somebody who suffers from intermittent anxiety, visiting a restaurant can sometimes be quite a tense experience. Will I like the food? If I don’t, should I eat it anyway? Will I seem uncultured if I don’t recognise the more exotic menu items? Are the waiting staff secretly judging me based on our brief interactions or overheard comments? The Menu takes these anxieties, which I’m sure are common to some degree amongst much of the population, and cranks the dial up to 11. Dinner is served The relatively mundane opening sees a group of customers pay $1,250 a head to visit an exclusive restaurant on an island, but even as they tuck in to their first courses, there are glances and comments that set off those internal alarm bells. It really makes for quite uncomfortable viewing. Among the guests are an obsessive foodie and his date, a restaurant critic, an actor, and a group of fintech bros. It feels like a very Knives Out kind of group. For the first third of the film we watch them tour the island and eat, with a looming sense of dread (owed to an expertly creepy performance from Hong Chau as the maitre d’, Elsa) and some very sharp comedic writing.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/03/the-menu_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/03/the-menu_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons in management from Jose Mourinho</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/03/12/jose-mourinho-management" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons in management from Jose Mourinho" /><published>2023-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/03/12/jose-mourinho-management</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/03/12/jose-mourinho-management">&lt;p&gt;Apologies for the near two-month gap between articles. Some changes in my personal life required my attention, but things are more settled now and updates should come more regularly - albeit with &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/01/08/what-to-expect-tsp-2023&quot;&gt;a slightly different flavour&lt;/a&gt; than before, and more variety in the subject matter I’ll be covering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest artefact to catch my attention is Patrick Barclay’s book &lt;em&gt;Mourinho: Further Anatomy of a Winner&lt;/em&gt;. As a Chelsea fan, Jose holds a special place in my heart despite his subsequent spells at Manchester United and Spurs, and his special relationship with his players and media mind games have always made him an interesting figure beyond mere club allegiance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book has only been updated as far as Chelsea’s 2015 Premier League title success, so there’s no coverage of Mourinho’s recent, more turbulent managerial stints, but it still provided some fascinating insights from the perspectives of both the press and the people who knew him best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;man-management&quot;&gt;Man management&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recruitment is a key part of football - especially for a manager at Chelsea or Real Madrid - but something that shone through clearly is Mourinho’s attention to individuals’ progression. Take this account from Joe Cole, who faced a tough start at Chelsea, but later showed dramatic improvement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“His criticism is always constructive - he’ll always sit me down and talk about my game and what he wants me to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mourinho was always on the lookout for those who wanted to learn, and was a firm believer that players are most likely to reach their potential when they are open to advice, rather than just relying on their natural ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-supportive-presence&quot;&gt;A supportive presence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mourinho was often described as a kind of “big brother” to his players, capable of being stern when needed, but often behaving as though he was one of them, trading jokes and joining in with their wild celebrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But his impact went beyond the squad, and he had a reputation for being friendly with everybody he met, including stewards and ball boys - even when playing away at opponents’ stadiums. When he initially parted ways with Chelsea in 2007, many around the club were reportedly distraught.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, even the less savoury side of Mourinho’s character - the wild accusations made against opponents and officials, for example - appears to stem from a desire to take one for the team. These moments would usually occur after poor performances, and meant that the headlines would often be about his remarks rather than what happened on the pitch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forward-as-one&quot;&gt;Forward as one&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a similar vein, Mourinho always strove for an inclusive dressing room. He wanted all his players to love and trust each other, reportedly even going as far as to mandate that the entire squad should eat together at the same table to preserve unity and prevent the formation of cliques within the club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mourinho always wanted to ensure that his team was performing as a collective - not relying on a few talented individuals - and the attention he paid to the entire squad meant that, somewhat unsually, even fringe players who struggled for first team minutes often spoke highly of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such was his focus on team spirit, in fact, that Mourinho reportedly didn’t even give the final team talk before most matches. Instead, he would give his directions earlier in the day, and a different player would be responsible for giving the last, rousing pre-game speech each week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inspiring-confidence&quot;&gt;Inspiring confidence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s not to say that Mourinho himself couldn’t motivate his men. One figure interviewed (unfortunately I didn’t note who) said that a good coach “must make his men feel big, not small”, and that’s precisely what he did. Here’s John Terry, for example, on Chelsea’s culture during the seasons between 2004 and 2006 when they won back-to-back titles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When you’ve got a manager drumming it into you every day that you are the best… it rubs off on the players and we go out there believing it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chelsea didn’t come from nowhere when Roman Abramovich arrived, but those seasons were the start of a period of domestic dominance. Mourinho’s approach here reminds me of the old saying, “Dress for the job you want, not the job you have” - only here he was mentally dressing his players for success. And given his track record, you can only say that it worked.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="football" /><category term="business" /><category term="managment" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">Apologies for the near two-month gap between articles. Some changes in my personal life required my attention, but things are more settled now and updates should come more regularly - albeit with a slightly different flavour than before, and more variety in the subject matter I’ll be covering. The latest artefact to catch my attention is Patrick Barclay’s book Mourinho: Further Anatomy of a Winner. As a Chelsea fan, Jose holds a special place in my heart despite his subsequent spells at Manchester United and Spurs, and his special relationship with his players and media mind games have always made him an interesting figure beyond mere club allegiance. The book has only been updated as far as Chelsea’s 2015 Premier League title success, so there’s no coverage of Mourinho’s recent, more turbulent managerial stints, but it still provided some fascinating insights from the perspectives of both the press and the people who knew him best. Man management Recruitment is a key part of football - especially for a manager at Chelsea or Real Madrid - but something that shone through clearly is Mourinho’s attention to individuals’ progression. Take this account from Joe Cole, who faced a tough start at Chelsea, but later showed dramatic improvement: “His criticism is always constructive - he’ll always sit me down and talk about my game and what he wants me to do.” Mourinho was always on the lookout for those who wanted to learn, and was a firm believer that players are most likely to reach their potential when they are open to advice, rather than just relying on their natural ability. A supportive presence Mourinho was often described as a kind of “big brother” to his players, capable of being stern when needed, but often behaving as though he was one of them, trading jokes and joining in with their wild celebrations. But his impact went beyond the squad, and he had a reputation for being friendly with everybody he met, including stewards and ball boys - even when playing away at opponents’ stadiums. When he initially parted ways with Chelsea in 2007, many around the club were reportedly distraught.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Glass Onion review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/13/glass-onion-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Glass Onion review" /><published>2023-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/13/glass-onion-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/13/glass-onion-review">&lt;p&gt;Just before Christmas 2022, Netflix released &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt;, the next film in the &lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt; series. Expecting another clever, witty mystery from Rian Johnson I sat down to watch it over the holiday period, but was disappointed to find it did not deliver anything close to the quality of its predecessor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/glass-onion_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before anybody takes this article the wrong way, I’ll start by saying this: &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt; is a good film. It looks great, the mystery is intriguing in part, there’s some enjoyable dialogue (particularly from Daniel Craig), and it kept me more engaged from start to finish than most modern releases do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt; is not even close to being &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; good as &lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt;. While there a number of reasons for this, in this article I’ll focus on what I think are the two biggest problems (with &lt;strong&gt;plenty of spoilers&lt;/strong&gt; along the way, so I advise that you actually watch the film before reading any further).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;intro-and-setup&quot;&gt;Intro and setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things start out promisingly enough. A bunch of prominent people receive puzzle boxes containing invitations to a billionaire’s private island, where it appears he’ll be hosting a murder mystery event. Given the genre, it’s clear something will go wrong, so from the start you’re keen to see what it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These opening scenes are very heavy on comedic lines, which makes the tone a little odd, but &lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt; also subverted some of the genre’s conventions, so it’s not necessarily surprising. Lastly, we see Benoit Blanc himself receive a box, but - importantly - we’re not shown how or why.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group get to the island and hang out a bit, and we are introduced to Edward Norton’s character, who falls into the “rich, slightly hippie asshole” archetype. There’s some tension with his ex-business partner, who nobody seems to want around, and she lashes out at the group and says they’re all leeches who rely on the billionaire for survival. Alongside this there’s some motive setup, with several characters given reasons to despise him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At dinner, Blanc solves the murder mystery before the fake death even occurs, but things get more complicated when a muscly vlogger chokes and the police say they can’t make it to the island before morning. The power goes out, people scatter, and somebody shoots the ex-partner. Seems like the legendary detective Benoit Blanc has a lot of work to do, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem-1-restarting-halfway-through&quot;&gt;Problem #1: Restarting halfway through&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well… wrong. Because the first mistake &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt; makes after building all this intrigue is to take us right back to the start of the story. This isn’t a short flashback, either - instead of watching Blanc solve the mystery, we need to retread a lot of ground to find out exactly how he got involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, the person who got shot was not in fact Andi, Miles Bron’s former business partner. She was already mysteriously killed in her own home prior to the whole event, and when her twin sister Helen asked Benoit Blanc to investigate her death, he convinced her to come to the island to pose as her sister and help him. He said it would be dangerous, but she was sold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/glass-onion_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spend what feels like an eternity waiting for the film to catch up with itself as we watch them prepare. Helen doesn’t consider herself as capable as the “shitheads” in the group, but acts more intelligently than them throughout. For example, between meeting Blanc and arriving on the island, she reads and memorises all her sister’s diaries to the degree of detail that she can pose as her in front of people who used to be her closest friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the present, we see that the person we now know as Helen is not actually dead - the bullet was blocked by her sister’s journal. This removes what could have been an emotional moment for Blanc (as he persuaded her to go to the island), but it turns out that the tear we saw him shed was actually due to him rubbing hot sauce in his eye. This part in particular felt like the filmakers choosing being clever over telling an engaging story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blanc, almost certainly the series’ main draw, then spends the rest of the film marvelling over Helen’s superhuman detective abilities. Even when she accidentally gets drunk (she’s usually a teetotaller) there are no negative consequences and she’s more effective than him. And when Blanc &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; get to take centre stage for the traditional “whodunnit?” speech, it’s actually just a huge filibuster to buy time for Helen to snoop around elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem-2-the-murderer-is-obvious&quot;&gt;Problem #2: The murderer is obvious&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More problematic is that &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt;’s resolution is completely predictable, and I called it shortly after the group arrived on the island. Murder mystery films usually have an obvious suspect who the audience is led to believe is the culprit before a surprise bait and switch in the final stages, but this film does no such thing, and the answer is just sitting there throughout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue is it’s clear from the start that writer Rian Johnson’s worldview approximately matches that of the average Twitter user. The original &lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt; had a character describe another as an “alt-right troll dipshit”, one of &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt;’s main characters is an exaggerated men’s rights vlogger with zero redeeming qualities, and there are a few lines in the first two thirds of the film where characters sneer about his slide to “the right” and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/glass-onion_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I am expressing no personal political opinions here (this is an entertainment site, after all) - just noting that throughout the films we get clues as to the writer’s own perspective on things, and this meta eventually proves enough for us to predict who he would likely portray as a murderer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because with the vlogger killed early on, which of the remaining characters would somebody with this outlook despise the most? Perhaps tech billionaires were front of mind given the recent furore around Twitter and Elon Musk, but Miles Bron was the obvious standout for me. Surprise, surprise - Blanc and Helen eventually deduce that he killed his ex-business partner, and for the finale we get to watch Bron grow increasingly frustrated as Helen trashes his expensive house, even burning the Mona Lisa, which he has out on loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone watching for a murder mystery on the level of the excellent &lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt;, it was disappointing not only that the story was so easy to predict, without any extra twist, but that the final scene also passed up the opportunity for any clever resolution to indulge in the fantasy of breaking a billionaire’s stuff. The film as a whole deserved a better ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll go back to what I said at the beginning - all this isn’t enough to make &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt; a bad film. It was clever (sometimes more so than it needed to be), occasionally beautiful, and Craig even got a few laughs out of me. I’ll certainly watch any further films in the series - I’ll just be hoping that they’re more like &lt;em&gt;Knives Out&lt;/em&gt; than this messy yet predictable instalment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3/5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="films" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">Just before Christmas 2022, Netflix released Glass Onion, the next film in the Knives Out series. Expecting another clever, witty mystery from Rian Johnson I sat down to watch it over the holiday period, but was disappointed to find it did not deliver anything close to the quality of its predecessor. Before anybody takes this article the wrong way, I’ll start by saying this: Glass Onion is a good film. It looks great, the mystery is intriguing in part, there’s some enjoyable dialogue (particularly from Daniel Craig), and it kept me more engaged from start to finish than most modern releases do. However, Glass Onion is not even close to being as good as Knives Out. While there a number of reasons for this, in this article I’ll focus on what I think are the two biggest problems (with plenty of spoilers along the way, so I advise that you actually watch the film before reading any further). Intro and setup Things start out promisingly enough. A bunch of prominent people receive puzzle boxes containing invitations to a billionaire’s private island, where it appears he’ll be hosting a murder mystery event. Given the genre, it’s clear something will go wrong, so from the start you’re keen to see what it is. These opening scenes are very heavy on comedic lines, which makes the tone a little odd, but Knives Out also subverted some of the genre’s conventions, so it’s not necessarily surprising. Lastly, we see Benoit Blanc himself receive a box, but - importantly - we’re not shown how or why.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/glass-onion_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/glass-onion_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What to expect from TSP in 2023</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/08/what-to-expect-tsp-2023" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What to expect from TSP in 2023" /><published>2023-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/08/what-to-expect-tsp-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/01/08/what-to-expect-tsp-2023">&lt;p&gt;It’s been quite a ride for &lt;em&gt;The Strat Pack&lt;/em&gt; since the site’s original soft launch in September 2021. More than a year later, after a site design upgrade and 76 articles, my musings on games and adjacent interests have amassed nearly 50,000 views, which is certainly more than I expected at the start. I appreciate everybody for taking the time to read them, and especially those who have emailed in to give their views and chat about their favourites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some articles have performed much as I’d have hoped - &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/02/19/newbies-guide-buying-formula-1-models&quot;&gt;my introduction to Formula 1 model collecting&lt;/a&gt; is the fourth most read article here, for example - but often there is a huge disconnect between the effort I expend writing an article (and how proud I am of it) and its reception, and that can be tough. A simple how-to guide can sometimes yield tens of thousands of views, while a sprawling retrospective can get nowhere near breaking into triple figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can add to that the pressure that I have put myself under to deliver weekly articles. This has a few knock-on effects, including the occasional rushed news or opinion piece when I run out of time, but the biggest consequence is forcing me to play games to a schedule. If I have a review or retrospective slated in for a specific date, I’ll sacrifice my evenings for the preceding week for play sessions to finish it, even if I’m not in the mood. But gaming is a longstanding hobby of mine, and it shouldn’t feel like a chore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I also feel like I’ve already covered most of the older games that immediately sprang to mind when I started the site, and there aren’t enough new titles I’m interested in to provide a consistent flow of content. When I paused work on posts over the Christmas break, I found myself playing a lot of endurance races in &lt;em&gt;Automobilista 2&lt;/em&gt;, and that wouldn’t be fertile ground for many articles without repeating myself a whole lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fear not - it may sound like I’m building up to shutting down the site, or at the very least going on hiatus, but what I actually want to say is that in 2023 I’ll be taking a more relaxed approach to &lt;em&gt;The Strat Pack&lt;/em&gt;. Articles will go up when I have something specific that I’m enthusiastic to write about - not on a fixed weekly basis - and I’ll open up the subject matter more often to films, television, music, and so on to accommodate this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome (I hope) is that although posts might be slightly less frequent, they’ll be of higher quality when they are published, and will be worth your time to read. It might sacrifice some numbers from algorithms that demand regular updates, but I think this approach will produce a site I can be more proud of, give me more time to play games I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to play, and be more accommodating to other changes in my life heading into the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for stopping by, and I hope you will continue to do so. Please &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thestratpack&quot;&gt;follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for updates regarding new articles, and I hope to connect with many more of you as the year goes on. All the best for 2023!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><summary type="html">It’s been quite a ride for The Strat Pack since the site’s original soft launch in September 2021. More than a year later, after a site design upgrade and 76 articles, my musings on games and adjacent interests have amassed nearly 50,000 views, which is certainly more than I expected at the start. I appreciate everybody for taking the time to read them, and especially those who have emailed in to give their views and chat about their favourites. Some articles have performed much as I’d have hoped - my introduction to Formula 1 model collecting is the fourth most read article here, for example - but often there is a huge disconnect between the effort I expend writing an article (and how proud I am of it) and its reception, and that can be tough. A simple how-to guide can sometimes yield tens of thousands of views, while a sprawling retrospective can get nowhere near breaking into triple figures. You can add to that the pressure that I have put myself under to deliver weekly articles. This has a few knock-on effects, including the occasional rushed news or opinion piece when I run out of time, but the biggest consequence is forcing me to play games to a schedule. If I have a review or retrospective slated in for a specific date, I’ll sacrifice my evenings for the preceding week for play sessions to finish it, even if I’m not in the mood. But gaming is a longstanding hobby of mine, and it shouldn’t feel like a chore. Furthermore, I also feel like I’ve already covered most of the older games that immediately sprang to mind when I started the site, and there aren’t enough new titles I’m interested in to provide a consistent flow of content. When I paused work on posts over the Christmas break, I found myself playing a lot of endurance races in Automobilista 2, and that wouldn’t be fertile ground for many articles without repeating myself a whole lot. Fear not - it may sound like I’m building up to shutting down the site, or at the very least going on hiatus, but what I actually want to say is that in 2023 I’ll be taking a more relaxed approach to The Strat Pack. Articles will go up when I have something specific that I’m enthusiastic to write about - not on a fixed weekly basis - and I’ll open up the subject matter more often to films, television, music, and so on to accommodate this. The outcome (I hope) is that although posts might be slightly less frequent, they’ll be of higher quality when they are published, and will be worth your time to read. It might sacrifice some numbers from algorithms that demand regular updates, but I think this approach will produce a site I can be more proud of, give me more time to play games I want to play, and be more accommodating to other changes in my life heading into the new year. Thanks for stopping by, and I hope you will continue to do so. Please follow me on Twitter for updates regarding new articles, and I hope to connect with many more of you as the year goes on. All the best for 2023!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – making history</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/25/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA 22 Career Mode&amp;#58; TSP United &amp;#8211; making history" /><published>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/25/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/11/25/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-4">&lt;p&gt;Last time out in my &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Career Mode series I was lucky to hold on to my job as TSP United manager after a disappointing 2026/27 season. Would I be able to handle the mounting pressure in England’s top flight with the board’s expectations ever increasing? Perhaps this photo might give you a clue…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a reminder, I’m playing this Career Mode campaign with special custom rules for some added challenge. I’m not to spend a penny on players (signing free agents is fine) and the focus is on &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players&quot;&gt;scouting and developing youth players&lt;/a&gt;. So my main source of new talent through this whole thing is to send a scout out around England occasionally and see what he brings back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this is the fourth instalment of my TSP United Career Mode series. Click here to catch up on the first six seasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/06/17/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-2&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – hitting the big time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/09/16/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-3&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – cup runs to remember&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202728---premier-league&quot;&gt;2027/28 - Premier League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a rough last season, I didn’t opt to make any signings heading into 2027/28, instead making some rearrangements as young players returned from loan. Notably, Gale took the spot between the sticks, relegating the inconsistent Parkin to the bench. Departures included former regular striker Prince, one of the few remaining original TSP United players.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were off the mark quickly and went on a frankly insane run of form considering our recent struggles, ending up top after ten games, having won 25 of the 30 available points. Gale was making saves well beyond his ability on paper, and by December I was wondering whether we might be on course to do a Leicester (who ironically were our closest title rivals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stumbled slightly over the Christmas period, lacking the squad depth to handle two games a week, but stayed on Leicester’s tail. As Chelsea took the top spot we were scraping victories, often coming back from steep deficits to win. But our form prevailed, and with five games left we inched ahead of the Blues. The fate of the league season was in our hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we beat Arsenal and Newcastle emphatically, Chelsea lost to City, putting us four points ahead. We had a chance to win the league in our penultimate game of the season at the Etihad, and didn’t let it go to waste. Pierre and Vaughan both netted braces, and the scoring was capped off by Goddard as we thrashed Pep Guardiola’s team and were crowned Premier League champions at the end of a truly improbable season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best player&lt;/strong&gt; - Annumanian, who broke Vaughan’s scoring record&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - N/A, because we made no signings&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Gale, who became the new first-choice GK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202829---premier-league&quot;&gt;2028/29 - Premier League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a league title under our belts, my sights were firmly set on a grand European finale to this Career Mode campaign. With most of our players improving, there was no need for huge squad changes, but I did bring Hunter into the first team at LM, moving the declining legend Willis to the bench.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We beat Man United in the Community Shield and made a strong start in the league despite losing Vaughan to a three-month injury. Our Champions League campaign was less smooth. We drew a tricky group, which featured both Inter and Bayern, and a defeat to the latter in the final group stage match saw us tumble out into the Europa League. The dream was over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unexpectedly, the Premier League became something of a saunter and we retained our title with a couple of games to go. Meanwhile, our Europa League run saw us face off with Manchester United, Villareal, and AC Milan, setting up a final date with a Liverpool team we’d smashed 4-0 just days before with a second-string lineup, on the final day of the league season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first team made no mistake on the big occasion. TSP United applied the early pressure before Pierre headed in a Hunter corner in the fifth minute. A fantastic Alisson performance kept Liverpool in the game, but goals from Annumanian and Vaughan meant we were four goals clear by half time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pierre got a fifth early in the second half, and when Neto was shown a red card we controlled the rest of the game. Proceedings were capped off by Willis, a late substitute, who grabbed the sixth and final goal in stoppage time with perhaps his last kick of a ball for TSP United. Maybe our Champions Leauge bid fell short, but we were European champions nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best player&lt;/strong&gt; - Annumanian, pushing the limits yet again&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - N/A, because we made no signings&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Hancock, straight in at CB on his loan return&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">Last time out in my FIFA 22 Career Mode series I was lucky to hold on to my job as TSP United manager after a disappointing 2026/27 season. Would I be able to handle the mounting pressure in England’s top flight with the board’s expectations ever increasing? Perhaps this photo might give you a clue… As a reminder, I’m playing this Career Mode campaign with special custom rules for some added challenge. I’m not to spend a penny on players (signing free agents is fine) and the focus is on scouting and developing youth players. So my main source of new talent through this whole thing is to send a scout out around England occasionally and see what he brings back. Note that this is the fourth instalment of my TSP United Career Mode series. Click here to catch up on the first six seasons: • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – hitting the big time • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – cup runs to remember 2027/28 - Premier League Despite a rough last season, I didn’t opt to make any signings heading into 2027/28, instead making some rearrangements as young players returned from loan. Notably, Gale took the spot between the sticks, relegating the inconsistent Parkin to the bench. Departures included former regular striker Prince, one of the few remaining original TSP United players.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/11/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>