<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-02-26T11:49:20+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">FIFA 22 is actually a big step forward</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/26/fifa-22-big-step-forward" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA 22 is actually a big step forward" /><published>2022-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/26/fifa-22-actually-pretty-good</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/26/fifa-22-big-step-forward">&lt;p&gt;With some time to kill and spotting a decent discount on Steam, I picked up a copy of &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt; a week or two ago. It’s too late in the game’s cycle to warrant a full review, but with Konami &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/01/efootball-2022-first-impressions&quot;&gt;royally screwing up &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; having come a surprisingly long way since &lt;em&gt;FIFA 20&lt;/em&gt; (which was the last entry in the series that I played), I wanted to share some of my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;football-is-harder-now&quot;&gt;Football is harder now…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few games in, I was worried EA had broken everything. I really hated &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;’s gameplay. Every player - even world-class wingers - felt sluggish and slow to turn and passes were randomly their targets. Whether attacking or defending, it felt like every player was running through treacle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But over time I came to appreciate what was happening. EA has refined &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt;’s gameplay in such a way that everything you do requires more consideration than before. There’s a focus on momentum and body weight in all aspects of the game. Especially when playing with lower league teams, you have to be very careful with direction. Even a single mistimed challenge can leave your defender off-balance and let the opposition through on goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/fifa-22_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, when you get it &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; right and breeze past a defender with a well-timed touch, it feels amazing. &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt; has just enough speed for quick players to feel pacey, but not some much that holding the thumbstick and mashing the right trigger is enough for them to beat any defender, as it was in &lt;em&gt;FIFA 20&lt;/em&gt;. The match engine feels much better balanced as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;but-sometimes-its-too-difficult&quot;&gt;…but sometimes it’s too difficult&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, if I have any gripe with the match engine, it’s over &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;’s Legendary difficulty. I’ve been playing &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; on their Legendary and six-star difficulties for years and would welcome a new challenge, but the way it’s been implemented here just isn’t fun to play against.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Legendary, even League Two teams will play quick, seemingly random passes inside your penalty area that are impossible to defend against with the tools the game gives you. They’ll frequently pepper their attacking play with random tricks you’d rarely see even in the Champions League, and in defence are ruthlessly effective in their blocks and interceptions.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/fifa-22_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Altogether, this means you’ll come to recognise that some attacking plays are undefendable, while only creating a few snatched chances yourself. For the moment I’ve dropped down to World Class, which frustratingly feels like it might be slightly &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; easy, so perhaps I’ll have to play with the sliders, too. It’s also early days, so maybe I’ll find a better balance later in my career once I start playing with more skillful players in the Premier League.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;career-mode-custom-teams-are-excellent&quot;&gt;Career Mode custom teams are excellent&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which, Career Mode has seen a few notable uplifts since my last outing. I wanted to give this a go partly after catching some of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitch.tv/goldbridgetv&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mark Goldbridge&lt;/a&gt;’s journey to Europe with TUS United, and partly because when I bought the game there was a graphics bug (now fixed) that made nighttime matches at Stamford Bridge unplayable, which ruled out a Chelsea career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;, when setting up Career Mode, you’re given the option to replace any team in the league system with your own club. There’s a surprising amount of customisation to indulge in, ranging from the name, logo, and kits to stadiums, pitch types, chants, pre-match anthems, and so on. You get a randomly generated squad of low-skilled players and embark on your quest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/fifa-22_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is greatly rewarding, not just in terms of titles and trophies but also the stories that emerge along the way. Your original players become club legends, and you face difficult decisions as you progress through the leagues and need to choose when to replace them. It also makes the &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; youth academy system much more relevant, as the youngsters you scout aren’t competing with the likes of Lukaku and Pulisic and could actually feature in your first team before long. It’s been a long time since Career Mode has received this much attention from EA and it’s great to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ironing-out-the-details&quot;&gt;Ironing out the details&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall sense I get from &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt; is that EA has spent time cleaning up the little details in all sorts of areas. Playing advantage after fouls, for example, now works almost perfectly. Not only does it apply to offside decisions when the defending team wins possession, but when the referee plays on, a timer appears on the screen and gives the player with the ball the opportunity to hit both triggers and bring it back for the free kick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improvements elsewhere include many new efficiencies for Career Mode menus, and we finally have option to skip those long, awkward cut scenes around interviews and contract negotiations (it’s set to holding a button by default, but can be changed to an instant skip in the settings). There are also a few new club details, like the aforementioned pre-match anthems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/fifa-22_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kick Off mode now has the ability to track match records between different players, which is a feature that appeared in &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; years ago but was sadly dropped, and is a great asset for those who play local multiplayer frequently. Another interesting addition is an &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;F1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-style rewind feature to undo your mistakes and try that shot again. It’s not a feature I’m ever likely to use, but it is nice to see EA paying so much attention to offline players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been dithering like I was over whether to pick up &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt; when the price comes down, questioning whether it would have changed enough in recent years to warrant a purchase from a non-Ultimate Team player, I’d advise you to grab it. It’s not perfect, but there’s a lot to love here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">With some time to kill and spotting a decent discount on Steam, I picked up a copy of FIFA 22 a week or two ago. It’s too late in the game’s cycle to warrant a full review, but with Konami royally screwing up PES and FIFA having come a surprisingly long way since FIFA 20 (which was the last entry in the series that I played), I wanted to share some of my thoughts. Football is harder now… A few games in, I was worried EA had broken everything. I really hated FIFA 22’s gameplay. Every player - even world-class wingers - felt sluggish and slow to turn and passes were randomly their targets. Whether attacking or defending, it felt like every player was running through treacle. But over time I came to appreciate what was happening. EA has refined FIFA’s gameplay in such a way that everything you do requires more consideration than before. There’s a focus on momentum and body weight in all aspects of the game. Especially when playing with lower league teams, you have to be very careful with direction. Even a single mistimed challenge can leave your defender off-balance and let the opposition through on goal. On the other hand, when you get it just right and breeze past a defender with a well-timed touch, it feels amazing. FIFA 22 has just enough speed for quick players to feel pacey, but not some much that holding the thumbstick and mashing the right trigger is enough for them to beat any defender, as it was in FIFA 20. The match engine feels much better balanced as a result. …but sometimes it’s too difficult In fact, if I have any gripe with the match engine, it’s over FIFA 22’s Legendary difficulty. I’ve been playing FIFA and PES on their Legendary and six-star difficulties for years and would welcome a new challenge, but the way it’s been implemented here just isn’t fun to play against. On Legendary, even League Two teams will play quick, seemingly random passes inside your penalty area that are impossible to defend against with the tools the game gives you. They’ll frequently pepper their attacking play with random tricks you’d rarely see even in the Champions League, and in defence are ruthlessly effective in their blocks and interceptions.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/02/fifa-22_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/02/fifa-22_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The newbie’s guide to buying Formula 1 models</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/19/newbies-guide-buying-formula-1-models" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The newbie's guide to buying Formula 1 models" /><published>2022-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/19/newbies-guide-buying-formula-1-models</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/19/newbies-guide-buying-formula-1-models">&lt;p&gt;Unless you’ve got the money and the space to fill your mansion with real Formula 1 cars, scale models are probably your best bet for having a little piece of motorsport history to admire at home. The world of Formula 1 models is one I’ve only recently joined and deciding what to buy can be a bit daunting, so I thought I’d write down everything I learnt from my research to help anybody else who finds themselves in the same situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choosing-a-model&quot;&gt;Choosing a model&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re thinking of buying a Formula 1 model, you probably have some idea of which car you’d like - perhaps a shrine to a favourite team or driver, or a souvenir from a particularly memorable race. The only advice I can offer here is to &lt;strong&gt;buy the car you want, not one you think will be more collectable&lt;/strong&gt;. It is very unlikely it will accrue enough extra value to warrant buying and storing it for years, so get one that will look nice on your shelf instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/formula-1-models_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you know which car you’re looking for, you’ll likely notice that models are available from multiple manufacturers. Sometimes you’ll be locked in to one maker based on your chosen car - &lt;strong&gt;Looksmart&lt;/strong&gt; are the only supplier of detailed Ferrari models, for example - but for most modern teams you’ll have make the classic collector’s decision: &lt;strong&gt;Minichamps&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Spark&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general consensus seems to be that there isn’t &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; much difference between the two, although Minichamps can be a little pricier (more on that later). A debate comes up now and then around the accuracy of Spark’s tyre proportions, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/f1models/comments/so5duo/the_definitive_minichamps_and_spark_wheel/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a recent Reddit post&lt;/a&gt; seemed to suggest that any difference is negligible, and I’m happy enough with the look of my Spark cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One quirk to be aware of when ordering cars that feature &lt;strong&gt;tobacco sponsors&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g. McLaren’s recent promotion of various BAT products) is that these will be missing from the model when it arrives. Spark provides these decals with the model so you can apply them yourself, but Minichamps does not.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/formula-1-models_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’ve selected a car and manufacturer, you’ll next need to choose a &lt;strong&gt;scale&lt;/strong&gt; for your model. Generally, model Formula 1 cars come in two sizes: &lt;strong&gt;1:43&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;1:18&lt;/strong&gt;. A 1:43 model of a 2021 Formula 1 car comes to about 14cm in length. I don’t own any 1:18 models, but doing the maths we can estimate that they’re roughly 33cm long. So make sure you’ve got enough space!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, &lt;strong&gt;price&lt;/strong&gt; will likely be as much of a consideration as anything else for many collectors, so here’s roughly what you’ll be paying for new models at each scale from the main manufacturers at the time of writing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Manufacturer&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1:43&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1:18&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Minichamps&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;£90&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;£192&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Spark&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;£65&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;£150&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that if your model comes with any special extras to celebrate the driver’s performance in the race - for example, a &lt;strong&gt;pit board&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;podium position marker&lt;/strong&gt; - you can expect to pay between £5 and £10 extra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ordering-a-model&quot;&gt;Ordering a model&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you’ve chosen a team, driver, race, manufactuer, and the scale of your model, but where can you actually buy it? A small selection of the most popular cars make it to &lt;a href=&quot;https://f1store.formula1.com/en/collectibles-and-memorabilia-model-cars/d-31772259-5628222460+z-93-3524959453?_ref=m-TOPNAV&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the official Formula 1 store&lt;/a&gt;, but most of the time your best bet is to use one of the &lt;strong&gt;specialist model car retailers&lt;/strong&gt; like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diecastlegends.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Diecast Legends&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://formulamodelshop.co.uk/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Formula Model Shop&lt;/a&gt;, or one of their equivalents in your part of the world. There is also a used market on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ebay.co.uk/b/Formula-1-Models/27397/bn_16568534?mkevt=1&amp;amp;mkcid=1&amp;amp;mkrid=710-53481-19255-0&amp;amp;campid=5337590774&amp;amp;customid=&amp;amp;toolid=10001&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;eBay&lt;/a&gt; for older models, but availability is down to luck and the usual auction site warnings apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/formula-1-models_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a similar note, if your model of choice is likely to be in high demand - for example, if it’s a special livery or from the race where the driver won the championship - you’ll likely want to &lt;strong&gt;preorder&lt;/strong&gt; it. While it may be in stock on release if you don’t, this isn’t guaranteed, and you may be forced to switch to a more expensive retailer or a different manufacturer. Models tend to be produced in a limited number, so once they’re gone, they’re gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you’re not too excited at this point, because &lt;strong&gt;models can take nine months or more to be produced&lt;/strong&gt; after being announced. Your retailer will usually provide an estimated dispatch date, which they’ll update based on information from the supplier. The manufacturer’s website may also give you some indication of what to expect. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sparkmodel.com/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Spark’s website&lt;/a&gt; has sections for models in development, coming soon, and post-release, while &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.miniatures-minichamps.com/gb/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Minichamps&lt;/a&gt; lists a handful of upcoming cars with their predicted months of release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-in-the-box&quot;&gt;What’s in the box&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: All of my models to date are Spark 1:43 models of 2021 Formula 1 cars. Details in this section are applicable to similar models only.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was quite impressed with &lt;strong&gt;Spark&lt;/strong&gt;’s presentation of its models when they arrived. Each one comes wrapped in cellophane, under which there is an outer cardboard sleeve with a sold back and “pillars” along the front sides to give a window effect. This is decked out in  team colours, perhaps with a special commemorative back panel if you’re lucky. The car itself sits inside a &lt;strong&gt;plastic display case&lt;/strong&gt;, screwed to a wooden base. There’s usually a piece of foam slipped under the front wing to protect it in transit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best advice I can give you amongst all the excitement of receiving a new model is to &lt;strong&gt;be very careful when opening and closing the case&lt;/strong&gt;. This is by far the riskiest manoeuvre in terms of potential damage to the car, so make sure you’re paying attention and taking appropriate care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/formula-1-models_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the model has any of the aforementioned extra pieces, they’ll be in a plastic bag slid under the car and taped to the base. Standing up a podium position board is as simple as removing it from the bag and folding the base into shape (they’re actually sturdier than that process makes them sound).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, any &lt;strong&gt;extra decals&lt;/strong&gt; will be in their own bag stuck to the underside of the base. I won’t go into the application process here, but I’d recommend looking up a tutorial on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QNYdd3Aley8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;how to apply model car decals&lt;/a&gt; to get those more controversial sponsors slid into place for the full effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s it! After all that painstaking research, the agonising months waiting for updates, and a nail-biting session applying decals, your model Formula 1 car is now complete and ready for display in a cabinet or on your mantelpiece! If you’re new to model cars, I hope this article has provided at least some additional information to help you make your selection and put your mind at ease about what you’re buying. If you have any further questions, feel free to reach out via the details below.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="motorsport" /><category term="formula-1" /><summary type="html">Unless you’ve got the money and the space to fill your mansion with real Formula 1 cars, scale models are probably your best bet for having a little piece of motorsport history to admire at home. The world of Formula 1 models is one I’ve only recently joined and deciding what to buy can be a bit daunting, so I thought I’d write down everything I learnt from my research to help anybody else who finds themselves in the same situation. Choosing a model If you’re thinking of buying a Formula 1 model, you probably have some idea of which car you’d like - perhaps a shrine to a favourite team or driver, or a souvenir from a particularly memorable race. The only advice I can offer here is to buy the car you want, not one you think will be more collectable. It is very unlikely it will accrue enough extra value to warrant buying and storing it for years, so get one that will look nice on your shelf instead. Once you know which car you’re looking for, you’ll likely notice that models are available from multiple manufacturers. Sometimes you’ll be locked in to one maker based on your chosen car - Looksmart are the only supplier of detailed Ferrari models, for example - but for most modern teams you’ll have make the classic collector’s decision: Minichamps or Spark? The general consensus seems to be that there isn’t too much difference between the two, although Minichamps can be a little pricier (more on that later). A debate comes up now and then around the accuracy of Spark’s tyre proportions, but a recent Reddit post seemed to suggest that any difference is negligible, and I’m happy enough with the look of my Spark cars. One quirk to be aware of when ordering cars that feature tobacco sponsors (e.g. McLaren’s recent promotion of various BAT products) is that these will be missing from the model when it arrives. Spark provides these decals with the model so you can apply them yourself, but Minichamps does not.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/02/formula-1-models_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/02/formula-1-models_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GTA IV’s immersive mechanics may be lost forever</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/12/gta-iv-immersive-mechanics-lost-forever" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTA IV's immersive mechanics may be lost forever" /><published>2022-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/12/gta-iv-immersive-mechanics-lost-forever</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/12/gta-iv-immersive-mechanics-lost-forever">&lt;p&gt;Rockstar practically broke Twitter with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RockstarGames/status/1489617718009606150&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;its announcement of what will surely be &lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto VI&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on 4th February. At the time of writing, the tweet is approaching 600,000 likes and fans are speculating over how the next iteration will build on the hyper-successful &lt;em&gt;GTA V&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while the most recent game is the one that broke all records, &lt;a href=&quot;https://venturebeat.com/2021/11/03/take-twos-bookings-grow-3-to-984-9m-as-gta-v-hits-155m-sold/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;selling more than 155 million copies and making more than $6 billion&lt;/a&gt; for Take-Two Interactive since its 2013 release, I still think that 2008’s &lt;em&gt;GTA IV&lt;/em&gt; is in many ways the pinnacle of the series, and maybe that’s precisely because it &lt;em&gt;didn’t&lt;/em&gt; try to do everything bigger and better all of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gta-iv_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;criticism-and-its-consequences&quot;&gt;Criticism and its consequences&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On release, some fans complained about &lt;em&gt;GTA IV&lt;/em&gt; being too grounded and gritty after the jet packs, planes, and tanks of &lt;em&gt;San Andreas&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/grand-theft-auto&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; should be all about the over-the-top explosions and chases, they said. Rockstar back-pedalled slightly with its second expansion, &lt;em&gt;The Ballad of Gay Tony&lt;/em&gt;, which provided at least some mayhem against the game’s weightier backdrop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;em&gt;GTA V&lt;/em&gt; in 2013. With the next - and last, to date - entry in the series, Rockstar set out to give these fans what they wanted. Michael, Franklin, and Trevor’s story encompassed all kinds of carnage, bringing the out-of-control feel of earlier games to the graphics and writing of the HD universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gta-iv_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to me, something always feels a bit off driving around that incarnation of Los Santos. The map’s much larger size meant it would never be as dense as &lt;em&gt;GTA IV&lt;/em&gt;, but it also feels much more… video gamey. Everything revolves around the player, with random pedestrians calling out to compliment your car, police zeroing in on witness-free gunshots in the middle of the desert and then disappearing when your back is turned, and every interaction ending in confrontation with either the city’s residents or law enforcement.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Civilian motorists jut out into your path to give you something to dodge, then face plant on the steering wheel, killed by a tap to their rear bumper. Everything is at its most dramatic, played up like it’s an 80s cop show, and there’s always the sense that - just like that squad car you just outran - everything ceases to exist when it’s outside of the player’s cone of vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-living-breathing-city&quot;&gt;A living, breathing city&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, &lt;em&gt;GTA IV&lt;/em&gt;’s Liberty City felt like it didn’t care whether the player, as Niko Bellic, was there or not. It felt like life would continue regardless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Niko walked the streets anonymously, free to listen in on conversations, dip into internet cafes, or visit the city’s tourist traps and take it all in. Police cars actually patrolled the city streets, and even just cruising around you’d see cops running after petty criminals. If you did choose the life of crime (and who didn’t? This is &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt;, after all) there was a chance your misdeed would go unnoticed if nobody was around to see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gta-iv_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might argue that this isn’t what &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; games are about - that they’re all about the carnage, the car chases and gunfights. But &lt;em&gt;GTA IV&lt;/em&gt;’s world-first, player-second ethos meant there were realistic rules of cause and effect that applied equally to both Niko and NPCs. In other words, the consequence of Niko’s natural place within his environment was that you could get much more creative with the commotion you could cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite pastimes in &lt;em&gt;GTA IV&lt;/em&gt; was seeing how far I could stretch the game’s AI and physics models. Think getting the police to arrest a guy you provoked because they saw him punch you, starting fights between pedestrians, or bribing a homeless guy so he’ll help you out in a jam. With careful planning, it was even possible to cause a traffic jam, start a vehicle fire, and watch the explosions jump from car to car, all while posing as a seemingly innocent bystander with no wanted level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lost-mechanics&quot;&gt;Lost mechanics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of this experimental-type fun disappeared with &lt;em&gt;GTA V&lt;/em&gt;. I tried setting up the same scenario (which you would have thought would be easier with the inclusion of the jerry can), but got one star as soon as the fire started, and two when it caught on. Shoot some “speed holes” in your own car under a bridge somewhere? The cops somehow have your description. Even just stand next to somebody for too long? Apparently that’s a crime now, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, given the amount of money Take-Two has made from &lt;em&gt;GTA V&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;GTA Online&lt;/em&gt;, I don’t think we’ll ever get another game like &lt;em&gt;GTA IV&lt;/em&gt;. The high-octane, no-holds-barred path is just too lucrative, especially when you consider how much more potential it has for additional, flamboyant online content, requiring eternal grinding or Shark cards to obtain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gta-iv_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why in my mind, &lt;em&gt;GTA IV&lt;/em&gt; will always be &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; great &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; game, created when Rockstar looked at the new Xbox 360 and PlayStation 3 hardware and thought, “What more will this allow us to give the player?” Now, after an entire generation without a new &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; game, the future looks rather grim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll do a full retrospective on &lt;em&gt;GTA IV&lt;/em&gt; when I have the time to play through the story again, but for now I’d simply urge you to go and browse YouTube to remind yourself of what an immersive place Liberty City was and remember all the small mechanics and systems that made it that way and have since fallen away. We might never see them in &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; again.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="grand-theft-auto" /><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">Rockstar practically broke Twitter with its announcement of what will surely be Grand Theft Auto VI on 4th February. At the time of writing, the tweet is approaching 600,000 likes and fans are speculating over how the next iteration will build on the hyper-successful GTA V. But while the most recent game is the one that broke all records, selling more than 155 million copies and making more than $6 billion for Take-Two Interactive since its 2013 release, I still think that 2008’s GTA IV is in many ways the pinnacle of the series, and maybe that’s precisely because it didn’t try to do everything bigger and better all of the time. Criticism and its consequences On release, some fans complained about GTA IV being too grounded and gritty after the jet packs, planes, and tanks of San Andreas. GTA should be all about the over-the-top explosions and chases, they said. Rockstar back-pedalled slightly with its second expansion, The Ballad of Gay Tony, which provided at least some mayhem against the game’s weightier backdrop. Enter GTA V in 2013. With the next - and last, to date - entry in the series, Rockstar set out to give these fans what they wanted. Michael, Franklin, and Trevor’s story encompassed all kinds of carnage, bringing the out-of-control feel of earlier games to the graphics and writing of the HD universe. But to me, something always feels a bit off driving around that incarnation of Los Santos. The map’s much larger size meant it would never be as dense as GTA IV, but it also feels much more… video gamey. Everything revolves around the player, with random pedestrians calling out to compliment your car, police zeroing in on witness-free gunshots in the middle of the desert and then disappearing when your back is turned, and every interaction ending in confrontation with either the city’s residents or law enforcement.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gta-iv_3.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gta-iv_3.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Gran Turismo 7: Everything we know</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/05/everything-we-know-gran-turismo-7" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gran Turismo 7&amp;#58; Everything we know" /><published>2022-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/05/everything-we-know-gran-turismo-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/02/05/everything-we-know-gran-turismo-7">&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that I am &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; excited for &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/gran-turismo&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so when we got &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JlbMzBnfnzM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a 32-minute “deep dive” video&lt;/a&gt; from the PlayStation State of Play this week, it only seemed right for me to dissect every second of it try to gather all the little details and clues about what we can expect to see in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_15.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video starred series producer Kazunori Yamauchi, speaking via a translator. He touted the new game, which marks &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt;’s 25th anniversary, as “the most complete &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; to date” and revealed a whole range of features and details that we hadn’t seen before, including more about the game’s focus on “car culture” as well as the actual racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is a summary of what I could ascertain from the video, which confirmed it’s going to be a long wait until the 4th March release date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-cars&quot;&gt;The cars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yamauchi revealed that &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; will feature &lt;strong&gt;more than 400 cars&lt;/strong&gt;. Over the course of the video we were treated to shots of road cars, sports cars, GT cars, historic cars, rally cars, and concept cars, confirming that the catalogue has all the variety that we’ve come to expect from the series. It was promised that additional cars will be delivered via online updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were shown several places to buy cars. &lt;strong&gt;Brand Central&lt;/strong&gt; is a shopping centre where players can buy around 300 new cars from 2001 and later. The &lt;strong&gt;used car dealer&lt;/strong&gt; will sell a different lineup of cars on a daily basis. These will generally be more affordable, but some models (the example given was 90s Japanese sports cars) will actually accrue value. The last marketplace shown was &lt;strong&gt;Brighton Antiques&lt;/strong&gt;, a place to buy legendary and famous cars like the Le Mans-winning Ford GT40 and James Bond’s Aston Martin DB5.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the focus on “culture”, the developers have made an effort to tell the stories behind the cars. The Gran Turismo Cafe (more on that later) features car designers talking about their work, while there are also &lt;strong&gt;museums&lt;/strong&gt; that tell the stories of certain manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scope for customisation looks huge. The &lt;strong&gt;tuning shop&lt;/strong&gt; offers around 60 performance parts per car, and the number of setup options looks downright daunting. For cosmetics, &lt;strong&gt;GT Auto&lt;/strong&gt; has more than 650 aero parts, 130 wheel types, and 1,200 paint colours to use, as well as the traditional car wash and oil change options. The &lt;strong&gt;livery editor&lt;/strong&gt; now grants players more freedom, with a higher sticker limit and additional areas to place them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve built your dream vehicle, &lt;strong&gt;Scapes&lt;/strong&gt; - first shown off in the reveal trailer - lets you take it to more than 2,500 locations around the world to take photos, with enough camera options to get really arty and abstract. As usual, you can also take and customise photos from races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_11.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Showcase&lt;/strong&gt; is a feature that allows you to show off your creative work. It looks almost like a social network. Players can upload photos, replays, liveries, livery elements, helmets, and race suits for others to view, vote on, download, and apply to their own vehicles and drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-tracks&quot;&gt;The tracks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; features &lt;strong&gt;97 track layouts across 34 locations&lt;/strong&gt; (10 in the Americas, 15 in Europe, and nine in Asia and Oceania), and we were shown many of these in the video. The real tracks that appeared were…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Americas&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Europe&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Asia/Oceania&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Laguna Seca&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Brands Hatch&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Autopolis&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Willow Springs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Goodwood&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Suzuka&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Daytona&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Red Bull Ring&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Fuji Speedway&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Interlagos*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Monza&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tsukuba&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Nurburgring&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Mount Panorama&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Circuit de la Sarthe*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Barcelona-Catalunya*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Spa-Francorchamps*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Some circuits were not shown in the circuit selection screen, but were visible either through gameplay footage or other menus (e.g. licence tests).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the classic fictional &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; tracks were also shown to be back with a visual upgrade. Those shown in the video were…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Americas&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Europe&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Asia/Oceania&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Blue Moon Bay Speedway&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Deep Forest Raceway&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;High Speed Ring&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Northern Isle Speedway&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Dragon Trail&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Kyoto Driving Park&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trial Mountain&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Sardegna&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tokyo Expressway&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Maggiore&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Broad Bean Raceway&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Alsace&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I spotted 29 circuits over the course of the deep dive video. It’s possible I may have missed others (please let me know if so), but for now that would mean there are five other locations yet to be revealed - two in Europe, and three in the Americas. As with cars, we have also been promised that additional tracks will be delivered via online updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;physics-graphics-and-effects&quot;&gt;Physics, graphics, and effects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polyphony Digital boasted that &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;’s driving model was refined based on feedback from experts such as Lewis Hamilton, GT drivers, and tyre manufacturer Michelin. The physics simulation takes into account factors like car setup, wind, and slipstream to ensure realistic handling, and lap times in the game should reflect their real-life counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some features were notably flagged as unique to the PlayStation 5. These included &lt;strong&gt;ray tracing&lt;/strong&gt;, the use of the DualSense controller’s haptic triggers to provide handling feedback (for example, simulating a locked tyre), and a &lt;strong&gt;3D audio&lt;/strong&gt; system that is supposed to give a better sense of where sounds are coming from. It’ll be interesting to see how much is missing for PS4 owners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real star of the show as far as graphics and effects were concerned, however, was the day/night cycle and weather. The developers have used meteorological data to simulate cloud formations unique to each geographical region, so for example the skies will behave differently in California and Japan. Stars, the moon, and even planets will appear in the night sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;’s rain looks spectacular, particularly the way the water sprays off the tyres. Track moisture is dynamic, meaning that when it stops raining the racing line dries out first, and a &lt;strong&gt;weather radar&lt;/strong&gt; has been added to help players track incoming rain clouds. Additionally, it was explained that on large tracks it can be raining in some areas but not others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, it might seem like a small detail to mention, but one other thing I noticed during this section of the video is that spectators are not static any longer. In a timelapse video showing off the rain effects, I noted that people were walking around in the spectator areas in the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;campaign-mode&quot;&gt;Campaign mode&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously known as GT mode, &lt;strong&gt;campaign mode&lt;/strong&gt; is where many players will spend most of their time. The setup looks similar to previous &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; games - you’re given a small number if credits (it looks like 20,000) to buy a car, and earn additional credits and cars by winning races and series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of other interesting features were shown, but not explained. Firstly, “collector points” were granted when the player won a new car, and there was some sort of levelling system. Secondly, after a race a progress bar named “&lt;strong&gt;daily workout&lt;/strong&gt;” filled up. When the objective was completed, the reward was a “roulette ticket”, which had “availability” for a particular date. It’ll be interesting to see what this is, but it feels a bit loot box-y…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another notable addition is the &lt;strong&gt;Gran Turismo Cafe&lt;/strong&gt;, which we were told sits at the centre of the map. Players are given a car collection menu (a set of cars they must aim to acquire), and on completion they receive rewards (the roulette ticket showed up here, too) and unlock tracks. The cafe is also where some of the aforementioned car commentary comes into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-modes&quot;&gt;Other modes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plethora of other modes were also sprinkled throughout the video. The most notable for me was the &lt;strong&gt;Custom Race&lt;/strong&gt; mode, which didn’t always appear in older &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; titles. This is essentially the sandbox offered by other games like &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/project-cars&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project Cars&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Assetto Corsa&lt;/em&gt;, allowing the player to select a track, cars, weather conditions and so on to set up their own races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere there was a &lt;strong&gt;Circuit Experience&lt;/strong&gt; mode, designed to help you to learn new tracks, and “&lt;strong&gt;mission races&lt;/strong&gt;”, which are special events that differ from the usual formula, like drag races and drift trials. The classic &lt;strong&gt;licence tests&lt;/strong&gt; also return, putting players through their paces to learn racecraft and spend hours driving the same few metres to earn that elusive gold trophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music was the slightly odd focus of some of the modes shown. Replays can now be set to music, with the camera changing in time with the soundtrack, but the effect wasn’t so different to a standard replay in my opinion. The highlight in this rather niche genre was the &lt;strong&gt;Music Rally&lt;/strong&gt; mode - basically a checkpoint race where the countdown syncs to the beat of the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, we were shown some of &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;’s multiplayer options, including &lt;strong&gt;two-player local split screen&lt;/strong&gt;, which is welcome, if a bit of a throwback. Online, there are lobbies and “meeting places”, which we were told are good for playing with friends, and &lt;strong&gt;Sport Mode&lt;/strong&gt;, which is where we can partake in “serious racing” with players around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t sure how much more we’d see of &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; before its release on 4th March, but not only did this video drop a lot more detail, it also served to further whet my appetite for some racing in a month’s time. With the launch date approaching at a rapid pace, this may well be my final opportunity to speculate about the game before it comes out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With its attention to detail and huge range of modes that should cater to both the sim racing and arcade racing fans out there, this game has the potential to be something really special. The addition of the historical content and dedication to the stories behind the pretty cars is something I’ve never seen in a video game before, and shows that the designers and developers are truly dedicated to their subject matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s one thing I’m still a little skeptical about, it’s that we still haven’t seen any footage from a PlayStation 4 console - let alone the original model. PlayStation 5 players are worried that the existence of a PS4 version will mean the game will have to hold back in some respects, but my concern is over performance and missing features on last-gen hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, it’s rare for me to be this excited about a game, and it’s even rarer for me to have sustained that excitement through the entire pre-release period. With solid on-track action, beautiful graphics, a generous selection of cars and tracks, stunning weather, and all the colour and educational aspects that come with the focus on “car culture”, &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; could be the definitive racing game - we’ll just have to wait to find out for sure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="gran-turismo" /><category term="racing" /><summary type="html">It’s no secret that I am very excited for Gran Turismo 7, so when we got a 32-minute “deep dive” video from the PlayStation State of Play this week, it only seemed right for me to dissect every second of it try to gather all the little details and clues about what we can expect to see in March. The video starred series producer Kazunori Yamauchi, speaking via a translator. He touted the new game, which marks Gran Turismo’s 25th anniversary, as “the most complete Gran Turismo to date” and revealed a whole range of features and details that we hadn’t seen before, including more about the game’s focus on “car culture” as well as the actual racing. What follows is a summary of what I could ascertain from the video, which confirmed it’s going to be a long wait until the 4th March release date. The cars Yamauchi revealed that Gran Turismo 7 will feature more than 400 cars. Over the course of the video we were treated to shots of road cars, sports cars, GT cars, historic cars, rally cars, and concept cars, confirming that the catalogue has all the variety that we’ve come to expect from the series. It was promised that additional cars will be delivered via online updates. We were shown several places to buy cars. Brand Central is a shopping centre where players can buy around 300 new cars from 2001 and later. The used car dealer will sell a different lineup of cars on a daily basis. These will generally be more affordable, but some models (the example given was 90s Japanese sports cars) will actually accrue value. The last marketplace shown was Brighton Antiques, a place to buy legendary and famous cars like the Le Mans-winning Ford GT40 and James Bond’s Aston Martin DB5.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_15.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/02/gran-turismo-7_15.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Microsoft, Activision Blizzard, and the future of gaming</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/22/microsoft-activision-blizzard" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Microsoft, Activision Blizzard, and the future of gaming" /><published>2022-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/22/microsoft-activision-blizzard</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/22/microsoft-activision-blizzard">&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a blog about the business of video games, but there was one piece of industry news this week that was such a shock that I had to cover it - Microsoft’s $69 billion acquisition of Activision Blizzard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/microsoft-activision-blizzard_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-long-time-coming&quot;&gt;A long time coming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really, this story started a lot earlier than that. Back in 2013, Microsoft was battered by critics following its announcement of the next-generation Xbox One console. While the Xbox 360 had won over gamers with its hefty library of acclaimed games, Microsoft’s promotional material for its new console was heavily focused on its multimedia capabilities and Kinect voice commands - an ethos embedded so deeply into the Xbox One’s design that it had an HDMI in port so users could route over video devices through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, along with some of the decisions around DRM and making the console online-only, was a serious misjudgement. Gamers previously addicted to &lt;em&gt;Gears of War&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Halo&lt;/em&gt; felt abandoned in favour of a more general, casual audience. Sony siezed its opportunity, using the slogan “for the players” for the competing PlayStation 4 and pushing a slew of exclusive titles to win over the masses - &lt;em&gt;Bloodborne&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Uncharted 4&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spider-Man&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;God of War&lt;/em&gt;. As of mid-2021, it was reported that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vgchartz.com/article/449842/switch-vs-ps4-vs-xbox-one-global-lifetime-sales-june-2021/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the PS4 had sold more than 115 million units&lt;/a&gt;, with the Xbox One lagging behind with sales of 50 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/microsoft-activision-blizzard_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the next generation came around in 2019, Microsoft was determined not to make the same mistake again. The new Xbox Series X was slightly more powerful than Sony’s PlayStation 5, and from the beginning it was clear that Microsoft’s focus was on the games - even the initial announcment trailer prominently featured Master Chief (&lt;em&gt;Halo Infinite&lt;/em&gt; would shortly follow), and the Xbox Game Pass became a clear focus for the company.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More significant changes were ongoing behind the scenes. Even as far back as 2014, Microsoft had acquired &lt;em&gt;Minecraft&lt;/em&gt; developer Mojang for $2.5 billion. Four developer acquisitions, including &lt;em&gt;Forza Horizon&lt;/em&gt; maker Playground Games, were announced at E3 2018, followed the next year by Double Fine, famous for &lt;em&gt;Psychonauts&lt;/em&gt;. The message was clear: Microsoft - and by extension Xbox - was all about the games now, and it would spare no expense in securing the manpower and creativity to make them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most significant acquisition for Xbox Game Studios came in September 2020, when it was announced Microsoft would pay $7.5 billion for ZeniMax Media, whose family of studios included Bethesda (&lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fallout 4&lt;/em&gt;), Arkane (&lt;em&gt;Prey&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Deathloop&lt;/em&gt;), id (&lt;em&gt;Doom&lt;/em&gt;), and MachineGames (&lt;em&gt;Wolfenstein&lt;/em&gt;). Shortly afterwards, it was confirmed that Bethesda’s as yet unnamed &lt;em&gt;Elder Scrolls VI&lt;/em&gt; game would be an Xbox and PC exclusive - a massive win for Microsoft considering that its predecessor &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt; sold more than 30 million copies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this was nothing compared to what was to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;activision-blizzard-king&quot;&gt;Activision Blizzard King&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a massive technology company trying to convince gamers to buy your console and subscribe to your games service, what’s the next biggest title you could add to your portfolio? You could certainly do a lot worse than industry heavyweights like &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Warcraft&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Overwatch&lt;/em&gt;, and even former PlayStation poster boys &lt;em&gt;Crash Bandicoot&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Spyro the Dragon&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;COD&lt;/em&gt; alone sells up to 30 million units per game, which is staggering when you consider that entries in the series are released on an annual basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there were the circumstances. Activision Blizzard has been under fire for nearly a year over its reported “frat boy” working culture, and in July 2021 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2021-07-22-state-of-california-sues-activision-blizzard-over-frat-boy-culture&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;was sued by the State of California&lt;/a&gt;. Amongst other accusations, the lawsuit alleged that female employees were subjected to “sexual harassment with no repercussion”. These claims were heavily covered in the gaming media and beyond, and would have dented the company’s reputation and, one would think by extension, its valuation in any potential deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/microsoft-activision-blizzard_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so Microsoft pounced. On 18th January 2022, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2022-01-18-microsoft-near-deal-to-buy-call-of-duty-maker-activision-blizzard-report&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Microsoft announced that it would pay $68.7 billion cash to acquire Activision Blizzard King&lt;/a&gt; (which also included the developer of the mobile phenomenon &lt;em&gt;Candy Crush&lt;/em&gt;). As far as many gamers were concerned, this came completely out of the blue, and sent shockwaves through Twitter and games news websites and blogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the initial announcement came a series of comments and clarifications. Microsoft said it was aware that Activision Blizzard games were popular across many platforms and that it planned to “continue to support those communities”. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2022-01-20-sony-says-it-expects-microsoft-to-ensure-activision-games-are-multiplatform&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sony issued a statement&lt;/a&gt; to say it expected Microsoft to “abide by contractual agreements and continue to ensure Activision games are multi-platform”. And &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2022-01-20/activision-employees-say-they-re-optimistic-about-acquisition&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;according to &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, employees at the company are optimistic that the new owner will help to bring about the cultural change required to make it a better place to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-next-for-gaming&quot;&gt;What next for gaming?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does all this mean for the average gamer? First, as the console wars intensify, expect more exclusives. Fine, you might think - I’ll just buy an Xbox and guarantee that I’ll be able to play &lt;em&gt;The Elder Scrolls&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/em&gt;. But what if (for example) Sony decides to buy EA and fragment the market further? Then, much like how you need Netflix, Amazon Prime, and Disney+ to watch all your favourite TV series, you’d need to splash out on an Xbox and a PlayStation to play all of your favourite games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alternative is that Microsoft is doing all of this to bolster its Game Pass offering. Third-party publishers might not see the value of putting their brand new flagship games on the streaming service and losing sales, but if the studios become a part of Xbox then that barrier is removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/microsoft-activision-blizzard_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking this a step further, could we eventually see Microsoft leave the console market altogether? What if Game Pass was eventually its main offering, allowing you to play a huge games library across your PC or - God forbid - your PlayStation? Perhaps we’ll even reach a point where physical hardware is not required, and instead you connect a controller to your TV and all Microsoft’s games are processed in the cloud and streamed to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody knows for sure what Microsoft’s long-term plan is except Microsoft itself. It’ll be interesting to see how all of this plays out - especially if it does come to the point where gamers are told that physical ownership is outdated, when many players take great pleasure in building a library of boxes and discs, and all the pride and security that come with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only time will tell, so watch this space.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="xbox" /><category term="industry" /><category term="call-of-duty" /><summary type="html">This isn’t a blog about the business of video games, but there was one piece of industry news this week that was such a shock that I had to cover it - Microsoft’s $69 billion acquisition of Activision Blizzard. A long time coming Really, this story started a lot earlier than that. Back in 2013, Microsoft was battered by critics following its announcement of the next-generation Xbox One console. While the Xbox 360 had won over gamers with its hefty library of acclaimed games, Microsoft’s promotional material for its new console was heavily focused on its multimedia capabilities and Kinect voice commands - an ethos embedded so deeply into the Xbox One’s design that it had an HDMI in port so users could route over video devices through it. This, along with some of the decisions around DRM and making the console online-only, was a serious misjudgement. Gamers previously addicted to Gears of War and Halo felt abandoned in favour of a more general, casual audience. Sony siezed its opportunity, using the slogan “for the players” for the competing PlayStation 4 and pushing a slew of exclusive titles to win over the masses - Bloodborne, Uncharted 4, Spider-Man, God of War. As of mid-2021, it was reported that the PS4 had sold more than 115 million units, with the Xbox One lagging behind with sales of 50 million. When the next generation came around in 2019, Microsoft was determined not to make the same mistake again. The new Xbox Series X was slightly more powerful than Sony’s PlayStation 5, and from the beginning it was clear that Microsoft’s focus was on the games - even the initial announcment trailer prominently featured Master Chief (Halo Infinite would shortly follow), and the Xbox Game Pass became a clear focus for the company.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/microsoft-activision-blizzard_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/microsoft-activision-blizzard_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Project Zomboid is a true sandbox game</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/29/project-zomboid-true-sandbox-game" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project Zomboid is a true sandbox game" /><published>2022-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/29/project-zomboid-true-sandbox-game</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/29/project-zomboid-true-sandbox-game">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; is yet another game that was sitting in my Steam library for a long time before I played it properly. Since the start of 2020, I’d clocked just ten hours (although granted a lot happened in the meantime). But when I saw its recent resurgence, I thought it was time to give it another go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-zomboid_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;virtual-playgrounds&quot;&gt;Virtual playgrounds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m always looking for better ways to explain what makes a game great for me. Recently, referring to a video about someone convincing his non-gamer girlfriend to play some games, &lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/gaming/comments/s9u9ta/friends_wife_started_playing_half_life_alyx_you/htpe90u/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a Redditor put it better than I could&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Her biggest complaint was that she couldn’t solve the problems as creatively as she wanted to and since she didn’t know common gaming tropes (like look at the thing in the room that’s a weird colour), it was difficult to figure out solutions that the game would actually accept.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even as somebody who recognises this kind of signposting, I think this is a reason why some games appeal to me more than others - for example, why I’ve never gotten into shooters as much as many other gamers. The games I enjoy - from &lt;em&gt;RollerCoaster Tycoon&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/the-sims&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, from &lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Assetto Corsa&lt;/em&gt; - all give the player an environment, a set of rules, and the freedom to do pretty much whatever they want. When the player asks a reasonable “Can I…?” question to these games, the answer is usually yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;into-the-wild&quot;&gt;Into the wild&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; takes this to a level I’ve never seen before. The game tasks the player with surviving a zombie apocalypse. They must find shelter, gather and prepare food, and defend themselves from the horde to live for as long as possible. There are no respawns - when your character dies, they’re dead. Everything that happens in between is up to your own inginuity.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d bounced off the game a few times because this can make it super difficult. A momentary lapse in concentration can lead to your character getting overrun, bitten, and infected. This meant I never lasted more than a few hours before losing everything. But like all good sandbox games, &lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; gives you the sliders to set up the scenario just how you want it. When somebody on Twitter recommended that I make things a bit easier for myself, I was finally able to interact with the game’s systems properly and came to understand them better, and that’s what got me hooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-zomboid_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game’s graphics are reminiscent of the original &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;, but the systems behind &lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; are immense. Everything from wellbeing to clothing, cooking to crafting, weather to vehicles, has such depth that each of them takes a while to learn on its own. In this respect it’s what I refer to as a “wiki game”, in that you’ll inevitably need to run the occasional web search to learn how to do something, but you don’t want to read online material for hours on end and ruin all the surprises for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-little-things&quot;&gt;The little things&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’ll save all that for the full review I’ll post soon once I’ve had more time to explore. Returning to my original point, what makes &lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; great is that you can intuit what to do based on what would work in real life. Examples of this that I’ve encountered so far include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Any empty container - bottles, pans, baths, etc. - can be filled with water, either to carry around with you and drink or to stockpile in case the utilities fail and the taps no longer run&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most clothing gathered by looting and from zombie corpses can be ripped into strips to dress your wounds if you’re scratched or bitten&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exercises like press-ups, sit-ups, and squats can help to keep your character fit, but your physical effectiveness will be reduced the next day when the corresponding muscles ache&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you can’t find an unlocked door or window to get into a building, you can smash a window instead - but you must remember to remove the broken glass or you’ll get cut climbing through&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level of detail is quite amazing. I imagine this is great for roleplayers, but even as a regular player it’s fantastic to be rewarded for thinking about small things that most games would ignore. Working out &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to do some things can be tricky - and that’s where the wiki comes in - but I feel like that is more than made up for each time you pull off your latest plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll cover &lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; in a much more detailed review in a few weeks, but for now I just wanted to say how much I’m enjoying it and encourage you to give it a go - even if it is with the difficulty turned down a notch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="project-zomboid" /><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">Project Zomboid is yet another game that was sitting in my Steam library for a long time before I played it properly. Since the start of 2020, I’d clocked just ten hours (although granted a lot happened in the meantime). But when I saw its recent resurgence, I thought it was time to give it another go. Virtual playgrounds I’m always looking for better ways to explain what makes a game great for me. Recently, referring to a video about someone convincing his non-gamer girlfriend to play some games, a Redditor put it better than I could: “Her biggest complaint was that she couldn’t solve the problems as creatively as she wanted to and since she didn’t know common gaming tropes (like look at the thing in the room that’s a weird colour), it was difficult to figure out solutions that the game would actually accept.” Even as somebody who recognises this kind of signposting, I think this is a reason why some games appeal to me more than others - for example, why I’ve never gotten into shooters as much as many other gamers. The games I enjoy - from RollerCoaster Tycoon to The Sims, from Grand Theft Auto to Assetto Corsa - all give the player an environment, a set of rules, and the freedom to do pretty much whatever they want. When the player asks a reasonable “Can I…?” question to these games, the answer is usually yes. Into the wild Project Zomboid takes this to a level I’ve never seen before. The game tasks the player with surviving a zombie apocalypse. They must find shelter, gather and prepare food, and defend themselves from the horde to live for as long as possible. There are no respawns - when your character dies, they’re dead. Everything that happens in between is up to your own inginuity.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-zomboid_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-zomboid_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">In defence of scripting in football games</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/15/defence-of-scripting-football-games" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In defence of scripting in football games" /><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/15/defence-of-scripting-football-games</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/15/defence-of-scripting-football-games">&lt;p&gt;Spend any length of time reading online forums for football games and you’ll come across complaints about “scripting” - the alleged way games like &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; artificially infuence games to create drama. This quirk of games’ design and programming is always portrayed in a negative light, and often rightly so, but I’d like to make a case for why it makes sense and improves the gameplay experience in certain circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-scripting&quot;&gt;What is scripting?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the critics, “scripting” - sometimes also referred to as “momentum” - is a perversion of the way football games should play. Unlike real football, &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; matches are under the complete control of a match engine, and by extension, the developers. And there have been accusations for years that EA Sports (and Konami, before &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/01/efootball-2022-first-impressions&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;eFootball&lt;/em&gt; killed the &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; series&lt;/a&gt;) has abused this power to create as much drama as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To those who are on the lookout for potential foul play, this invisible hand makes itself known in semi-predictable ways, usually to give teams suffering heavy losses a fighting chance or to prevent the player team from running away with every match, or the league title. Some of the most common complaints allege that scripting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Makes goals easier for both teams to score in the final minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Causes shots to hit the post, passes to go off course, etc. when the game doesn’t “want” the player to win the game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grants even the weakest opponents - and in particular goalkeepers - superstar skills if the game favours them in the match&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensures Career Mode rivals win the player wins, draws when the player draws, etc. to keep the title race as close as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many players say the biggest giveaway that scripting has taken effect is when one team has far more possession and shots on goal but fails to win. This has become something of a meme, particularly in &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/01/25/football-manager-addictive-spreadsheet/&quot;&gt;the stats-obsessed world of &lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and was probably at least partly responsible for the emergence of the expected goals (xG) metric in the real game.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of this may be coincidence, of course, and the big teams do suffer these frustrating matches in the Premier League and beyond. EA has denied that it scripting exists in &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; (as far as I know, Konami has never spoken on the issue), so it could be that what is observed is not the result of an algorithm designed to control the outcome of matches, and instead a culmunation of all the systems that simulate form, fatigue, skills, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the frequency of these events has convinced some players that scripting exists. What would be the developers’ motive to implement it, you might ask? The purported answer is that the added drama makes the game more emotional and therefore more addictive, as well as encouraging less skilled players by ensuring they always have a chance at securing a freak win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody except the developers knows whether scripting really exists in any given game, or to what level it influences matches, but I’ve seen enough evidence in my own play to suspect it’s there in some form. The assumption I’m never sure about, however, is that a “pure” football game would play better. The scripting rumours have persisted in one form or another since the mid-2000s, and there have been &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;some great football games&lt;/a&gt; in that time. So when does it work and when does it not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;when-scripting-works&quot;&gt;When scripting works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I will concede that scripting would be very frustrating in online game modes, where you usually only play each opponent once and therefore don’t have a chance for the luck to level out. It would also affect online rankings, promotion and relegation from divisions, and so on. It would be even worse if it spanned to modes where money is involved, but we have at least had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2021-03-03-fifa-scripting-lawsuit-withdrawn-after-ea-provides-plaintiffs-with-detailed-technical-information-and-access-to-speak-with-our-engineers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;confirmation from EA that there is no scripting in Ultimate Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But offline, I believe it can actually create a more enjoyable experience. This is certainly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the case my Chelsea side visit Burnley and lose to two wonder goals, but it can certainly liven up games against weaker teams. Statistically you’d expect the big club to pervail comfortably, but that’s not always the case in real life and constant 3-0 wins would get boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my best &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; games have been those where everything seems to be going the opposition’s way. When I play Southampton at home and they park the bus I can spend nearly the whole game trying to pick apart the AI’s defence, their goalkeeper performing all kinds of acrobatics when I get the odd shot away. When a chance falls to my striker with two minutes to go I expect him to miss because he’s barely been able to control the ball for 88 minutes, but when the ball hits the back of the net and secures the 1-0 win, that hard-fought triumph is one of the best feelings in the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “scripting” - or at least the randomised part of the game that leads people to &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; there is scripting - leads to added challenge and interesting stories in games that might have been nothing but boring domination. This reflects real life matches, when big teams have off days against bottom-of-the-table sides using very defensive setups, and really adds tension to the in-game title battle when I know City and Liverpool are winning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, scripting or not, unpredictability is what makes football the world’s favourite sport and what makes football games worth playing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="pro-evolution-soccer" /><category term="football" /><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">Spend any length of time reading online forums for football games and you’ll come across complaints about “scripting” - the alleged way games like FIFA and PES artificially infuence games to create drama. This quirk of games’ design and programming is always portrayed in a negative light, and often rightly so, but I’d like to make a case for why it makes sense and improves the gameplay experience in certain circumstances. What is scripting? According to the critics, “scripting” - sometimes also referred to as “momentum” - is a perversion of the way football games should play. Unlike real football, FIFA matches are under the complete control of a match engine, and by extension, the developers. And there have been accusations for years that EA Sports (and Konami, before eFootball killed the PES series) has abused this power to create as much drama as possible. To those who are on the lookout for potential foul play, this invisible hand makes itself known in semi-predictable ways, usually to give teams suffering heavy losses a fighting chance or to prevent the player team from running away with every match, or the league title. Some of the most common complaints allege that scripting: Makes goals easier for both teams to score in the final minutes Causes shots to hit the post, passes to go off course, etc. when the game doesn’t “want” the player to win the game Grants even the weakest opponents - and in particular goalkeepers - superstar skills if the game favours them in the match Ensures Career Mode rivals win the player wins, draws when the player draws, etc. to keep the title race as close as possible Many players say the biggest giveaway that scripting has taken effect is when one team has far more possession and shots on goal but fails to win. This has become something of a meme, particularly in the stats-obsessed world of Football Manager, and was probably at least partly responsible for the emergence of the expected goals (xG) metric in the real game.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/scripting_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIFA is my new year’s resolution (kind of)</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/08/fifa-new-years-resolution" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA is my new year's resolution &amp;#40;kind of&amp;#41;" /><published>2022-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/08/fifa-new-years-resolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/01/08/fifa-new-years-resolution">&lt;p&gt;There’s an episode of &lt;em&gt;South Park&lt;/em&gt; that first aired about a decade ago where Stan wakes up one day and everything is shit. The food he eats is shit. The chatter on the radio is shit. The new films at the cinema are shit. Everything he used to like is at best unremarkable and at worst unforgivably flawed. He has grown up, and in doing so has turned into a cynic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently realised that was what I had become in recent years. A duo of experience (a sense of having seen it all before) and jadedness (thanks in large part to online commenters finding fault in just about everything) meant I couldn’t enjoy a lot of things I used to. My favourite band’s latest album wasn’t a patch on their output in the early 2000s, and new games were full of microtransactions and soulless compared to classics from years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cutting-out-the-noise&quot;&gt;Cutting out the noise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 2022, I’ve decided to put a stop to this. I’m not the complete isolation “cabin in the woods” type, but I do believe that one of the pitfalls of the internet age is that we’re exposed to a deluge of opinion on just about everything. If you and a couple of your friends like a new TV series then that’s no longer enough - you’ll also feel inclined to seek out its subreddit and pore over the world’s thoughts on each episode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this works as intended, it’s amazing. We get fruitful discussions with people all over the place about interests that might not be popular where we’re from. When it doesn’t, we find ourselves second guessing everything we like, wondering what flaw a hypothetical cynic might point out. When that second mindset takes hold it becomes very difficult to enjoy anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; series, for example. The internet’s view of the games is that they change very little each year, lure kids into what are at best frivolous microtransactions and at worst casino-emulating lootboxes, and are plagued with bugs and scripted results. With all that in mind, why bother playing?&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;giving-games-a-chance&quot;&gt;Giving games a chance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I fancied playing a football game, and given that &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/01/efootball-2022-first-impressions&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;eFootball&lt;/em&gt; has effectively killed the &lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt; series&lt;/a&gt;, I switched on a digital copy of &lt;em&gt;FIFA 20&lt;/em&gt; that I picked up for about £5 in a sale last year to give it another go. Just as importantly, I made a conscious effort to make my mind a clean slate, free of past judgements and crticisms I’d read about the series. I decided I would judge it only by what was directly in front of me on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having played nearly a season’s worth of Career Mode in the last week, I can say that &lt;em&gt;FIFA 20&lt;/em&gt; is a solid football game. It looks great - the stadiums in particular look just like their real-world counterparts. The animations are as slick as you like. The opponents are challenging and varied, and some of my favourite matches are when teams come to Stamford Bridge to park the bus and I have to unpick their defences. And the whole thing has a lot of fanfare about it. &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; feels connected to the wider football world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Games are never perfect, and this is no exception - including in some of the ways commonly pointed out online. Career Mode itself does enough, but hasn’t substantially changed in years. Sometimes players don’t react the way you want or expect them to. And every so often you find yourself in a game where your relegation fodder opponents play like prime Barcelona and you’re in for a grind because the game &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; you to lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while I might previously have tuned out or lost interest, I now look past these minor annoyances and consider the sum of the game. I think about some of the retro games I’ve played - &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;even all-time classics like &lt;em&gt;PES5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - and know they also had flaws that were overlooked because I was simply having too much fun. Then I stop analysing everything, focus on the game, and try to let the atmosphere absorb me as I push for the next goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lifes-too-short-not-to-have-fun&quot;&gt;Life’s too short not to have fun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the attitude I’m trying to keep with me in 2022. Whether it’s in gaming, film, television, music - even politics - I’m going to try to cut myself off from the online commentary, consume media and make my own mind up before I read about anything, and hopefully find more fun and enjoyment than I have for some without the internet spoiling everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not about putting up with bad games or manipulative practices. I’ll still call out features I think could be improved and content I think should have been included in the box price. But I want my enjoyment or disappointment with each game to come from my personal preferences and judgements - not what somebody else got stuck in my head before I even started playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So happy new year to everybody who has stumbled upon &lt;em&gt;The Strat Pack&lt;/em&gt;! I hope you have a fantastic 2022 and discover a ton of things you love. And if you find any gems you think I’d like, please do share them with me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">There’s an episode of South Park that first aired about a decade ago where Stan wakes up one day and everything is shit. The food he eats is shit. The chatter on the radio is shit. The new films at the cinema are shit. Everything he used to like is at best unremarkable and at worst unforgivably flawed. He has grown up, and in doing so has turned into a cynic. I recently realised that was what I had become in recent years. A duo of experience (a sense of having seen it all before) and jadedness (thanks in large part to online commenters finding fault in just about everything) meant I couldn’t enjoy a lot of things I used to. My favourite band’s latest album wasn’t a patch on their output in the early 2000s, and new games were full of microtransactions and soulless compared to classics from years ago. Cutting out the noise For 2022, I’ve decided to put a stop to this. I’m not the complete isolation “cabin in the woods” type, but I do believe that one of the pitfalls of the internet age is that we’re exposed to a deluge of opinion on just about everything. If you and a couple of your friends like a new TV series then that’s no longer enough - you’ll also feel inclined to seek out its subreddit and pore over the world’s thoughts on each episode. When this works as intended, it’s amazing. We get fruitful discussions with people all over the place about interests that might not be popular where we’re from. When it doesn’t, we find ourselves second guessing everything we like, wondering what flaw a hypothetical cynic might point out. When that second mindset takes hold it becomes very difficult to enjoy anything. Take the FIFA series, for example. The internet’s view of the games is that they change very little each year, lure kids into what are at best frivolous microtransactions and at worst casino-emulating lootboxes, and are plagued with bugs and scripted results. With all that in mind, why bother playing?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fifa-20_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Classic Splinter Cell is back after a 15-year hiatus!</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/18/splinter-cell-remake" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Classic Splinter Cell is back after a 15-year hiatus!" /><published>2021-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/18/splinter-cell-remake</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/18/splinter-cell-remake">&lt;p&gt;Ubisoft has announced that it’s working on a &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake! This Christmas miracle landed on my desk just in time for the last article of the year, so join me one last time in 2021 as we run through what we know (and what we don’t) about this long-awaited revival of a beloved series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a long time coming. There hasn’t been a &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; game at all since 2013’s &lt;em&gt;Blacklist&lt;/em&gt;, and many fans (myself included) feel there hasn’t been an entry that has respected the series’ stealth ethos in more than 15 years. After all that time, many thought that Sam Fisher might never return to the shadows, and so many rumours circulated over the years that it became easy to dismiss any talk of a new game instantly. But here we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/splinter-cell_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you believe the people in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HH1_ZCSf_HY&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the promotional YouTube video&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; is valued as the series that defined what Ubisoft could make - and could be - at a time when it was largely known for &lt;em&gt;Rayman&lt;/em&gt;. Fast forward to 2021 and you might be a little nervous, as the company is now known for churning out regular &lt;em&gt;Assassin’s Creed&lt;/em&gt; games and its recent player-angering announcement that it would be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pcgamer.com/ubisofts-nft-scheme-criticized-as-useless-costly-ecologically-mortifying-by-french-trade-union/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;introducing NFTs to some of its upcoming titles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, all the noises coming from the developers in the video make it sound like they understand and cherish what made &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; special. All the key elements - the importance of light and shadow, the little details like realistic bullet holes in fish tanks, and of course Sam’s signature night vision and infrared goggles - are discussed. The team also note the cinematic nature of the game and its story (although there’s been no word yet on whether fan favourite Michael Ironside will reprise the lead role or not).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-do-we-know&quot;&gt;What do we know?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But really, we currently know very little about the new &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake. After dissecting the video and &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ubisoft.com/en-us/article/4adJLuhgYrPboHAPRfK7Oz/splinter-cell-remake-begins-development-at-ubisoft-toronto&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the accompanying Ubisoft press release&lt;/a&gt;, I can say only the following for certain (as far as anything is certain in gaming):&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The remake is being developed by Ubisoft Toronto and is in “the earliest stages of development”, so don’t expect it any time soon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game is being rebuilt using the Snowdrop engine, which is the same one used by Ubisoft’s upcoming &lt;em&gt;Avatar&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; games&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many of the team are “stealth purists” who worked on earlier &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; games and want to their “spirit” to “remain intact”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game will remain linear, which hopefully means &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; will avoid the curse of Ubisoft’s frequently bland open-world collectathons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unlike more recent games in the series, the remake will reward players who play tactically with the objective to “be a ghost”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The remake will receive a visual upgrade with possible innovation in animation, AI, and audio - Ubisoft says this will deliver “the spirit of the old with the comfort of the new”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in summary: not much. We can essentially say that Ubisoft is working on a &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake that will be available at some point in the distant future and will bear some level of resemblance to the older games in the series, but details are certainly very thin on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cautious-optimism&quot;&gt;Cautious optimism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s probably too early to get excited, but as somebody who’s been waiting for a “real” &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; game since 2006’s &lt;em&gt;Double Agent&lt;/em&gt; (or 2005’s &lt;em&gt;Chaos Theory&lt;/em&gt;, if we’re being less generous) it’s very difficult not to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the unease underlying any optimism about the &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake is necessary because of how much the games industry has changed since the first game’s release in 2002. New entries in beloved series are launched as £60 microtransaction shopfronts, single player campaigns bizarrely require internet connections, and companies that always have their sights set on the next trendy buzzword now see NFTs as their next big moneymaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/splinter-cell_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent example of a rerelease gone wrong was &lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto Trilogy - The Definitive Edition&lt;/em&gt;, which initially looked like some easy fan service to restore some old favourites but turned awry when Rockstar delivered an often ugly, glitchy mess for the full retail price of a brand new game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the &lt;em&gt;Splinter Cell&lt;/em&gt; remake falter in a similar way? For now I can take some comfort in the developers’ words and the fact that this appears to be a full remake (unlike &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt;, which was only a remaster), but we’ll only find out for sure as we get more details, gameplay videos, and eventually get our hands on the full game. It’s going to be a long wait for sure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="splinter-cell" /><category term="stealth" /><summary type="html">Ubisoft has announced that it’s working on a Splinter Cell remake! This Christmas miracle landed on my desk just in time for the last article of the year, so join me one last time in 2021 as we run through what we know (and what we don’t) about this long-awaited revival of a beloved series. It’s been a long time coming. There hasn’t been a Splinter Cell game at all since 2013’s Blacklist, and many fans (myself included) feel there hasn’t been an entry that has respected the series’ stealth ethos in more than 15 years. After all that time, many thought that Sam Fisher might never return to the shadows, and so many rumours circulated over the years that it became easy to dismiss any talk of a new game instantly. But here we are. If you believe the people in the promotional YouTube video, Splinter Cell is valued as the series that defined what Ubisoft could make - and could be - at a time when it was largely known for Rayman. Fast forward to 2021 and you might be a little nervous, as the company is now known for churning out regular Assassin’s Creed games and its recent player-angering announcement that it would be introducing NFTs to some of its upcoming titles. Still, all the noises coming from the developers in the video make it sound like they understand and cherish what made Splinter Cell special. All the key elements - the importance of light and shadow, the little details like realistic bullet holes in fish tanks, and of course Sam’s signature night vision and infrared goggles - are discussed. The team also note the cinematic nature of the game and its story (although there’s been no word yet on whether fan favourite Michael Ironside will reprise the lead role or not). What do we know? But really, we currently know very little about the new Splinter Cell remake. After dissecting the video and the accompanying Ubisoft press release, I can say only the following for certain (as far as anything is certain in gaming):</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/splinter-cell_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/splinter-cell_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">You’re in the zone until you’re not</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/12/youre-in-the-zone-until-youre-not" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You're in the zone until you're not" /><published>2021-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/12/youre-in-the-zone-until-youre-not</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2021/12/12/youre-in-the-zone-until-youre-not">&lt;p&gt;Flow is a weird thing, all inconsistent and unpredictable. When I go to play a video game, one of two things can happen - either I will bounce straight off it almost immediately, or I’ll become completely immersed and play for hours and hours over a period of weeks before eventually burning out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent examples of games that haven’t properly captured my attention include &lt;em&gt;Project Zomboid&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/the-sims&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I’m sure they’re high-quality games, but they just didn’t grip me. And because they haven’t proven themselves to me in that way yet, I don’t know if they ever will. Meanwhile, I can go months without getting into &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/01/25/football-manager-addictive-spreadsheet/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Fallout 4&lt;/em&gt; and suddenly something will click and I’ll be sucked in all over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/verstappen-cc.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-flow-state&quot;&gt;The flow state&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is it that special place where a game keeps calling you back? Where you think about it when you’re not playing? I feel like it’s the same thing as flow, which is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;described by Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A flow state… is the mental state in which a person performing some activity is fully immersed in a feeling of energised focus, full involvement, and enjoyment in the process of the activity. In essence, flow is characterised by the complete absorption in what one does, and a resulting transformation in one’s sense of time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got thinking about this after seeing several examples of flow in action:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/10/running-formula-1-for-your-feet&quot;&gt;When I go running&lt;/a&gt;, sometimes I’m on complete autopilot, while other times I really feel the strain of each metre I cover.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been picking up my guitar more often recently. Sometimes I can play for hours and things just feel and sound right, but sometimes my timing and tone feels a little off no matter what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In sport, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/azzEnM6-Isk?t=295&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Max Verstappen’s almost-perfect qualifying lap&lt;/a&gt; at the Saudi Arabian Grand Prix, in which he appeared to be in a supreme flow state because colliding with a barrier on the final corner.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I described earlier in the article, my personal experience is that this phenomenon can also apply to gaming, both for the esports elites and for the casual gamer who can’t stop playing a title they’re hooked on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-into-the-zone&quot;&gt;Getting into the zone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what puts you “in the zone”? For me, a flow state sits on the border between comfort and discomfort. If a task is too easy then it is mundane. If it is too difficult then I may get frustrated or feel I’m not making progress and give up. In between, where an activity is challenging enough to keep me engrossed but easy enough that I feel like I’m achieving something, is where the best games keep me coming back for session after session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/transport-fever&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transport Fever 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. When I first picked it up I was playing it for weeks, battling to turn a profit on my transportation empire. But as I became more experienced with the game I developed a reliable strategy to repay the initial loan and build a functioning network. At this point the game became less challenging and it didn’t hold my attention as well as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tag/racing&quot;&gt;Racing games&lt;/a&gt; - most recently for me &lt;em&gt;Assetto Corsa&lt;/em&gt; - are also a good example of this theory in action. When I first play a new motorsport game, one of the key tasks is to finetune the AI until it provides just enough challenge and I am not regularly finishing either first or last. It’s a tricky balancing act, and when I get it right I can drive consecutive endurance races for a while. However, if I stop playing the game for long enough for any reason, my driving skills fade slightly, the game gets harder, and it’s more difficult to get back into because losing all the time is frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enabling-flow-with-game-design&quot;&gt;Enabling flow with game design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can this teach us about game design? If enabling a flow state is the way to keep players playing, this seems to leave devs with two options…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is to finetune difficulty to a level where a specific group of players find their zone. An example of this is the Amiga classic &lt;em&gt;Deluxe Galaga&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/11/20/pi-hut-retro-gaming-kit-retropie&quot;&gt;which I recently wrote about&lt;/a&gt; - you can’t change the difficulty and must raise your game to the challenge. This approach is less common in modern day gaming, probably because publishers want games to make as much money as possible, and setting the bar too high may alienate less skilled players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other option is to give the players the toolbox required to build their own perfect challenge. The AI ability and aggression sliders in most modern racing games are an example of this, as is the multitude of self-imposed challenges possible (and cheats available) in a sandbox game like &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;. However, the downside of this approach is that the player must invest a chunk of time to find the right balance for their ability, and less committed players may drop off before they find their own personal sweet spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s for more intelligent and serious minds than mine to decide what is the best answer for any particular game, but personally I vastly prefer the latter option. Not only does the sandbox approach let me tweak the game to the perfect level to induce my own flow state, but it also lets me adjust it for other states - if I’m tired, for example, or just want to experiment with the game’s sandbox rather than seeking victory or achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo © &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/79618484@N02/48733228773&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Interceptor73&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/?ref=ccsearch&amp;amp;atype=rich&quot;&gt;CC BY 2.0&lt;/a&gt;). Cropped.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">Flow is a weird thing, all inconsistent and unpredictable. When I go to play a video game, one of two things can happen - either I will bounce straight off it almost immediately, or I’ll become completely immersed and play for hours and hours over a period of weeks before eventually burning out. Recent examples of games that haven’t properly captured my attention include Project Zomboid and The Sims 4. I’m sure they’re high-quality games, but they just didn’t grip me. And because they haven’t proven themselves to me in that way yet, I don’t know if they ever will. Meanwhile, I can go months without getting into Football Manager or Fallout 4 and suddenly something will click and I’ll be sucked in all over again. The flow state What is it that special place where a game keeps calling you back? Where you think about it when you’re not playing? I feel like it’s the same thing as flow, which is described by Wikipedia as follows. “A flow state… is the mental state in which a person performing some activity is fully immersed in a feeling of energised focus, full involvement, and enjoyment in the process of the activity. In essence, flow is characterised by the complete absorption in what one does, and a resulting transformation in one’s sense of time.” I got thinking about this after seeing several examples of flow in action: When I go running, sometimes I’m on complete autopilot, while other times I really feel the strain of each metre I cover. I’ve been picking up my guitar more often recently. Sometimes I can play for hours and things just feel and sound right, but sometimes my timing and tone feels a little off no matter what I do. In sport, see Max Verstappen’s almost-perfect qualifying lap at the Saudi Arabian Grand Prix, in which he appeared to be in a supreme flow state because colliding with a barrier on the final corner.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/verstappen-cc.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2021/12/verstappen-cc.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>