<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-09-03T21:47:55+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">How to run a half marathon (better)</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/09/03/how-to-run-half-marathon-better" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to run a half marathon (better)" /><published>2023-09-03T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-09-03T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/09/03/how-to-run-half-marathon-better</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/09/03/how-to-run-half-marathon-better">&lt;p&gt;Long-time readers of this blog might remember that &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/09/09/how-to-run-half-marathon&quot;&gt;I ran a gruelling half marathon back in September 2022&lt;/a&gt;. I finished, but was reduced to a brisk walk at points, and ended up crossing the line in a disappointing 2 hours 20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was partly down to my preparation, which was interrupted for COVID-related reasons a month before the event, and partly due to pain in my knees (possibly related to needing to increase my distances so quickly), which started giving me hassle well before the halfway point and became unbearable later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I was determined not to let that happen again, and strove to achieve a result representative of my capability when the event arrived in September. So here goes another article about how to run a half marathon - but this time, better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/half-marathon_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;half-marathon-training-plan&quot;&gt;Half marathon training plan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I was going to avoid more disappointment, I couldn’t leave anything to chance. I knew I could run the 21.1km in less than two hours, but it would take commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 2023’s half marathon already in mind, I kept running through the winter, and slowly built up my distance over the year. This meant a religious schedule of two runs per week - a 7.5km midweek run and a maximum distance weekend run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept this up throughout 2023, with the exception of illness and holidays - although I did sneak in 12km along the Edogawa river &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/05/14/lesson-curiosity-japan&quot;&gt;when I was staying in Tokyo&lt;/a&gt;. Once I hit the half marathon distance I was aiming for, I alternated between that and 15km runs on the weekend to maintain my stamina while preserving my knees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Month&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Runs&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Avg. distance&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Longest distance&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;7.35km&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;7.44km&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;February&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;7.40km&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;7.44km&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;March&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;9.31km&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;12.26km&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;April&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;10.75km&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;15.71km&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;May&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;10.45km&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;15.16km&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;June&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;11.43km&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;17.42km&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;July&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;13.23km&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;21.84km&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;August&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;11.81km&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;21.23km&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By September, I’d run more than 640km in 2023, and had just enjoyed a serious morale boost from a couple of half marathon personal bests in August training runs (my record, which still stands at the time of writing, is 1 hour 57 minutes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gentler increases in distance were kinder to my knees than 2022’s messy training schedule, and not having to change running shoes at the last minute also probably helped. I had a slight nagging ankle injury in the weeks before the race, but took care to avoid exacerbating it, and felt ready to go as the big day approached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preparing-for-a-half-marathon&quot;&gt;Preparing for a half marathon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took my last light 7.5km warmup run on Wednesday morning, four days before the half marathon, to give my ankle some rest. I then turned my attention to some of the smaller aspects of preparation that I overlooked before last year’s race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the weeks leading up to the event I experimented with pre-run foods. The night before my final full-distance training run (which was the one where I set my personal best) I ate a big pasta meal, so I made sure to do the same on the Saturday night before the race to take on plenty of carbohydrates and build a store of energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also made the slightly risky but ultimately fruitful decision not to take a drink with me. In 2022, I carried a bottle of Lucozade Sport, a sugar-heavy beverage which was too sickly to drink mid-run. I’ve never taken water on my training runs, so I decided to ditch the extra weight and grab water at the checkpoints if I needed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;running-a-half-marathon-again&quot;&gt;Running a half marathon (again)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The morning arrived and I was feeling confident but still a little nervy. This wasn’t helped by a long wait before the start, as the organisers had moved from a rolling start to waves. It was approaching 20 degrees before I even got going, so I knew the heat would play a role since my training was mostly in the early mornings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set off, trying my best to ignore those around me and run at a natural pace. Every couple of kilometres I pulled out my phone and checked my pace - my personal best had an average pace of 5 minutes 33 seconds per kilometre, so if I caught myself going any faster I tried to slow down a little to keep some energy in the tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This worked very well for about 15km. My split times, taken at 5km intervals, showed my average pace per kilometre varied by just &lt;em&gt;two seconds&lt;/em&gt; over the first three quarters of the race, and I see that as a huge success in terms of pacing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was on for another personal best until the final six kilometres, where the fatigue from the heat really kicked in and my pace dropped to around 5 minutes 50 seconds per kilometre. It was rough going, with little shade and the only respite coming from a hose spraying cool water over the road outside the local fire station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I knew I was doing well, and I was still set on avoiding 2022’s disappointment, so I kept running. I didn’t have a final sprint in me, but I kept a solid pace and finished in 1 hour 58 minutes - 22 minutes and 2,500 places ahead of last year’s effort!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/half-marathon_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it might not &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; have been the personal best I was dreaming of after a strong start, on reflection I’m extremely happy to have achieved what I initially set out to do - to right the wrongs of 2022 and finish a half marathon in less than two hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-i-learnt&quot;&gt;What I learnt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the last 24 hours - and indeed the last year - I’ve essentially been running a big experiment. Subsequently, I’ve proven some of the things I &lt;em&gt;thought&lt;/em&gt; I learnt after last year’s race, and have stumbled across a few other pointers, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training&lt;/strong&gt; - I knew this even before I was a victim of bad luck in 2022, but it’s worth reiterating: Training is a lot kinder on your body if you make sure you have enough time to slowly build your distances, giving your legs, knees, and ankles a chance to get used to the workout and allowing time for injuries to heal if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pre-race nutrition&lt;/strong&gt; - A carbohydrate-heavy meal (in my case pasta) the night before running seems to work wonders, providing a plentiful supply of energy. I also ate a couple of bananas early in the morning on race day, which seemed to go down well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water&lt;/strong&gt; - Unless you do so on your training runs, carrying even 500ml of water with you is an extra weight for the entire distance. At future events I plan to continue turning up empty-handed, making use of the drinks stations on the route instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pacing&lt;/strong&gt; - It is &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; helpful to set a time you’re proud of across the full race distance in training. Take note of the pace and you’ll have a reference point against which to measure your pace on the day, as well as a psychological boost knowing that you’ve done this before and you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; make it if you just keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s everything I have for this year, and after I publish this article I’m going to sign off for some well-earned rest. If you’re an experienced runner and you have any more tips, please let me know, and if you’re a newbie with questions, I’d be happy to help if you send me a tweet or email! All the details you need are below.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="running" /><summary type="html">Long-time readers of this blog might remember that I ran a gruelling half marathon back in September 2022. I finished, but was reduced to a brisk walk at points, and ended up crossing the line in a disappointing 2 hours 20 minutes. This was partly down to my preparation, which was interrupted for COVID-related reasons a month before the event, and partly due to pain in my knees (possibly related to needing to increase my distances so quickly), which started giving me hassle well before the halfway point and became unbearable later on. This year I was determined not to let that happen again, and strove to achieve a result representative of my capability when the event arrived in September. So here goes another article about how to run a half marathon - but this time, better.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/half-marathon_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/half-marathon_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Gran Turismo review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/08/25/gran-turismo-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gran Turismo review" /><published>2023-08-25T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-08-25T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/08/25/gran-turismo-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/08/25/gran-turismo-review">&lt;p&gt;I love &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; - I’ve been playing it since the 90s. But if you asked me to choose a video game series for a film adaptation, it would be near the bottom of my list. After all, racing games are full of on-track action, but no matter how good they are, they don’t have a narrative that could support a feature film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;366&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZPzRySXmRmA?si=qtUdasiOLvEPuYcz&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, Sony and friends had an ace up their sleeve - a real life story that could back up their games. That story is the tale of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jann_Mardenborough&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jann Mardenborough&lt;/a&gt;, a skilled sim racer who earns a chance to compete at the GT Academy - a programme run by Nissan and &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; that aims to turn gamers into real race drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s safe to say the film is not a classic for all time. From the moment I saw the first trailer I could basically guess the major plot beats, and it flip-flops between a cliched underdog story and a thiny veiled advertisement for the &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; games in the form of a justification for all those teenage hours spent playing.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same way the Marlboro man tried to convice us that you could be strong and rugged like a cowboy if you smoked cigarettes, this film wants you to believe that you could be a pro racer if you just spent a few more hours playing &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt;, because it is just &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; realistic. The irony, for anyone who isn’t aware, is that the GT Academy featured in the film has been defunct since 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; won’t be winning any Oscars, it does work on two levels. The first is that, not content with telling Mardenborough’s story alone, there’s a B-plot that revolves around a Nissan marketing executive (played by Orlando Bloom) attempting to convince his bosses to back the GT Academy project. As such, the rookie driver isn’t going for wins - he’s fighting to keep up with pack, prove himself, and dissuade his backers from pulling their funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even that wouldn’t have been enough, though, because this film is absolutely carried by David Harbour, who plays a former driver who quits his mechanic job at a leading team to coach at the academy and serve as Jann’s race engineer. The character archetype and plot beats are familiar, but they’re delivered with a combination of sarcasm, jadedness, and enthusiasm that nobody else matches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film’s second redeeming quality is its on-track visuals. While they’re plastered with more cheesy game-like graphics than an F1 sprint race, they are really well shot, and motorsport fans will enjoy the sweeping views of cars racing around familiar locations like the Red Bull Ring and the Nurburgring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cherry on the cake is the finale, which takes place at the 24 Heures du Mans. The director (Neill Blomkamp) lavishes in the occasion with near-perfect authenticity as the teams stand to attention for the French anthem and the tricolore is delivered via helicopter. The race plays out with some artificial drama thrown in, and then the podium celebrations are faithful to the real event, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can probably guess, by the end of the story Mardenborough finds success, gets the girl, and his parents realise they were wrong to give him grief over his gaming habit. &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; is unremarkable as a story, but if you can turn off your critical brain for a couple of hours then there’s an awful lot of pretty racing to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3/5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="films" /><category term="reviews" /><category term="gran-turismo" /><category term="motorsport" /><category term="racing" /><summary type="html">I love Gran Turismo - I’ve been playing it since the 90s. But if you asked me to choose a video game series for a film adaptation, it would be near the bottom of my list. After all, racing games are full of on-track action, but no matter how good they are, they don’t have a narrative that could support a feature film. Luckily, Sony and friends had an ace up their sleeve - a real life story that could back up their games. That story is the tale of Jann Mardenborough, a skilled sim racer who earns a chance to compete at the GT Academy - a programme run by Nissan and Gran Turismo that aims to turn gamers into real race drivers. It’s safe to say the film is not a classic for all time. From the moment I saw the first trailer I could basically guess the major plot beats, and it flip-flops between a cliched underdog story and a thiny veiled advertisement for the Gran Turismo games in the form of a justification for all those teenage hours spent playing.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/08/gran-turismo_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/08/gran-turismo_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">I’ve launched a YouTube channel!</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/08/20/youtube-channel-launch" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I've launched a YouTube channel!" /><published>2023-08-20T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-08-20T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/08/20/youtube-channel-launch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/08/20/youtube-channel-launch">&lt;p&gt;It’s an idea I’ve been toying with under one guise or another for the last decade, but I’ve finally bitten the bullet and done it: I’ve launched &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtube.com/@stratpackblog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not wanting to come to a new platform empty handed, I’ve produced six initial videos which are all &lt;strong&gt;available to watch right now&lt;/strong&gt; on the new channel, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtube.com/@stratpackblog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@stratpackblog&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•   &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/6NSguzN5nD0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pro Evolution Soccer 5&lt;/em&gt; (PS2) retrospective&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/4-mBbCjNaCk&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;GTA IV&lt;/em&gt; is the best sandbox in the series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/ARb_KAixfjs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Formula 1 97&lt;/em&gt; (PS1) retrospective&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/4x2lhBJstQU&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Why is everything a live service?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fP44WMJryzI&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The internet is wrong about the &lt;em&gt;F1&lt;/em&gt; games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/uZXBRDvMJQk&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt; is the most addictive spreadsheet ever made&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eagle-eyed reader might notice that these videos are adaptations of previous articles I’ve posted on the blog. As well as posting the videos to YouTube, I’ve also made them available via the article pages on the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So please do check them out, and feel free to let me know &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:stratpackblog@gmail.com&quot;&gt;by email&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thestratpack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; if you have any feedback. I’m really testing the waters here as far as video content is concerned, and trying to adapt to the new format without losing my voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the first few videos are adaptations of articles, this also opens the door to all sorts of new ideas that are better suited to video, so look out for some exciting stuff in the coming months as I explore them and get to grips with editing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, please &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtube.com/@stratpackblog&quot;&gt;visit the channel&lt;/a&gt;, subscribe to stay up to date with new videos as I publish them, and let me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">It’s an idea I’ve been toying with under one guise or another for the last decade, but I’ve finally bitten the bullet and done it: I’ve launched a YouTube channel! Not wanting to come to a new platform empty handed, I’ve produced six initial videos which are all available to watch right now on the new channel, @stratpackblog: •   Pro Evolution Soccer 5 (PS2) retrospective •   GTA IV is the best sandbox in the series •   Formula 1 97 (PS1) retrospective •   Why is everything a live service? •   The internet is wrong about the F1 games •   Football Manager is the most addictive spreadsheet ever made The eagle-eyed reader might notice that these videos are adaptations of previous articles I’ve posted on the blog. As well as posting the videos to YouTube, I’ve also made them available via the article pages on the site. So please do check them out, and feel free to let me know by email or on Twitter if you have any feedback. I’m really testing the waters here as far as video content is concerned, and trying to adapt to the new format without losing my voice. While the first few videos are adaptations of articles, this also opens the door to all sorts of new ideas that are better suited to video, so look out for some exciting stuff in the coming months as I explore them and get to grips with editing. In the meantime, please visit the channel, subscribe to stay up to date with new videos as I publish them, and let me know what you think!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Battling for the drivers’ championship at F1 Arcade in London</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/07/21/f1-arcade-london" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Battling for the drivers' championship at F1 Arcade in London" /><published>2023-07-21T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-07-21T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/07/21/f1-arcade-london</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/07/21/f1-arcade-london">&lt;p&gt;I recently had the opportunity to visit a place I’d been dying to see since it opened at the start of this year - the &lt;a href=&quot;https://f1arcade.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;F1 Arcade&lt;/a&gt; in London. Essentially a bar crammed full of sim racing setups, the website made it look like a dream for a &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/racing/&quot;&gt;keen virtual racer&lt;/a&gt; like myself. But would it live up to the hype built by the Formula 1 PR machine?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/f1-arcade-london_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tucked away close to St Paul’s Cathedral, the bar itself is very slick, with decor based on circuit layouts and the start lights, and screens everywhere showing either Formula 1 clips (including Romain Grosjean’s near-deadly crash in Abu Dhabi, which struck me as a bit odd) or whatever happens to be on Sky Sports F1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lights-out-and-away-we-go&quot;&gt;Lights out and away we go&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On arrival, we were shown to our area, which consisted of five rigs, each with two ultra-wide displays, a seat with force feedback, and an F1-style steering wheel and pedals. In general the bottom screen was used for gameplay, while the top showed standings and information alongside a TV camera-style view of the on-track action. Oddly, the view defaulted to the T-cam, which felt unnatural with a wheel in front of me, but it was easy enough to switch into the cockpit with a few button presses.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To play, we registered with our phones via a QR code and were automatically split between five teams - one for each seat. Players were called up to races that lasted around four minutes, with assists adjusted to their perference with levels from a beginner mode where the car practically drives itself all the way to assists off and manual gear shifts. I was there to relax, so I stuck somewhere in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t be certain, but the game looked like a modified version of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-1&quot;&gt;the Codemasters &lt;em&gt;F1 23&lt;/em&gt; game&lt;/a&gt;. Each race had ten entrants - five human drivers and five AI cars, who seemed to be subject to some rubber banding to prevent anyone from running away or falling behind too much. Points were allocated for finishing positions, with various add-on awards for overtakes, time spent on the tarmac, fastest laps, and so on. At the end of each race, each driver’s points were added to their team’s total to update the championship leaderboard - an extremely tense time later in the evening!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/f1-arcade-london_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The track selection turned out to be one of the few disappointments of the night. After seeing Monza, Bahrain, and Spa in the first few races, the game went on something of a Silverstone streak - and it turned out that those were the only circuits we’d get to play. Looking around the room after we finished, I could only see the same four tracks, which is a shame since F1 has so many classic circuits, but perhaps F1 Arcade has decided they’re the most accessible for beginners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;keeping-the-stewards-busy&quot;&gt;Keeping the stewards busy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several other omissions from the F1 games, and perhaps the biggest is DRS - so you’re on your own when it comes to overtaking. More problematic is the absence of any rules. Dangerous driving, cut corners, and so on all go completely unpunished, which can result in gross miscarriages of justice when it comes to results if you can’t trust your friends to obey the honour system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, penalties for collisions would be a right mess, because it turns out Turn 1 is even more of a tangle when driving alongside a group of friends who never play racing games. In my first race (at Monza, of all places), I used the time-tested strategy of hanging back and picking my way through the carnage after the fact, but in later races the game placed me higher up the grid, and the first few corners were a tense wait for the inevitable connection from behind in the braking zones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick from that point was to get into the lead and take the Verstappen approach, building as much of a gap as possible from P2 during the first lap. In the one race where I didn’t make it through Turn 1 unscathed, fighting my way through the pack turned out to be a difficult prospect, since every time I overtook someone they’d misjudge their braking heading into the next turn and take me out all over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-team-sport&quot;&gt;A team sport&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’re not exactly talking &lt;em&gt;iRacing&lt;/em&gt; levels of gameplay or driving standards, but the truth is that F1 Arcade is one of the best evenings out I’ve ever had. The team dynamic, with drivers battling it out on track and their teammates shouting support from behind, is fantastic, and drives the perfect mix of comraderie and banter as you fight for the win, both on the circuit and in the overall championship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a passion for motorsport, at least a few friends, some cash to spare (currently £16 to £21 per driver, depending on the day/time), and you’re in the area, a visit to F1 Arcade is a no-brainer. More than anything else, it’s just a lot of fun to take a traditionally solo hobby and transform it into a party game.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="motorsport" /><category term="formula-1" /><category term="racing" /><category term="london" /><summary type="html">I recently had the opportunity to visit a place I’d been dying to see since it opened at the start of this year - the F1 Arcade in London. Essentially a bar crammed full of sim racing setups, the website made it look like a dream for a keen virtual racer like myself. But would it live up to the hype built by the Formula 1 PR machine? Tucked away close to St Paul’s Cathedral, the bar itself is very slick, with decor based on circuit layouts and the start lights, and screens everywhere showing either Formula 1 clips (including Romain Grosjean’s near-deadly crash in Abu Dhabi, which struck me as a bit odd) or whatever happens to be on Sky Sports F1. Lights out and away we go On arrival, we were shown to our area, which consisted of five rigs, each with two ultra-wide displays, a seat with force feedback, and an F1-style steering wheel and pedals. In general the bottom screen was used for gameplay, while the top showed standings and information alongside a TV camera-style view of the on-track action. Oddly, the view defaulted to the T-cam, which felt unnatural with a wheel in front of me, but it was easy enough to switch into the cockpit with a few button presses.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/07/f1-arcade-london_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/07/f1-arcade-london_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Asteroid City review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/07/15/asteroid-city-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Asteroid City review" /><published>2023-07-15T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-07-15T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/07/15/asteroid-city-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/07/15/asteroid-city-review">&lt;p&gt;Not many films will get me to the cinema these days, but 2023 is due to have a few of them. First up, faced with a weekend without any football or motorsport, I took a Saturday morning trip to see Wes Anderson’s new picture, &lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/asteroid-city_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll start with the easy part: Wes Anderson films are always beautiful to look at. &lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt; is no exception, and its setting - a dusty town in the Nevada desert - plays a helping hand in making the film’s aesthetic memorable, with the juxtaposition of orange dust and blue sky, split by the horizon, dominating most frames.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The director’s knack for composition also returns. Almost every shot could be a painting, and as in all of Anderson’s films, mise en scene is used to great effect, with little clues and details dotted around for the keen-eyed viewer to spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot revolves around a competition hosted in the town, which sees a group of talented and very geeky kids demonstrate their impressive scientific inventions in a bid to win a $5,000 prize from the US military. All is derailed when an alien visits (he’s animated in &lt;em&gt;Isle of Dogs&lt;/em&gt;-style stop motion, if you were wondering), and the characters must deal with subsequent quarantine in the middle of nowhere.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opening reveals that &lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt; is actually a film about a play of the same name, and between scenes we see glimpses of the author’s life, casting for the show, and the actors’ behind-the-scenes tribulations, usually narrated on-screen by Bryan Cranston. This serves as a way for Anderson to explain certain aspects of the film, and eventually seeps into the main production, with people showing up in the wrong scenes or questioning their stage characters’ motivations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, this is a star-studded film, with everybody from Tom Hanks and Scarlett Johansson to Edward Norton and Jeff Goldblum popping up. As a Hanks fan, I was a little disappointed he didn’t have more to do, but it was Jason Schwartzman who stood out in the shoes of a war photographer forced to break the news of his wife’s death to his children in a way that was somehow both touching and comedic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all interesting and entertaining enough, but with several in-universe subplots as well as the overarching dual plot, I was left questioning what &lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt; was actually &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt;. It wasn’t a film about an alien visit, because the sci-fi angle wasn’t ever explored in any detail. You could argue it was about loss, especially considering the mantra repeated towards the end, but in the main story Schwartzman’s character quickly moved on and his girls’ reactions were mainly played for comedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the timing of production and release, when the word “quarantine” started to be thrown around I thought it may even turn out to be about the COVID-19 pandemic and subsequent lockdown, but I struggled to draw many more parallels there, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fictional author of &lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt;, played by Norton, says his play is about “infinity”, suggesting more of an extra-terrestrial focus, and there are a few questions posed in this respect. Where did the alien come from and where did he go? What was the motive for his visit to Earth? And once word gets out and the wider public knows there is life out there, will the world change in irreversible ways?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue is that these questions are asked too late, are primarily treated as rhetorical, and receive little screen time in a film cluttered with a myriad of side stories across two main plots. &lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt; is never dull - it’s carried along nicely by stylish aesthetics, solid performances, and memorable exchanges that demonstrate its contributors’ mastery of the medium - but it flits between so many characters and themes that for me it never got going as well as Anderson’s previous films.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3/5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="films" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">Not many films will get me to the cinema these days, but 2023 is due to have a few of them. First up, faced with a weekend without any football or motorsport, I took a Saturday morning trip to see Wes Anderson’s new picture, Asteroid City. I’ll start with the easy part: Wes Anderson films are always beautiful to look at. Asteroid City is no exception, and its setting - a dusty town in the Nevada desert - plays a helping hand in making the film’s aesthetic memorable, with the juxtaposition of orange dust and blue sky, split by the horizon, dominating most frames. The director’s knack for composition also returns. Almost every shot could be a painting, and as in all of Anderson’s films, mise en scene is used to great effect, with little clues and details dotted around for the keen-eyed viewer to spot. The plot revolves around a competition hosted in the town, which sees a group of talented and very geeky kids demonstrate their impressive scientific inventions in a bid to win a $5,000 prize from the US military. All is derailed when an alien visits (he’s animated in Isle of Dogs-style stop motion, if you were wondering), and the characters must deal with subsequent quarantine in the middle of nowhere.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/07/asteroid-city_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/07/asteroid-city_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Yakuza 6: The Song of Life (PS4) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/07/08/yazuka-6-song-of-life-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yakuza 6&amp;#58; The Song of Life (PS4) retrospective" /><published>2023-07-08T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-07-08T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/07/08/yakuza-6-song-of-life-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/07/08/yazuka-6-song-of-life-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since I published one of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/retro&quot;&gt;my longer gaming articles&lt;/a&gt;, but after playing &lt;em&gt;Yakuza 6: The Song of Life&lt;/em&gt;, I felt compelled to put pen to digital paper. This is another post that sits somewhere between the review and retrospective categories, but like others in the series, this is a remarkable game that deserves discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/yakuza-6_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Released in 2016, &lt;em&gt;The Song of Life&lt;/em&gt; was the seventh mainline game in the &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt; series (the numbering was thrown off by the 2015 prequel &lt;em&gt;Yakuza 0&lt;/em&gt;, which I’ll likely revisit in a future article). It follows the traditional series main character Kazuma Kiryu as he investigates a personal mystery that takes him on a journey across Japan and is revealed to be linked to his yakuza past in Kamurocho.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;friends-and-foes&quot;&gt;Friends and foes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first picked up the &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt; series, I thought the story would consist of Japanese men in suits sitting around in dark rooms discussing who’s on whose turf. While there is a fair amount of that, &lt;em&gt;Yakuza 6: The Song of Life&lt;/em&gt; takes a much more personal approach, with a story exploring the bonds between family and friends.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having just come out of prison, Kiryu finds that his adoptive niece Haruka has gone missing from the Okinawa ophanage they run togther. He heads back to Tokyo to search for her, but finds the Chinese mafia has invaded his turf while he was away. Disorientated, he follows the only lead he has and sets off to Hiroshima prefecture to retrace her last known steps and uncover clues as to her whereabouts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/yakuza-6_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hiroshima sections have a summer holiday feel. Kiryu is dropped into an unfamiliar town with a few friends, a rival, and a potential love interest, and for some time you spend your days playing baseball and frequenting the local bar. The local yakuza - played by real life actors, headed by Takeshi Kitano - are the real stars, and transform from antagonists, to jesters, to brothers over the course of 18 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kiryu eventually learns that Haruka was hit by a car in Kamurocho and is in a coma. Perhaps a bigger shock is that she has a baby son, Haruto, who he takes into his care. The rest of the story unravels the mystery of what Haruka was up to and who Haruto’s father is, and - surprise, surprise - it turns out that it’s all entwined with the gangs’ tussle over the red light district and an 80-year old secret in Hiroshima.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is intriguing, but feels a couple of hours too long, with lengthy flashback cutscenes that went on for hours after the characters I cared most about were relegated to the background. It kept feeling that everything was going to wrap nicely, before introducing another layer of conspiracy and double-crossing to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/yakuza-6_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, this could be seen as a brave move, with the game continuing beyond where most would leave off, into a kind of epilogue where the characters face consequences for their actions. &lt;em&gt;Yakuza 6&lt;/em&gt;’s writing is expert at painting people as the bad guys, only to show their humanity in the most heartwrenching ways, and the finale is heartbreaking (even if it does undermine its own impact somewhat).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;two-shades-of-kiryu&quot;&gt;Two shades of Kiryu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always like the &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt; games as a little slice of Japan. By that I don’t mean that I think real Yakuza are huge guys wearing loud suits - I mean that Ryu Ga Gotoku Studio captures the atmosphere really well, right down to small details like the combinis and the real drinks in the vending machines. It might sound weird, but there were some points at which locations in the game evoked such strong memories of places I’ve visited in &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/japan&quot;&gt;Japan&lt;/a&gt; that I could almost smell them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that the gameplay is somewhat divorced from the story. In cutscenes, Kiryu is portrayed as a kind, gentle man who looks after orphans, but he spends most of the game delivering brutal beatdowns at the drop of a hat. Most of the main story missions involve him trying to get somewhere before a large group of threatening men block his way. Invariably, he yells something and they fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/yakuza-6_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the combat has more depth than I initially thought (more on that in a moment), it’s likely the game would still become a bit of a drag without its writing and acting. It’s rare that a series has you caring so much about the fate of its characters, and &lt;em&gt;Yakuza 6&lt;/em&gt;’s story undoubtedly benefits from its real-life acting talent - even if their more detailed faces sometimes look a little odd next to the original models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This drama is juxtaposed with some laugh out loud moments, particularly when it comes to the side missions, which in &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt; tradition cover a much more diverse range of subjects, from virtual assistants to time travel. A particular highlight for me was a story where some loser took Kiryu to an internet cafe and introduced him to “live chat” (cam girls) - his complete lack of basic computing knowledge and overblown, one-key-at-a-time typing animations were hilarious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enter-the-dragon&quot;&gt;Enter the dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned, the main mechanic of &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt; is the fighting, and boy will Kiryu find any excuse. Guy doesn’t like the look of me at an izakaya? Fight. Guy takes offence when I tell him to stop pissing in the street? Fight. Friend tries to stop me from kidnapping a baby? Also a fight. It’s all quite campy, usually involving people getting aggressive at the end of a cutscene and adopting fighting stances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the game goes on, more of the encounters are boss fights - usually signified by both participants ripping their shirts off before they duel. These are a bit more dramatic, set in arenas with plenty of implausably large objects to pick up and hit each other with. When your opponent is worn down enough, they’ll enter a heat mode, surrounded by red mist and noticeably more aggressive. In general, the boss fights are memorable and quite varied in terms of the tactics required to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/yakuza-6_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside the bosses, the game begins to pit you against more enemy types - big brutes with long health bars, agile ninjas, and so on. But from a certain point it just ups the numbers. While it’s cool to fight 15 guys at once and come out on top, it means half the battle is skirting the edges of the mob and picking off a straggler where you can, because entering the main fray means a frustrating and suicidal cycle of getting knocked down and hit again as you try to get up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, however, a turning point. Upgrade your stats and skills enough and the game becomes far more satisfying. Your punches connect with multiple enemies at once in crowds, your blocks are more effective, and heat mode enables moves that - after some quick time event-style button hits - can knock away half the health of the toughest enemies if successful. Overall, once you’ve earned it, combat is far more complex and rewarding than I gave it credit for in the early game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;too-much-fun-to-care&quot;&gt;Too much fun to care&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the rough edges - and the PS4 did struggle with some of the busier parts of Kamurocho before &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/07/02/playstation-5-first-impressions&quot;&gt;I upgraded to a PS5&lt;/a&gt; - I found &lt;em&gt;Yakuza 6: The Song of Life&lt;/em&gt; to be a delightful return to the games of yesteryear. There’s a world with plenty of content to explore but without any collectathon objectives, an engaging story with varied and likeable characters, and mechanics that require thought and practice to master. And all of this comes on a disc as a single, complete package that’s playable forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes in tone and fidelity (some cutscenes are noticeably more detailed than others, where characters look like mannequins with flapping jaws) are what made a certain era of video games, from roughly the start of the PS1’s lifespan to the the beginning of the Xbox 360 generation, so enjoyable. When the game’s fidelity is lower, our minds fill in the blanks, which makes titles more engrossing and fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yakuza 6&lt;/em&gt; is by no means perfect - it can be frustrating, feels a little long, and parts of the plot require some leaps in logic - but it’s probably the best and most gripping game I’ve played so far this year. Come to explore Tokyo and Hiroshima and you’ll undoubtedly stay for the story, characters, and the outlandish sideshows.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="yakuza" /><category term="retro" /><summary type="html">It’s been a while since I published one of my longer gaming articles, but after playing Yakuza 6: The Song of Life, I felt compelled to put pen to digital paper. This is another post that sits somewhere between the review and retrospective categories, but like others in the series, this is a remarkable game that deserves discussion. Released in 2016, The Song of Life was the seventh mainline game in the Yakuza series (the numbering was thrown off by the 2015 prequel Yakuza 0, which I’ll likely revisit in a future article). It follows the traditional series main character Kazuma Kiryu as he investigates a personal mystery that takes him on a journey across Japan and is revealed to be linked to his yakuza past in Kamurocho. Friends and foes When I first picked up the Yakuza series, I thought the story would consist of Japanese men in suits sitting around in dark rooms discussing who’s on whose turf. While there is a fair amount of that, Yakuza 6: The Song of Life takes a much more personal approach, with a story exploring the bonds between family and friends.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/07/yakuza-6_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/07/yakuza-6_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">PlayStation 5 first impressions</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/07/02/playstation-5-first-impressions" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PlayStation 5 first impressions" /><published>2023-07-02T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-07-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/07/02/playstation-5-first-impressions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/07/02/playstation-5-first-impressions">&lt;p&gt;I had reason to reward myself last week, and having been hovering in indecision for some time, I decided it was finally time to pull the trigger and buy a PlayStation 5. After a short time with the console, here are my thoughts on Sony’s next-gen offering and how it measures up so far with the immensely successful PlayStation 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/ps5_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before diving in, it’s worth noting that the PS5 is still &lt;em&gt;expensive&lt;/em&gt;. The disc edition launched in 2020 at £450 in the UK, and almost three years on there have been no discounts - in fact, the same console will now cost you £480, after Sony upped the price. Still, I had reason to treat myself, so I decided to see this as an investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unboxing-and-setup&quot;&gt;Unboxing and setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the outer sleeve is a white, PlayStation-branded box, inside of which a cardboard tray holds the accessories (controller, power cable, HDMI cable, USB cable, and stand). I was surprised to find the PS5 itself simply suspended between two brackets underneath, but I suppose Sony must have done the calculations on the likelihood of damage and decided this was safe enough for transportation.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the earliest teasers, the initial impression when unboxing the console is that it is &lt;em&gt;big&lt;/em&gt; - bigger along every dimension than my launch PS4, to a degree where I still wonder whether my TV unit is giving the PS5 enough space and ventilation. I don’t mind the actual design as much as some others seem do, but it remains to be seen how easy it will be to keep all the pointy-out bits at the top clean of dust and dirt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you have good, strong nails, because one of the first things you’ll be doing is picking a cap out of the bottom of the PS5 to be able to screw in the stand. There is a nice little storage slot on the bottom of the base for what you removed, and the PS5 feels relatively sturdy once everything is in place. Aside from that, all you need to do is hook up all the cables in the relevant places and you’re good to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you turn the PS5 on for the first time, there’s a slick installation wizard that guides you through PlayStation Network sign-in, privacy and power settings, and so on. You &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be able to transfer the data from your PS4 automatically via WiFi, but this failed for me for an uknown reason (apparently “some data could not be copied” - why? And what about the rest?). By this point I’d installed some games and apps myself, so I gave up and made do with just my profile and save data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gui-and-experience&quot;&gt;GUI and experience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Migration issues aside, from the moment you land on the PS5’s main dashboard you can feel that it’s far more responsive than its predecessor. As Sony loaded more and more into the PS4’s interface it wasn’t uncommon to have to wait a few seconds for screens to load in. There’s none of that here, and everything is nice and snappy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/ps5_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing games works much as it did before - and that goes for both PS5 games and PS4 games, which sit seamlessly alongside their next-gen counterparts. The only issue I ran into here is that it seems that if you own a PS4 disc but have bought a digital PS5 upgrade for the game, the PS4 version associated with the disc sometimes takes precedence in the ordering - hardly the end of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a little tinkering, taking screenshots (vital for those who, say, run little-read gaming blogs) can also be sped up significantly compared to the PS4. The panel opened by pressing the Create button no longer pauses the game, which is a bit inconvenient, but it can be adjused so that a tap automatically creates a screenshot - much easier than having to open the sidebar and press the Square button ever was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gaming&quot;&gt;Gaming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the PS5 (mostly) set up, and having given myself a brief self-guided tour of the dashboard, it was time to dive into the next-generation gaming I’d heard so much about. Without any PS5 games to hand, my first stop was the PlayStation Store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fifa-23&quot;&gt;FIFA 23&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On sale for £17, a digital copy of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA 23&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; seemed like a good option to tide me over. The gameplay is as smooth as it has ever been, and stadiums and crowds have noticeably more detail. However, it’s hard to feel that you’re playing a truly next-gen game when there are so many similarities to every &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; since about 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/ps5_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To its credit, it does play a slower, more considered game of football than its predecessor, with each pass requiring more thought than before. I did encounter a few too many instances where the AI passed to a teammate in my penalty area and I didn’t even have a chance to place my defender for a tackle or block before they’d scored, which felt somewhat frustrating, but maybe it’s an adjustment thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two noteworthy sound features in &lt;em&gt;FIFA 23&lt;/em&gt;. The first is that certain sounds - the referee’s whistle, the ball hitting the net, and so on - come from your controller, which was so annoying that I turned it off after playing one match. The second is that the soundtrack consists of various songs from &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; games dating back to the 90s, which is a nice touch to mark the final entry bearing the famous name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gran-turismo-7&quot;&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrote in &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review&quot;&gt;my review of the PS4 version&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/gran-turismo&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a fantastic racing game on the track, hindered by a grating microtransaction funnel of an economy off it. That was one of several reasons I was hesitant to pay £10 to upgrade the game to its PS5 version, but I decided to give it a go, and in the end I was glad I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/ps5_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; just the next-gen version of the same game I was playing on PS4, it felt much more like a new game than &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; did. As expected, there is slightly more detail in the graphics - the areas around the circuits are denser, and the cars seem shinier than they did last generation. But that’s not the true value of the upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The much bigger and unexpected benefit was that the &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; of the game completely changed. &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; uses the PS5’s adaptive triggers to great effect, increasing resistance to braking at high speeds, for example, or relaying your lack of grip due to tyre wear. I’m not sure &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; the game translates road feel to vibration and trigger tension (I’m sure there must be all sorts of complicated mathematics behind it), I just know it’s the best I’ve ever seen outside of a full sim racing setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;yakuza-6-the-song-of-life&quot;&gt;Yakuza 6: The Song of Life&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My in-progress PS4 game at the time of my generational leap (and something you’ll be able to read about in a month or two) was &lt;em&gt;Yakuza 6&lt;/em&gt;. In Tokyo and Hiroshima’s more populated areas, it sometimes felt like it was pushing the base PS4 to its limits, with an occasionally stuttering frame rate and some jagged edges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even without a formal upgrade, the difference on PS5 is noticeable. The game runs more smoothly, graphical artefacts seem to be reduced, and loading times have certainly improved. It’s a promising sign for future enjoyment of my PS4 back catalogue on the new console as I wait for more PS5 games to trickle in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s getting harder as the decades to go on to justify the value of a console straight out of the blocks. I remember that I was immediately blown away the first time I plugged in a PlayStation 2 or Xbox 360, but ever since we entered the HD era the improvements from one generation to the next are incremental more than anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I can say after a few days with the PlayStation 5 is that it’s a lot more responsive than my PS4, which would sometimes feel as though it was creaking along even when just using the menus or certain streaming apps, although I suppose that’s to be expected given the power differential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaming-wise, it will take some time to see how developers use the upgraded hardware. &lt;em&gt;FIFA 23&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt; - the latter especially - both do things that their PS4 versions don’t, but they’re hardly innovations with a massive impact on gameplay - they’re more add-ons and flourishes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll see how I feel a few years down the line, but for now I’m happy with my purchase. This generation still has a lot in store, the PS5 is a significant upgrade from the PS4, and I know I’ll play enough games to justify the price tag - even at £480. Whether I’d feel as pleased as an upgrading PS4 Pro user, I don’t know, but in my personal circumstances the PS5 feels like the right choice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="playstation" /><category term="hardware" /><category term="gran-turismo" /><category term="fifa" /><summary type="html">I had reason to reward myself last week, and having been hovering in indecision for some time, I decided it was finally time to pull the trigger and buy a PlayStation 5. After a short time with the console, here are my thoughts on Sony’s next-gen offering and how it measures up so far with the immensely successful PlayStation 4. Before diving in, it’s worth noting that the PS5 is still expensive. The disc edition launched in 2020 at £450 in the UK, and almost three years on there have been no discounts - in fact, the same console will now cost you £480, after Sony upped the price. Still, I had reason to treat myself, so I decided to see this as an investment. Unboxing and setup Under the outer sleeve is a white, PlayStation-branded box, inside of which a cardboard tray holds the accessories (controller, power cable, HDMI cable, USB cable, and stand). I was surprised to find the PS5 itself simply suspended between two brackets underneath, but I suppose Sony must have done the calculations on the likelihood of damage and decided this was safe enough for transportation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/07/ps5_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/07/ps5_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Are you saving too much money?</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/18/are-you-saving-too-much-money" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are you saving too much money?" /><published>2023-06-17T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-06-17T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/18/are-you-saving-too-much-money</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/18/are-you-saving-too-much-money">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to money, I’m something like a squirrel. I receive it and I tuck it away for later use, ensuring a more pleasurable future. But I recently heard a convincing argument for spending more in the present to avoid missing out on experiences that may not be possible later on, and thought that was worth exploring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;delaying-gratification-for-too-long&quot;&gt;Delaying gratification for too long&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pdst.fm/e/chrt.fm/track/G454/traffic.megaphone.fm/SIXMSB5490111876.mp3?updated=1686753558&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;This weekend’s episode of Modern Wisdom&lt;/a&gt; featured trader and hedge fund manager Bill Perkins, who was on the podcast to discuss his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Die-Zero-Getting-Your-Money/dp/0358099765/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Die With Zero&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He essentially gave a warning against saving too much money for too long, instead advising listeners to use the resources of health, wealth, and time together to maximise the number of positive life experiences you get to enjoy before you die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His logic here was that by focusing on your bank balance and waiting for retirement to start spending and really enjoying life, you’ll miss out on irreplaceable experiences in the meantime. You’re unlikely to be able to do physically demanding things when you’re old, you can’t do hedonistic things when you’re married with kids, and your kids won’t want you to read bedtime stories to them when they’re teenagers, so you need to prioritise the right things at the right times in your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue, Perkins said, is that many people have blockers to spending money. Either their egos are tied to their wealth, or the habit of saving becomes so ingrained that they lose the mental connection between hard work and subsequent enjoyment, and become drones working jobs they don’t enjoy on the promise of a future reward somewhere over the horizon that may never become a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His advice was to instead treat life like a game of &lt;em&gt;Tetris&lt;/em&gt;, not only selecting the experiences you’d like to live out but also slotting them into the right places where you have the money, time, endurance, and flexibility to make the most of them. Memories pay dividends, he added - living is not just about the moment, but enjoyment in the years afterwards recalling experiences and telling stories.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-money-saving-instinct&quot;&gt;The money saving instinct&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on my own life, I think there is a natural tendency to save every penny that some people have to overcome more than others. I was never poor growing up, but I did come from a working class town, and when I first moved to London I was just about scraping by, considering every purchase in detail and lucky if I had anything left to transfer to my savings account at the end of each month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I got my first corporate job, I suddenly had disposable income, but my instinct was to save as much as I could rather than paying for any luxuries. What if I lost my job? Or I reached a point where my wage stagnated for years? While building some form of financial cushion was undoubtedly a good move, I took this to an extreme and missed out on a lot of experiences in my 20s as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, just as I reached a level of income where I felt comfortable to loosen the purse strings somewhat, the COVID pandemic hit and I was stuck at home in lockdown. I developed anxiety during the long isolation, so even when I started to emerge more in 2022, mundane things like train journeys were absolute ordeals and I really had to push myself to get back out there with everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My struggles in the last few years have given me an increased appreciation of the variety of experiences life has to offer, and since then I’ve been doing my best to say yes to as much as possible. I’ve visited Greece and &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/05/14/lesson-curiosity-japan&quot;&gt;Japan&lt;/a&gt;, and accepted invitations I might have turned down to eat different foods and play new sports and games. This has meant exposing myself to potential public embarrassment - something my anxiety never would have allowed at last year’s levels - but helps me to grow more resilient and generates new memories with my friends and colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;finding-the-golden-mean&quot;&gt;Finding the golden mean&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this relates to one of Aristotle’s ideas, which he explained in &lt;em&gt;The Nicomachean Ethics&lt;/em&gt;. He argued that all possible traits exist along a spectrum, with deficiency and excess at either end and an ideal golden mean in the middle - essentially a more complex version of the saying, “All things in moderation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saving all excess income leads to missed opportunities and experiences, and spending everything you earn on experiences means a less stable future. With that in mind, I intend to hover near the golden mean, maintaining a baseline level of savings, but continuing to embrace chances to try new things as they arrive. As Perkins said, if I don’t live life now, then I may never have a second shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you haven’t already done so, I’d very much recommend listening to &lt;a href=&quot;https://pdst.fm/e/chrt.fm/track/G454/traffic.megaphone.fm/SIXMSB5490111876.mp3?updated=1686753558&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the full episode of Modern Wisdom&lt;/a&gt; featuring Bill Perkins, in which he explains his philosophy on life and approach to balancing health, wealth, and time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="money" /><category term="philosophy" /><summary type="html">When it comes to money, I’m something like a squirrel. I receive it and I tuck it away for later use, ensuring a more pleasurable future. But I recently heard a convincing argument for spending more in the present to avoid missing out on experiences that may not be possible later on, and thought that was worth exploring. Delaying gratification for too long This weekend’s episode of Modern Wisdom featured trader and hedge fund manager Bill Perkins, who was on the podcast to discuss his book Die With Zero. He essentially gave a warning against saving too much money for too long, instead advising listeners to use the resources of health, wealth, and time together to maximise the number of positive life experiences you get to enjoy before you die. His logic here was that by focusing on your bank balance and waiting for retirement to start spending and really enjoying life, you’ll miss out on irreplaceable experiences in the meantime. You’re unlikely to be able to do physically demanding things when you’re old, you can’t do hedonistic things when you’re married with kids, and your kids won’t want you to read bedtime stories to them when they’re teenagers, so you need to prioritise the right things at the right times in your life. The issue, Perkins said, is that many people have blockers to spending money. Either their egos are tied to their wealth, or the habit of saving becomes so ingrained that they lose the mental connection between hard work and subsequent enjoyment, and become drones working jobs they don’t enjoy on the promise of a future reward somewhere over the horizon that may never become a reality. His advice was to instead treat life like a game of Tetris, not only selecting the experiences you’d like to live out but also slotting them into the right places where you have the money, time, endurance, and flexibility to make the most of them. Memories pay dividends, he added - living is not just about the moment, but enjoyment in the years afterwards recalling experiences and telling stories.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Starfield could be the fix for The Outer Worlds… and Fallout 4</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/14/starfield-fix-the-outer-worlds-fallout-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starfield could be the fix for The Outer Worlds... and Fallout 4" /><published>2023-06-14T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-06-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/14/starfield-fix-the-outer-worlds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/14/starfield-fix-the-outer-worlds-fallout-4">&lt;p&gt;There was a time in about 2018 when I thought &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/the-outer-worlds&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Outer Worlds&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; would be the fix for &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fallout&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fallout 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That doesn’t mean that I &lt;em&gt;hated&lt;/em&gt; Bethesda’s most recent “proper” game - I completed two lengthy playthroughs, one on release and one during the COVID pandemic - but for whatever reason it just didn’t grab me in the same way that old RPGs like &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/elder-scrolls&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oblivion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;watered-down-wasteland&quot;&gt;Watered-down wasteland&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, as I read more analysis, I began to understand why that was. While &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/elder-scrolls&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fallout&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fallout 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and other games had left me to forge my own way through their worlds, &lt;em&gt;Fallout 4&lt;/em&gt; let me craft my character’s &lt;em&gt;appearance&lt;/em&gt;, but didn’t offer half of their flexibility when it came to their &lt;em&gt;story&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/starfield_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt; also suffered from this issue to a degree, of course, casting the player as the “chosen one” Dragonborn, but it was much easier to ignore. &lt;em&gt;Fallout 4&lt;/em&gt; not only had a character-defining main quest, but featured worse side quest writing, and mismatched dialogue menu options and response tones, and in voicing the main character presented them as a much more developed individual in-game, leaving little to the player’s imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the main quest stole a lot of the focus away from the world. Not only did it seem there were fewer side quests, but they were less remarkable in their content than those in previous games, and there was less potential for interesting stories since most quests focused on gunplay, rather than talking your way out of trouble. It was enough to make you yearn for the richness of the Mojave Wasteland (sans nuclear winter).&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-pale-imitation&quot;&gt;A pale imitation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when Obsidian, the developer behind &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fallout&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fallout: New Vegas&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, announced that it was working on a new &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/rpg&quot;&gt;RPG&lt;/a&gt;, my excitement hit fever pitch. Their prior work included once of the most roleplay-friendly games and immersive worlds of all time, so surely a game of their own would restore all the features we loved and blow the watered-down &lt;em&gt;Fallout&lt;/em&gt; out of the water?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer was… not really. &lt;em&gt;The Outer Worlds&lt;/em&gt; was a game of above-average quality, but it never really captured my attention and I didn’t get anywhere close to completing the story. The structure - a series of hubs on different planets - obstructed any chance of recapturing the “man against the world”, choose-your-own-adventure feel of its predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest issue for me, however, was the tone. &lt;em&gt;The Outer Worlds&lt;/em&gt; felt like it was written by a sixth-form politics student, a game-shaped manifestation of the Twitter accounts that repeatedly yell “Isn’t capitalism bad?” without acknowledging any of its benefits or offering a viable alternative. This also meant that most quest decision points offered only saintly good or comically bad options, with no moral grey area or tough dilemmas to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining third of &lt;em&gt;The Outer Worlds&lt;/em&gt;’ personality was… quirkiness, to a degree never seen before in Bethesda games, despite their occasional oddball moments. Somehow Obsidian managed to crank this up to eleven while also sanitising it was far as possible, culminating in a bland, jokey atmosphere reminiscent of the modern Marvel movie formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-ray-of-hope&quot;&gt;A ray of hope&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;em&gt;Starfield&lt;/em&gt;. I know it’s a marketing cliche at this point, but watching the preview at the weekend I really felt that thrill of old Bethesda games again, like I could really go anywhere and do anything in this game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonally, the new game looks to be just what you’d expect from the makers of &lt;em&gt;The Elder Scrolls&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Fallout&lt;/em&gt;. That is, it’s primarily set in a serious world with serious characters, with just the occasional quirky beat on the side - the return of the Adoring Fan as an optional trait-based follower, for example. This helps massively with immersion, as unless I choose to see humorous content it looks like I can count on &lt;em&gt;Starfield&lt;/em&gt; to play it straight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Size and freedom is always an issue with space games, as the nature of space exploration means areas must be broken up between planets. How can you provide enough planets to simulate a region of space without them being procedurally generated and empty? The jury will be out in September, but somehow Bethesda appears to found a happy middle ground between the sparse vastness of &lt;em&gt;No Man’s Sky&lt;/em&gt; and the tightly-packed &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt; map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will the gunplay be like? Will planets feel repetitive? What exactly will the ratio of hand-built content to algorithmically generated areas be? How cumbersome will travel between planets feel? There are a lot of open questions ahead of &lt;em&gt;Starfield&lt;/em&gt;’s launch, but I’m hoping Bethesda has combined its experience with fan feedback on recent games and produced that rare special RPG - after all, with the increasingly casual changes introduced in &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Fallout 4&lt;/em&gt;, it may be the last chance many players give it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-future-is-bright-hopefully&quot;&gt;The future is bright (hopefully)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Todd Howard so enthusiastically reminded us during &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uMOPoAq5vIA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the &lt;em&gt;Starfield&lt;/em&gt; deep dive&lt;/a&gt;, this is the first new world Bethesda has created in decades, and a new subgenre for the studio, so even beyond the usual launch bugs that come with a game so complex, there’s a lot that could go wrong. But from what we’ve seen, it feels like some lessons have been learnt and the balance is there, so I’m cautiously optimistic ahead of 6th September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More generally, this is the most enthusiastic I’ve been about gaming for years. Between &lt;em&gt;Starfield&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;Metal Gear Solid 3&lt;/em&gt; remake, and some of the smaller games shown off over trailer season, it feels like there’s a healthier vein of larger studios and publishers shrugging off &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/10/14/why-is-everything-a-live-service&quot;&gt;the live service-obsessed, microtransaction-filled, multiplayer-first trend&lt;/a&gt; of recent years and investing in the high-quality single-player games we’ve all been waiting for.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="starfield" /><category term="rpg" /><category term="the-outer-worlds" /><category term="fallout" /><category term="elder-scrolls" /><summary type="html">There was a time in about 2018 when I thought The Outer Worlds would be the fix for Fallout 4. That doesn’t mean that I hated Bethesda’s most recent “proper” game - I completed two lengthy playthroughs, one on release and one during the COVID pandemic - but for whatever reason it just didn’t grab me in the same way that old RPGs like Oblivion did. Watered-down wasteland Over time, as I read more analysis, I began to understand why that was. While Skyrim, Fallout 3, and other games had left me to forge my own way through their worlds, Fallout 4 let me craft my character’s appearance, but didn’t offer half of their flexibility when it came to their story. Skyrim also suffered from this issue to a degree, of course, casting the player as the “chosen one” Dragonborn, but it was much easier to ignore. Fallout 4 not only had a character-defining main quest, but featured worse side quest writing, and mismatched dialogue menu options and response tones, and in voicing the main character presented them as a much more developed individual in-game, leaving little to the player’s imagination. Additionally, the main quest stole a lot of the focus away from the world. Not only did it seem there were fewer side quests, but they were less remarkable in their content than those in previous games, and there was less potential for interesting stories since most quests focused on gunplay, rather than talking your way out of trouble. It was enough to make you yearn for the richness of the Mojave Wasteland (sans nuclear winter).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/06/starfield_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/06/starfield_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why do we believe morality is in decline?</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/10/why-we-believe-morality-in-decline" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why do we believe morality is in decline?" /><published>2023-06-10T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-06-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/10/why-we-think-morality-in-decline</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/06/10/why-we-believe-morality-in-decline">&lt;p&gt;It’s a little embarrassing to admit it publicly, but I sometimes suffer from the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/lewronggeneration/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;le wrong generation&lt;/a&gt;” syndrome that seems to plague online comments sections. A little nostalgia is healthy, but occasionally I bring myself down with the thought that I could have lived in a generally more friendly and pleasant era than the one I inhabit, which isn’t productive at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;are-things-really-getting-worse&quot;&gt;Are things really getting worse?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine my intrigue then, when I stumbled across an article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.experimental-history.com/p/the-illusion-of-moral-decline&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the illusion of moral decline&lt;/a&gt; by Adam Mastroianni this week. In it, he provides the figures that show that people believe morality is in decline, people have &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; believed that morality is in decline, and that by objective measures morality hasn’t actually declined at all - if anything, it may have improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This begs the question: If things are getting better, why do we always think they’re getting worse? Mastroianni’s article offers several possible reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People just say that morality is in decline when asked because they think it makes them look more moral personally&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People are nicer to you when you’re a kid and therefore seem to get meaner when you grow up and they treat you like an adult&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People hear cherry-picked stories about how lovely the past was from relatives, television series, and films&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People think younger generations are less moral than they were because they are biased to forget immoral things they did when young&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main theory put forward in the article is that people pay more attention to negative information, but memories of positive things last longer. Therefore the present seems worse than it is, and the past seems better than it was, misleading us to believe morality is in decline.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;additional-factors&quot;&gt;Additional factors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with Mastrianni’s points (as I should - he’s a proper social psychologist with statistics to back him up and everything), but his article also got me thinking about additional elements that might be contributing. While natural biases certainly play a big part, I also think there are environmental factors in the modern world that amplify the effect of our tendency to believe the present is worse than it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;were-shown-more-immorality&quot;&gt;We’re shown more immorality&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From real-life horrors to disturbing fiction, it’s a lot easier to come into contact with immoral content in 2023. It’s not unusual to encounter terrifying or gory images on social media, the 24/7 news cycle is always hungry for new negative stories, and there are any number serial killer documentaries available on demand on your favourite streaming site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the realm of the arts, we now casually watch series that would never get made decades ago. I can turn on &lt;em&gt;Yellowjackets&lt;/em&gt; and see people doing horrific things (no spoilers), &lt;em&gt;Breaking Bad&lt;/em&gt; was about a brutal drug lord, and Netflix even made a series about Jeffrey Dahmer. I’ve been reading St Augustine’s &lt;em&gt;Confessions&lt;/em&gt;, and even back in the fourth century he was writing about how he felt he absorbed negativity from drama into his soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even taking a step back down the morality scale, it’s easy to see how the internet could turn us all into pessimists. At one time porn would have meant a dirty video or magazine your friend found - now it’s thousands of women flaunting themselves on social media to advertise their OnlyFans accounts. And how many arguments would you see or get into in the 1990s? In 2023, I can open my phone at any time and read a Twitter dispute that the participants would like never have in real life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;we-believe-more-things-are-immoral&quot;&gt;We believe more things are immoral&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I dive in, there’s a point to be made around the word “immoral”. Somebody answering a survey might not necessarily have to believe that people have become more sinful or evil to respond that morality is in decline. They could also have fewer positive experiences with others, or see others express more views that they personally disagree with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, increasing polarisation in politics (and other arenas) is a likely contributor to the impression of immorality - and this looks to be supported by a spike after 2016 in some of Mastrianni’s graphs. Speaking in US terms, Democrats and Republicans used to be respectful rivals - now they both see each other as a “threat to democracy” and their country itself, to a level where it’s almost become a meme for social media users not to be able to endure a Thanksgiving dinner with relatives from the opposing camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US has always been split almost 50/50 politically, so even if you believe one party to be immoral, the level of immorality hasn’t really changed - it just seems the rhetoric has reached a level where people are much more sensitive to others who have views incompatible with theirs, and therefore might be more likely to &lt;em&gt;view&lt;/em&gt; (and report) them as immoral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;more-immoral-people-are-getting-caught&quot;&gt;More immoral people are getting caught&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decades ago, it was easier to be invisibly immoral. Without CCTV and DNA analysis, it is likely that a greater number of criminals went undetected. Without the internet, the widest reach anybody’s unsavoury views could muster depended on how loudly they could yell in the town square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty standard example of the need to consider the causes &lt;em&gt;behind&lt;/em&gt; statistics. If more murderers are going to jail, that &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; mean there are more murders, but it could also mean there is more justice being dealt. If more people seem to be saying objectionable things, that &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; mean there are more people with these beliefs, or it could just mean they have an easier way to reach more people - and get called out - than before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we’re &lt;em&gt;seeing&lt;/em&gt; more people get caught. Once upon a time, a local murderer’s arrest would be reported in the newspaper, and if you missed that day’s issue or television bulletin then you’d likely miss the story. Now these news stories are run 24/7 on television, go viral on social media, are pushed to our phones as notifications, and are available forever online - so it’s easy to feel like there are more of these stories around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you’ve made it this far without doing so, I’d really recommend you take the time to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.experimental-history.com/p/the-illusion-of-moral-decline&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;read the original article&lt;/a&gt;. It’s far better researched and more scientifically backed than my two cents are.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="philosophy" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">It’s a little embarrassing to admit it publicly, but I sometimes suffer from the “le wrong generation” syndrome that seems to plague online comments sections. A little nostalgia is healthy, but occasionally I bring myself down with the thought that I could have lived in a generally more friendly and pleasant era than the one I inhabit, which isn’t productive at all. Are things really getting worse? Imagine my intrigue then, when I stumbled across an article on the illusion of moral decline by Adam Mastroianni this week. In it, he provides the figures that show that people believe morality is in decline, people have always believed that morality is in decline, and that by objective measures morality hasn’t actually declined at all - if anything, it may have improved. This begs the question: If things are getting better, why do we always think they’re getting worse? Mastroianni’s article offers several possible reasons: People just say that morality is in decline when asked because they think it makes them look more moral personally People are nicer to you when you’re a kid and therefore seem to get meaner when you grow up and they treat you like an adult People hear cherry-picked stories about how lovely the past was from relatives, television series, and films People think younger generations are less moral than they were because they are biased to forget immoral things they did when young The main theory put forward in the article is that people pay more attention to negative information, but memories of positive things last longer. Therefore the present seems worse than it is, and the past seems better than it was, misleading us to believe morality is in decline.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>