<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-29T20:41:38+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Strat Packer’s blog</title><subtitle>Creative and intellectual output beyond the realm of my day job</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Death Stranding 2 at the Tokyo Game Show 2024</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/29/death-stranding-2-tgs-2024" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Death Stranding 2 at the Tokyo Game Show 2024" /><published>2024-09-29T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-29T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/29/death-stranding-2-tgs-2024</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="death-stranding" /><category term="playstation" /><summary type="html">🐈‍⬛ We’ve had another small glimpse of Death Stranding 2: On The Beach. During a 90-minute session at the Tokyo Game Show, Kojima Productions showed off a few new cutscenes and an odd Instagram-esque photo mode. The clips got my hopes up that Sam will spend more time with a fleshed-out team on his latest journey, giving more character to a game that had a lot of interesting ideas but too many soulless holograms for my taste.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Parking Garage Rally Circuit review - an addictive ’90s-inspired racer</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/22/parking-garage-rally-circuit-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parking Garage Rally Circuit review &amp;#45; an addictive '90s-inspired racer" /><published>2024-09-22T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-22T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/22/parking-garage-rally-circuit-review</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="indie" /><category term="retro" /><category term="pc" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">I said at the end of my Concord article that the current triple-A malaise might push me to play more indie games, and it wasn’t an empty threat. Astro Bot was a surprise double-A hit, with a stripped-back scope and simple gameplay loop that made it feel like playing a retro game on PS5 steroids. Parking Garage Rally Circuit takes things a step further – it looks like a retro game, too! Speed and control While Walaber Entertainment’s official description says PGRC is meant to look like a Sega Saturn game, it still hits the spot for me as a PlayStation kid. The title screen demo mode, the waving chequered flag in the menu background, the music, and the countdown to the race start all nail that 1990s aesthetic. As the name suggests, the game has you driving rally cars in parking garages. I initially thought I’d made a mistake buying it – the handling seemed simple to the point of boredom, there was no sense of speed, and the ghost cars all seemed to be miles ahead without any mistakes on my part. Drifting is the name of the game – I should have paid better attention to the tutorial! Then I realised how important drifting is. Hold X (on a controller) as your car veers around a bend and your tyres will squeal – but more importantly, you’ll build up a charge that allows you to slingshot yourself with a speed boost on corner exit. Chain a few drifts together and suddenly you’ll be pushing 100mph. After the first few levels, the circuits become more complex and you’ll need to memorise the course to know when to drift around blind corners. Each lap is a challenge in memory and split-second reactions to get – and stay – ahead. It’s an addictive experience more akin to a platformer than a racing game. Touring the USA There are eight circuits in total, themed around US cities from San Francisco to Boston. One of my favourites – albeit one of the most difficult to master – is the New York track, which features a jump over the crown of the Statue of Liberty. There’s plenty of variety, and some levels even mix things up with mid-race changes like rolling boulders or power cuts casting the track into darkness. My only small gripe with the circuit layouts and handling model is how easy it is to roll the car or end up off-course. Sometimes this is your own fault, but it can be frustrating when your entire run is ruined because of a particularly sharp edge or a ramp that launches you into obstacles or beyond the track limits at the top. The circuits are varied and challenging – New York is a particular highlight To unlock the next circuit, you must achieve at least a bronze trophy by beating a target time. When you’ve done all eight, you’ll unlock the next car class, which is faster and heavier. At the end of all three classes (24 events in total), you’re done, and any additional challenge comes from chasing gold in previous events. It took me two and a half hours to pass every race, but mastery would take much longer. When you earn a silver medal for a track, you also unlock Endurance mode, which is a checkpoint-based timed run. Again, I found battling against ghosts from the leaderboard to be extremely addictive – not least because this is a rare game where you have a chance at the global top spot if you get it right. Simple but addictive And that about sums it up. Parking Garage Rally Circuit is simple, short, sweet, and has enough depth in terms of medals and rankings to keep you playing well beyond your first run through its roster of events. I imagine this will fall into my rotation of fun little games to load up when I have 20 or 30 minutes to spare and don’t have the time to invest in a cinematic title with an elaborate story. The graphics, the music, and the gameplay all do a convincing job of emulating console games of the 1990s, to a degree where I could easily mistake this for a long-forgotten title pulled from my PlayStation collection. If you’re the kind of person who gets pulled in by “just one more go” games that test your memory and reactions, you’ll easily recoup your investment over a few hours. 4/5</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/parking-garage-rally-circuit_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/parking-garage-rally-circuit_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">PlayStation 5 Pro and 30th anniversary limited editions</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/19/playstation-5-pro-30th-anniversary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PlayStation 5 Pro and 30th anniversary limited editions" /><published>2024-09-19T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-19T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/19/playstation-5-pro-30th-anniversary</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="playstation" /><category term="industry" /><summary type="html">🎮 It’s been a busy month for Sony, who revealed both the PlayStation 5 Pro and a selection of retro grey consoles and accessories for PlayStation’s 30th anniversary. But there’s little to celebrate - the Pro will cost £700, and if you want to play physical games then all consoles in both lineups require a clip-on disc drive that must be registered online. The expense and restrictions killed my interest, and raise questions over the future of console gaming.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Astro Bot review - a shot of pure fun and PlayStation nostalgia</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/19/astro-bot-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Astro Bot review &amp;#45; a shot of pure fun and PlayStation nostalgia" /><published>2024-09-19T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-19T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/19/astro-bot-review</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="astro-bot" /><category term="playstation" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">A lot of the weirdness in modern gaming comes from critics and consumers who are overly concerned with the business side of the industry, focused on sales figures, profitability, and competition between manufacturers rather than the quality of the games they play. It’s an odd predicament – perhaps unique to video games – and it’s one that Astro Bot blasts straight through. When you play this game, it’s impossible to think about anything except what’s on the screen. Astro Bot is a pure shot of fun and nostalgia from start to finish Much of that is due to the game’s retro simplicity – not in terms of difficulty, but in the premise and core gameplay: Astro Bot is on a level. He must get from Point A to Point B. There are obstacles in his way, either enemies or physical hurdles. You must find a way to overcome them, and have fun doing so. That’s it. There’s no grand narrative here. No jarring commentary on real-world issues, or mechanics that make you sigh and yearn for what gaming once was. The only time my mind drifted from the level before my eyes was to consider the choices behind its design, and my conclusion was usually something like: “The person at Team Asobi who made this really knows how to make a fun game!” Hopping through the galaxy The beauty of Astro Bot’s story is that it barely has one. 300 bots are riding in a spaceship shaped like a PlayStation 5 when it is attacked by an alien. It explodes, its parts and the bots scattered across the galaxy. The alien steals the CPU, and Astro Bot blasts off on his controller mini-ship to find the parts and his friends. There is one level per planet, with planets divided into star systems, each capped with a final boss and a stage themed around a beloved PlayStation game. Even exploring the galaxy map is a lot of fun, with secret levels to uncover and ships carrying collectables to chase. I couldn’t help but compare it to the expansive but much more sterile and borderline indecipherable map in Starfield. Far from glorified menus, even the star system screens have their secrets to uncover Each level has a handful of bots to save – some generic, some dressed up as characters from PlayStation history. When Astro finds them, they’re stowed inside his controller ship, and at the end of the level they’re sent back to the planet the ship crashed on, where the PS5 mothership’s carcass serves as the centrepiece of a museum full of all the bots you’ve discovered and rescued to date. The other main collectable is jigsaw puzzle pieces. While Astro’s Playroom used these to construct a pretty mural, Astro Bot gives them a much more practical application. Completing a smaller puzzle unlocks new functionality at the crash site – a hub to change outfits or give your ship a lick of paint, for example. Two-button challenge Astro Bot’s gameplay is just as simple: he can run, jump, use boosters in his feet, and hit enemies. Don’t let that fool you – there’s some challenging platforming to be found, both in the main levels towards the end of the game, but especially in unlockable gauntlet stages themed around the PlayStation symbols (you’ll be very thankful that your PS5’s SSD allows near-instant reloads upon death). While one mistake is usually enough to kill Astro, checkpoints are so frequent that you only ever lose a few seconds of progress. I was grateful for this as a way of reducing the risk when trying out a new mechanic or attempting an ambitious manoeuvre to reach some distant platform in search of treasure – vital in a game with so many secret areas and obscurely located bots to be rescued. Special abilities - like becoming a giant sponge - add variety across levels Many levels have a special upgrade, giving Astro a booster pack, an extended punch reach, or climbing abilities, for example. My favourites were a mod that enabled him to contract into a rolling ball a la Marble Blast, and a very creative stage that transformed him into a sponge, growing larger as he absorbed water. The levels themselves also have creative ideas that add variety and sometimes completely change the premise midway through – an ability that shrinks Astro to the size of a mouse and unlocks access to a miniscule level-within-a-level, for example, or an Arabian village level that morphs into a sandstorm hellscape once the player lets a genie out of his lamp to wreak chaos across the area. Retro futurism To me, Astro Bot is what I dreamt gaming might look like when I was playing back in the 1990s. Sure, I expected graphics to improve, but I also thought that the ideas would expand with them. Instead, we got technically sophisticated titles that look great but play like semi-interactive films (especially on PlayStation). Astro Bot might not look as lifelike as The Last of Us or God of War, but it is very crisp and smooth, which is important in a platformer. Where it really shines, though, is in its visual variety – there are grassy levels, snowy levels, underwater levels, spooky levels, retro Minecraft-esque levels where everything is made of tiny blocks… My favourite was an art deco casino stage that felt very Cuphead, complete with evil anthropomorphic cards throwing the rest of the deck at you. Slo-Mo Casino is so colourful and stylish that it was hard to choose just one screenshot Many games have themed sections, but Astro Bot’s attention to detail sets it apart. Sometimes it’s in the animation – for example, the way Astro skates and twirls along icy surfaces. Sometimes it’s the enemies, who are given accessories and abilities to match the level’s theme. And sometimes it’s the sheer number of objects on the screen – each gem, leaf, or gold nugget is a separate item with full physics, and the game revels in letting you smash through full piles of them. All of this is also extremely tactile. Astro Bot was built for the PS5’s controller, and makes better use of it than any other game I’ve played (edging out Gran Turismo 7, which does a solid job). You can sense each individual object and surface through its vibration, lending the world a very physical feel – especially in levels where Astro is curled up in a ball, rolling over panels adorned with spikes. Fun above all else While getting from A to B is the name of the game, Team Asobi has excelled at adding unique attractions for the player to investigate. These are usually clearly signposted, and whenever you find yourself asking “Can I do X?”, the answer is a resounding yes, rewarded by coins. Can I kick that football into the goal? Sure. Can I jump through the hoop with those dolphins? You bet – here’s your prize. Another favourite moment occurred on a snowy level, where I encountered two penguins building the base of a snowman. To my delight, Astro Bot was able to nudge the ball around the area and collect snow from the ground until he’d built a snowball bigger than himself. These might sound like inconsequential details, but they demonstrate how the developer prioritised fun above all else. Piles of objects like this are fully interactive - you can wade or smash through as you wish One more variation on the genre comes in those setups involving large numbers of objects and space to play with the physics. I mentioned that sometimes this means Astro wading through chest-high pits of items, but it can also be a pile of inflatables stacked precariously at the top of a water slide, or opening a compartment that dumps a squirrel’s entire store of acorns on Astro’s head. The fun continues on the crash planet, where certain areas and activities require tens, or even hundreds, of your rescued bots to chip in to lift heavy objects or form human ladders. It’s cute to see usually hostile faces like Psycho Mantis contribute to the effort, and some stunts and animations are wacky in and of themselves. If you’ve never seen 60 bots swing a pig by the tail, you haven’t lived. Branded brethren Aside from the gameplay, one of the most notable things about Astro Bot is how closely it is tied to the PlayStation brand. The objective of the entire game is to reconstruct a giant PS5, of course, and the novelty for many players will come from collecting characters and unlocking their trademark items and scenes – even if, classily, those individuals and their games are never directly named. That’s nice, but the more surprising nostalgia for me came from smaller details in the levels. The coins Astro collects (which always reminded me of chocolate coins) are stamped with the PlayStation logo. The save slots are PS1 memory cards. Some ropes and wires are PS1 controller extension cables, complete with chunky connectors. And – perhaps my giddiest discovery – even the raindrops in the spooky levels form the controller button symbols when they hit the ground. PlayStation symbology is often subtly woven into levels - like these triangle mushrooms PlayStation branding is often very plain. Its logo and trademarks are increasingly minimalist, and as the generations have gone on any remaining colour has been sucked out. Even the symbols on the PS5 controller are grey, abandoning their signature hues. Sony has little of the fun and vibrance of a brand like Nintendo. But when you take all those icons, restore their colour, and place them amid the bright, cutesy vibe of Astro Bot, it’s amazing what a difference it makes. This is the first time in years – perhaps decades – that the PlayStation brand has sparked any kind of wonder in me, and at times the throwbacks triggered the shot of adrenaline I used to enjoy watching that PS1 boot screen as a kid. Generational talent I wouldn’t want every game to be Astro Bot. There is room for more serious titles that try to look realistic and tackle impactful themes. But I would like more games to be like Astro Bot. Unless you have a Nintendo console or the stomach for sub-par kids’ games, it’s very rare for a game to be such all-out fun. It’s a refreshing way to switch off and focus entirely on gameplay, like I did 25 years ago. But Astro Bot took roughly 15 hours to play every level from start to finish. I’m not complaining about that – its RRP is lower than most games and I’d rather play a concise game of consistent quality than an endless collectathon – but it does mean that it’s too long to run on vibes alone. The gameplay has to match. Astro Bot's immense polish is likely a result of its deliberately constrained scope Team Asobi has delivered near-flawlessly in that department. Astro Bot’s controls are natural, consistent, and responsive – everything you need in a platformer where a split-second jump can have huge stakes – and the controller feedback elevates the experience to joyful levels. The controls are solid enough to support not only the casual explore-and-progress levels, but also the more challenging gauntlets that present one threat after another with zero thinking time. So the game plays well. It does things with the PS5 controller that no other game has. The graphics, while simple and bright, are crisp and polished. It’s all on the disc, with no live services or add-ons. And – perhaps most importantly – Astro Bot puts fun front and centre. Together, it’s the sum of its parts and then some, the most complete package we’ve had so far this generation. If you have a PS5, even if platformers aren’t your usual jam, I very much recommend you play it. 5/5</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/astro-bot_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/astro-bot_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hideo Kojima: Connecting Worlds - inspirational but sanitised</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/13/hideo-kojima-connecting-worlds" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hideo Kojima&amp;#58; Connecting Worlds &amp;#45; inspirational but sanitised" /><published>2024-09-13T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-13T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/13/hideo-kojima-connecting-worlds</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="death-stranding" /><category term="metal-gear-solid" /><category term="documentaries" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">It’s no secret that Hideo Kojima likes attention, and I’m sure he would have loved the idea of Connecting Worlds, a film that is ultimately part-documentary, part-marketing exercise. This is 100 percent modern Kojima, post-his fashionable makeover circa 2019. There are a lot of arty shots of him in empty offices and studios, and a compendium of clips of his famous friends complimenting him. But simultaneously, beneath the gushing praise from Geoff Keighley, Chvrches, and George Miller, there’s something purer on display. Seeing Kojima at work is to witness an inspirational passion for creation that I used to absorb through the pages of the gaming magazines I read growing up. In the 2020s, it serves as a reminder that video games are more than sales figures and Twitter arguments.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hideo-kojima-connecting-worlds_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hideo-kojima-connecting-worlds_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">I finally played Astro’s Playroom!</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/08/astros-playroom" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I finally played Astro's Playroom!" /><published>2024-09-08T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-08T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/08/astros-playroom</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="astro-bot" /><summary type="html">🤖 I finally played Astro’s Playroom! I initially wrote it off as a tech demo, but with all the praise for Astro Bot, I wanted to see what the fuss was about. I really enjoyed the flow and variety in the platforming, the unique ideas, and the nostalgic nods to PlayStation’s past. I’ll definitely play Astro Bot next.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Concord’s failure should be a wake-up call for the video game industry</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/06/concord-live-service-fail" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Concord's failure should be a wake-up call for the video game industry" /><published>2024-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/06/concord-live-service-fail</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="concord" /><category term="playstation" /><category term="industry" /><summary type="html">What a week it’s been in the video game industry! We’ve witnessed one of the most remarkable failures ever, as Concord - the Firewalk Studios-developed live service game into which Sony had invested so much in the hope it would be the next big thing - was shut down after just two weeks in operation. Much of the criticism of the title was written off by its supporters and the press as “hate”, but this story is actually a culmination of a number of factors that should not be swept under the carpet. If they are, then game developers and publishers might miss the important lessons that should be learnt from Concord’s demise.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/concord_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/concord_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Year In Between - my debut novel is available now!</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/02/the-year-in-between-novel" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Year In Between - my debut novel is available now!" /><published>2024-08-26T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-26T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/09/02/the-year-in-between-novel</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="the-year-in-between" /><category term="writing" /><category term="books" /><summary type="html">My first ever novel, The Year In Between, is now available for purchase! The book was a labour of love that took hundreds of hours to finish, but I’m aware that competition is fierce for your hard-earned money and the limited space on your bookshelf, so I’ve put together a short article to give you a better idea of the themes it explores and what to expect should you choose to read it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/the-year-in-between_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/the-year-in-between_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GTA IV’s Liberty City is still the best virtual city ever made</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/08/25/grand-theft-auto-iv-liberty-city" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTA IV's Liberty City is still the best virtual city ever made" /><published>2024-08-25T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-25T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/08/25/grand-theft-auto-iv-liberty-city</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="grand-theft-auto" /><category term="retro" /><summary type="html">In its review upon the game’s release in 2008, GamesRadar called Liberty City “the biggest reason to delve into GTA IV”. Its writers said it was “easily 100 times more detailed” than the map of its predecessor, Grand Theft Auto: San Andreas, concluding that altogether, the city was “convincingly like the real thing”. GTA IV tells story of Niko Bellic, but Liberty City has a life of its own It truly was like nothing we’d ever seen. Spanning three islands totalling just over six square miles, GTA IV’s map was nowhere near as expansive as the region depicted by Rockstar’s 2004 title, but it was perhaps the densest video game setting ever built in terms of population and detail - and certainly in character. For players focused on the story and the violence, many of the small touches that made Liberty City such a great virtual city probably passed by unnoticed. But even then, they undoubtedly felt that what they were playing was a premium product, even if they didn’t know why. My goal in this article is to pick apart those minutae that make GTA IV’s world such a compelling imitiation of a real-life city.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/gta-iv_9.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/gta-iv_9.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Notice anything different?</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2024/08/25/notice-anything-different" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notice anything different?" /><published>2024-08-25T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-25T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2024/08/25/notice-anything-different</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">🎨 Notice anything different? In preparation for some big upcoming news, I’ve given my website a lick of paint. I’m hoping the new design will make it easier to find the best articles (as well as just generally looking cooler). Feel free to drop me an email if you have any ideas to make it even better.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>