<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-23T17:14:03+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">GTA VI leak: Beyond the videos</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/23/gta-vi-leak-beyond-the-videos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTA VI leak&amp;#58; Beyond the videos" /><published>2022-09-23T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-23T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/23/gta-vi-leak-beyond-the-videos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/23/gta-vi-leak-beyond-the-videos">&lt;p&gt;We saw one of the biggest leaks in video game history last Sunday as a hacker uploaded a huge number of videos and images from Rockstar’s upcoming &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/grand-theft-auto&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto VI&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to the internet, and it’s safe to say online discussion around this unexpected sneak peek has been a complete mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gta-vi_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The early footage shows several interesting locations, features, and segments of dialogue that give us clues about what we can expect on the game’s release, which is likely years away. However, most of the comments I’ve seen on social media have completely ignored the big picture to focus on rough edges that are extremely unlikely to be present in the final game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching all of this, I felt compelled to delay my planned article this week and write about &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt; instead. I’ll stress that I have no special inside knowledge about the leak or the game itself, but I hope I can at least offer some more considered thoughts than those currently spewed across the web. In brief, the whole debacle has taught me three things…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-people-know-nothing-about-hacking&quot;&gt;1. People know nothing about hacking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“[X Rockstar employee] is going to be in trouble” was a common theme on Reddit, as wannabe cybersecurity experts offered rundowns of exactly how the person whose name appeared in some of the videos was outwitted by a social engineering attack that gave the attacker access. Others were sure that online messages indicated this was the work of a disgruntled employee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that there are two things that we know about the incident - at least since &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RockstarGames/status/1571849091860029455&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rockstar confirmed there was a “network intrusion” on Monday&lt;/a&gt;. Firstly, we know that a hacker gained access to &lt;em&gt;some Rockstar systems&lt;/em&gt; (not even necessarily their network, since so much happens on cloud services these days). Secondly, we know that they were able to download some videos and images created &lt;em&gt;at some point in the game’s development&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. We don’t know if they phished someone, we don’t know if they used some ultra-sophisticated zero-day vulnerability, and we don’t know if a storage platform was improperly configured and allowed them access. We don’t know what happened, and Rockstar is probably still piecing it together itself, so there’s no point in blindly speculating - especially when that speculation involves pointing the finger at individual employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that point - sure, somebody’s name appears on screen in some of the videos, but if a hacker steals files from a shared location they could have &lt;em&gt;anybody’s&lt;/em&gt; name on them, regardless of how they got in. That person just &lt;em&gt;recorded&lt;/em&gt; the videos. Confidently asserting that they were the cause of the breach is at best foolish, and at worst borderline slander.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-people-know-nothing-about-development&quot;&gt;2. People know nothing about development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d have thought that in 2022’s tech-driven society, with all the developer blogs and behind-the-scenes footage we’re treated to, that people would have a rough idea of what goes into making a video game. Unfortunately not, it appears, as Sunday’s discussion threads were jammed with complaints about &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt;’s graphics, despite the game being years off release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It looks nearly the same as &lt;em&gt;GTA V&lt;/em&gt;,” people whined. &lt;em&gt;Of course it does&lt;/em&gt;. The footage is obviously from a very early version of the game - likely borrowing a lot from the last entry - where the developers are testing out systems to see what works and laying the groundwork for later, more polished versions. There are going to be rough edges, and for all we know they could no longer exist, since we don’t know when the videos were captured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rockstar was evidently concerned about this reaction too, as evidenced in the statement it tweeted earlier this week:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We are extremely disappointed to have any details of our next game shared with you all in this way. Our work on the next &lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto&lt;/em&gt; game will continue as planned and we remain as committed as ever to delivering and experience to you, our players, that truly exceeds your expectations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: Stop judging our game on janky alpha footage that was never meant to be made public, you idiots. It’s also clear that many of the clips may have been recorded &lt;em&gt;specifically to inform bug fixes&lt;/em&gt;, as the creator seems to focus attention on issues like clipping and AI mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you watch the videos with a curious eye, rather than a critical one, they actually offer an inside view of game development that we rarely get to see. For example, the pop-ups that litter the screen during the restaurant robbery (like HOSTAGE_POLICE_ARRIVAL, GENERIC_CURSE_TO_SELF, and CALL_FOR_SUPPORT_RESPONSE) are a fascinating glimpse of how AI reactions, animations, and sound clips are handled behind the scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-rockstar-might-actually-deliver-on-gta-vi&quot;&gt;3. Rockstar might actually deliver on &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of August I wrote about &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/08/05/gta-vi-first-details-scepticism&quot;&gt;how skeptical I am about &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Early details suggested that the series might be moving in the direction of live services following the success of &lt;em&gt;GTA Online&lt;/em&gt;, and given that this is the first &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; game to be released since Rockstar worked out how to print free money, I’m concerned about what that might mean for the single-player experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a few leaked clips haven’t completely allayed my fears, what they have done is reassured me that the minutiae and attention to detail that Rockstar is known for are still there. Beyond the debug messages, clipping, and placeholder textures, there are already signs of some real touches of class - the fluidity of new female lead character’s walking animations, for example, or the two NPCs discussing Lifeinvader conspiracy theories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between that and the obstructed views of Vice City in the background, I’m feeling much more confident that the detail that makes &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt;’s worlds so much fun to explore will still be present. And then there’s the restaurant robbery, complete with the second main character controlled by AI to back you up. It could be a Story Mode set piece, but I’m crossing my fingers that this means more ad hoc interactivity with the world and NPCs than in previous games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, despite the fact that they certainly would have liked to introduce us to the game in a more controlled fashion, the &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt; leak shows enough potential that it should really have been a net positive for Rockstar in my opinion. Instead, they’ve needed to engage in damage limitation because the internet is stupid and expects a game with years of development left to go to look like a finished AAA product - or at least that’s my two cents.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="grand-theft-auto" /><category term="industry" /><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">We saw one of the biggest leaks in video game history last Sunday as a hacker uploaded a huge number of videos and images from Rockstar’s upcoming Grand Theft Auto VI to the internet, and it’s safe to say online discussion around this unexpected sneak peek has been a complete mess. The early footage shows several interesting locations, features, and segments of dialogue that give us clues about what we can expect on the game’s release, which is likely years away. However, most of the comments I’ve seen on social media have completely ignored the big picture to focus on rough edges that are extremely unlikely to be present in the final game. Watching all of this, I felt compelled to delay my planned article this week and write about GTA VI instead. I’ll stress that I have no special inside knowledge about the leak or the game itself, but I hope I can at least offer some more considered thoughts than those currently spewed across the web. In brief, the whole debacle has taught me three things… 1. People know nothing about hacking “[X Rockstar employee] is going to be in trouble” was a common theme on Reddit, as wannabe cybersecurity experts offered rundowns of exactly how the person whose name appeared in some of the videos was outwitted by a social engineering attack that gave the attacker access. Others were sure that online messages indicated this was the work of a disgruntled employee. The truth is that there are two things that we know about the incident - at least since Rockstar confirmed there was a “network intrusion” on Monday. Firstly, we know that a hacker gained access to some Rockstar systems (not even necessarily their network, since so much happens on cloud services these days). Secondly, we know that they were able to download some videos and images created at some point in the game’s development.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gta-vi_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gta-vi_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – cup runs to remember</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/16/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-3" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA 22 Career Mode&amp;#58; TSP United &amp;#8211; cup runs to remember" /><published>2022-09-16T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/16/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/16/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-3">&lt;p&gt;The years are flying by in my &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Career Mode series, and after surviving our first season in the top flight, the fans are now expecting TSP United to push on and improve their standing amongst England’s best clubs in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a reminder, I’m playing this Career Mode campaign with special custom rules for some added challenge. I’m not to spend a penny on players (signing free agents is fine) and the focus is on &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players&quot;&gt;scouting and developing youth players&lt;/a&gt;. So my main source of new talent through this whole thing is to send a scout out around England occasionally and see what he brings back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this is the third instalment of my TSP United Career Mode series. Click here to catch up on the first four seasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/06/17/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-2&quot;&gt;FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – hitting the big time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202526---premier-league&quot;&gt;2025/26 - Premier League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a top-flight season under our belts, it was time to cement our place in the Premier League, and that meant strengthening in some key areas. Free agent centre backs Adhoum and Alba came in to provide some depth, Anami was retrained to join them in defence, and I signed a clubless left midfielder named Albanese now that Annumanian was playing up front.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a slow start, but some good form towards the end of 2025 meant we crept into the top half at the start of the new year. The goal of the season undoubtedly came from club legend Willis against Liverpool, cutting in from the wing and rounding Allison to give TSP United an early lead at Anfield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the issues started. Annumanian suffered an injury around the 25-game mark (luckily, he’d return in scoring form before May) and Aguerre’s poor form gave me no choice but to give the youngster Parkin more chances in goal. In better news, academy product Hunter was steadily developing as a right-wing understudy to Pierre, and Green stepped in at left back to replace a declining Marcos Alonso, who would retire at the end of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the league campaign ended in mid-table mediocrity, our FA Cup run culminated in a dramatic triumph against Arsenal at Wembley. After going 2-0 down in the early stages, we dragged ourselves back to 2-2, before going in 3-2 down at the break. Arsenal had a man sent off in the second half, and a late equaliser from Pierre took the game to extra time, where Annumanian wrote himself into the TSP United history books with the winning goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best original player&lt;/strong&gt; - Willis/Hutton, the two survivors from League 2&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - Alba, providing much-needed depth at CB&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Green, earning his first-team spot&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202627---premier-league&quot;&gt;2026/27 - Premier League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With our FA Cup victory came a Europa League spot, and with the hectic schedule that European football brings incoming, we once again needed to strengthen the squad. Club legend Johnson left, opting for a move elsewhere due to a lack of playing time. The pickings were slim, but we signed another free agent named Aguirre - this time at right back - and sent the scouts back out to England and Scotland to top up the academy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our efforts were rewarded with what I consider to be an impressive first run in the Europa League. With games coming fast, our youngsters took to the pitch, with striker Goddard the standout, scoring a hat trick as we beat group leaders AZ 3-2 in the final game to secure our progression. After destroying Young Boys in the first knockout round, we didn’t have enough to beat Atalanta in the Round of 16 and tumbled out of the competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The board were expecting us to qualify for the Europa League via the league this year, but our mixed fortunes early on gave way to the most dire run of form of my managerial career so far. In the end we finished tenth, well short of the board’s expectations, largely due to poor performances from Parkin and his defence. Vaughan broke the Premier League season scoring record, which should give you an idea of what a disaster it was at the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With nothing to write home about from the domestic cup runs and the league season ending in disappointment, the highlight of 2026/27 was without doubt our first European campaign - not only because of how far we progressed, but because it was mainly down to our next generation of players. The future of TSP United looks bright, but having missed out on most of my objectives I can only hope I’m around long enough to see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best original player&lt;/strong&gt; - Willis, still going strong at LM after six years&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - Aguirre, who made some exciting runs from RB&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Goddard, back with 18 goals in 31 apps&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">The years are flying by in my FIFA 22 Career Mode series, and after surviving our first season in the top flight, the fans are now expecting TSP United to push on and improve their standing amongst England’s best clubs in 2025. As a reminder, I’m playing this Career Mode campaign with special custom rules for some added challenge. I’m not to spend a penny on players (signing free agents is fine) and the focus is on scouting and developing youth players. So my main source of new talent through this whole thing is to send a scout out around England occasionally and see what he brings back. Note that this is the third instalment of my TSP United Career Mode series. Click here to catch up on the first four seasons: • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues • FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – hitting the big time 2025/26 - Premier League With a top-flight season under our belts, it was time to cement our place in the Premier League, and that meant strengthening in some key areas. Free agent centre backs Adhoum and Alba came in to provide some depth, Anami was retrained to join them in defence, and I signed a clubless left midfielder named Albanese now that Annumanian was playing up front.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to run a half marathon</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/09/how-to-run-half-marathon" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to run a half marathon" /><published>2022-09-09T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-09T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/09/how-to-run-half-marathon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/09/how-to-run-half-marathon">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/running&quot;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt; on and off for years, but I was in two minds when I first considered signing up to a half marathon earlier this year. Towards the end of 2021 I’d completed &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/10/running-formula-1-for-your-feet&quot;&gt;a one-hour event&lt;/a&gt;, but a half marathon was double the distance, a whole new level of commitment, and a step into the unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/half-marathon_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spoiler alert - I finished the race. I didn’t do it in quite the way I’d hoped, but I’m happy with what I achieved and plan to go back stronger and better prepared next year. In that spirit, I thought that while everything was fresh in my mind it would be a good time to share what I’ve learnt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-for-a-half-marathon&quot;&gt;Training for a half marathon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first things you need in order to run a half marathon are time to train, somewhere to run (the streets are your best bet), good running shoes, and light and comfortable clothes to run in. The important thing here is to pick an outfit and stick to it - don’t buy a new shirt and save it for the main event, because you won’t know whether it chafes until it’s too late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started training properly in March, six months ahead of the event in September. Prior to that I’d been running about 5km twice a week, so I started to ramp that up. My midweek run started at 5km and eventually became 7.5km, while my long weekend run slowly scaled up until I ran my first half marathon distance in July. Given that I was running up and down hills and the event course would be flat, I thought I was well set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two moments that turned out to be crucial came towards the end of my training. Firstly, one day the tread of my trusty running shoes fell off while I was out running the streets of my neighbourhood. I thought I chose the replacements well, but over time I started to feel complaints from my knees and the outside of my right foot, and it only got worse. When I did my final preparation run it took a week for them to feel somewhat normal again.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second stroke of bad luck came about a month before the race, when I ended up looking after somebody who came down with COVID. Fortunately I didn’t catch it myself (that might have been game over completely), but it did keep me off the streets for two weeks. In the end, I managed only four more runs - two short, two long - before the event itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;running-a-half-marathon&quot;&gt;Running a half marathon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the day came, everything was set. I had run a non-stop half marathon distance the week before and my knees had mostly recovered, and the forecasted rain disappeared, leaving a morning that was dry but not too hot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first mistake was arriving at the time suggested by the event organisers. I ended up queueing for nearly an hour to use a toilet before the race and missed my start time by 20 minutes. Aside from the boredom and discomfort, starting three hours after my usual running time meant it was considerably warmer than I was used to when I crossed the start line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first mile was a breeze, with an early challenge emerging only as I entered a tunnel. I had plenty in the tank to deal with the slope, but the underground section was unexpectedly hot, and I could feel the sweat dripping down my forehead. Although I felt fine, this was when the first doubts started to creep in over whether I could keep this up for 21km.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My pace slipped slightly over the next few miles, but I still felt strong. The only nagging concern was over my knees, which had started to give the first indications that there was a painful journey ahead. This was exacerbated by a section where I had to traverse some cobbled streets, where I needed to watch every step to avoid slipping or folding an ankle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit that by the seventh mile I was starting to lag, with stitches forming on either side of my stomach. I endured the pain for a while longer, but by the time I hit the eight-mile mark it was too much. I pulled to the side of the road and tried to keep up a brisk walk, swigging from the sports drink I’d brought along and praying for recovery and a second wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never regained the same level of energy I enjoyed at the beginning, but after about a mile I did force myself to start running again. I could see my knees were red, and every step hurt more and more until I was worried something would snap at some point. Passing strewn-out runners being tended to by paramedics wasn’t exactly reassuring, but I remained determined to keep going, even if progress was slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/half-marathon_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the final kilometre or so the streets were lined with spectators, which helped me to muster enough for a final push. When I checked my split times later, the was a noticeable increase in my pace as I drew closer to the finish, and I finally made it across the line after about two hours and 20 minutes - not quite what I was aiming for, but an achievement nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-i-learnt&quot;&gt;What I learnt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I finished the race, the half marathon didn’t &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; go to plan. In the days since, I’ve thought carefully about how things played out and have identified some key areas to improve on for next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Running shoes&lt;/strong&gt; - Do you remember how I mentioned that you shouldn’t switch out your equipment shortly before a race? My forced change of running shoes was a prime example, as I didn’t have time to realise the damage they were doing to my feet and legs. My top priority is to buy a better quality pair that I can train in throughout my next attempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water&lt;/strong&gt; - I opted to take a sports drink with me for the race, thinking that replacing my lost sugar and salt would give me an extra burst of energy. But its thick, sugary taste was almost nauseating when running, and discouraged me from drinking. Next time I’ll stick to water, and perhaps try the energy sachets that many of the other runners were using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pace&lt;/strong&gt; - I started out ambitious, aiming for the two-hour mark, and it blew up in my face after about two thirds of the race distance. Next time I’ll set out at a more comfortable pace, because running slightly slower throughout is better overall than starting quickly and running out of steam later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there you have it. That’s everything I know about how to run a half marathon, and also what I’ve learnt about how &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to run a half marathon. I hope this article is useful if you’re preparing for your own race, and if you have any tips for my second attempt next year, please let me know.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="running" /><summary type="html">I’ve been running on and off for years, but I was in two minds when I first considered signing up to a half marathon earlier this year. Towards the end of 2021 I’d completed a one-hour event, but a half marathon was double the distance, a whole new level of commitment, and a step into the unknown. Spoiler alert - I finished the race. I didn’t do it in quite the way I’d hoped, but I’m happy with what I achieved and plan to go back stronger and better prepared next year. In that spirit, I thought that while everything was fresh in my mind it would be a good time to share what I’ve learnt. Training for a half marathon The first things you need in order to run a half marathon are time to train, somewhere to run (the streets are your best bet), good running shoes, and light and comfortable clothes to run in. The important thing here is to pick an outfit and stick to it - don’t buy a new shirt and save it for the main event, because you won’t know whether it chafes until it’s too late. I started training properly in March, six months ahead of the event in September. Prior to that I’d been running about 5km twice a week, so I started to ramp that up. My midweek run started at 5km and eventually became 7.5km, while my long weekend run slowly scaled up until I ran my first half marathon distance in July. Given that I was running up and down hills and the event course would be flat, I thought I was well set. Two moments that turned out to be crucial came towards the end of my training. Firstly, one day the tread of my trusty running shoes fell off while I was out running the streets of my neighbourhood. I thought I chose the replacements well, but over time I started to feel complaints from my knees and the outside of my right foot, and it only got worse. When I did my final preparation run it took a week for them to feel somewhat normal again.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/half-marathon_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/half-marathon_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">F1 Manager 2022 is like a revival of old movie games</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/02/f1-manager-2022-movie-game-revival" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="F1 Manager 2022 is like a revival of old movie games" /><published>2022-09-02T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/02/f1-manager-2022-movie-game-revival</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/09/02/f1-manager-2022-movie-game-revival">&lt;p&gt;There was a time, certainly in the 2000s but also arguably as early as the 1980s - I’m looking at you, &lt;em&gt;ET&lt;/em&gt; - when most video games based on films were disappointments. There were some notable exceptions, like the excellent &lt;em&gt;Spider-Man 2&lt;/em&gt;, but all too often movie tie-ins were dull, mediocre games with recognisable textures and voices copied and pasted into the right places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f1-manager-2022_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sports game have largely avoided the same fate - perhaps because their real-life counterparts translate more easily into a video game format. &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/pro-evolution-soccer&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;PES&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; have always given us enjoyable recreations of professional football, there have been countless iterations on golf, and across the pond &lt;em&gt;Madden&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;NBA&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;MLB&lt;/em&gt; are all long-running series. For those who want on-brand motorsport, &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-1&quot;&gt;Codemasters’ &lt;em&gt;F1&lt;/em&gt; series&lt;/a&gt; has done a consistent job of providing entertaining racing since its first true edition surfaced in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year there’s a new face on the scene - &lt;em&gt;F1 Manager 2022&lt;/em&gt;, developed by Frontier. From the very beginning it’s been promoted on its presentation, with early screenshots compared favourably to Codemasters’ graphics. Official teams and drivers were expected of a licensed game, and when early access opened we also saw that it features the flashy F1 race intro sequence, radio audio from the real drivers, and commentary from Crofty at key in-race moments. With all that on its side, what could go wrong?&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f1-manager-2022_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, for a start, the racing is not as impressive in motion as it was in still images. Like &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/football-manager&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the game’s simulation is obviously based on a series of strategic calculations rather than a physics model, and it suffers from the same mismatch with its 3D representation. Drivers take odd racing lines and steer erratically, for example, leaving you on edge when watching onboard cameras as they always look like they’re about to spin out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That would be forgivable for a management game - it certainly is for &lt;em&gt;FM&lt;/em&gt;’s unnatural-looking players - but for &lt;em&gt;F1 Manager 2022&lt;/em&gt; the visual disconnect just helps to highlight other shortcomings. When you sell realism, players expect realism, and the reaction to the game’s launch has given me a new appreciation for the way &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/08/27/motorsport-manager-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Motorsport Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; cleverly streamlined the complexities of motorsport into a sort of cartoonish card game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f1-manager-2022_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/F1Manager/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;F1 Manager&lt;/em&gt;’s subreddit&lt;/a&gt; is full of complaints of game-breaking issues. Players are frustrated at the limited instructions they can issue to drivers, simple and repetitive practice sessions, drivers cutting across the racing line and blocking their cars’ fast laps, and intermediate tyres that they say perform better than slicks in the dry. And it doesn’t seem there’s much challenge to be found amongst the chaos, either - even players managing backmarkers like Haas and Williams are finding they can be championship contenders by the second season if they optimise their cars’ development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To Frontier’s credit, they appear to be engaging with players more than most developers have historically in similar situations, and seem to be keen to gather feedback. Hopefully most of the bugs can be fixed fairly quickly, but it remains to be seen whether the balance and missing detail will be rectified in this year’s game. For now, however, it looks like &lt;em&gt;F1 Manager 2022&lt;/em&gt; is a revival of the classic movie game - a title that relies on licences and familiar faces to sell, but lacks substance beyond its slick presentation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="f1-manager" /><category term="formula-1" /><category term="racing" /><category term="management" /><summary type="html">There was a time, certainly in the 2000s but also arguably as early as the 1980s - I’m looking at you, ET - when most video games based on films were disappointments. There were some notable exceptions, like the excellent Spider-Man 2, but all too often movie tie-ins were dull, mediocre games with recognisable textures and voices copied and pasted into the right places. Sports game have largely avoided the same fate - perhaps because their real-life counterparts translate more easily into a video game format. FIFA and PES have always given us enjoyable recreations of professional football, there have been countless iterations on golf, and across the pond Madden, NBA, and MLB are all long-running series. For those who want on-brand motorsport, Codemasters’ F1 series has done a consistent job of providing entertaining racing since its first true edition surfaced in 2010. This year there’s a new face on the scene - F1 Manager 2022, developed by Frontier. From the very beginning it’s been promoted on its presentation, with early screenshots compared favourably to Codemasters’ graphics. Official teams and drivers were expected of a licensed game, and when early access opened we also saw that it features the flashy F1 race intro sequence, radio audio from the real drivers, and commentary from Crofty at key in-race moments. With all that on its side, what could go wrong?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f1-manager-2022_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f1-manager-2022_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Muse – Will Of The People review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/08/26/muse-will-of-the-people-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Muse &amp;#8211; Will Of The People review" /><published>2022-08-26T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-26T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/08/26/muse-will-of-the-people-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/08/26/muse-will-of-the-people-review">&lt;p&gt;I’m back after a longer-than-expected break for COVID-related reasons, and have returned just in time for Muse’s first new album in nearly four years, &lt;em&gt;Will Of The People&lt;/em&gt;. While &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/music&quot;&gt;it’s relatively rare for me to discuss music&lt;/a&gt; on this blog, I’ve been a huge Muse fan since I was a teenager, so I thought I’d jot down some notes from my initial listens to share with you all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/muse-will-of-the-people_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months leading up to its release, Muse frontman Matt Bellamy billed &lt;em&gt;Will Of The People&lt;/em&gt; as “a greatest hits album of new songs”, revisiting the styles of the band’s previous eight studio albums across its ten tracks. It’s unsurprising, then, that what he and his bandmates delivered is an eclectic collection of songs that range from heavy metal to emotional piano ballads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the quality? Opinions on individual tracks will vary depending on your tastes for different Muse eras, but for me heavy rocker Kill Or Be Killed sits with their very best, there are a couple of decent guitar-heavy songs, and much of the record is B-tier pop-rock. The lows - there are &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; lows - are nowhere near as dismal as the worst tracks on some of their other albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you enjoy &lt;em&gt;Will Of The People&lt;/em&gt; will depend on what you’re expecting. We can almost say for certain now that the Muse that delivered &lt;em&gt;Origin of Symmetry&lt;/em&gt; is gone for good, but if you’re open to enjoying their more playful, overblown side - and not averse to some quite significant shifts in sound and theme - then the album provides nod-along pop, heavy guitar riffs, and surprisingly emotional moments in almost equal measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the very least, it’s a definite step up from 2018’s disappointing, synth-heavy effort &lt;em&gt;Simulation Theory&lt;/em&gt;. At best, you could make an argument that this is Muse’s best album since &lt;em&gt;The 2nd Law&lt;/em&gt; or even &lt;em&gt;The Resistance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;track-by-track&quot;&gt;Track by track&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Will Of The People&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Catchy pop-rock track that works fantastically as a set opener at live gigs. Doesn’t outstay its welcome like previous songs in this category (Psycho) and has more lyrical depth than some reviewers give it credit for. While it’s often written off as another Muse call for revolution, in reality it transforms during the second verse into a warning about those who seek positive change but go too far and “throw the baby out with the bath water”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Compliance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Another misunderstood song, sometimes mistaken as an anti-mask/vaccine track, but actually in my view provides some quite thoughful commentary on how directionless individuals are swept up by ideologically-fuelled online movements in a bid to find purpose. Musically, eerie verses and some very funky bass make Compliance enjoyable despite its heavy pop leanings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Liberation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Musically reminiscent of the tail end of The Globalist with similar lyrical themes to Defector, with the Queen-style harmonies of United States of Eurasia thrown in for good measure. Varied enough to be engaging, but the “thank you” segment always feels disappointing because everything to that point feels like it’s building to something. But as the first time we’ve heard Matt Bellamy properly break out his piano since 2015, I’ll take it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Won’t Stand Down&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The verses feel very Imagine Dragons and often jar with the breakdowns and chorus, but when it gains momentum it’s hard not to move too. Ascending, synth-backed choruses get the adrenaline pumping, and everything past the two-minute mark is heavier than we’ve heard Muse in years. Delivers the guitar riffs Muse fans endlessly hope for, but not the classical elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Ghosts (How Can I Move On)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Bellamy takes to the stage alone with this piano ballad, which would feel right at home on his solo Record Store Day 2021 LP &lt;em&gt;Cryosleep&lt;/em&gt;. The lyrics sometimes stumble over themselves a little, but the composition, themes, and longing vocals are enough to make this a surprisingly welcome interlude. Along with Euphoria, this marks the emotional high of the album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. You Make Me Feel Like It’s Halloween&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It’s hard to argue in favour of Halloween, especially when it comes right after a track as heartfelt as Ghosts. It’s fun and groovy, but between the organ, the title, and the B-movie horror sound effects, it sticks out as an oddity on the album and feels more like a Halloween novelty track than something that belongs on a mainline Muse record. It does earn a few bonus points for the guitar solo, however, which is far better than it has any right to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Kill Or Be Killed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Without a doubt the best song on the album, and perhaps the best track Muse have delivered in a decade - maybe even 15 years. Kill Or Be Killed is some of the heaviest rock the trio have ever recorded, taking a similar tone to fan favourite &lt;em&gt;Absolution&lt;/em&gt; bonus track Fury, but with added punch. The lyrics, chord progressions, and general feeling all scream “classic Muse”, and one can only hope that we’re treated to more music like this in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Verona&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In my opinion this is &lt;em&gt;WOTP&lt;/em&gt;’s weakest track, and not just because it lives in Kill Or Be Killed’s shadow. Verona is a synthy love song with shades of U2, which is a side of modern Muse that is often bemoaned. It builds up nicely, but ultimately does little to earn its place as the album’s second-longest song, and is the only one I’ve found myself occasionally skipping already. It has heart, but there’s nothing particularly Musey about it - I can imagine myself checking my watch as a support band plays something very similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Euphoria&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It took a few listens, but Euphoria has quickly become one of my favourites. I’m not big on the almost shouted verses, but there’s something to the chords and sustain-heavy guitar solos that takes me back to the early-to-mid-2000s when I first discovered Muse and felt all their songs deeply. It’s upbeat, it has probably the best guitar solo on the album, and there’s more desperation to the melodies than I thought the band could muster in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. We Are Fucking Fucked&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If &lt;em&gt;WOTP&lt;/em&gt; is a greatest hits-style tour of Muse’s previous work, the verses here are as close as we get to &lt;em&gt;Showbiz&lt;/em&gt;. I’m split on the song in general - it’s lively, but the chorus where Bellamy lists bad things in the world feels basic, and there’s a point near the end where he just yells “fuck off” a couple of times. Luckily, the guitar work is enough to keep pushing through it, and it only increases in intensity as the album comes to a close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4/5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="muse" /><category term="guitar" /><summary type="html">I’m back after a longer-than-expected break for COVID-related reasons, and have returned just in time for Muse’s first new album in nearly four years, Will Of The People. While it’s relatively rare for me to discuss music on this blog, I’ve been a huge Muse fan since I was a teenager, so I thought I’d jot down some notes from my initial listens to share with you all. In the months leading up to its release, Muse frontman Matt Bellamy billed Will Of The People as “a greatest hits album of new songs”, revisiting the styles of the band’s previous eight studio albums across its ten tracks. It’s unsurprising, then, that what he and his bandmates delivered is an eclectic collection of songs that range from heavy metal to emotional piano ballads. As for the quality? Opinions on individual tracks will vary depending on your tastes for different Muse eras, but for me heavy rocker Kill Or Be Killed sits with their very best, there are a couple of decent guitar-heavy songs, and much of the record is B-tier pop-rock. The lows - there are some lows - are nowhere near as dismal as the worst tracks on some of their other albums. Whether you enjoy Will Of The People will depend on what you’re expecting. We can almost say for certain now that the Muse that delivered Origin of Symmetry is gone for good, but if you’re open to enjoying their more playful, overblown side - and not averse to some quite significant shifts in sound and theme - then the album provides nod-along pop, heavy guitar riffs, and surprisingly emotional moments in almost equal measure. At the very least, it’s a definite step up from 2018’s disappointing, synth-heavy effort Simulation Theory. At best, you could make an argument that this is Muse’s best album since The 2nd Law or even The Resistance.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/08/muse-will-of-the-people_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/08/muse-will-of-the-people_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GTA VI: First details leave plenty of room for scepticism</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/08/05/gta-vi-first-details-scepticism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTA VI&amp;#58; First details leave plenty of room for scepticism" /><published>2022-08-05T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-05T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/08/05/gta-vi-first-details-scepticism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/08/05/gta-vi-first-details-scepticism">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gta-vi_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was last week, nearly nine whole years after the release of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/grand-theft-auto&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2022-07-27/gta-6-release-date-rockstar-cleans-up-image-after-employee-backlash&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;an article by &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt;’s Jason Schreier&lt;/a&gt; finally provided some concrete information on its sequel - at least if you believe his ex-Rockstar sources. The piece focused mainly on how progressive Rockstar is apparently now trying to be, but we did get some interesting details on &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt; has been in development since 2014, but insiders predict the release date is still at least two years away&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game will feature a playable female protagonist, who will be one half of a Bonnie and Clyde-inspired duo who are the stars of the story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is codenamed &lt;em&gt;Project Americas&lt;/em&gt;, and was originally meant to cover large parts of North and South America, but was cut down to a fictional Miami (presumably Vice City) to keep the scope manageable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There will be more building interiors than in previous &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; games, and Rockstar plans to add new missions and cities on a regular basis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the online reaction to the article consisted of misguided complaints about the female character, and perhaps-not-so-misguided concerns about how the tone of the game will be affected by the shift in its developer’s culture. But for me, the thing that set the alarm bells ringing was the line about &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt;’s setting and how the game will be extended after launch.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;early-red-flags&quot;&gt;Early red flags&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would happily play a game as a female character, and I could &lt;em&gt;tolerate&lt;/em&gt; a &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; game with blunted satire (it’s been going downhill since the peak that was &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/02/12/gta-iv-immersive-mechanics-lost-forever&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;GTA IV&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, anyway), but what would be harder to stomach is a sequel that doesn’t stand on its own two feet as a quality &lt;em&gt;game&lt;/em&gt;, and instead seeks to establish a platform to keep people spending for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rockstar stumbled upon this model with &lt;em&gt;GTA V&lt;/em&gt;. The main game released in 2013, and as players completed the story and moved on to &lt;em&gt;GTA Online&lt;/em&gt; the company pivoted, realising that it could make more money by having players pay real money to buy imaginary, multiplayer-only cars and yachts, only otherwise obtainable through endless hours of grinding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lines in the article that stood out to me the most were about the scope and roadmap for the project. If Schreier’s sources are correct, the game will release with a Vice City setting but extra missions and cities will be added later. He praises this as a way to avoid development crunch, but my worry is about what this model means for players and the game overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;approach-with-caution&quot;&gt;Approach with caution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Games companies have realised in recent years that they can make a lot of money from live service games, and titles that would have previously been almost certain single-player classics - think &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Diablo Immortal&lt;/em&gt;, for example - have been ruined by the model, prioritising microtransactions over completeness and - y’know - &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible for a title to have online and add-on elements &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; be a good game, but I guess what I’m saying is that I don’t trust modern Rockstar to deliver an experience that I will enjoy as much as previous &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; games. The company’s trademark used to be top-tier single player titles, but it seems that &lt;em&gt;GTA Online&lt;/em&gt;’s popularity has changed all that, with the company even going so far as to cancel planned single-player expansions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still have 2018’s &lt;em&gt;Red Dead Redemption 2&lt;/em&gt; as proof of what Rockstar can achieve in the single player arena, but the few details we have been given on &lt;em&gt;GTA VI&lt;/em&gt; don’t sound all that appealing. It’s early days, and it could still turn out to be the sequel we’re all dreaming of, but while any &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; game used to be a slam-dunk preorder, I think I’ll be waiting for far more information - maybe even reviews - before spending my hard-earned cash on this one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="grand-theft-auto" /><category term="industry" /><category term="game-design" /><summary type="html">It was last week, nearly nine whole years after the release of Grand Theft Auto V, that an article by Bloomberg’s Jason Schreier finally provided some concrete information on its sequel - at least if you believe his ex-Rockstar sources. The piece focused mainly on how progressive Rockstar is apparently now trying to be, but we did get some interesting details on GTA VI: GTA VI has been in development since 2014, but insiders predict the release date is still at least two years away The game will feature a playable female protagonist, who will be one half of a Bonnie and Clyde-inspired duo who are the stars of the story It is codenamed Project Americas, and was originally meant to cover large parts of North and South America, but was cut down to a fictional Miami (presumably Vice City) to keep the scope manageable There will be more building interiors than in previous GTA games, and Rockstar plans to add new missions and cities on a regular basis Much of the online reaction to the article consisted of misguided complaints about the female character, and perhaps-not-so-misguided concerns about how the tone of the game will be affected by the shift in its developer’s culture. But for me, the thing that set the alarm bells ringing was the line about GTA VI’s setting and how the game will be extended after launch.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gta-vi_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gta-vi_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Stray (PC) review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/29/stray-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stray (PC) review" /><published>2022-07-29T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-29T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/29/stray-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/29/stray-review">&lt;p&gt;Just in case you hadn’t already heard, &lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt; is a game where you play as a cat. Ever since it was shown off at a PlayStation event in 2020, the internet has been abuzz with talk about it, but mostly from the memey cat angle rather than any discussion of the actual game. Intrigued, I picked up a copy when it was finally released last week so I could find out for myself whether it was a compelling experience or just popular due to its feline protagonist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/stray_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;into-the-depths&quot;&gt;Into the depths&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt;’s opening moments are peaceful. Waking up with your cat buddies, you run as a pack through an overgrown passage, taking their lead as you learn to navigate the environment on four feet. But tragedy strikes and the cat misses a jump, sliding into a pit where you’re unable to reach your pals. You limp through a door and enter a cyberpunk city full of neon and robots whose heads look like the old Apple error icon. From there, the rest of the game concerns your quest to find a way back to the fabled Outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right away, you’ll notice that this is a beautiful game. The cat animation is very well done, from general movement right down to the little ear twitches, and nearly every environment looks like it could be ripped straight from the concept art. While the plaudits will go to the neon-draped streets, I’m a particular fan of some of the robots’ living quarters, which are stacked high with books and 90s computing equipment. I hope BlueTwelve Studio will find the time to add a photo mode later, because the camera angles, the cat’s poses, and the on-screen prompts obstruct some fantastic frames.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/stray_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically speaking, the bulk of &lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt; consists of simple 3D platforming. With a rough knowledge of where you’re going, you’ll need to scramble up pipes, signs, and air conditioning units to find a path above the city to reach your destination. Sometimes you’ll need to evade snappy little headcrab-like enemies called Zurks, and at others there are simple puzzles that involve rolling barrels around or finding and inserting plugs into computers. Some of my favourites utilised cat-specific mechanics – walking on a keyboard to send a message, or scratching a blind to reveal the window behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-cats-best-friend&quot;&gt;A cat’s best friend&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the scope of the game would be somewhat limited if you spent its entirety alone as a cat. The robots talk to the cat as though it has human-level intelligence, but it can’t speak back, and can only carry small objects. Luckily, fairly early on you meet a robot named B-12 who acts as a conduit between the cat and the world, translating dialogue and grabbing items on your behalf. I won’t go into the reasons in this mostly spoiler-free review, but by the end of the game you could make a strong argument that B-12 is the real main character, and that the whole show exists to tell his story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of said story you’ll see a variety of areas, from slums and sewers to city streets and canals, and – with a little help from B-12 and his superior dexterity – there’s a surprising mechanical variety for a game about a cat. While the game’s bread and butter is the humble item fetch quest – the type where you’ll stumble on the solution if  you just explore the area enough – there are also parts involving fast-paced pursuits, some slightly clunky stealth sections, and even third-person shooter elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/stray_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stray might be fairly simple in terms of gameplay, but its charm and atmosphere pull it through. Although the city is more threatening than the initial natural area, it is still backed by a light, synthwave-style soundtrack that both matches its environs and delivers a relaxing experience that very much feels like you are exploring the city districts with the innocence and curiosity of a cat. This is despite some fairly high stakes in the story, which spans about five hours and has some quite touching moments (quite an achievement when you consider there is no spoken dialogue in the game).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;understandable-limitations&quot;&gt;Understandable limitations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that topic, this is a game by a small studio, and it does show. I’m not as concerned as others about the length of the game – it has a dense enough concentration of detail and quality that it still feels like a good proposition – but there are some elements where it’s clear money had to be saved. For example, whenever a character needs to put on an item of clothing during the story, the screen fades to black and when we return they are magically wearing it. It’s forgivable in the circumstances, but that extra animation or two would have gone a long way to maintain the player’s immersion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt; also doesn’t seem to be incredibly well optimised for PC play. It’s not game breaking – for 95 per cent of my play time performance was flawless, even while exploring some of the more dense and beautiful environments I previously mentioned – but there were certain areas where the frame rate suffered somewhat, even running on &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/07/15/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition-review&quot;&gt;my new 3070 Ti&lt;/a&gt;. It also crashed once fairly early on, although that may have been because I Alt-tabbed to my notes at a time it didn’t like, because thankfully the issue didn’t reoccur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/stray_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s &lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt; in a nutshell. I wouldn’t exactly call it groundbreaking, but BlueTwelve have built a charming, atmospheric, and pretty world for you to lose a few hours in. The game may be a little short for some people’s tastes, but at about a third of the release price of a AAA game, I’m not complaining. &lt;em&gt;Stray&lt;/em&gt; is enjoyable, original, and a game I might return to as a sort of comfort play once enough time has elapsed for me to have forgotten the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4/5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="platformer" /><summary type="html">Just in case you hadn’t already heard, Stray is a game where you play as a cat. Ever since it was shown off at a PlayStation event in 2020, the internet has been abuzz with talk about it, but mostly from the memey cat angle rather than any discussion of the actual game. Intrigued, I picked up a copy when it was finally released last week so I could find out for myself whether it was a compelling experience or just popular due to its feline protagonist. Into the depths Stray’s opening moments are peaceful. Waking up with your cat buddies, you run as a pack through an overgrown passage, taking their lead as you learn to navigate the environment on four feet. But tragedy strikes and the cat misses a jump, sliding into a pit where you’re unable to reach your pals. You limp through a door and enter a cyberpunk city full of neon and robots whose heads look like the old Apple error icon. From there, the rest of the game concerns your quest to find a way back to the fabled Outside. Right away, you’ll notice that this is a beautiful game. The cat animation is very well done, from general movement right down to the little ear twitches, and nearly every environment looks like it could be ripped straight from the concept art. While the plaudits will go to the neon-draped streets, I’m a particular fan of some of the robots’ living quarters, which are stacked high with books and 90s computing equipment. I hope BlueTwelve Studio will find the time to add a photo mode later, because the camera angles, the cat’s poses, and the on-screen prompts obstruct some fantastic frames.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/stray_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/stray_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Portal 2 (PC) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/22/portal-2-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portal 2 (PC) retrospective" /><published>2022-07-22T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-22T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/22/portal-2-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/22/portal-2-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;There was a time, way back in 2007, when Valve was a company that made video games, and released a little collection called &lt;em&gt;The Orange Box&lt;/em&gt;. Having already completed &lt;em&gt;Half-Life 2&lt;/em&gt; on PC by that point, I had the most fun with a new title tacked onto the end of the compendium named &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt;, which presented a unique blend of the first-person shooter and puzzle genres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; tasks the player with solving various challenges using a portal gun. This tool can fire two portals – orange and blue – which appear as large ovals on the walls. Walk through one and you’ll come out of the other, and the same holds true for various objects you’ll use to complete the levels. This innovative gameplay mechanic, plus some sarcastic, fourth wall-breaking dialogue, earnt &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; a place in many gamers’ hearts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Valve published &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt;, which made many of the era’s “best of” lists, but for one reason or another never joined my game library. Curious, I picked up a copy for the grand sum of £1.43 in a recent Steam sale, in the hope that it still stands up 11 years later. After an eight-hour playthrough of the sequel, I can say that &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; tries to do much more than the original, and while it is successful in some respects, in my view it fails in others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thinking-with-portals&quot;&gt;Thinking with portals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; begins with the player waking up in a room at Aperture Laboratories, and it doesn’t take long for its signature tone to show as we’re instructed to complete our mandatory time staring at a painting on the wall to feel “mentally reinvigorated”. With that complete, we go back to bed, but apparently we sleep for too long because when we wake the dormitory building is ruined and there’s someone pounding on the door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This turns out to be Wheatley, a hapless but well-intentioned floating eye robot voiced by Stephen Merchant. There’s a clever bit here where the game asks us to press A to speak, but that button just makes us jump, which Wheatley points out. Now we’ve familiarised ourselves with the controls and met our new companion, Wheatley rips our bedroom from the building and whisks us off to the main facility for some “emergency testing”.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the test lab, we start working with portals. As in the first &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; game, each puzzle is essentially a self-enclosed cell with an entry and an exit, beyond which there is a lift to reset everything and take us to the next level. Between the player and their escape can lie any combination of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•  &lt;strong&gt;Weighted cubes&lt;/strong&gt; - usually need to be placed on buttons&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Light-refracting cubes&lt;/strong&gt; - can be used to divert lasers to receptors&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Lasers&lt;/strong&gt; - deal damage, but activate devices when pointed the right way&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Turrets&lt;/strong&gt; - monitor for the player and kill them near-instantly on firing&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Gravity rays&lt;/strong&gt; - push and pull objects, including the player&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Various gels and gel dispensers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re getting ahead of ourselves a little here. The first puzzles are relatively simple – initially we’re only allowed to use portals provided to us, and then eventually we’re allowed to fire blue portals. This introductory section was obviously required to bring new players up to speed with the series’ mechanics, but it won’t be too challenging to anyone who played the first game. &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; wants to do more than this, however…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dude-wheres-my-cake&quot;&gt;Dude, where’s my cake?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valve had something of a problem coming into &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt;. The standout character of the original &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; was GLaDOS – the robotic, yet sassy host putting us through all these tests. But we killed her at the end of the game. So to ensure she could return and deliver more of the wisecracks we all love, they contrived a way for the clumsy Wheatley to accidentally flip all her switches, bringing her back to life. She takes us to the heart of the test centre, we get the orange portal gun, and the real fun begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GLaDOS says she wants to test with us forever, but she’s obviously still harbouring some resentment about the whole killing her thing. “Well done,” she says after another completed puzzle. “Here are the test results: You are a horrible person. We weren’t even testing for that.” Wheatley pops in from time to time, telling us he’s working on a way to break us out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, he sets us free through a hatch in the test chamber wall, and we’re dashing through the service passages of the testing facility past production lines manufacturing cubes and turrets, on the run from GLaDOS. It’s neat to use portals in a non-testing environment, although it does come with some difficulties, which I’ll discuss in more detail later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all very fast-paced, but this is where Wheatley started to grate on me a bit. I like Stephen Merchant, and have enjoyed some of his other work – especially his role as Ricky Gervais’s agent in &lt;em&gt;Extras&lt;/em&gt; – but Wheatley just does not stop providing irritating commentary on everything that we do, and it becomes especially annoying when he starts nagging you to get a move on when you’re trying to figure out what the game wants you to do to move to the next area. Admittedly there are some funny jokes in there, but compared to GLaDOS’s cold delivery it’s all a bit overdone and obnoxious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, GLaDOS captures us in a cell, but she uses some faulty turrets we and Wheatley produced, which break the glass. Wheatley shows up and we plug him in and transfer his consciousness into GLaDOS’s body to end her reign over the testing centre. But somewhat predictably, Wheatley is less keen to escape once he realises his newfound power. Instead, he condemns GLaDOS to life inside a potato battery and becomes evermore suspicious of us, eventually punting us both down to the pits of the facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-from-the-past&quot;&gt;Learning from the past&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is probably the best segment of the game in terms of both story and gameplay. We end up in a decrepit Aperture testing facility, which has a &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/bioshock&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-esque vibe with its decaying mid-century furnishings. The voice guiding us through this area is that of Cave Johnson, the founder of Aperture Science. Since he’s dead and can’t be there in person, we are played recordings he prepared for candidates as they reached each test chamber, which feels more akin to the dialogue in the original &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The puzzles are more challenging here, and while they do make use of old-fashioned versions of the modern testing equipment, the historic test centre also has its own tricks up its sleeve. These tricks, it turns out, come mostly in the form of the aforementioned gels and dispensers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•  &lt;strong&gt;Blue gel&lt;/strong&gt; – lets you bounce higher to reach new areas&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;Orange gel&lt;/strong&gt; – lets you sprint at super speed and build momentum&lt;br /&gt;
•  &lt;strong&gt;White gel&lt;/strong&gt; – moon rock-based (remember that), makes surfaces portalable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are used in conjunction with each other to create some great puzzles that really freshen up the formula. By the end of this segment you’ll be placing portals under dispensers to distribute gel where it’s needed before executing elaborate combinations of sprints, jumps, bounces, and portal shots to reach your destination. The most satisfying parts of &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; are those that make you feel super smart for thinking in more than three dimensions to solve a chamber, and these puzzles certainly deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We eventually find GLaDOS in her potato form and begin to make our way through the 70s-era areas, and then those from the 1980s. Along the way we’re met with the “startling” revelation (it’s actually signposted as much, if not more than, Wheatley’s turn to the dark side) that GLaDOS is actually the digitised form of Johnson’s personal assistant Caroline, who was put in charge of the facility when he died. GLaDOS has a vague recollection of this, which serves as her motivation to kill Wheatley and regain control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;taking-back-control&quot;&gt;Taking back control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forming an unlikely partnership, we fight our way to the surface to deal with Wheatley. We find that he’s already making his mark on the test centre, and has apparently been crossbreeding cubes and turrets to produce limping, non-functional offspring. When he learns of our presence he wants to test us, but his chambers are far too easy, so he steals GLaDOS’s designs. This is where the gravity beams come into play, again adding a challenging twist as we now need to try to direct objects – and ourselves – through the air. As the thrill of watching us test wears off, Wheatley grows slowly more insane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For once in a game with an unusual central mechanic, the final boss fight is actually very well done. Wheatley floats around in the middle of the arena and fires missiles at you, which you must send through portals at various angles to circumvent his shields and hit him. GLaDOS throws corrupted cores to you at various intervals, which you attach to Wheatley to gradually weaken him. Once enough of these are connected, we’re directed to press the same “stalemate button” we used to defeat GLaDOS earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the game’s final masterstroke. Wheatley has rigged the button to explode, which damages the testing centre and blows a hole in the roof. There it is, staring right at you: the moon. You remember that the white gel that made surfaces portalable was made of moon rocks, and take a chance. You fire a portal directly at the moon, and the vacuum of space tears Wheatley apart. It’s rare that a game’s final moments are my favourite, but this was a great callback and ups the stakes while so well while maintaining mechanical consistency that it may be the exception to the rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GLaDOS, now in control, pulls us back through the portal as Wheatley spirals off into space. Back on Earth, she decides that the least problematic option is just to let us go. We ascend to the surface past a bizarre choir of dancing turrets (I have no idea how that idea got any further than the brainstorming whiteboard) and step outside into the sunlight. The end credits are set to another song – this time sung by GLaDOS – about how happy she is to finally be rid of us, and we get a final scene of Wheatley drifting through space expressing his remorse before everything fades to black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;straying-from-the-formula&quot;&gt;Straying from the formula&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were parts of &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; I loved, and elements I didn’t see the need for at all. Despite its first-person perspective, Portal is a puzzle game, and it works best when it’s challenging the player to use the tools at their disposal to escape the cell the testing centre has built for them. There’s something immensely satisfying about the Checkoff’s gun-ness of it all – you know everything there must be used, but how? At the game’s strongest it follows an enhanced version of this format, and you’re forced to think not just in portals but also according to the effects of gels and gravity rays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in trying to make &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; bigger and better than its predecessor, Valve had to break it out of that bright white box. Beyond the testing chamber, it’s unclear what’s part of the puzzle and what’s just scenery. The most jarring moments were when the game seemed to be guiding me down a path, only for me to realise after much retreading that it was expecting me to have shot a portal at a tiny grey dot a mile away in the previous area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; is often brought up in “game of the generation” conversations, but honestly I prefer the far more concise and focused original. That said, there are still plenty of enjoyable puzzles in the various testing centres you explore over its eight-hour span, and even if Wheatley gets quite annoying early on, there is a lot of content that subverts the player’s expectations in amusing and surprising ways. If you didn’t play &lt;em&gt;Portal 2&lt;/em&gt; back in 2011 then by all means go back for a playthrough – just don’t expect the earth-shattering experience some talk it up to be, and don’t overlook the original.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="portal" /><category term="puzzle" /><summary type="html">There was a time, way back in 2007, when Valve was a company that made video games, and released a little collection called The Orange Box. Having already completed Half-Life 2 on PC by that point, I had the most fun with a new title tacked onto the end of the compendium named Portal, which presented a unique blend of the first-person shooter and puzzle genres. For the uninitiated, Portal tasks the player with solving various challenges using a portal gun. This tool can fire two portals – orange and blue – which appear as large ovals on the walls. Walk through one and you’ll come out of the other, and the same holds true for various objects you’ll use to complete the levels. This innovative gameplay mechanic, plus some sarcastic, fourth wall-breaking dialogue, earnt Portal a place in many gamers’ hearts. In 2011, Valve published Portal 2, which made many of the era’s “best of” lists, but for one reason or another never joined my game library. Curious, I picked up a copy for the grand sum of £1.43 in a recent Steam sale, in the hope that it still stands up 11 years later. After an eight-hour playthrough of the sequel, I can say that Portal 2 tries to do much more than the original, and while it is successful in some respects, in my view it fails in others. Thinking with portals Portal 2 begins with the player waking up in a room at Aperture Laboratories, and it doesn’t take long for its signature tone to show as we’re instructed to complete our mandatory time staring at a painting on the wall to feel “mentally reinvigorated”. With that complete, we go back to bed, but apparently we sleep for too long because when we wake the dormitory building is ruined and there’s someone pounding on the door. This turns out to be Wheatley, a hapless but well-intentioned floating eye robot voiced by Stephen Merchant. There’s a clever bit here where the game asks us to press A to speak, but that button just makes us jump, which Wheatley points out. Now we’ve familiarised ourselves with the controls and met our new companion, Wheatley rips our bedroom from the building and whisks us off to the main facility for some “emergency testing”.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/portal-2_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/15/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition review" /><published>2022-07-15T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-15T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/15/nvidia-3070-ti-founders-edition-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/15/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition-review">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been watching the price of Nvidia 30 series graphics cards for years with a view to upgrading from my modest but reliable &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/09/01/asus-geforce-dual-gtx1060-o6g-review/&quot;&gt;Asus GeForce Dual GTX 1060 O6G&lt;/a&gt;. With cryptocurrency prices crashing and hardware finally coming back into stock at reasonable(ish) prices, I finally pulled the trigger and made the outlay for a Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was giddy with excitement as I installed the new card inside my PC. I was no longer playing catch-up - here I was holding a glossy box containing a flagship component anyone would want to add to their rig. So did it fulfil my high-end gaming dreams? Well… Kind of. Read on to hear all about the hype, the perks, and the tribulations of 3070 Ti ownership…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unboxing-installation-and-troubleshooting&quot;&gt;Unboxing, installation, and troubleshooting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition came in a slick little package, as you’d expect from a premium product. The card was snugly nestled in foam inside a sturdy box, with a little cavity underneath for the quick start booklet and the special power adapter required to hook it up to your system. The set is incredibly photogenic, as you can see above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slid my 1060 out of the case and replaced it with the 3070 Ti with minimal fuss. I’d been a little wary of the fit, but it actually turned out to be slightly narrower than my previous card. This generation of cards demands a lot of power, and you must plug two cables from your power supply into Nvidia’s adapter, which connects to your card. A lesson from experience here - use two separate cables for this, not two connectors on the same wire.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While my old graphics card was essentially plug and play, the 3070 Ti turned out to be very fiddly to get working properly. Over the first day or two I was seeing poor performance in games and even the occasional unscheduled PC restart. Through trial, error, and a lot of Googling, I ended up making the following changes, which seem to have stabilised things somewhat:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•  Swapped to two separate power cables to the card&lt;br /&gt;
•  Reinstalled the drivers from scratch with Display Driver Uninstaller&lt;br /&gt;
•  Cut my minimum processor state to 10 percent in my power plan&lt;br /&gt;
•  Switched to a RAM Extreme Memory Profile (XMP) in the BIOS&lt;br /&gt;
•  Adjusted some Nvidia Control Panel settings for specific games&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d already upgraded to a 750W power supply ahead of time, but after spotting rising temperatures I also installed three more fans in my case to keep things cool. The 3070 Ti is working much better now, but I still don’t think it’s &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; at peak performance, and in the medium term I plan to install faster memory to eliminate any further bottlenecking by other components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gaming-performance&quot;&gt;Gaming performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With card installed and functional (kind of - some of the above took days’ worth of tinkering alongside some of the tests I’m about to describe), I did what any sane person would do: I loaded up some of my games and cranked all the settings up to the maximum to see what the 3070 Ti could do. For what it’s worth, all this is running on a monitor capable of 1440p at 75Hz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll start with &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; because it was by far the clunkiest game to configure. EA give you a grand total of five graphics settings to play around with (helpfully, this is only possible outside of the game menus), and it initially seemed like no matter what I did the game would stutter horribly or be plagued by screen tearing after installing the 3070 Ti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the point at which I switched to an XMP profile in my BIOS, before turning to the Nvidia Control Panel for some finetuning. Configuring the V-sync setting to Adaptive seemed to do the trick, and &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt; now runs smoothly, looking sharper than before and especially slick during close-ups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transitioning to the 3070 Ti with &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-1&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;F1 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was absolutely painless, and it’s one of the games with the most impressive graphical upgrades. Codemasters’ simcade racer is capable of ray tracing, which means you have a choice between silky smooth gameplay or losing a few frames for nicer shadows and reflections. I usually choose the former for top-end performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tag/call-of-duty&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Call of Duty: Warzone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was also easy to configure and required the least tinkering. I essentially just turned everything up to max settings - including ray tracing - and limited the frame rate to the 75 FPS that my monitor is capable of. The game runs flawlessly, and I’m looking forward to getting stuck in with some friends in the near future with the improved fidelity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s a slightly older game, I was impressed by the step up in &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/grand-theft-auto&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;GTA V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s performance when I ran it with the 3070 Ti under the hood. The extra power allowed me to turn on the game’s more elaborate visual effects and more detailed textures, and cruising around Los Santos - particularly against the orange and pink skies at dusk - has never looked better or smoother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I’ll give &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/cities-skylines&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a mention because I’ve been playing it again recently. Paradox’s city builder was released in 2015 and lacks the fancy graphical features and settings of some of the other games on this list, but the 3070 Ti does a good job of improving performance, sharpening some of the previously rough edges and providing a consistent frame rate, which sometimes creaked along a little bit in more built-up areas on my 1060.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I’d liken an upgrade to the Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition to an upgrade to a PlayStation 5 or &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/xbox&quot;&gt;Xbox Series X&lt;/a&gt; - you’ll see a noticable improvement to your gaming experience, but the difference won’t be black and white like the day you plugged in an Xbox 360 and saw games in HD for the first time. These days it’s all in the little details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would advise against the upgrade if you’re either not very technical or not prepared to commit the time and money needed to ensure the card can perform at its best. You won’t know for sure until you have the card up and running how many fiddly little settings you’ll need to tinker with or which other components might need an upgrade to keep up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you’re into your PC gaming and in this for the long run, the 3070 Ti does deliver on what it promises - at least after some configuration and troubleshooting. Nvidia’s flagship graphics card series has given my game collection a nice facelift, and I’m certainly looking forward to diving into some titles that were built for this generation of cards and their new features.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="hardware" /><category term="graphics-cards" /><summary type="html">I’ve been watching the price of Nvidia 30 series graphics cards for years with a view to upgrading from my modest but reliable Asus GeForce Dual GTX 1060 O6G. With cryptocurrency prices crashing and hardware finally coming back into stock at reasonable(ish) prices, I finally pulled the trigger and made the outlay for a Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition. I was giddy with excitement as I installed the new card inside my PC. I was no longer playing catch-up - here I was holding a glossy box containing a flagship component anyone would want to add to their rig. So did it fulfil my high-end gaming dreams? Well… Kind of. Read on to hear all about the hype, the perks, and the tribulations of 3070 Ti ownership… Unboxing, installation, and troubleshooting The Nvidia GeForce RTX 3070 Ti Founders Edition came in a slick little package, as you’d expect from a premium product. The card was snugly nestled in foam inside a sturdy box, with a little cavity underneath for the quick start booklet and the special power adapter required to hook it up to your system. The set is incredibly photogenic, as you can see above. I slid my 1060 out of the case and replaced it with the 3070 Ti with minimal fuss. I’d been a little wary of the fit, but it actually turned out to be slightly narrower than my previous card. This generation of cards demands a lot of power, and you must plug two cables from your power supply into Nvidia’s adapter, which connects to your card. A lesson from experience here - use two separate cables for this, not two connectors on the same wire.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nvidia-geforce-rtx-3070-ti-founders-edition_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cities: Skylines: A guide to schools, universities, and education</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/08/cities-skylines-education-guide" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cities&amp;#58; Skylines&amp;#58; A guide to schools, universities, and education" /><published>2022-07-08T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-08T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/08/cities-skylines-education-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/07/08/cities-skylines-education-guide">&lt;p&gt;Planning and managing a growing city in &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt; is a lot like building a house of cards. Every individual element is connected, and they must all progress in unison, maintaining a careful balance. Once one part falls away - perhaps through a power cut or a health crisis, for example - it is very easy for everything to fall apart. Your city is constantly on the edge of chaos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/cities-skylines-education_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently jumped back into the game after a years-long hiatus, having splurged on a Humble Bundle with many of the expansions, and the problem I was met with concerned my citizens’ education. I didn’t want a sprawling industrial complex in my city, but the fancy office buildings that were popping up were complaining they didn’t have enough educated workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My subsequent investigation into the &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt; education system led to the article that follows, which attempts to explain how it all fits together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;education-levels&quot;&gt;Education levels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt; uses four levels to describe citizens’ education: uneducated, educated, well educated, and highly educated. These correspond to the most advanced educational institution that each citizen has graduated from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Citizens who have completed no education are &lt;strong&gt;uneducated&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
• Citizens who have graduated from elementary school are &lt;strong&gt;educated&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
• Citizens who have graduated from high school are &lt;strong&gt;well educated&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
• Citizens who have graduated from university are &lt;strong&gt;highly educated&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to note that citizens must attend the relevant educational institution at the corresponding life stage - for example, a young adult who did not attend high school cannot then go to university. This means that as you develop your education system (which we’ll cover in a moment) it will take time for new youngsters to filter up through the ranks.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/cities-skylines-education_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check on your citizens’ current education levels in a few different ways. First, you can see education levels for residents of a particular building by clicking on it. Most usefully, however, you can view a summary of the entire city’s education levels by clicking on the education icon on the toolbar and reviewing the pie chart in the pane that appears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-do-we-need-educated-citizens&quot;&gt;Why do we need educated citizens?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: Educating your citizens will help your city develop. This manifests in several different but interconnected ways across all three main zoning types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the simplest level, certain education standards are required for certain jobs. If you click a commercial or industrial building, you’ll see a summary of the jobs offered by level. If you don’t have enough educated workers, jobs at the higher end will go unfilled, either limiting that employer’s growth or - in the worst case scenario - even causing the business to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/cities-skylines-education_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But educated residents don’t just improve their workplaces - they also give their homes a boost. Residential blocks are more likely to level up when the people who live inside are better educated, assuming you’ve also put the work in to raise the land value far enough to make it possible. Interestingly, there’s also an in-game tip that says educated citizens produce less rubbish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-educate-citizens&quot;&gt;How to educate citizens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might expect, if you want to accelerate your citizens’ education then the first step is ensuring that the right schools and universities are available to them. &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt; has a US-style education system and you’ll want to build from the bottom up, making slow but steady progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;strong&gt;elementary school&lt;/strong&gt; is the first stop for your young citizens. Then you’ll want to make sure they can secure a place at a &lt;strong&gt;high school&lt;/strong&gt; (or &lt;strong&gt;institute of creative arts&lt;/strong&gt;). Finally, well educated young adults can go to &lt;strong&gt;university&lt;/strong&gt; (or a &lt;strong&gt;community college&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;modern technology institute&lt;/strong&gt;) to take the final step and become highly educated model citizens ready for office jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/cities-skylines-education_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first consideration when building this infrastructure is quantity. The tabs on the Education pane show the availablility of places at each institution, and you’ll want to make sure that their capacity is well clear of the number of eligible students to ensure that everybody who wants to can attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accessibility is just as important. When you’re placing a building, the nearby roads will turn green to show which residences can easily attend, but you should also provide schools and universities with strong public transport links to enable citizens from further afield to make their way in, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;extra-encouragement&quot;&gt;Extra encouragement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you put the above plan into action, you’ll see your citizens’ education levels increase dramatically over the next few generations, but there are also a few more changes you can make to give things a little extra push.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the &lt;strong&gt;public library&lt;/strong&gt; is an anomaly when it comes to educational buildings. Libraries mostly provide entertainment, but they do provide a very small educational boost for citizens, particularly at the lower end of the education hierarchy - just don’t expect overwhelming results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final weapons in your arsenal are education-related policies, which can be applied to either your entire city or to individual areas as required. &lt;strong&gt;Education Boost&lt;/strong&gt; is your best friend here, providing a 25 percent budget increase and making citizens more likely to choose education over work. &lt;strong&gt;Educational Blimps&lt;/strong&gt; is another winner, providing a small boost at no cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, you should avoid some of the other policies. In particular, &lt;strong&gt;School’s Out&lt;/strong&gt; will push citizens into work over university, and &lt;strong&gt;For-Profit Education&lt;/strong&gt; will force them to pay to learn, to the exclusion of less well-off residents. So make sure these aren’t checked to avoid putting extra hurdles in the way of your citizens’ quest for knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="cities-skylines" /><category term="management" /><summary type="html">Planning and managing a growing city in Cities: Skylines is a lot like building a house of cards. Every individual element is connected, and they must all progress in unison, maintaining a careful balance. Once one part falls away - perhaps through a power cut or a health crisis, for example - it is very easy for everything to fall apart. Your city is constantly on the edge of chaos. I recently jumped back into the game after a years-long hiatus, having splurged on a Humble Bundle with many of the expansions, and the problem I was met with concerned my citizens’ education. I didn’t want a sprawling industrial complex in my city, but the fancy office buildings that were popping up were complaining they didn’t have enough educated workers. My subsequent investigation into the Cities: Skylines education system led to the article that follows, which attempts to explain how it all fits together. Education levels Cities: Skylines uses four levels to describe citizens’ education: uneducated, educated, well educated, and highly educated. These correspond to the most advanced educational institution that each citizen has graduated from. • Citizens who have completed no education are uneducated. • Citizens who have graduated from elementary school are educated. • Citizens who have graduated from high school are well educated. • Citizens who have graduated from university are highly educated. It’s important to note that citizens must attend the relevant educational institution at the corresponding life stage - for example, a young adult who did not attend high school cannot then go to university. This means that as you develop your education system (which we’ll cover in a moment) it will take time for new youngsters to filter up through the ranks.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/cities-skylines-education_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/07/cities-skylines-education_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>