<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-19T18:01:31+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Strat Packer’s blog</title><subtitle>Creative and intellectual output beyond the realm of my day job</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Sanitised F1 75 launch event was saved by its edgy host Jack Whitehall</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/19/f1-75-event-jack-whitehall" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sanitised F1 75 launch event was saved by its edgy host Jack Whitehall" /><published>2025-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/19/f1-75-launch-jack-whitehall</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="formula-1" /><category term="motorsport" /><summary type="html">You can almost imagine the planning meetings at Formula 1 headquarters ahead of the sport’s first live season launch event, held at the O2 Arena in London last night. What would appeal most to broadest possible demographic of new, young fans? Smiling drivers and team principals. “Inspirational” brand videos from each team. And live music. Young people still like Take That, right? Formula 1 used to have a raw feel to it. What made the great races and championships of the last 74 years wasn’t flashy on-screen graphics or feeling like you were on first-name terms with the drivers - it was how much motorsport from top to bottom felt like a big club of geeks tweaking designs and setups, speculating on strategy, and enjoying the thrill of the on-track action. Since then - and especially since Liberty Media’s acquisition of F1 in 2017 - that feeling has become a lot more corporate and… well, boring. Drive to Survive has turned the paddock into a reality show, and drivers have become increasingly censored to protect sponsorships - see the FIA’s recent ban on swearing. In short, old F1 was about both spectacle and substance, but in an attempt to capture a wider and younger audience, the balance has been pushed much more towards the former - even to the extent of producing artificial spectacle when on-track action is not enough. If it’s not TikTok-friendly, it’s out. I was skeptical when F1 75 was announced. Heading into the sport’s 75th season, a two-hour live event would be held to unveil all ten teams’ liveries (not cars, liveries). It felt a lot more dinner suits and Instagram snaps than oil fumes and telemetry print-outs, and many long-time fans questioned what the point was.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/f1-75-event-jack-whitehall_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/f1-75-event-jack-whitehall_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Avowed has some interesting features</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/17/avowed-release" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Avowed has some interesting features" /><published>2025-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/17/avowed-release</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="rpgs" /><summary type="html">🐻 Avowed has me conflicted. The main story sounds like a chore and I prefer immersive sim RPGs to its more static world, but I really enjoyed this week’s episode of The Besties, which covered some of the more innovative features Obsidian has brought to the table. These include speech checks more involved than “is X greater than Y”, and graceful, immersive dialogue when the player stumbles upon quest locations earlier than planned.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sega and Sports Interactive were right to cancel Football Manager 25</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/11/football-manager-25-cancelled" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sega and Sports Interactive were right to cancel Football Manager 25" /><published>2025-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/11/football-manager-25-cancelled</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="industry" /><category term="football-manager" /><summary type="html">If you read this blog regularly, you’ll likely agree that the games industry in 2025 is a Wild West of anti-consumer practices. Developers and publishers seem set on milking as much money from customers as possible, regardless of the damage done to beloved series or the reputations of the companies themselves. One unfortunate habit studios have developed is to release horribly broken games. Even if a title is obviously unfit for public consumption, they prefer to rake in gamers’ hard-earned cash now and worry about fixing the mess in later patches. Think Cyberpunk 2077, Star Wars Outlaws, or Cities: Skylines 2. Therefore the easy option would have been for Sega and Sports Interactive to sand off Football Manager 25’s rough edges and release it, and we should praise them for cancelling this year’s edition in favour of maintaining the series’ quality.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/football-manager-25_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/football-manager-25_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The government won’t protect your access to live service games</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/06/uk-government-live-service-petition" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The government won't protect your access to live service games" /><published>2025-02-06T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/06/uk-government-live-service-petition</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="industry" /><category term="gran-turismo" /><summary type="html">An attempt to protect gamers against publishers’ abrupt shuttering - or “sunsetting” - of live service games failed this week, after the government stated that there are “no plans to amend UK consumer law on disabling video games”. A petition that had passed the 10,000-signature threshold for parliamentary discussion was put in front of the government, but the Department for Culture, Media, and Sport said that while it recognises gamers’ concerns, it would not be changing existing laws surrounding digital obsolescence any time soon.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uk-government-live-service-petition_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uk-government-live-service-petition_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kingdom Come: Deliverance 2 looks fantastic</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/06/kingdom-come-deliverance-2-release" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kingdom Come&amp;#58; Deliverance 2 looks fantastic" /><published>2025-02-06T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/06/kingdom-come-deliverance-2-release</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="rpgs" /><summary type="html">⚔️ Kingdom Come: Deliverance 2 looks fantastic. Having watched some of the gameplay circulating online, it strikes me as what I thought a Bethesda RPG might look like by 2025 back when I was playing Oblivion. I don’t know when I’ll next have the time to put aside for such a sprawling adventure, but it’s certainly earned a place on my backlog for when I do.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Once Upon a Time in Hollywood: Tarantino’s novel kills the mystery</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/01/once-upon-a-time-in-hollywood-novel-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Once Upon a Time in Hollywood&amp;#58; Tarantino's novel kills the mystery" /><published>2025-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/02/01/once-upon-a-time-in-hollywood-novel-review</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">As the first Quentin Tarantino film I saw at the cinema, I have a something of a soft spot for Once Upon a Time in Hollywood (2019). While I wasn’t as keen on the typically violent ending, the picture the director painted of 1960s Los Angeles was captivating, perfectly complemented by the period soundtrack and Leonardo DiCaprio and Brad Pitt’s performances as an actor and his stunt double navigating the unforgiving world of Hollywood after the peak of their careers. How does a story so entwined with certain visuals and music translate to the written word - especially when said novelisation is the author’s debut? We found out in 2021, when Tarantino published a 400-page reworking he described as “a complete rethinking of the entire story”. While it’s not terrible, I will say that I’m glad he gave us the film first, because the novel is not half as enthralling.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/once-upon-a-time-in-hollywood-novel_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/once-upon-a-time-in-hollywood-novel_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Forza Horizon 5 is coming to PlayStation 5</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/31/forza-horizon-5-playstation-5" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Forza Horizon 5 is coming to PlayStation 5" /><published>2025-01-31T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/31/forza-horizon-5-ps5</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="forza" /><category term="racing" /><category term="industry" /><summary type="html">🏁 Forza Horizon 5 is coming to PlayStation 5 this spring. Another Xbox crown jewel landing on Sony’s console raises some interesting questions about the future of the games industry. If all the studios Microsoft bought are too costly to run on Xbox sales alone and their games must be released more widely, what reason will be left to buy an Xbox to begin with?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GTA VI might get away with a $100 price tag, but your game can’t</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/24/gta-vi-price-100-dollars" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTA VI might get away with a $100 price tag, but your game can't" /><published>2025-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/24/gta-vi-100-dollar-price</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="industry" /><category term="grand-theft-auto" /><summary type="html">After a decade-long wait and with development costs reportedly stretching into the billions, it has long been rumoured that Rockstar might try to crank up the price of Grand Theft Auto VI when it launches. The standard price for games has already increased from £50 to £60 in recent years, and it has been speculated that GTA VI’s RRP could skyrocket all the way up to $100 (approximately £80). That would already be a punch in the gut for gamers reeling from the rising cost of living and a faltering job market, but it’s one they might be able to stomach for GTA VI in particular. Rockstar has a track record for producing high-quality titles, with GTA V (2013) and Red Dead Redemption 2 (2018) both receiving widespread acclaim. Many players are still exploring their sprawling worlds to this day.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/gta_vi_100_dollars_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/gta_vi_100_dollars_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Assassin’s Creed Shadows has been delayed again</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/10/assassins-creed-shadows-delayed" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assassin's Creed Shadows has been delayed again" /><published>2025-01-10T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/10/assassins-creed-shadows-delayed</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="assassins-creed" /><summary type="html">🏯 Assassin’s Creed Shadows has been delayed again. The release date for Ubisoft’s controversial title has dropped to 20th March to allow extra time for polish. To appease fans, the developer released a video showing off the game’s parkour. However, the environments steal the show for me. I have little confidence in its story or gameplay, but I might well be tempted to explore the world once Shadows is fully patched and heavily discounted.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Pathless Path: A call to action to escape your desk job</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/07/the-pathless-path-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Pathless Path&amp;#58; A call to action to escape your desk job" /><published>2025-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog/2025/01/07/the-pathless-path-review</id><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="business" /><category term="career" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">In The Pathless Path, Paul Millerd makes the case that life should be about more than work, and that people should invest more time and effort in finding their true calling - one that is more engaging and fulfilling than the daily grind. A rough representation of the daydream The Pathless Path inspired for me When Millerd’s own corporate consulting career was disrupted by health issues, he gained a new outlook on life. He left New York and spent time in Asia, first working freelance consulting gigs before developing online training courses and writing more. He found himself in a far happier place as a result. He argues that too many people unquestioningly follow a default path, where regular raises and promotions make it easy to continue in an unfulfilling career and switch off the voice questioning your happiness. With sufficient coping strategies, Millerd says people can tolerate consistent misery almost indefinitely. But if not that, then what else? The Pathless Path prompts readers to discover what they would be if they weren’t simply workers. By identifying what you enjoy doing, you can work backwards to build a life around that - ideally one that leaves you happier and better serves the people and communities around you. It’s inspiring stuff. I often daydream about a future where I manage to make a living from a software as a service project, this blog, or some other creative endeavour. I have no doubt that I’d wake up with greater motivation each day if granted that kind of agency and freedom to focus on what interests me. Millerd would argue that freedom is already there, but few actually recognise or take advantage of it. However, The Pathless Path almost overlooks the biggest factor that chains most people to their desks for 40 hours per week - money. When the author left his corporate job, he managed to find income through freelance consulting and moved to Taiwan, where the cost of living is lower. He does mention that those on the pathless path must learn to view money differently, but his biggest obstacle through the book seems to be a fear of making a fool of himself, rather than dread of ending up completely broke. I have a family to support and a mortgage to pay, and if I left my traditional career, I’m not confident I’d be able to find enough customers to avoid whittling my savings down to nothing and being forced to return to the rat race. Of course, I might be surprised if I ever did try it, but it feels as though holding a tolerable nine-to-five job is a necessary sacrifice to ensure long-term stability. Therefore, The Pathless Path was more of an escapist read - something philosophically interesting that I’d be keen to try if the mortgage was paid off, I somehow came across a large sum of money, or a side project gained some momentum, but that didn’t provide a practical path from A to B for me. 3/5</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/the-pathless-path_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/the-pathless-path_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>