<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-04-01T09:34:21+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Stellar Blade is a challenging and stylistic gaming nostalgia trip</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2024/04/01/stellar-blade-demo-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stellar Blade is a challenging and stylistic gaming nostalgia trip" /><published>2024-04-01T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-01T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2024/04/01/stellar-blade-demo-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2024/04/01/stellar-blade-demo-review">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Stellar Blade&lt;/em&gt; demo is here! There are many adjectives that could be applied to Level Up’s much-discussed PlayStation 5 exclusive - beautiful, unique, gruesome, and challenging, to name a few - but for me, more than anything else, the upcoming action-adventure title is a nostalgia trip to previous eras of gaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/stellar-blade_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the early 2000s, when I was a child, I didn’t have much of my own money for games. My purchases were gated by my parents, who knew nearly nothing about what was worth paying for, and my only gauge of quality was a review in the odd gaming magazine. Subsequently, box art and blurbs came into play, and there were some real wildcards in my collection that I asked for purely on a whim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes this paid off - games like &lt;em&gt;Operation: WinBack&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;King of Bowling 2&lt;/em&gt; were off the beaten path, hardly classics, but a lot of fun with friends. It was this blind experimentation that also led me to more praised games that I just hadn’t heard of through friends, like &lt;em&gt;Smuggler’s Run&lt;/em&gt; and early &lt;em&gt;Final Fantasy&lt;/em&gt; entries. Of course, other times I happened across the occasional stinker, but these were few and far between, and the sunk cost meant I stuck with most of my purchases anyway.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The upcoming PS5 game &lt;em&gt;Stellar Blade&lt;/em&gt; reminds me very much of that time and that category of game. It sits outside of the genres I usually play, comes from an until-now almost unknown studio, and with so much of the discussion surrounding its release focusing on its main character’s looks, there’s little information out there to help to determine its quality. The mystery surrounding the game stirred my intrigue when a demo was released going into the Easter bank holiday weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-very-different-challenge&quot;&gt;A very different challenge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Stellar Blade&lt;/em&gt; demo lasted maybe two hours, and I played it across three sessions over a couple of days. I’m an outsider to this particular subset of action adventure game, so a fair amount of dying and retrying probably padded out my playtime, but my point is that despite the challenge I kept coming back. I even woke up on Sunday thinking about booting it up, which is rare for a game these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game’s structure added to my nostalgia trip. &lt;em&gt;Stellar Blade&lt;/em&gt; is decidedly linear. You follow a path and beat the enemies to proceed. If you can’t beat a boss, you take a break and you come back later. Beyond an introduction to each skill you learn, there’s no handholding when it comes to strategy, and there’s no open world offering something easier to distract you. If you spend £70 on this game when it comes out on 26th April, there’s a chance you could be stuck at a single point for weeks until you figure out the patterns and - as the kids say - &lt;em&gt;get good&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/stellar-blade_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all that potential frustration just increases the payoff when you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; work it out, and that satisfaction comes in a beautiful package. Sure, Eve’s own model-scanned beauty has been much publicised, but the world also looks great, the monsters have a level of gruesome detail I could only dream of in past generations, and gameplay is underscored by an extensive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q3ZakaCqhe0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;original soundtrack&lt;/a&gt; (reportedly featuring &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pushsquare.com/news/2024/02/interview-shift-up-on-ps5s-highly-promising-stellar-blade&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;100 songs&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, &lt;em&gt;Stellar Blade&lt;/em&gt;’s demo gives an impression of a game crafted with a great deal of care and attention to detail. The aim here is obviously to create a very polished end product, with a fine-tuned difficulty presenting a significant challenge, but also a memorable experience consisting of a combination of visuals, audio, and gameplay unlike almost any other game being released at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-tuning-required&quot;&gt;Some tuning required&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there’s plenty to praise, there are a few rough edges here and there that could be tweaked prior to &lt;em&gt;Stellar Blade&lt;/em&gt;’s full release later this month, which is to be expected given that it is by far developer Shift Up’s biggest project to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, world traversal can sometimes feel a little clunky. Running around is just fine (and I dread to think how long it took to have Eve’s hair flow so naturally), but some of the more platform-like sections require a precision that doesn’t feel possible with the current controls. I don’t think I ever actually died to a misaligned jump, but I always felt like I was right on the edge of doing so, and maybe I got lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/stellar-blade_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of my other quibbles revolve around the defensive side of combat, and being an occasional dabbler in the genre, this may well come down to skill. Blocks and dodges in particular feel inconsistent. Sometimes they’ll be deemed “perfect” and you’ll avoid damage, while other times they’ll fail despite very similar input and timing, or Eve will take such a small sidestep that you don’t avoid the damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest source of frustration for me was healing. During combat, you can heal by drinking a potion. However, this cannot be done while Eve is mid-animation. If an enemy chains its attacks, you can sometimes go from a significant amount of health to almost nothing, and die while spamming up on the D-pad to no effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s worth noting - especially in the spirit of the type of game that &lt;em&gt;Stellar Blade&lt;/em&gt; evokes memories of - that as I acclimatised to the game these quirks became part of the challenge. I learnt to work with and around them, rather than fight them, as I battled my way through the demo. Perhaps they just come with the territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-footnote-on-playable-demos&quot;&gt;A footnote on playable demos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we’re down the gaming nostalgia rabbit hole, I feel a quick note on playable demos is warranted. In the PS1 and PS2 eras, distribution limitations meant that these were only available on magazine discs, but once Xbox Live (and broadband connections) became mainstream in the Xbox 360 generation, a good portion of releases allowed players to download a short trial to try them out before buying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the beauty of the downloadable playable demo is that I can sample a game that I would never usually play, at zero risk to my wallet. Would I have bought &lt;em&gt;Stellar Blade&lt;/em&gt; without playing it beforehand? Not likely, and if I did, it would probably have been years down the line and at a heavy discount. But now that I’ve played it, enjoyed it, and confirmed its quality, I’m tempted to buy it at or near release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, downloadable demos all but dried up during the lifespan of the PS4 and Xbox One. Not to get too conspiratorial, but this also coincided with an increasing number of bland and broken AAA games. If you’re a developer with a solid product and nothing to hide, I think there are big rewards to be gained from putting a snippet out there early for the public to get their teeth into before investing further.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="stellar-blade" /><category term="industry" /><summary type="html">The Stellar Blade demo is here! There are many adjectives that could be applied to Level Up’s much-discussed PlayStation 5 exclusive - beautiful, unique, gruesome, and challenging, to name a few - but for me, more than anything else, the upcoming action-adventure title is a nostalgia trip to previous eras of gaming. Back in the early 2000s, when I was a child, I didn’t have much of my own money for games. My purchases were gated by my parents, who knew nearly nothing about what was worth paying for, and my only gauge of quality was a review in the odd gaming magazine. Subsequently, box art and blurbs came into play, and there were some real wildcards in my collection that I asked for purely on a whim. Sometimes this paid off - games like Operation: WinBack and King of Bowling 2 were off the beaten path, hardly classics, but a lot of fun with friends. It was this blind experimentation that also led me to more praised games that I just hadn’t heard of through friends, like Smuggler’s Run and early Final Fantasy entries. Of course, other times I happened across the occasional stinker, but these were few and far between, and the sunk cost meant I stuck with most of my purchases anyway.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2024/04/stellar-blade_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2024/04/stellar-blade_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Apple Watch Series 8 review: You’ll get it when you get one</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2024/03/10/apple-watch-series-8-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apple Watch Series 8 review&amp;#58; You'll get it when you get one" /><published>2024-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2024/03/10/apple-watch-series-8-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2024/03/10/apple-watch-series-8-review">&lt;p&gt;I can’t remember a technology product I’ve been so undecided on for so long as the Apple Watch. Since the first generation launched in 2015, I’ve watched Apple’s iteration from afar, always unsure as to whether a smartwatch could ever provide enough benefit to warrant a price tag of at least a few hundred pounds. A lot of it came down to a question of intrusion - if I’ve been working to &lt;em&gt;reduce&lt;/em&gt; the number of notifications interrupting my life, why would I want them strapped to my wrist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/apple-watch_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with certain changes approaching in my life that will put strain on my time management, I decided to give the Apple Watch a go to reduce the number of times I need to pick up my phone, while implementing measures to limit distractions. First, I would keep the number of notifications pushed to the watch to a minimum, and second, I would make much better use of Siri and the Shortcuts app to make it easier to retrieve the information I need most often without opening any apps.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ordering-unboxing-and-setup&quot;&gt;Ordering, unboxing, and setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that I was planning on using the watch as little as possible, it didn’t make sense to go for a top-of-the-line model, and I was leaning towards the (relatively) affordable Apple Watch SE. However, battery life was a key concern, and the SE doesn’t support Apple’s fast charging technology, so in the end I settled on a refurbished Series 8 (GPS), purchased directly from the manufacturer for £299.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The packaging was slick, as you’d expect from an Apple product, but not &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; as straightforward as an iPhone package. Because watches and straps can be bought separately, they come in individual packs within an outer sleeve, and somehow I opened nearly every box upside down. But that’s hardly the end of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Apple Watch hardware has a solid build quality. The strap slots into the body of the watch with a nice click, and I like that the fastening pushes excess length underneath the strap, rather than relying on another fragile loop to hold it in place. The screen is very clear - on a par with the iPhone - and my only small frustration from a hardware perspective is that the curved edges can sometimes make it a little difficult to hit corner icons (and at other times, leads to unintended taps).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial setup process is relatively seamless, with a wizard to guide you through connecting the watch to your iPhone, setting your initial activity targets, installing available watch apps to match those on your phone, and so on. Within ten minutes of opening the box, the Apple Watch was fully synced and up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;user-interface-and-notifications&quot;&gt;User interface and notifications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial time with the Apple Watch was spent learning how to navigate its menus and apps, which is achieved through a combination of the touchscreen and the crown, which rotates with a nice weight. Less straightforward was working out where Apple draws the line between the watch and the iPhone - in particular, it’s not always clear whether the setting you need will be on the device itself or on the phone app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your watch face, which is the default display on the watch, is one of those items that must be configured from your iPhone. You can choose from a series of faces, which dictate the layout of the time and various other elements. Then you can add what Apple calls Complications - essentially small widgets from apps that allow you to show information like the temperature, the likelihood of rain, the time in another location, or the battery status, around the edges of the main face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/apple-watch_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also some aspects of notifications and applications themselves that aren’t initially obvious. For example, if an app is iPhone-only and you choose to mirror notifications to your watch, it will only trigger a haptic notification if sounds are turned on for your phone notifications. That side of things can seem like a bit of a mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another common question is whether an app requires an iPhone app, a watch app, or both. The clearest example is WhatsApp (iPhone only). You can push notifications to the watch and send replies, but Siri on the watch can’t send new messages to contacts. When I asked Siri to play a podcast using Overcast from my watch, it downloaded an entire watch-specific app rather than just hitting play on my iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Syncing data - for example, Apple Health metrics and Nike Run Club activity - can also sometimes take some convincing. It &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; still happen reliably, but there can be delays, so it’s best to think of the Apple Watch as the live view and your phone as the historical database. That said, some of these issues may have been linked to interference from my old smartwatch, and I’ve had better luck since removing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;apps-shortcuts-and-conveniences&quot;&gt;Apps, Shortcuts, and conveniences&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing message notifications just by raising my wrist is a huge timesaver. There are various settings to configure here, but if like me you’re concerned with the privacy implications of message previews flashing up on your watch, the workaround is for the notification to first show the sender/app’s name and photo/icon, and then to display the full text when you tap to confirm that you’re in a good spot to read it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned, I’ve also been experimenting with Shortcuts for things I’d usually pick up my phone for. For example, I can now tell Siri to show me upcoming Premier League games on TV and get that information automatically in a few seconds, rather than searching Google and dodging adverts to find it myself on the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/apple-watch_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big selling point for the Apple Watch is its health features, which provide some interesting metrics (even if they are of dubious utility). My most-used apps are Sleep - which both blocks out notifications during sleeping hours and tracks the quality of your rest - and Heart Rate, which provides a decent barometer of your circulatory health and shows how your body responds to exercise and stressful situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/running&quot;&gt;an avid runner&lt;/a&gt;, the most transformative Apple Watch app for me has been Nike Run Club. The watch version works completely independently, meaning I can go out and run without my phone bouncing around in my pocket, and see my current distance, time, and pace with a flick of my wrist, rather than fumbling around with sweaty hands to unlock my phone. It also gives your wrist a buzz every time you complete a kilometre, so you might not even need to check at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;apple-pay-and-security&quot;&gt;Apple Pay and security&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my most frequent reasons for taking my phone out was to use Apple Pay, and being able to check out at a shop or enter a Tube station just by tapping the watch is a game changer, even if it sometimes feels a bit awkward (either because it feels like you’re showing off your watch, or because of the flexible positions you’ll need to adopt to make contact with some readers - especially as a left-hander).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to note here is that the watch does have to be &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; close to the sensor for the payment to go through. This isn’t an obstruction to payment, but I’m unable to say at this point what the long-term effects of all those taps will be on the screen, and wouldn’t be surprised to see some scratches creep in over time if its toughness is akin to the screen on the iPhone. You &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; hover the watch just over the reader to avoid physical contact, but that requires more precision than I can usually manage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/apple-watch_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A question I always had about Apple Pay on the watch was over security. If I added cards to a device with neither Touch ID nor Face ID, how could they be usable to me but not to thieves? If somebody mugged me for the Apple Watch, what was there to stop them going on an unauthenticated spending spree using my Apple Pay cards?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Apple Watch, Apple Pay is triggered with a double tap of the side button. Apple’s rather ingenious answer to the security question is a feature called Wrist Detection, which automatically senses when the watch is taken off your wrist and locks it with a passcode. This can be a little annoying when you want to use the watch while it’s charging, but it provides peace of mind when it comes to Apple Pay and theft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;battery-life-and-charging&quot;&gt;Battery life and charging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew before buying an Apple Watch that the battery life would make or break it. Apple estimates that the Series 8 lasts up to 18 hours, which is touch and go for those who want to track their sleep and therefore can’t leave it on charge all night. With that in mind, I immediately turned off some features like the always-on screen in an attempt to make the watch workable with quick, occasional charging sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I’ve been pleasantly surprised. The battery life I’ve seen has been better than Apple’s estimates, and if I charge the watch to almost 100 percent at 9am before I start work, it’s not uncommon for it to be at about 70 percent by the early evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; need to charge the Apple Watch every day, but the battery capacity will not be an issue for the vast majority of users. You’d have to use it constantly not to get a solid day out of it (I could probably stretch it to two if I really needed to), and the main challenge is timing some quick charges to avoid missing sleep or exercise tracking. My solution is to charge when I’m showering or getting ready for bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This schedule is made possible by the fast charging feature, and I’m grateful that I clocked this before buying and chose the Series 8 over the SE. From five percent, the Apple Watch approaches a full charge in around 45 minutes, with the last 15 or 20 percent taking a little longer, but still only around an hour in total. Note that in modern Apple fashion, the Apple Watch comes with a charging cable but &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a plug adapter, so if you want to plug it into a wall you’ll need to buy a USB-C adapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could I live without an Apple Watch? Yes. Would I go out and buy another one tomorrow if I lost my current one today? Also yes. While not an essential purchase, wearing an Apple Watch has made my most-accessed information available in a quick and largely hands-free way, and while I won’t be ditching my iPhone any time soon, it has drastically reduced the number of times I pick up it up every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, Apple had smart answers to all of my initial questions and concerns. I can hide the content of notifications so I don’t accidentally expose anything, Apple Pay gets locked behind a PIN if my watch falls into somebody else’s hands, and the battery lasts more than long enough for it to make it through a typical day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The user experience isn’t &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; as slick as I’ve come to expect from Apple, and this primarily stems from unclear boundaries between what can be achieved on the watch, and what requires the more in-depth apps on the iPhone. However, while it’s not the most obvious out of the box, you do eventually get a feel for it, and you normally only need these options during setup and configuration anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Apple Watch Series 8 is a solid product and a big step up from my previous smartwatch. There are some minor frustrations, but these are all software-based and may be improved upon in future updates. Most importantly, the watch performs in both the health tracking and productivity arenas, with almost everything wrapped up in the clear and glossy interfaces that long-time Apple users will be familiar with. While the value isn’t immediately obvious, you’ll get it when you get one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;4/5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="reviews" /><category term="apple" /><category term="wearables" /><category term="running" /><summary type="html">I can’t remember a technology product I’ve been so undecided on for so long as the Apple Watch. Since the first generation launched in 2015, I’ve watched Apple’s iteration from afar, always unsure as to whether a smartwatch could ever provide enough benefit to warrant a price tag of at least a few hundred pounds. A lot of it came down to a question of intrusion - if I’ve been working to reduce the number of notifications interrupting my life, why would I want them strapped to my wrist? But with certain changes approaching in my life that will put strain on my time management, I decided to give the Apple Watch a go to reduce the number of times I need to pick up my phone, while implementing measures to limit distractions. First, I would keep the number of notifications pushed to the watch to a minimum, and second, I would make much better use of Siri and the Shortcuts app to make it easier to retrieve the information I need most often without opening any apps.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2024/03/apple-watch_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2024/03/apple-watch_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Sims (PC) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2024/02/11/the-sims-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sims (PC) retrospective" /><published>2024-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2024/02/11/the-sims-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2024/02/11/the-sims-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;If you think of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/the-sims&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; today, you’ll likely think of the EA money printing machine and its endless conveyor belt of expansion and stuff packs. The modern games have a cutesy, sanitised face, and the bright marketing material reflects their apparent positioning as a platform for teenage girls to build their dream homes and lifestyles, rather than a semi-accurate and challenging simulation of life’s ups and downs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That wasn’t always the case. When the original game was released in 2000, it did contain some humour (especially through Maxis’s renowned flavour text) but the game itself was an attempt to explore social and architectural themes through the most realistic recreation of life possible with the technology of the time – and as a result of its limitations, one that often strays into unsettling territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;366&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/EMvzbbuVA2c?si=_Mx6L8_kJ9xefy-R&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-virtual-doll-house&quot;&gt;A virtual doll house&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a time before video games were such big business. &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; would certainly contribute to the industry’s growth and transformation into the corporate nightmare we know today (it eventually sold more than 11 million copies, without even considering the sequels), but at the time the game was conceived in the 1990s it wasn’t unusual for a game to be based entirely around a single designer with an interesting idea and a vision of how it might be fun for players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, that visionary was &lt;em&gt;SimCity&lt;/em&gt; designer Will Wright. After losing his house to the 1991 Oakland firestorm, Wright began to ponder whether the process of rebuilding his home and life might in fact be a suitable basis for a game. To begin with, his concept focused on the architecture and furnishings, but it eventually evolved into the idea of a virtual doll house filled with simulated people, appraising the value and attractiveness of their surroundings and living out their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/the-sims_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Build and Buy Mode retained these original tools, but Wright realised that controlling the Sims themselves and playing through their relationships and careers made for a more entertaining game. Even then, his company wasn’t sold on the idea. While Wright thought the concept was of natural interest (“people are fascinated with people”), Maxis didn’t think players would want to simulate household chores when video games could let them do far more exciting things they could only dream of. &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; was even given the internal nickname “the toilet game”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, while Wright’s vision did come to fruition following EA’s acquisition of the studio, and &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; and its sequels would sell millions of copies and expansion packs, it’s worth remembering that original game wasn’t developed with sales optimisation in mind. This was a case of one man pursuing a concept that felt interesting to him. The game’s manual even featured a recommended reading list, detailing books on architecture, design, and planning that its creators had studied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fed-watered-and-romanced&quot;&gt;Fed, watered, and romanced&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the most basic of tutorials, &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; is easy to pick up. Fundamentally, the game revolves around keeping Sims happy by topping up eight meters representing their hunger, bladder, fatigue, and so on by interacting with objects. Wright and his team developed a reported 14 iterations of the interface because they wanted it to be playable without reading the manual, and this would prove crucial in making it a breakout game that appealed to a near universal audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond keeping Sims’ basic needs satisfied, &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; is an open-ended simulation of life, with the player open to pursue marriage and children, career success, material wealth, or mastery of the arts via their virtual dolls, without the imposition of any real success or fail state by the game beyond death. This provides natural accessibility, because the next action in any given situation is normally obvious to the player due to their real-world experiences and dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/the-sims_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The game suggests certain story spaces,” Wright &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rockpapershotgun.com/making-of-the-sims&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;told Rock Paper Shotgun&lt;/a&gt; in a 2008 interview. “We saw players presented with a game about everyday life, and they gravitated towards them. Can you kiss? Can they fall in love? Can they die? And a lot of these were just the normal parts of everyday life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims 2&lt;/em&gt; would eventually bake in generational storytelling through aspirations, wants, fears, and a full ageing model, but the formula wasn’t perfectly balanced in 2000, and the stories that emerged in &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; were often memorable because of how rough an approximation of life it was. Even while playing for this article, my Sim had a proposal rejected because his sweetheart was too hungry, started a fire while trying cook dinner, and then immediately started a second fire when he tried again. In its heyday, these stories would spread rapidly between friends and on forums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;house-of-screams&quot;&gt;House of screams&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting facet of &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;’ internals is the artificial intelligence exhibited by its characters. It’s easy to think of the game as player-led - I click the chair and tell my Sim to sit in it - but if that was entirely the case then a Sim left to their own devices would just stand idle until a critical need failed and they died. This would break the “living doll” illusion, so Wright and his team needed to find a way to bestow free will upon Sims that was possible to achieve on the PCs of the 1990s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ingenious solution they came up with - and one that might not sound too far from the truth for anybody who has studied marketing or sales - is that the heavy lifting would be done by the objects around the Sims. Any item that can provide a benefit to a nearby Sim screams this into the void, and the Sim’s role is to filter all of these signals based on the current status of their needs and their personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We couldn’t make the people smart enough so we had to make the environments smarter,” Wright &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ign.com/articles/1999/09/29/the-sims-interview&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;told IGN&lt;/a&gt; in 1999 as he discussed the inner workings of Sims’ minds. “All the intelligence is embedded in the object in the environments.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s no coincidence, then, that to this day unattended Sims will quickly end up playing video games on the computer. Human players will often queue up mundane tasks to manage and progress their lives (cooking, taking out the rubbish, reading, cleaning the shower, and so on), and if these drive their fun meter low enough then it will be the entertainment offered by the computer that calls out the loudest, leading the Sim to choose it over reading the newspaper or sitting in an armchair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-hedonic-treadmill&quot;&gt;The hedonic treadmill&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another pertinent mechanic is that by which Sims appraise the new objects you spend their hard-earned simoleons on. When you return to Live Mode after placing a new item, sometimes Sims will automatically spawn an action titled “What’s this?”. They’ll walk over to their new possession, consider it for a few seconds, and then express their opinion with full force, either yelling and applauding if they approve of your purchase or making their disdain known if they don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/the-sims_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick behind the scenes, and the detail that introduces a real-life parallel, is that whether a Sim loves a new item or not is based upon the average value of all the other objects in the house (with penalties if they already own multiples of the same item). For a positive response, the new buy must be worth at least 20 percent more than the average value. Because this is a moving target, what impresses your Sims when they’re poor may offend them once they’re rich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see this as less of a critique of consumerism as a whole and more as a warning regarding the hedonic treadmill you may find yourself on if progress and material wealth are your sole objectives and focus. It’s difficult to avoid - it’s the nature of the human mind that even the shiniest new purchase will eventually fade into the background amongst your other, older possessions - but it’s worth remembering the times when you had much less and practicing gratitude for what you now have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;behind-closed-doors&quot;&gt;Behind closed doors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a surface level, &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; encapsulates the American Dream and the optimism of the 1950s and 1960s. Sims begin their lives with $20,000 - enough to purchase a humble home filled with low-quality belongings - and through networking, hard work, and self-improvement can earn their way to the hilltop mansion and a state-of-the-art TV set. All this is set against the wistful soundtracks of Buy and Build Mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What sets the game apart is a mood that alternates between mid-century consumer bliss and an unnerving sense that something is fundamentally wrong. I’ll spare you the essay on why &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; is a parody of late-stage capitalism and foreshadows society’s collapse - I’m not part of the anti-capitalist crowd - but there is an unsettling element, partly due to technical limitations but also because of deliberate gameplay elements, that something is not right beneath the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/the-sims_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A contributing factor here is that &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; is purposefully abstract by design. Wright knew that perfectly simulating real life wouldn’t be possible in 2000 - that’s an impossible order even with 2024 hardware - so characters’ actions often lack detail and they speak in a garbled language called Simlish. The Sims’ native tongue emulates real dialects in its sounds, but is deliberately indecipherable so players’ minds can fill in the blanks and add meaning, upping the surreal factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another is that the game outwardly projects a mood similar to films like &lt;em&gt;American Beauty&lt;/em&gt; – a suburban world where the sun is perpetually shining on the picket fences, the birds are tweeting, and the neighbours come to your door with their home cooking. The same chirpy, feel-good tone becomes jarring when your Sim has a mental breakdown and pees his pants, a burglar enters their home while they’re sleeping, or you receive an anonymous and vaguely threatening phone call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;an-imperfect-simulation&quot;&gt;An imperfect simulation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complicating things further is that while the Sims’ lives might not be as bright as they appear on the surface, the same may be true of the player. For the most part, &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; is a dream playground for the escapist who wishes for more control than they feel over their real life, but when its more sinister elements creep in they can have an uncanny quality that breaches the divide between the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; offers a simplified view of the world. Happiness is having eaten, slept, and been to the bathroom recently. Effort bestows wealth, and Sims are told just how much they must improve for a promotion. Relationships are measured in numbers, with each interaction assigned a distinct positive or negative value. Skill progression is linear, and time spent tickling the piano keys is guaranteed to pay off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/the-sims_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a child in 2000, playing the game as a way to escape my parents’ constraints and imagine my adult future, and one of reasons I drifted away from the series was a feeling I was substituting productive contribution towards my real life by indulging in a fantasy world that offered short-term entertainment but no sustainable fulfilment. The moments the melancholy undertones shone through in the music were a jarring reminder of this, making a late-night play session feel that much lonelier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there are the times the game seems to go out of its way to make the player uncomfortable. The desperate screams as Sims watch their homes burn. The grave jingle that plays when a Sim passes away. The spooky music that randomly chimes in at night (even worse when you try and fail to search the lot for a ghost). There’s an undertone of menace to &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; that seems designed to catch you out from time to time, and makes you wonder if you’re really the watcher or the watched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-virtual-box-of-chocolates&quot;&gt;A virtual box of chocolates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is what you make it, and so is &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;. The last 24 years have seen players tell the stories of multi-generational families in painstaking detail, build mind-bogglingly complex dream houses, and invent ever more concerning ways to torture their little virtual people. The sequels (with the possible exception of &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/12/05/things-missing-the-sims-4&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) only expanded upon the possibilities and enabled further creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with success comes money, and with money comes bureaucracy and pressure. It’s been more than two decades since EA released &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;’s earliest expansion packs, and in that time it feels like the game’s focus has shifted from life simulation towards an imagining of a perfect existence where the characters all have Pixar-style faces and it’s very hard for things to go wrong unless you want them to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; has lost a lot of its original tone and character along the way. Aesthetics and pre-cooked stories seem to be the name of the game since &lt;em&gt;The Sims 3&lt;/em&gt;, and the uncanny vibe that permeated &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;’s gameplay has long given way to a chipper and almost childish tone that rules out anything remotely shocking - let alone the original’s ever-present sense of dread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be honest: &lt;em&gt;The Sims 2&lt;/em&gt; is my favourite game in the series for playability (the systemic upgrades were worth a small sacrifice to the levels of weirdness), but &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; will always be the most special entry. From the concept itself, to all the odd and creepy gameplay quirks, to the iconic soundtrack, nothing has come close to the unique atmosphere of Will Wright’s virtual doll house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a list of high-quality articles and videos on &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;, which served both as inspiration and as means to verify the little details I &lt;em&gt;thought&lt;/em&gt; I remembered about a game from the year 2000, but needed to check weren’t fabrications of my young mind. While presented in no specific order, they are all worthy of your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://gamephilosophy.org/wp-content/uploads/confmanuscripts/pcg2012/Tirrell%202012%20-Dumb-People-Smart-Objects-The-Sims-and-the-Distributed-Self.pdf&quot;&gt;Dumb People, Smart Objects: &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; and the Distributed Self&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(Game Philosophy Network)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.rockpapershotgun.com/making-of-the-sims&quot;&gt;Making of: &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Rock Paper Shotgun)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9gf2MT-IOsg&quot;&gt;The Genius AI behind &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Game Maker’s Toolkit)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.gamesradar.com/the-making-of-the-sims/&quot;&gt;The Making of &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (GamesRadar)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sims_(video_game)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Wikipedia)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ign.com/articles/1999/09/29/the-sims-interview&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt; interview&lt;/a&gt; (IGN)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/The_Sims_Prima_Official_eGuide/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;: Prima Official eGuide&lt;/a&gt; (Internet Archive)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jI0dCKmZKpQ&quot;&gt;What is &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/a&gt; (Michael Aguero)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="the-sims" /><category term="strategy" /><category term="simulation" /><category term="retro" /><summary type="html">If you think of The Sims today, you’ll likely think of the EA money printing machine and its endless conveyor belt of expansion and stuff packs. The modern games have a cutesy, sanitised face, and the bright marketing material reflects their apparent positioning as a platform for teenage girls to build their dream homes and lifestyles, rather than a semi-accurate and challenging simulation of life’s ups and downs. That wasn’t always the case. When the original game was released in 2000, it did contain some humour (especially through Maxis’s renowned flavour text) but the game itself was an attempt to explore social and architectural themes through the most realistic recreation of life possible with the technology of the time – and as a result of its limitations, one that often strays into unsettling territory.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2024/02/the-sims_4.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2024/02/the-sims_4.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cities: Skylines II review</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2024/01/14/cities-skylines-ii-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cities&amp;#58; Skylines II review" /><published>2024-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2024/01/14/cities-skylines-ii-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2024/01/14/cities-skylines-ii-review">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines II&lt;/em&gt; is Paradox Interactive’s follow-up to 2015’s &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/cities-skylines&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a city builder that served as a spiritual successor to &lt;em&gt;SimCity&lt;/em&gt; in the aftermath of EA’s 2013 mess. In the following years, the original &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt; received no fewer than 11 expansion packs, as well as a smaller number of cosmetic add-ons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;366&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tvd63NN3qR4?si=ZoE9LYWbDctSKKrF&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, Paradox decided &lt;em&gt;Cities&lt;/em&gt;’ systems needed more a more fundamental overhaul, and thus the sequel was delivered in October 2023. The release was plagued by reports of bugs and performance issues, with accusations it was rushed into stores. But it looked enjoyable enough in the footage I saw, and I decided to give it a go when I &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/11/21/notes-brief-stay-austin-tx&quot;&gt;returned from Austin&lt;/a&gt; and had a little more free time to spare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-brand-new-toolbox&quot;&gt;A brand new toolbox&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise of &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines II&lt;/em&gt; is much the same as its predecessors. The player is the founding mayor of a new city on a small plot of land and must keep things running by ensuring vital services are provided while balancing their finances.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s obvious that a lot of effort has been put into improving the toolset players use to build their cities. You won’t use any of these more often the road tool, which has been revamped with new features to better handle lanes, crossings, and more. The only frustration is that it’s still hard to find space for supports at complex junctions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/cities-skylines-ii_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public transport options have more depth than ever. After building tracks and designing lines, you now can now choose how many vehicles are assigned to each line and set pricing to try to convince the Cims to ditch their cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a departure from the original &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt;, terraforming is now free. This has received a mixed response online, with some accusations that this was a necessary change due to issues with how building plots look when they sit on slopes, but I quite like being able to build elevated highways and railways without worrying about cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;artificial-general-intelligence&quot;&gt;Artificial general intelligence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning players will be all too aware that in the original game even the best-planned city would eventually collapse under the load of traffic, and all these tools wouldn’t count for much if the beautiful cities they enabled simply ground to a halt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the traffic simulation has been completely redone. While vehicles used to plot the shortest route from A to B and stick to it, they now seem to actively respond to the traffic around them. This includes better use of lanes, but also opens up the possibility of taking an alternative route if their first choice is congested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/cities-skylines-ii_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not mean that road design is no longer a consideration. If you fail to consider how Cims will use your roads – particularly when zoning new areas that will place additional strain on existing infrastructure – you will encounter traffic jams. The difference is that these both form, and can be resolved, in a natural way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a simulation, &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines II&lt;/em&gt; offers more depth than any previous city builder. In particular, the decision making used by vehicles and pedestrians means that the player must consider traffic flow in a realistic way, rather than second-guessing an ultimately flawed approximation, as in the first game. This enables lifelike solutions to lifelike problems, and leads to a more natural-looking city as the end result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cooking-the-books&quot;&gt;Cooking the books&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a true city builder isn’t just about constructing a beautiful virtual model village – the genre is underpinned by management mechanics that require you to run a stable economy while keeping your city’s citizens happy. Unfortunately, this is the area where I found &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines II&lt;/em&gt; to be the most lacking in its current state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equation is the same as it ever was. The population expects basic services (power, water, sanitation, and so on), and running the infrastructure to provide it costs money. The player must balance the books by setting taxation levels for residents and businesses, and selling excess capacity to neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/cities-skylines-ii_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue for &lt;em&gt;Cities II&lt;/em&gt; as a game is that it seems impossible to lose. On the side of citizens’ happiness, there’s little demand for said services because any delta to your current capacity is outsourced to neighbouring cities. No waste management facilities? No problem – there are already dustbin lorries taking care of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accounting is just as flawed. Early in the game, when my expenditure on services exceeded my tax revenue, I noticed that my monthly budget was still in the green due to “government subsidies” that would mysteriously appear in my income whenever needed to balance things out. More confusingly, my cash balance would often increase even when the budget screen showed I should be losing money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes &lt;em&gt;Cities II&lt;/em&gt; feel rather empty as a management game. My only theory is that perhaps Paradox decided the early game was too challenging in testing and tried to smooth out the numbers for inexperienced players. Unfortunately, it now feels like the whole thing is on guardrails, and that you couldn’t fail even if you tried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;something-to-build-on&quot;&gt;Something to build on&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines II&lt;/em&gt; is a frustrating game in its current state. The potential of the upgraded tools and AI systems is clear, but there’s little satisfaction to be found in a game that can be played carelessly with minimal risk of failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradox Interactive appears to have recognised this, along with complaints about the game’s performance, and has suspended the game’s original roadmap to try to address its more fundamental issues. (For the record, &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines II&lt;/em&gt; was a smooth experience for me until my city reached a high population, and even then, the worst I saw were some frame rate stutters when quickly moving the camera.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, your decision over whether to purchase the game or not will come down to your passion for city builders and your faith in the developer. If you’re anxious to try out the latest in the genre and trust Paradox to build on this foundation then you’ll probably get a lot of fun out of it, but if you’re less fussed then it might be better to wait until the patches have been applied and perhaps even grab a discount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3/5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="reviews" /><category term="strategy" /><category term="management" /><category term="cities-skylines" /><summary type="html">Cities: Skylines II is Paradox Interactive’s follow-up to 2015’s Cities: Skylines, a city builder that served as a spiritual successor to SimCity in the aftermath of EA’s 2013 mess. In the following years, the original Cities: Skylines received no fewer than 11 expansion packs, as well as a smaller number of cosmetic add-ons. At some point, Paradox decided Cities’ systems needed more a more fundamental overhaul, and thus the sequel was delivered in October 2023. The release was plagued by reports of bugs and performance issues, with accusations it was rushed into stores. But it looked enjoyable enough in the footage I saw, and I decided to give it a go when I returned from Austin and had a little more free time to spare. A brand new toolbox The premise of Cities: Skylines II is much the same as its predecessors. The player is the founding mayor of a new city on a small plot of land and must keep things running by ensuring vital services are provided while balancing their finances.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2024/01/cities-skylines-ii_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2024/01/cities-skylines-ii_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Merry Christmas from Strat Packer</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/21/merry-christmas-from-strat-packer" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Merry Christmas from Strat Packer" /><published>2023-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/21/merry-christmas-from-strat-packer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/21/merry-christmas-from-strat-packer">&lt;p&gt;If your December has been anywhere near as busy as mine then you’ll understand the dearth of articles and videos in recent weeks, as a few ongoing reviews and retrospectives have taken a back seat to social events and Christmas preparations (and rightfully so). Don’t worry - I’ll return to those projects in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, though, I’d just like to say that I hope anybody out there who stumbles upon this humble little blog has a merry Christmas and a new year full of happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking on a personal level, 2023 has been transformational for me. I’ve reached a satisfying place professionally and have connected with some inspiring people both IRL and in the pleasant little corner of Twitter I’ve found myself settling into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s hope that 2024 continues in a similar vein for us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– &lt;strong&gt;Strat Packer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;highlights-of-2023&quot;&gt;Highlights of 2023&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you get bored over the Christmas break and need some reading material to tide you over, look no further. Below is a list of some of my favourite articles from 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;video-games&quot;&gt;Video games&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/09/10/starfield-searching-for-god&quot;&gt;Searching for God in &lt;em&gt;Starfield&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/07/08/yazuka-6-song-of-life-retrospective&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yakuza 6: The Song of Life&lt;/em&gt; retrospective&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/09/25/ea-sports-fc-24-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt; review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;travel-and-leisure&quot;&gt;Travel and leisure&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/11/21/notes-brief-stay-austin-tx&quot;&gt;Notes from a brief stay in Austin, TX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/09/03/how-to-run-half-marathon-better&quot;&gt;How to run a half marathon (better)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/05/14/lesson-curiosity-japan&quot;&gt;A lesson in curiosity from Japan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/07/21/f1-arcade-london&quot;&gt;F1 Arcade, London&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;philosophy-and-sociology&quot;&gt;Philosophy and sociology&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/09/17/anxiety-locus-of-control-gratitude&quot;&gt;Anxiety, locus of control, and gratitude&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/06/10/why-we-believe-morality-in-decline&quot;&gt;Why do we think morality is in decline?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;films-music-and-books&quot;&gt;Films, music, and books&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/11/11/atlas-shrugged-ayn-rand&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; by Ayn Rand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/07/15/asteroid-city-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt; review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/04/23/panic-at-the-disco-viva-las-vengeance-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viva Las Vengeance&lt;/em&gt; review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/08/25/gran-turismo-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo&lt;/em&gt; review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/01/13/glass-onion-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt; review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•   &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/03/18/the-menu-review&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Menu&lt;/em&gt; review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">If your December has been anywhere near as busy as mine then you’ll understand the dearth of articles and videos in recent weeks, as a few ongoing reviews and retrospectives have taken a back seat to social events and Christmas preparations (and rightfully so). Don’t worry - I’ll return to those projects in 2024. For now, though, I’d just like to say that I hope anybody out there who stumbles upon this humble little blog has a merry Christmas and a new year full of happiness. Speaking on a personal level, 2023 has been transformational for me. I’ve reached a satisfying place professionally and have connected with some inspiring people both IRL and in the pleasant little corner of Twitter I’ve found myself settling into. Let’s hope that 2024 continues in a similar vein for us all. – Strat Packer Highlights of 2023 If you get bored over the Christmas break and need some reading material to tide you over, look no further. Below is a list of some of my favourite articles from 2023. Video games •   Searching for God in Starfield •   Yakuza 6: The Song of Life retrospective •   EA Sports FC 24 review Travel and leisure •   Notes from a brief stay in Austin, TX •   How to run a half marathon (better) •   A lesson in curiosity from Japan •   F1 Arcade, London Philosophy and sociology •   Anxiety, locus of control, and gratitude •   Why do we think morality is in decline? Films, music, and books •   Atlas Shrugged by Ayn Rand •   Asteroid City review •   Viva Las Vengeance review •   Gran Turismo review •   Glass Onion review •   The Menu review</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/01/tsp.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes from a brief stay in Austin, TX</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/21/notes-brief-stay-austin-tx" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes from a brief stay in Austin, TX" /><published>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/21/notes-brief-stay-austin-tx</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/21/notes-brief-stay-austin-tx">&lt;p&gt;Through a stroke of good fortune I was recently invited to spend a few days in Austin, Texas, and having never been to the United States I jumped at the chance. The city wasn’t on my to-visit list and I had minimal prior knowledge about the local area, so I had little idea of what to expect from my visit to the Lone Star State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/austin-tx_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dots-and-lines&quot;&gt;Dots and lines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first things I noted on arriving in the US is how spread out everything is. Each shop and restaurant is on its own large plot, like in &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/cities-skylines&quot;&gt;a city builder game&lt;/a&gt;, and because everybody drives everywhere you can’t be sure if your journey is actually walkable even if your destination is ten minutes away as the crow flies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the sides of the mammoth roads, which are full of the kind of vehicles you have to climb up into, are an abundance of billboards - most commonly for food, locally brewed beers, and lawyers. I always thought the ubiquity of &lt;em&gt;Better Call Saul&lt;/em&gt;-style adverts was a media exaggeration, but they really do line the highways.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until you’re there, it’s hard to appreciate how little consideration seems to be given to public transport in some US cities. I saw some buses and a tram, but the car is king. Even though the eight-lane highways are frequently congested, this means Uber is your primary means of getting around as a visitor, which rapidly spirals in cost - in one day alone I spent more than $55 zipping between landmarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cautious-optimism&quot;&gt;Cautious optimism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A benefit of so many Uber trips is that I could speak to a variety of locals, who were in equal measure excited about the tech boom and cautious about the preservation of what in their view makes Austin unique. Not a journey passed without the driver discussing AI, Elon Musk, and the Cybertruck. This mostly took a positive tone - or in one case absolute awe when trying to describe &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tesla.com/giga-texas&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the futuristic local Tesla factory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps these topics were self-selecting due to my easy identification as a visiting foreigner in tech, but they were still discussed enthusiastically. Everyone also mused on how much the city has grown and changed in recent years, and a few mentioned the ongoing campaign to ensure the area’s cultural hallmarks aren’t lost in the ongoing transformation (under the tagline “keep Austin weird”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample size I amassed isn’t anywhere near enough to generalise confidently, but I’d sum up the Texas residents I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; speak to as friendly and - perhaps more importantly - optimistic. It was refreshing that even those who brought up concerns about elements of the current situation were still positive, rather than envious or bitter, about technological innovation and the people who make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;exploring-downtown&quot;&gt;Exploring downtown&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I escaped the office to head downtown, I took a car to the Texas State Capitol - an Italian Renaissance-inspired building with a red granite exterior which is taller than even the US Capitol. While the structure itself is impressive, I enjoyed exploring the grounds, where amongst other things there was a miniature Statue of Liberty standing on a plinth and a large tablet inscribed with the Ten Commandments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/austin-tx_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The streets to the south are a bustling area full of eateries, bars, and venues for comedy and music. I was around at the wrong time of day for most of this, but it was a pleasant enough walk and there were some beautiful murals dotted around. It’s clear there’s a developing homeless problem, but as of yet it’s nothing compared to the scenes from San Francisco that are frequently posted online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet further south is the Colorado River, around which there are relaxed, leafy trails full of joggers and cyclists. The path passes under South Congress Bridge, which is famous for housing around a million bats in the crevices of its architecture. I couldn’t see them in the daytime, but it was a slightly surreal experience to suddenly realise where I was as I heard their loud collective chirping above me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think there are many more landmarks to see if I return, but it feels like an evening downtown is a key part of the Austin experience that I missed out on. I’ll try to find an opportunity for that next time - I’d really like to go back, stay in town a little longer, and create more downtime to chat, relax, and soak up the optimistic vibe.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="travel" /><category term="usa" /><category term="technology" /><category term="business" /><summary type="html">Through a stroke of good fortune I was recently invited to spend a few days in Austin, Texas, and having never been to the United States I jumped at the chance. The city wasn’t on my to-visit list and I had minimal prior knowledge about the local area, so I had little idea of what to expect from my visit to the Lone Star State. Dots and lines One of the first things I noted on arriving in the US is how spread out everything is. Each shop and restaurant is on its own large plot, like in a city builder game, and because everybody drives everywhere you can’t be sure if your journey is actually walkable even if your destination is ten minutes away as the crow flies. Along the sides of the mammoth roads, which are full of the kind of vehicles you have to climb up into, are an abundance of billboards - most commonly for food, locally brewed beers, and lawyers. I always thought the ubiquity of Better Call Saul-style adverts was a media exaggeration, but they really do line the highways.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/11/austin-tx_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/11/austin-tx_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Atlas Shrugged by Ayn Rand</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/11/atlas-shrugged-ayn-rand" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Atlas Shrugged by Ayn Rand" /><published>2023-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/11/atlas-shrugged-ayn-rand</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/11/atlas-shrugged-ayn-rand">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; is something of an anomaly. For every online commenter promoting Ayn Rand’s modern classic as essential reading, there’s a critic advising against ever picking it up at all, and it’s hard to separate opinions based on incompatibility with the holder’s politics from those critiquing it as a work of literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/atlas-shrugged_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was hard to justify committing to a 1,200-page novel when I might just have been wasting my time, but I recently decided it was time to take the plunge and form my own opinions. With a slight trepidation - and, admittedly, a curiosity to learn more about the philosophy that &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/bioshock&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; opposed so strongly - I finally took it on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-disaster-of-denying-reality&quot;&gt;The disaster of denying reality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a tragic scene about halfway through &lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; where a diesel-powered passenger train breaks down outside a tunnel in the Colorado mountains. The local workers know there is no option but to hold the train – there are no other diesel engines available, and sending a coal-powered locomotive through such a long and poorly ventilated passage would almost certainly end in disaster.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One passenger – a politician – is not satisfied with their explanations, and sends a telegram to the train company’s CEO in New York demanding the train continues its journey. The CEO urges one of his executives to make it happen, and the executive sends a carefully worded telegram to the local workers ordering them to find “an engine” to send the train “safely” to its destination “without unnecessary delay”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this point in the story laws have been passed, ostensibly to clamp down on out-of-control barons of industry, that tie men to their jobs. They are not allowed to quit or to be sacked, which strips them of the power to object. If they refuse to follow orders or attempt to leave their roles, they will be put in front of a governmental tribunal that will likely bar them from all future work, condemning them to poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those in charge of the area know that this puts them in an impossible situation. The careful wording of the executive’s message absolves him of any responsibility – he can claim the selection of a coal engine was incompetence on their part, or blame them for the politician’s anger if they rightly hold the train where it is. Some of them scheme and try to find ways to deflect potential blame onto their coworkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, despite everybody working on the line knowing that setting the train off with a coal engine is the wrong decision and completely immoral, nobody speaks up to stop it. They know that to do so would be to choose to save the lives of those on board, but would entrap themselves, their wives, and their children in a life of poverty when they would be sentenced for illegally resigning from their roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody wants the final call on their conscience. But rather than facing reality, they turn their backs on it, and the order is passed all the way from the CEO down to the lowliest worker – a boy who is paid simply to follow commands and not to think for himself. He sets the train off, and 300 people die in the subsequent disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;decoupling-effort-and-reward&quot;&gt;Decoupling effort and reward&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ayn Rand’s novel about a parallel, dystopian United States is littered with accounts of failures and accidents caused by the incompetence that stems from overreaching laws seeking misguided justice, but the Colorado rail disaster is the first that she describes in such grim detail, meaning it hits much harder emotionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point in the book, the protagonist, capable railway chief operating officer Dagny Taggart, is living in an isolated house in the countryside, having left the city and her job to flee the imposing and ever encroaching regulations that are stifling her best efforts to keep the railroad running and America moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disaster marks something of a turning point. When she hears the news on the radio she rushes back to her office, realising that she simply cannot stand by and watch the growing incompetence cause such harm. It is her duty to do her best in spite of the opposing forces that are promoting mediocrity in all areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the doers who are the heroes in &lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; – those like Dagny who make things happen, with the optimism to imagine a better world and the competence to deliver on their ideas. Rand’s characters believe they are entitled to the reward that their intellect and commitment brings in exchange for providing work, a living, and of course the benefits of the technologies they invent to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is juxtaposed against a homeless man’s account of a car factory he previously worked at, where the owners decided the workers would be paid by need, not by effort or ability, as voted on at an annual meeting. He explains the effect: “[The worker] had to beg in public for relief from his needs… listing all his troubles and miseries… because it’s miseries, not work, that had become the coin of the realm.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result of the scheme? The man and his competent colleagues’ output flagged as they avoided expending effort that would sap their energy and health and for which they would not be rewarded. In the end, the entire scheme failed and the car factory closed down, putting everyone out of work, damaging the local economy, and condemning even those who were originally on lower wages to zero income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;literally-atlas-shrugged&quot;&gt;Literally &lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was immediately struck by the parallel to the modern clamour on social media to stake a claim as to who is least privileged and to provide praise and reward on this basis, rather than celebrating those who strive to build, produce, achieve, and make the world a better and more prosperous place regardless of their background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a book published in 1957, &lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; contains an astounding number of such likenesses to the world in 2023, and if it were more widely read and understood (which perhaps it would be if it wasn’t 1,200 pages long) I think it would be referenced more often than &lt;a href=&quot;https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/wow-this-is-just-like-1984&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the “literally &lt;em&gt;Nineteen Eighty-Four&lt;/em&gt;” meme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The men in Washington waging war on the industrialists are driven by ideology over reason, and go unchecked because they have successfully driven fear into the public that they could lose their livelihoods if they dare challenge them. Even when the leadership are presented with objective facts that show their policies are failing, they simply accuse the dissenter of being obtuse and illogical – “that’s only theory”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This secondary assault on language is part and parcel of the antagonists’ philosophy – countries adopting their policies around the world prepend “People’s State” to their names, and the changes are all announced in the name of fairness and prosperity. Objective reality is denied and ignored in favour of subjective beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deep-rooted problems with their worldview are explained in depth in a rogue radio broadcast by John Galt, the leader of a strike by the country’s greatest innovators that demands the return of meritocracy. His rant, which spans some 60 pages, is essentially an essay detailing Rand’s objectivist philosophy, accusing the “looters” of acting more out of hatred for the rich than concern for the poor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Destruction is the only end that the mystics’ creed has ever achieved… If they profess to be moved by love, yet are not deterred by piles of human corpses, it is because the truth about their souls is worse than the obscene excuse you have allowed them, the excuse that the end justifies the means and that the horrors they practice are means to nobler ends. The truth is that those horrors are their ends…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The mystics’ scramble for spoils is only a screen to conceal from their mind the nature of their motive… They do not want to own your fortune; they want you to lose it; they do not want to succeed, they want you to fail; they do not want to live, they want you to die…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leaders’ doublethink reaches cartoonish levels shortly after, when Galt is  caught and his captors repeatedly state that he is not imprisoned or under arrest even when he’s being held by armed guard in a locked-off hotel. They then insist that they want him to work with them “voluntarily” while putting him through electrical torture. By this point they’ve spent so long convincing themselves of their good intentions and ignoring reality that it seems they genuinely struggle to tell the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;objectivity-as-a-foundation&quot;&gt;Objectivity as a foundation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; often seems to be sniggered at online, usually with the implication that it’s a book a privileged university student reads to inform a naïve worldview, but for me it was both gripping as a story and - while I don’t agree with every view expressed by the positively-framed characters - it’s a book that sends a clear and undeniable message: competence is vital to a flourishing and sustainable society, and competence can only thrive when objective fact is held above all else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of publication nobody could have known the unprecedented era of peace and prosperity that the world was about to embark upon. While developments since then have been undoubtedly positive, they have also created a layer of abstraction in most peoples’ daily lives. I don’t need to think about where food comes from, how my home is powered, or what my computer is made of. These things just… appear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we squabble over sports, social policies, and which Netflix series shoudn’t have been cancelled, &lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; serves as a reminder that we should never take our eyes off the work that is essential to our way of life. The preferences and beliefs we have the luxury of holding shouldn’t interfere with societal underpinnings that were built on rationality, science, and the study of objective fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not to say that we shouldn’t challenge convention - by all means, if somebody has an innovative new approach then it should be trialled and adopted if successful. But it’s a dangerous game to tear down proven and relied-upon systems because the alternative looks good through the rose-tinted lenses of ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atlas Shrugged&lt;/em&gt; imagines a world where an ideology that places emotion before practicality gains enough momentum that it disrupts the production of materials, transportation systems, and food supply chains. Just as the COVID-19 pandemic demonstrated just how precarious our modern lifestyles are, Rand’s novel warns us not to take the fundamentals and the people who make them work for granted.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="reviews" /><category term="business" /><summary type="html">Atlas Shrugged is something of an anomaly. For every online commenter promoting Ayn Rand’s modern classic as essential reading, there’s a critic advising against ever picking it up at all, and it’s hard to separate opinions based on incompatibility with the holder’s politics from those critiquing it as a work of literature. It was hard to justify committing to a 1,200-page novel when I might just have been wasting my time, but I recently decided it was time to take the plunge and form my own opinions. With a slight trepidation - and, admittedly, a curiosity to learn more about the philosophy that BioShock opposed so strongly - I finally took it on. The disaster of denying reality There’s a tragic scene about halfway through Atlas Shrugged where a diesel-powered passenger train breaks down outside a tunnel in the Colorado mountains. The local workers know there is no option but to hold the train – there are no other diesel engines available, and sending a coal-powered locomotive through such a long and poorly ventilated passage would almost certainly end in disaster.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/11/atlas-shrugged_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/11/atlas-shrugged_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FC 24 Career Mode: Everton – fighting for Premier League survival</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/05/fc-24-career-mode-everton-part-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FC 24 Career Mode&amp;#58; Everton &amp;#8211; fighting for Premier League survival" /><published>2023-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/05/ea-fc-career-mode-everton-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/11/05/fc-24-career-mode-everton-part-1">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a year since I last updated my &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Career Mode series, guiding TSP United into England’s top flight. With my enthusiasm for &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/ea-sports-fc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; yet to wane, I thought it was time to start a new campaign with a new club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;366&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lIIoK1mN7dk?si=dz72swPam1LqnwI1&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick note before we start: If you read the previous series, you might be aware that I play Career Mode with some special rules to increase the challenge. Last time around that was a ban on paid-for transfers to focus on youth development, but I’ve slightly altered my guidelines this time around for added entertainment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transfers in must be realistic.&lt;/strong&gt; That means that if a player is at a club that is significantly outperforming my team, he wouldn’t want to sign for us, and he’s off limits even if I have enough money to buy him.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bid responses must be realistic.&lt;/strong&gt; If a player is kicking up a fuss and has requested a transfer, I must accept reasonable bids for him. Likewise, if a much bigger team makes an offer for one of my stars, he’s going to want to leave for Champions League football, and I must let him go.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No free agents.&lt;/strong&gt; The services of some very useful players become available free of charge in Career Mode, and I probably abused this to an extent last time out. This time, free agents are completely off limits.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, all this adds up to: “I’m trying to make Career Mode as realistic as possible, and therefore I must consider what decision would be made in real life, rather than the choice that benefits me most according to the game’s mechanics.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setting-the-scene&quot;&gt;Setting the scene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve read or watched any of my recent &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/ea-sports-fc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FC 24&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; content, you’ll probably have noticed that I was playing a Chelsea Career Mode as Mauricio Pochettino. But after a couple of seasons I’d finally won the Premier League, and between my tactics and the players’ development, it felt like the game was getting a bit easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the beginning of the 2025/26 season, I tried applying for jobs at teams lower in the Premier League, but for whatever reason they always rejected me. To force the issue, I skipped through months until I was finally sacked by Chelsea, and once I was unemployed I was offered only a single role: that of Everton manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/fc-24-career-mode_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an ambitious job, and I inherited a mess. With six games to go, Everton were 18th in the league with just 23 points. Brighton, Burnley and Nottingham Forest were also entangled in the relegation scrap, with Middlesbrough well off the pace in 20th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More problematic was the squad situation. The team I took over was in bad form, stripped of key players, and lacking a natural left back. While my main focus was Premier League survival, I also began work in the background to shift the deadwood, and opened talks regarding moves for some of my favourite Chelsea youth talent, who stood no chance of game time at Stamford Bridge after my departure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202526---premier-league&quot;&gt;2025/26 - Premier League&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first game in charge was a return to Tottenham, and I immediately took a more cautious approach with an emphasis on safe passes. The drop in player quality - a lack of pace and finesse - made it difficult to penetrate the defence, but we did manage to keep it tight at the back, earning a 0-0 draw in a drab affair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any impressions that survival would be easy were destroyed in midweek when we lost 3-1 to Fulham at home, but the following weekend saw a shock smash-and-grab as Everton snatched a 2-0 win away at Old Trafford, sneaking our goals after somehow surviving sustained pressure from Manchester United.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/fc-24-career-mode_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our wings were clipped once again as Aston Villa took all three points in a scrappy game at Goodison Park that saw plenty of chances for the home team, but little quality finishing. A late consolation goal from Beto was all we could muster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With two games to go, Everton sat in 17th, just above the drop zone, with a two-point advantage and a game in hand over 18th-placed Burnley. With a superior goal difference, one point from our final two games would be enough to secure survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First up was a dramatic away clash against fellow strugglers Brighton. Despite going 2-0 down inside ten minutes, my Everton team eventually fought back to 3-3, but conceded an 86th-minute penalty after Joao Pedro was brought down by a last-ditch challenge by right-back Patterson. Mbuemo converted, we lost 4-3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/fc-24-career-mode_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meant our Premier League survival rested on our final day fixture at home to Wolves. Burnley were still two points behind, but with their last fixture taking them away to the Amex Stadium, there was every chance they could still escape the drop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The critical match couldn’t have started better, with Vargas netting an opener straight from kick-off, but Wolves equalised via Guedes after 17 minutes and quickly took control of the game, eventually taking a 3-1 lead as he completed his hat trick. At the other end, Beto failed to capitalise on countless opportunities, and while Everton did eventually pull one goal back, we relinquished control of our fate in a 4-2 defeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There had been no news from the Amex when referee blew the final whistle, but it turned out we’d been very lucky. Burnley had earned a draw at Brighton and closed the gap to one point, so we were effectively one goal from relegation, but as it was, we’d survived by the skin of our teeth in 17th place with 27 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/fc-24-career-mode_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d done enough to keep Poch in a job, but there was a lot of work to do ahead of the 2026/27 season. A number of deals made in the background meant a refreshed Everton squad would be assembled in time for August, but I’ll maintain some suspense and save the full details of the comings and goings for Part 2…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best player&lt;/strong&gt; - Beto, a ray of hope in an otherwise dismal squad&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - N/A, but the window is approaching…&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - N/A, check back next season&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="ea-sports-fc" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">It’s been a year since I last updated my FIFA 22 Career Mode series, guiding TSP United into England’s top flight. With my enthusiasm for EA Sports FC 24 yet to wane, I thought it was time to start a new campaign with a new club. A quick note before we start: If you read the previous series, you might be aware that I play Career Mode with some special rules to increase the challenge. Last time around that was a ban on paid-for transfers to focus on youth development, but I’ve slightly altered my guidelines this time around for added entertainment: Transfers in must be realistic. That means that if a player is at a club that is significantly outperforming my team, he wouldn’t want to sign for us, and he’s off limits even if I have enough money to buy him.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/11/fc-24-career-mode_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/11/fc-24-career-mode_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Like a Dragon: Hands on with both new games at EGX 2023</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/14/like-a-dragon-hands-on-egx-2023" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Like a Dragon&amp;#58; Hands on with both new games at EGX 2023" /><published>2023-10-14T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/14/like-a-dragon-hands-on-egx-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/14/like-a-dragon-hands-on-egx-2023">&lt;p&gt;I attended my first post-pandemic &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/egx&quot;&gt;EGX&lt;/a&gt; this week in London, and while the event itself was certainly subdued compared to previous years, I was very excited to get my hands on two new entries in the &lt;em&gt;Like a Dragon&lt;/em&gt; series ahead of their release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;366&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tLzeBN6utDc?si=x7ZxIHOPuzCAS8Az&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While both are brand new games, &lt;em&gt;The Man Who Erased His Name&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Infinite Wealth&lt;/em&gt; come from two very different angles that could be said to represent the series’ past and future. Here are my initial thoughts after trying them for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;like-a-dragon-gaiden-the-man-who-erased-his-name&quot;&gt;Like a Dragon Gaiden: The Man Who Erased His Name&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staking a claim amongst the longest video game titles ever, &lt;em&gt;Like a Dragon Gaiden: The Man Who Erased His Name&lt;/em&gt; picks up the story of fan favourite protagonist Kazuma Kiryu from where it was left off in &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/07/08/yazuka-6-song-of-life-retrospective&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yakuza 6: The Song of Life&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. While it will be released on PlayStation 4, it is probably also the first game in the &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt; series to be developed with the primary focus on the PlayStation 5 and Xbox Series X.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My demo gave me 15 minutes to run around a neon-soaked theme park for the wealthy, designed after a Japanese castle. It was unclear how far into the story this segment takes place, but Kiryu was going by his Joryu moniker after faking his death to protect his adopted family. The island was packed with the amusements you’d expect from a &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt; game, and was a really visually arresting setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/like-a-dragon_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In classic style, as soon as Kiryu arrives he’s greeted by way of a fight with a group of thugs. Combat gameplay feels very smooth, and Kiryu’s secret agent-style persona gives him some special gadgets to use. I can’t remember the specific names, but these include a dash, drones, a grenade, and a lasso. They fit perfectly with classic &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt;’s frantic combat and are a lot of fun to deploy in battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the rest of my time exploring the island. The boutique has outfits far quirkier than I remember in previous titles, and the arena gave me further opportunity to test my fighting skills against waves of enemies. Overall, I’m very much looking forward to this game’s release in November, and it felt great to slide back into Kiryu’s shoes and return to the original &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt; formula after &lt;em&gt;Like a Dragon&lt;/em&gt;’s turn-based battles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;like-a-dragon-infinite-wealth&quot;&gt;Like a Dragon: Infinite Wealth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Infinite Wealth&lt;/em&gt; is the next mainline &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/like-a-dragon&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Like a Dragon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; game starring new lead Ichiban Kasuga and featuring RPG-style party combat. After nearly an hour of queueing I entered the Sega booth to find Ichiban washed up in Hawaii and having formed a squad of four, featuring a noticeably aged Kazuma Kiryu. My 20-minute demo allowed me to explore the beach and a small area of the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main impression is that the game is basically more of the same following 2020’s &lt;em&gt;Yakuza: Like a Dragon&lt;/em&gt;. The available mission didn’t sound too interesting, so I mainly roamed Hawaii to see what I could find, getting into some fights along the way. Combat has been refined a little, with movement allowed within a circle that can trigger contextual moves involving objects or teammates, and Kiryu has a special ability that breaks up the turn-based fights with some real-time brawling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the Hawaiian setting exposes more of the series’ shortcomings than previous games. It’s not as exciting or packed as &lt;em&gt;The Man Who Erased His Name&lt;/em&gt;’s neon theme park, but more problematic are the the English-speaking locals. Most of them sound like that one weirdo from the last game, but worse is that they reveal just how basic NPC dialogue is. Then again, perhaps this is nothing new for some fans - is this just what it’s like to play a &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/yakuza&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; game if you speak Japanese?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;egx-2023---an-event-in-decline&quot;&gt;EGX 2023 - an event in decline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sega’s &lt;em&gt;Like a Dragon&lt;/em&gt; offerings were certainly my personal highlight of this year’s EGX (formerly the Eurogamer Expo, and recently transplanted to Earls Court to the ExCel). I also had a great time hanging out with friends in the arcade and retro areas, which were a lot of fun and had plenty of consoles and machines to try out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/like-a-dragon_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the main reason I (and probably many others) go to these events is to try out new and upcoming games. Sega brought two &lt;em&gt;Yakuza&lt;/em&gt; games, two &lt;em&gt;Persona&lt;/em&gt; games, and a &lt;em&gt;Sonic&lt;/em&gt; game. &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros. Wonder&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3&lt;/em&gt; were also present, but there was little else in terms of major studios and series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In years gone by there would be huge displays from the likes of Microsoft and EA, but with the big players preferring their own tightly-controlled showcases there was no sign of them on the floor here. Unfortunately it seems that EGX as an event may be in decline, with a lower quality offering for the admission fee. I can only hope the Eurogamer team is able to turn it around before it suffers the same fate as E3.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="yakuza" /><category term="like-a-dragon" /><category term="egx" /><category term="events" /><category term="london" /><summary type="html">I attended my first post-pandemic EGX this week in London, and while the event itself was certainly subdued compared to previous years, I was very excited to get my hands on two new entries in the Like a Dragon series ahead of their release. While both are brand new games, The Man Who Erased His Name and Infinite Wealth come from two very different angles that could be said to represent the series’ past and future. Here are my initial thoughts after trying them for myself. Like a Dragon Gaiden: The Man Who Erased His Name Staking a claim amongst the longest video game titles ever, Like a Dragon Gaiden: The Man Who Erased His Name picks up the story of fan favourite protagonist Kazuma Kiryu from where it was left off in Yakuza 6: The Song of Life. While it will be released on PlayStation 4, it is probably also the first game in the Yakuza series to be developed with the primary focus on the PlayStation 5 and Xbox Series X.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/10/like-a-dragon_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/10/like-a-dragon_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FC 24 Career Mode: How to scout and develop youth players</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/07/ea-sports-fc-24-how-to-scout-develop-youth-players" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FC 24 Career Mode&amp;#58; How to scout and develop youth players" /><published>2023-10-07T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-07T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/07/ea-sports-fc-24-how-to-scout-develop-youth-players</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2023/10/07/ea-sports-fc-24-how-to-scout-develop-youth-players">&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest joys of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/ea-sports-fc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;EA Sports FC 24&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s Career Mode is to scout the next generation of talent and nurture them until they’re world class, continuing your team’s legacy without the need for hundreds of millions of pounds of spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;366&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/B-BpWXR8fcA?si=TbsAiUg_4CzRIo-o&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s tremendously satisfying to develop young players, but a solid youth setup also helps to slow down Career Mode, maintaining a long-term challenge in a game that encourages you to buy the world’s top stars and dominate from the off. Here’s how to get started with scouting, signing, and training promising youngsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: left; margin-top: 20px; padding: 10px; background: #ffd900; width: 97%; border-radius: 5px;&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note&lt;/b&gt;: This is an updated version of &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players&quot;&gt;a previous &lt;i&gt;FIFA&lt;/i&gt; article&lt;/a&gt;. While there are &lt;i&gt;some&lt;/i&gt; new features, unfortunately Career Mode hasn't changed much since then.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hiring-and-assigning-scouts&quot;&gt;Hiring and assigning scouts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to address is the top of your youth academy funnel - namely, hiring a decent scout. Head to the youth staff page and assess your current options. The most important factors are their experience rating (reflecting how likely they are to find players) and judgement (how accurately they assess players’ abilities).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/fc-24-youth-development_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your current scouts are no good, you can spend some of your transfer budget on a new one. When you’re satisfied with their skills, you need to send them to set up a scouting network. You can choose which country they’re searching in, how long they’re there for, and select specific player traits you want them to look for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I’m biased, but I usually like to fill my team with young English players, so I send my scout out on broad, long-term assignments in England and leave him to it. If you have different priorities then you might want to mix things up with shorter searches in different countries and with different criteria and parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reviewing-scout-reports&quot;&gt;Reviewing scout reports&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a short set-up period, your scouts will begin to deliver monthly reports to your inbox. These consist of a list of players with rough estimations of their current and potential abilities (which is why the scout’s judgement rating was so important).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/fc-24-youth-development_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To filter this list down, I normally start with a baseline potential OVR rating - usually 80 if I’m managing a Premier League side, or 83 to 85 at a top team. If a player has no chance of exceeding this lower limit then it’s very unlikely that they’ll ever feature in my first team even if they develop perfectly, so I send them on their way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the upper bounds of a player’s potential are above my threshold then I turn my attention to their minimum potential. If it’s also quite high - say in the mid-70s - then I’ll recruit the youngster to see how they develop in my academy. If it’s lower, there’s a risk they’ll be a dud. I leave them on the report so my scout can take a closer look and return with an updated assessment of their potential ability next month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;managing-your-youth-squad&quot;&gt;Managing your youth squad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with scouting, you’ll receive monthly updates on your youth squad as their OVR ratings improve and their potential ability becomes more accurate. It might sound brutal, but the main purpose of this report is to check who falls short. If one of your recruits’ potential OVR falls below your minimum threshold, don’t be afraid to let them go and free up space in your youth academy. Football is a harsh world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/fc-24-youth-development_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a player progresses to an acceptable OVR rating - usually in the mid-60s, for me - and plays in a position where he’s likely to get game time, it’s time for a promotion to the senior team to continue his development with the big boys. Beware that once a player leaves the youth squad you will lose visibility of his potential, so try not to promote players while their potential OVR range is too wide if you can help it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally a player will essentially force a promotion. You’ll recieve an email telling you he’s unsettled, with a choice between adding him to your main squad or losing him. If a player is still in my academy then he usually has decent potential (otherwise he’d have been dropped), so I normally offer him a professional contract and then loan him out if he’s not quite good enough to play alongside the first team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-team-experience&quot;&gt;First-team experience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the time finally comes, either through judgement or coercion, ensure your young players get some decent game time in the first team so they can reach their full potential. I normally treat them as though they have a few more OVR points than they do, filling my bench with youngsters and subbing them on whenever I’ve established a solid lead and can risk a few mistakes from inexperience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cup matches, which are arguably less important and are more likely to be against lower-level opposition, should be a big opportunity for young players to get some minutes on the pitch. Consider starting some young talent in the cup - particularly goalkeepers, who aren’t likely candidates to be subbed on during other games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/fc-24-youth-development_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New for &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/ea-sports-fc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FC 24&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Career Mode is a feature that allows you to hire and fire coaches of varying ability. This directly influences the speed and degree to which your players improve, so ensure you have enough coaches, that they’re as skilled as possible, and they’re suited to your playstyle to help boost your youngsters’ development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when you try your best, circumstances (or the sheer number of youth players you’re farming) don’t always allow for everyone to get the minutes they need on the pitch. If a player isn’t playing regularly then don’t be afraid to send them out on loan. Incoming offers are always for loans with the option to buy and the other club will walk away if you try to negotiate, but don’t be put off by this bug - delegating the response to your director of football will allow you to renegotiate a standard loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow this pattern, exposing young players to first-team football via the bench, cup starts, and loans. You should see their OVR increase by a few points per season (you can check this on the Squad Hub screen). Eventually some will develop enough to earn starting places in your lineup, and maybe - if you’re lucky - in a few seasons’ time a new world superstar will graduate from your youth academy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="ea-sports-fc" /><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">One of the greatest joys of EA Sports FC 24’s Career Mode is to scout the next generation of talent and nurture them until they’re world class, continuing your team’s legacy without the need for hundreds of millions of pounds of spending. It’s tremendously satisfying to develop young players, but a solid youth setup also helps to slow down Career Mode, maintaining a long-term challenge in a game that encourages you to buy the world’s top stars and dominate from the off. Here’s how to get started with scouting, signing, and training promising youngsters. Note: This is an updated version of a previous FIFA article. While there are some new features, unfortunately Career Mode hasn't changed much since then.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/10/fc-24-youth-development_2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2023/10/fc-24-youth-development_2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>