<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stratpack.blog//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-06-10T17:42:24+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Strat Pack</title><subtitle>Strategy and simulation gaming and adjacent interests</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Bioshock Infinite (PC) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/10/bioshock-infinite-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bioshock Infinite (PC) retrospective" /><published>2022-06-10T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-06-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/10/bioshock-infinite-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/10/bioshock-infinite-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;I’m on the war path in 2022, finally playing through all sorts of games that I probably &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have completed years ago, but for one reason or another passed me by. Next in line is &lt;em&gt;Bioshock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; - the 2013 follow-up to two fantastic games that I hold among my all-time favourites. The switch from my beloved Rapture to Columbia demoted this one to my “to play” list, and once the initial hype died down so did any urgency I had to pick it up - until, that is, it went free on the Epic Games store a few weeks ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bioshock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; is a game that can certainly be described as interesting on several levels. The core premise and story itself is interesting, including how it entwines itself with the series’ universe. The potential readings into what the designers and writers meant by it all are interesting. And at its most fundamental level, as a piece of video gaming entertainment, it’s interesting to notice the ways in which the &lt;em&gt;Bioshock&lt;/em&gt; formula has been tweaked to paper over some of the shortcomings and criticism of the first two games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-tale-of-two-timelines&quot;&gt;A tale of two timelines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most fundamental difference between &lt;em&gt;Bioshock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; and the two games that came before it is that the iconic underwater city of Rapture is no more. This time out, our setting is Columbia – a flying city of interconnecting platforms that was established by Father Comstock, a religious leader who is seen as the ultimate authority and God’s right-hand man. The brief opening sees you take a row boat to a lighthouse, and essentially only fills you in that you’re a man named Booker DeWitt who has travelled from New York to settle his gambling debts. Then it launches you into the clouds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parts of Columbia you are shown carefully construct your impression of the city over the first hour or two. Unlike Rapture, the city is thriving when you arrive, and it initially seems rather idyllic until you begin to notice certain undercurrents. These eventually come to the surface when DeWitt wins a raffle, the prize for which is presented by “the loveliest white girl in Columbia”. Your reward, it turns out, is a chance to hurl a ball at a pair of lower-class citizens in stocks, but before you can do anything DeWitt is recognised as the “false shepherd”. From that moment, you’re on the run.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A switch is flicked here, and the game becomes a lot more violent both literally and figuratively. The shooting begins and the racism bubbles to the surface as your travels take you through areas branded with slogans like “Protecting our Race”. I was a bit worried at this point that the sum of the game’s story would be a lazy “religion is bad and racist”, but &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt; has more up its sleeve yet. Things get properly interesting when we run across Elizabeth – the girl DeWitt’s debtors have apparently been demanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Held captive and under observation by Comstock, Elizabeth is quickly established as having a supernatural power to open “tears” to other worlds. We break her out of her tower and – after some convincing that killing so many people is a necessity that doesn’t make us evil – she joins us in a failed escape attempt. We’re knocked out, and when we wake up we’re introduced to the Vox Populi – a rebel group attempting to start an uprising and overthrow Comstock. They’ll help us if we provide weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elizabeth is enamoured with the Vox and their promise of a better and fairer life for the people of Columbia, but when she brings us into a world where their revolution is in full throw it is clear that they are bent on tearing the city apart and killing even the most insignificant citizens. In this timeline DeWitt is their martyr, and the Vox turn on us because a living Booker “complicates the narrative”. Even Elizabeth steps in when the Vox leader Daisy is about to kill an industrialist’s child, and stabs her in the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A face-off with the spirit of Lady Comstock yields a twist – until now we’ve been led to believe that Elizabeth is Comstock’s daughter, but this is thrown into doubt. When Songbird – a giant, mechanical brute of a bird that guarded her tower – tracks us down, she sacrifices herself into captivity to save DeWitt’s life. Another jump between worlds leads us into a mental asylum, where we see glimpses of Elizabeth’s “rehabilitation” by Comstock’s regime, and a further switch enables a brief conversation with an elderly Elizabeth in 1984, set against the backdrop of Columbia invading New York. She hands us what will later turn out to be the key to stopping Songbird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot happens from here on out as the game culminates in a fight through Comstock’s airship to kill the man himself. We have a final (and long) battle with the Vox on the top deck, using the new intel to harness Songbird to our advantage before we lose control of him and Elizabeth is forced to transfer us into another world… and we end up in Rapture. It turns out Columbia and Rapture exist in parallel worlds. When we surface, there are lighthouses as far as the eye can see, and Elizabeth explains that there is “always a man, always a city” - an infinite number of alternate timelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learn a lot through some muddled scenes here, but the overall gist is this: Elizabeth is DeWitt’s daughter Anna, who he was forced to hand over to Comstock to settle his gambling debts. Comstock himself was rendered impotent due to inter-world travel via tears, but wanted Elizabeth to be his heiress and take over Columbia when he stepped down or died. Hearing this, DeWitt wants to go back in time and kill Comstock so none of this can happen, but realises that Comstock is in fact another version of &lt;em&gt;himself&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeWitt was offered a chance to be baptised and absolved of his sins when he returned from war, but turned the priest down. In a parallel timeline, he accepted the baptism and became religious, eventually transforming into Father Comstock and founding Columbia. As Elizabeths from various worlds converge on DeWitt in the lake where this took place, he allows them to drown him to keep her from the harm that would otherwise be inflicted by Comstock. The screen fades to black, and the game ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reading-between-the-lines&quot;&gt;Reading between the lines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a high level, &lt;em&gt;Bioshock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; can be read as a warning about extremism on both sides of politics. Father Comstock’s regime is authoritarian, with slogans on the billboards, police in military uniforms on the street corners, and a horribly mistreated underclass of workers and ethnic minorities. But when the Vox Populi rise up, they too commit atrocities, with indiscriminate killings of anybody they deem to be part of the establishment – even children. It’s a cautionary tale about how easy it is for anyone to convince themselves they are “the good guys” and justified in undertaking horrible acts because they think their cause is worthy enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is supported by a few segments that offer commentary on the gulf that sometimes exists between the stories we tell ourselves and reality. Notably, Elizabeth is thoroughly convinced by just a few lines from the Vox Populi about how they’ll make Columbia a better place. Later, we see the priority the revolutionary group places on the narrative it has built. Although he is also fighting against Comstock, a dead DeWitt is more useful to Daisy Fitzroy because if he is living then he loses his martyr status, which is a cornerstone of their propaganda. Building a polarising story is more important to them than their integrity. &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt; shows the power of blind adherence to ideology to corrupt, even when a movement started with worthy intentions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an important and relevant message for the real world, but it doesn’t &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; work in-game because Comstock’s regime is so cartoonishly evil that you could make an argument that just about anything else would have been preferable. In fact, everyone in &lt;em&gt;Bioshock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; is a hopeless caricature – Comstock as the insane cult leader and industrial tycoon Albert Fink as the capitalist without morals, for example. Daisy herself is a rare example of a character with some ambiguity – initially seeking justice before power pushes her over the ethical edge – far more interesting than all-out good or evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting here that all this is conveyed in a much more engaging way than the themes of the first two &lt;em&gt;Bioshock&lt;/em&gt; titles. This is possible because Columbia is alive around us, and there are NPCs we can listen to and interact with who aren’t just manic splicers rambling nonsense – ranging from major characters like Comstock and Daisy Fitzroy to enemies and random citizens. In &lt;em&gt;Bioshock&lt;/em&gt;, most exposition came though audio logs dotted around the ruins of Rapture. They still exist in &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt; and supplement the story with some colour, but the bulk of the main narrative is absorbed through experience – conversations with characters and observation of the city in motion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also points, especially early on, where Elizabeth expresses her dismay at DeWitt’s killing. This is a theme more akin to that of the original &lt;em&gt;Bioshock&lt;/em&gt;, which questioned gamers’ ability to make their own decisions. This is a first-person shooter, and we simply accept that shoot is what we must do in every situation where the game will let us. Elizabeth, on the other hand, is new to this world, and shocked at the carnage we leave in our wake. It’s not explored as consistently as it could have been, but this thread at least comes to a head when she turns to violence herself later on, stabbing Daisy in the back to spare the young boy she’s about to kill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take this a step further, Elizabeth and her character development could also be read as an analogy for the naivety of youth in general. She leaves captivity having read about the world in her library (akin to school) and is shocked at the reality outside. Her idealistic pacifism is eventually shattered, as I mentioned above. And she is impressionable enough to be won over quickly and completely by the Vox Populi’s promises, only realising her mistake when she sees what their revolution really looks like. The course of Infinite’s story is an education in practicality and critical thinking for her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;playing-the-game&quot;&gt;Playing the game&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;em&gt;Bioshock&lt;/em&gt; series lends itself to discussions of story and themes, gaming is an interactive medium, and ultimately none of it would stand up if the gameplay experience was no good. What we get with &lt;em&gt;Bioshock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; is a steady refinement of what came before in the first two games. The series’ shooting has never been the best. Unlike something responsive and weighty like &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/call-of-duty&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, combat in this game is a lot more about wearing down enemies’ health bars over time using the tools at your disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And those tools are as varied as any game’s. The selection of guns is what you’d expect from a modern FPS, but the “vigors” – powers embedded in your hand which replace plasmids this time around - are where the designers really got creative. These range from classics like lightning and fire to some that are really out there. My favourite was Murder of Crows, which allows you to throw a nest at your enemies’ feet so that birds attack them. Vigors are what sets &lt;em&gt;Bioshock&lt;/em&gt; apart, and my only complaint is that the game didn’t make it clearer that while two vigors sit in your quick-use slots for easy access, you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; still access them all at any time via a radial menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elizabeth is unique as a companion. While most sidekicks are annoying at best and game over machines at worst, Elizabeth is invulnerable to damage and serves instead as a tool to enhance the player’s experience. She picks locks to helps you progress, and often runs ahead, helping to guide you in the right direction. She throws items like ammo and money to Booker, and even her tears become a gameplay mechanic – you can shout to her to fabricate cover, weapons, health, turrets, and more. It’s so rare for a companion to be so genuinely useful that I found this directly contributed to the weight of the story, and you miss her when she’s taken away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Columbia itself also offers a chance for Irrational Games to add some variety to the series’ gameplay. Gone are the claustrophobic corridors of Rapture, which have been replaced in large part by open outdoor areas. The difference is night and day, and you’re much more likely to be engaged in ranged combat than in even the most expansive parts of Andrew Ryan’s underwater city. Staying on brand as a flying city, Columbia is full of Sky-Line rails, which enable DeWitt to slide around on a grappling hook-style device and drop down on enemies from above when the opportunity arises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foes range from standard foot soldiers (melee, pistol, machine gun, RPG, sniper, etc.) to  specialists. Firemen blast you with flames, and raven-themed warriors can teleport and hack at you with a sword, for example. The largest and most challenging enemy type is the Handyman, which benefits from great speed, extended reach, and the ability to take a large amount of your health if it hits you. The best of the lot, however, was the Motorised Patriot – robots modelled after the US Founding Fathers who storm into battle in a hail of bullets, shouting patriotic slogans as they join the fray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt;’s most memorable sequences are when the game decides to mix things up. Lady Comstock provides one of the more interesting fights, summoning ghost soldiers to do her bidding in a way that reminded me of Clifford Unger in &lt;em&gt;Death Stranding&lt;/em&gt;. I thought the battle was fairly short at first, but she returns several times in different arenas. Mechanically, it’s a nice change of pace to be forced to balance fighting the boss herself with dealing with her henchmen as they advance on your position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another notable mention goes to the mental asylum where Elizabeth is held later in the game. This features surprisingly good stealth gameplay, where if you are caught by a rotating sentry’s torch you are ambushed by a group of tough inmate enemies in creepy masks. The section culminates in a huge jump scare, where you pull a lever and turn around to find one of the sentries, which you’ve been tiptoeing around all along, right behind you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no regrets about taking the time to play &lt;em&gt;Bioshock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; after nine years. There were elements I enjoyed – the opening chapel, the Motorised Patriots, and some of the grander spaces will all stick with me – but I felt Columbia was less atmospheric than Rapture, held back by the little details. The vending machines, for example, were just as creepy as Rapture’s, but their voices felt like imitations of the old ones (which can be explained by the parallel worlds plot point, but still). Maybe it’s also because I missed Rapture’s claustrophobia and the horror elements that the first two games employed, but it also seemed like the sub-nautical state had more of a story to tell as a city, while &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt;’s tale was much more about the individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_8.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that sounds like I’m being negative, I’m not. &lt;em&gt;Infinite&lt;/em&gt; was still a fantastic game, head and shoulders above most other titles out there – particularly in &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/shooters&quot;&gt;the FPS genre&lt;/a&gt; – and it was clear that Irrational Games had spent a lot of time working out how they could act on some of the criticism directed at the first two games in the trilogy while still maintaining its character. While the transition to a new city was a mixed success, the gameplay is a definite step up, especially with Elizabeth and her tears to keep you company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There aren’t many games with enough depth to be worth a 2,500-word retrospective, but &lt;em&gt;Bioshock&lt;/em&gt; has pulled it off again. &lt;em&gt;Bioshock Infinite&lt;/em&gt; is a mesh of complex ideas, some of which work better than others, but the underlying message about the perils of blind adherence to ideologies on all sides of the political spectrum is if anything more relevant now than it was back in 2013. If politics and philosophy aren’t your thing, there’s also a compelling personal story about DeWitt, Comstock, and Elizabeth to unpick. And if you don’t care about that… Well, there’s quite an enjoyable video game here, too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="bioshock" /><category term="shooters" /><summary type="html">I’m on the war path in 2022, finally playing through all sorts of games that I probably should have completed years ago, but for one reason or another passed me by. Next in line is Bioshock Infinite - the 2013 follow-up to two fantastic games that I hold among my all-time favourites. The switch from my beloved Rapture to Columbia demoted this one to my “to play” list, and once the initial hype died down so did any urgency I had to pick it up - until, that is, it went free on the Epic Games store a few weeks ago. Bioshock Infinite is a game that can certainly be described as interesting on several levels. The core premise and story itself is interesting, including how it entwines itself with the series’ universe. The potential readings into what the designers and writers meant by it all are interesting. And at its most fundamental level, as a piece of video gaming entertainment, it’s interesting to notice the ways in which the Bioshock formula has been tweaked to paper over some of the shortcomings and criticism of the first two games. A tale of two timelines The most fundamental difference between Bioshock Infinite and the two games that came before it is that the iconic underwater city of Rapture is no more. This time out, our setting is Columbia – a flying city of interconnecting platforms that was established by Father Comstock, a religious leader who is seen as the ultimate authority and God’s right-hand man. The brief opening sees you take a row boat to a lighthouse, and essentially only fills you in that you’re a man named Booker DeWitt who has travelled from New York to settle his gambling debts. Then it launches you into the clouds. The parts of Columbia you are shown carefully construct your impression of the city over the first hour or two. Unlike Rapture, the city is thriving when you arrive, and it initially seems rather idyllic until you begin to notice certain undercurrents. These eventually come to the surface when DeWitt wins a raffle, the prize for which is presented by “the loveliest white girl in Columbia”. Your reward, it turns out, is a chance to hurl a ball at a pair of lower-class citizens in stocks, but before you can do anything DeWitt is recognised as the “false shepherd”. From that moment, you’re on the run.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/06/bioshock-infinite_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting the full Martin Brundle experience at Thruxton</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/03/btcc-formula-4-thruxton-2022" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting the full Martin Brundle experience at Thruxton" /><published>2022-06-03T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-06-03T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/03/btcc-formula-4-thruxton-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/06/03/btcc-formula-4-thruxton-2022">&lt;p&gt;I got back to Thruxton last week after nine months away, travelling down to Andover to watch the British Touring Car Championship, Formula 4, and other support races. It was a gorgeous day (so much so that I felt its effects for days to come) - perfect for sitting out in the fresh air and watching some racing from the grass banks at one of the country’s fastest circuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/thruxton-btcc-formula-4-2022_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time I visited the track the action came mainly from the racing - notably &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/08/29/btcc-formula-4-thruxton/&quot;&gt;a particularly incident-packed Mini Challenge race&lt;/a&gt;. The drivers seemed a bit more chilled out this year, however, and while there was some good jostling for position, the racing was friendly enough that the only DNF we saw was a Mini whose front left wheel simply gave way coming out of the Club chicane behind the safety car - a rather bizarre incident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I still maintain that &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/10/31/brands-hatch-best-views-uk-motorsport&quot;&gt;Brands Hatch has the best views in the country&lt;/a&gt;, Thruxton’s grandstands at Club give a good angle on the action, and its banked viewing areas mean you can see well no matter when you arrive or how much you move around. This year I explored a bit further than before, moving past Campbell and Cobb and around towards Segrave and Noble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/thruxton-btcc-formula-4-2022_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching Formula 4 cars navigate the Campbell-Cobb chicane from just behind the barriers was quite something. The angle reminded me of the segments in Sky’s Formula 1 practice coverage where Martin Brundle stands at different points on the track, observing the variations between drivers’ approaches and watching the weight shift across the wheels as they turn in.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The northmost viewing area is set up on a hill on the exit of Segrave and running down towards Noble. Therefore it doesn’t offer quite as much action as the complex itself, but it does provide a nice, clear space to catch the cars running at speed for any budding motorsport photographers, and was well worth the climb to see the cars from the slightly different perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/thruxton-btcc-formula-4-2022_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another area I visited for the first time this year was the paddock. Accessible via a pedestrian tunnel on the home straight, it extends out towards the airfield and is fully open to spectators, at least on BTCC weekend. Of particular interest to me were the Formula 4 team tents, where some of the cars were stripped down for all sorts of work, with panels missing to expose their front suspensions, engines, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, it was another successful day out. I feel like Thruxton isn’t often mentioned in the same conversations as more famous circuits like Silverstone and Brands Hatch that have hosted Formula 1 grands prix, but it should certainly be high on your list if you live in the south of England and you want to watch some exciting motor racing on a very fast track.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="motorsport" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="formula-4" /><summary type="html">I got back to Thruxton last week after nine months away, travelling down to Andover to watch the British Touring Car Championship, Formula 4, and other support races. It was a gorgeous day (so much so that I felt its effects for days to come) - perfect for sitting out in the fresh air and watching some racing from the grass banks at one of the country’s fastest circuits. Last time I visited the track the action came mainly from the racing - notably a particularly incident-packed Mini Challenge race. The drivers seemed a bit more chilled out this year, however, and while there was some good jostling for position, the racing was friendly enough that the only DNF we saw was a Mini whose front left wheel simply gave way coming out of the Club chicane behind the safety car - a rather bizarre incident. While I still maintain that Brands Hatch has the best views in the country, Thruxton’s grandstands at Club give a good angle on the action, and its banked viewing areas mean you can see well no matter when you arrive or how much you move around. This year I explored a bit further than before, moving past Campbell and Cobb and around towards Segrave and Noble. Watching Formula 4 cars navigate the Campbell-Cobb chicane from just behind the barriers was quite something. The angle reminded me of the segments in Sky’s Formula 1 practice coverage where Martin Brundle stands at different points on the track, observing the variations between drivers’ approaches and watching the weight shift across the wheels as they turn in.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/06/thruxton-btcc-formula-4-2022_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/06/thruxton-btcc-formula-4-2022_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Resident Evil 2 Remake (PS4) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/27/resident-evil-2-remake-ps4-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Resident Evil 2 Remake (PS4) retrospective" /><published>2022-05-27T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-27T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/27/resident-evil-2-remake-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/27/resident-evil-2-remake-ps4-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;My journey through the &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/resident-evil&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; universe continued this month as I picked up 2019’s &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil 2 Remake&lt;/em&gt; on PlayStation 4. There were a lot of these on the shelf at my local preowned video game shop, which I thought was an ominous sign, but I’m pleased to report that Capcom have done a sterling job of extracting the best bits from the 1998 original and bringing them into the 21st century in a very slick package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we get started, you might be wondering - is a long article about a three year-old remake of a 24 year-old game &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; a true retrospective? The label isn’t super important to me, but it’s certainly too late in the day to call this a review, and enough of the soul of the original &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil 2&lt;/em&gt; has been retained to give this piece a retro vibe. If you can think of a better name, let me know. Seriously, I spent way too much time thinking about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;welcome-to-raccoon-city&quot;&gt;Welcome to Raccoon City&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/06/resident-evil-hd-remaster-retrospective&quot;&gt;recently completed the first game&lt;/a&gt;, that was my natural comparison point going in, and some big differences were immediately clear. First, this is a full remake, and it shows. The graphics are up there with the best modern games and we get full cinematic cut scenes that don’t just look like PS2 models with HD textures applied. The flip side of this is that the first game’s gorgeous static backgrounds are gone – but hey, you can’t have everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of static cameras, we now look over the main characters’ shoulders in third person, and oh the things we see from this new perspective. The increased graphical fidelity makes much more gore possible this time out, and the game revels in it, with close-ups of bodies being ripped apart and bits of zombies’ faces being blown off as you shoot them. I don’t think it’s an exaggeration to say this could be the most violent video game I’ve ever played in terms of the detail and volume of blood and guts on display.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remarked that &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; felt like a puzzle game in horror dressing, but its sequel strays further towards the scary end of the spectrum, combining both jump scares and psychological horror. Much of the game is spent exploring dark areas with a torch, dreading whatever might be lurking around the next corner. Hidden zombies will startle you, not least because grabs are harder to avoid, but some of the game’s most effective mechanics - which we’ll cover later - are the ones that build a quiet and persistent sense of dread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-places-and-new-faces&quot;&gt;New places and new faces&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resident Evil 2&lt;/em&gt; gives you the choice of playing as pretty boy police rookie Leon Kennedy (who I chose), or Claire Redfield, younger sister of Chris from the first game. This once again gives you two campaigns that are broadly similar with some different story content. The voice acting is a definite step up from the previous game, but it still has some awkward moments - for example, telling a guy to “hang in there” as the bottom half of his body is ripped off, or the famous delivery of the “horrible things I’ve seen” line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game lacks the original’s unity of place, but has a similar overall structure that has you exploring areas, solving puzzles, and unlocking new rooms to progress, with the occasional boss peppered in. Things start with a semi-tutorial at a petrol station before you move to the police station, which is a substitute for the first game’s mansion. You’ll spend the bulk of the game retracing your steps there before the later game descends into the sewer and the Umbrella lab. It all culminates in an epic final chase with fire and enemies on all sides as you race to escape the self-destructing facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we’re covering the story, Ada Wong is a character worth mentioning. She pops up fairly early on and tells you she’s with the FBI, and is a big presence from there on in - you even play a small gameplay segment as her. She’s consistently cold to Leon, begrudgingly cooperating with him to kill zombies, but then she suddenly kisses him and can’t bear to shoot him when she’s revealed to be a traitor. I’m really not skipping over too much there, either. The sudden changes in their relationship are just plain jarring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fights-with-freaks&quot;&gt;Fights with freaks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, you encounter a variety of enemies along the way, ranging from standard zombies to more agile variants that crawl the ceilings, plant mutants, dogs, and so on. I found even the regular zombies more challenging than in the first game, taking quite a few bullets to down and even then sometimes getting back up or crawling towards me. The move to full 3D means we now get free aim, which adds to the frantic nature of encounters as you line up your shots, and means the terror comes from your own skill and not panic about whether the auto-aim will do what you’re hoping for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also applies to bosses, who are scarier and more difficult to beat than in &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt;. You’ll quickly become well acquainted with the G-virus mutant Birkin, who you’ll fight no fewer than three times over the course of the game. These are generally satisfying battles as you target the orange eyes on his ever-strengthening body. The exception is the Type 2 fight, which traps you with the boss on a tiny platform. No matter what you do, he &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be defeated with a swinging shipping container, which takes an age to arrive after you press the button and kills you instantly if you get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Type 2 is the low point for &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil 2&lt;/em&gt;’s bosses, Mr X is certainly the peak. After a certain point, this unkillable brute roams the police station, drawn to the noise you make by running, shooting zombies, or bursting through doors. When I first encountered him I ran, and it was downright terrifying as it slowly dawned on me that the thudding I was hearing was the sound of his footsteps as he tracked me down. Trying to fly through puzzles while he got closer and closer, aware that he could smash into the room at any moment, is one of those gaming memories that will stay with me forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-icing-on-the-cake&quot;&gt;The icing on the cake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this comes wrapped up in a package that includes exactly the quality of life improvements I was longing for when playing through &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/06/resident-evil-hd-remaster-retrospective&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resident Evil HD Remaster&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. One huge change is the ability to drop items anywhere, which reduces the pain of limited inventory space when you come across a critical item with no slots remaining. Typewriters return as the save mechanism, but you no longer need to collect and spend ribbon, which means you’re not punished for changing your mind about your loadout after you save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From these additions to the beautiful graphics, the detailed 3D environments to the plentiful journals and notes that litter the areas and provide additional backstory, it’s clear that this remake of the second game in the series was put together by people who really cared about what they were making. This even shows in the implementation of features that might seem like gimmicks in lesser titles - for example, the use of the DualShock 4’s built-in speaker for certain actions like unlocking doors is a nice touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resident Evil 2 Remake&lt;/em&gt; is a glossy and carefully constructed game that has earnt a place in my list of favourites. The story and acting can be cheesy, and if hardcore &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; fans’ accounts are to be believed then it’s not entirely consistent with canon, but it’s a well-made rollercoaster ride of a game that you should play just for the experience itself. The tone of the series has certainly shifted towards action-horror here, and it will be intriguing to see where it goes next if and when I pick up the sequel.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="resident-evil" /><category term="horror" /><category term="survival" /><summary type="html">My journey through the Resident Evil universe continued this month as I picked up 2019’s Resident Evil 2 Remake on PlayStation 4. There were a lot of these on the shelf at my local preowned video game shop, which I thought was an ominous sign, but I’m pleased to report that Capcom have done a sterling job of extracting the best bits from the 1998 original and bringing them into the 21st century in a very slick package. Before we get started, you might be wondering - is a long article about a three year-old remake of a 24 year-old game really a true retrospective? The label isn’t super important to me, but it’s certainly too late in the day to call this a review, and enough of the soul of the original Resident Evil 2 has been retained to give this piece a retro vibe. If you can think of a better name, let me know. Seriously, I spent way too much time thinking about this. Welcome to Raccoon City Having recently completed the first game, that was my natural comparison point going in, and some big differences were immediately clear. First, this is a full remake, and it shows. The graphics are up there with the best modern games and we get full cinematic cut scenes that don’t just look like PS2 models with HD textures applied. The flip side of this is that the first game’s gorgeous static backgrounds are gone – but hey, you can’t have everything. Instead of static cameras, we now look over the main characters’ shoulders in third person, and oh the things we see from this new perspective. The increased graphical fidelity makes much more gore possible this time out, and the game revels in it, with close-ups of bodies being ripped apart and bits of zombies’ faces being blown off as you shoot them. I don’t think it’s an exaggeration to say this could be the most violent video game I’ve ever played in terms of the detail and volume of blood and guts on display.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-2-remake_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Warzone’s Godzilla v Kong event is better than it sounds</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/20/call-of-duty-warzone-godzilla-v-kong" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Warzone's Godzilla v Kong event is better than it sounds" /><published>2022-05-19T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-19T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/20/call-of-duty-warzone-godzilla-v-kong</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/20/call-of-duty-warzone-godzilla-v-kong">&lt;p&gt;Any semi-regular reader of this blog will know that I’m a fairly frequent critic of &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review&quot;&gt;live services&lt;/a&gt; and games that make their money with microtransactions, so it may come as a surprise that this week’s article is about &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty: Warzone&lt;/em&gt; - and it’s simply about how much fun I’m having.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/warzone-godzilla-v-kong_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compounding my apprehension about the new &lt;em&gt;Godzilla v Kong&lt;/em&gt; event was the skepticism over video games based on films that has been drilled into gamers over decades. More often than not, these games are some of the most generic titles out there, relying on character recognition to recoup their development costs. Put simply, they’re not usually very good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe Operation Monarch’s strength, therefore, is that it’s not a standalone &lt;em&gt;Godzilla v Kong&lt;/em&gt; game. Instead of a quickly thrown together full title, it’s a separate game mode that retains &lt;em&gt;Warzone&lt;/em&gt;’s core gameplay and adds some extra excitement on top by setting two “titans” loose on the map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the off, Godzilla and Kong roam Caldera doing their thing and generally looking scarier than your human enemies. Kong throws rocks and imposes his “wrath”, jumping up and stomping down on anything in his path. Godzilla’s signature attack is his heat ray (it’s coloured more like an ice beam, but whatever), which is equally devastating to anything directly in front of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/warzone-godzilla-v-kong_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s quite fun just to have the titans on the map. They’re constantly roaring, threatening to disrupt your plans with their destructive powers, and just generally looking quite cool on the horizon. And although it’s tangental to your main goals, it feels super cool (and very unlike &lt;em&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/em&gt;) to pilot a plane and circle them in the air, peppering them with bullets.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are objectives here. Players can collect “intel” by dealing damage to the titans, opening crates, and killing other operators. The intel gives you perks, ranging from familiar items like gas masks and armour vests all the way to something called a “SCREAM device”, which allows you to direct the titans’ signature moves towards any point on the map you wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you couldn’t care less about Godzilla and Kong, the beauty of the event is that it adds some extra spice to the &lt;em&gt;Warzone&lt;/em&gt; formula. Everyone has their own tactics when things get towards the final circle, but the best laid plans can quickly go out the window when you see an incoming ground pound or heat ray barrage pop up on the map right on your location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/warzone-godzilla-v-kong_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The added randomness keeps you on your toes and leads to situations you wouldn’t usually encounter, adding more of a frantic feel as you’re attacked from all angles by the titans and other competing squads. It also means that even if a team secures a building right in the middle of the final circle, they still might not be safe if they have to flee Kong’s wrath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operation Monarch is &lt;em&gt;Warzone&lt;/em&gt; on steroids. It’s a whole lot of fun, and I’d recommend making the most of it before it disappears on 25th May. If you looked at the promotions and shrugged like I did, give it a go - at the very least you’ll come away from a few games with a smile on your face.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="call-of-duty" /><category term="shooters" /><summary type="html">Any semi-regular reader of this blog will know that I’m a fairly frequent critic of live services and games that make their money with microtransactions, so it may come as a surprise that this week’s article is about Call of Duty: Warzone - and it’s simply about how much fun I’m having. Compounding my apprehension about the new Godzilla v Kong event was the skepticism over video games based on films that has been drilled into gamers over decades. More often than not, these games are some of the most generic titles out there, relying on character recognition to recoup their development costs. Put simply, they’re not usually very good. Maybe Operation Monarch’s strength, therefore, is that it’s not a standalone Godzilla v Kong game. Instead of a quickly thrown together full title, it’s a separate game mode that retains Warzone’s core gameplay and adds some extra excitement on top by setting two “titans” loose on the map. From the off, Godzilla and Kong roam Caldera doing their thing and generally looking scarier than your human enemies. Kong throws rocks and imposes his “wrath”, jumping up and stomping down on anything in his path. Godzilla’s signature attack is his heat ray (it’s coloured more like an ice beam, but whatever), which is equally devastating to anything directly in front of him. It’s quite fun just to have the titans on the map. They’re constantly roaring, threatening to disrupt your plans with their destructive powers, and just generally looking quite cool on the horizon. And although it’s tangental to your main goals, it feels super cool (and very unlike Call of Duty) to pilot a plane and circle them in the air, peppering them with bullets.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/warzone-godzilla-v-kong_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/warzone-godzilla-v-kong_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIFA 22 Career Mode: How to scout and develop youth players</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA 22 Career Mode&amp;#58; How to scout and develop youth players" /><published>2022-05-13T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-13T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/13/fifa-22-how-to-scout-and-develop-youth-players">&lt;p&gt;There are different ways to tackle &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt;’s Career Mode. Some players prefer to take the Paris Saint-Germain approach and build out a squad of the best players in the world, spending hundreds of millions to secure the top talent. In fact, you might even say that’s what EA seems to encourage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some - myself included - prefer a slower-paced challenge, finding young players with potential and nurturing them through carefully-timed promotion to the senior squad and ample game time with the first team. There’s a lot more going on with this sort of approach, so I’ve put this article together to run through the basics that you need to know to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;refining-your-youth-setup&quot;&gt;Refining your youth setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing you’ll want to do is address the top of your youth academy funnel and hire a decent scout. Head to the youth staff page and assess your current options. The most important factors are their experience rating (as far as I can decipher, this reflects how likely they are to find players) and judgement (how accurate their assessments of players’ abilities are).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/fifa-22-youth-development_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your current scouts are no good, you can always spend some of your transfer budget on a new one. When you’re satisfied with their skills, you need to send them to set up a scouting network. You can choose which country they’re searching in, how long they’re out there for, and select specific traits you want them to look for in a young player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1&quot;&gt;My Career Mode game&lt;/a&gt; is focused on young English players, so I usually send my scout out on long-term assignments in England and leave him to it. If you have different priorities then you might want to mix things up with shorter searches in different countries and with different parameters.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scouting-out-fresh-talent&quot;&gt;Scouting out fresh talent&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a short set-up period, your scouts will begin to deliver monthly updates to your inbox. These reports consist of a list of players with rough estimations of their current and potential abilities (at this point you’re probably seeing why the scout’s judgement rating was so important earlier).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/fifa-22-youth-development_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To filter this list down, I normally start with a baseline potential OVR rating - usually 80 if I’m managing a Premier League side. If a player has no chance of exceeding this lower limit then it’s very unlikely that they’ll ever feature in my first team even if they develop perfectly, so I send them on their way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the upper bounds of a player’s potential are above my threshold then I turn my attention to their minimum potential. If it’s also quite high - say in the mid-70s - then I’ll recruit the youngster right away to see how they develop in my academy. If it’s lower and there’s a risk they’ll be a dud, I’ll leave them on the report so my scout can take a closer look and return with a more accurate assessment of their potential ability next month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;managing-your-youth-squad&quot;&gt;Managing your youth squad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with scouting, you’ll receive monthly updates on your youth squad and over time their OVR will improve and their potential ability will become more accurate. The main use for this report is to check who falls short - if one of your recruits’ potential OVR falls below your minimum threshold, don’t be afraid to let them go and free up space in your youth academy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/fifa-22-youth-development_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a player progresses to an acceptable OVR and plays in a position where he’s likely to get game time, it may be time for a promotion to the senior team to optimise his development. Beware, however, that once a player leaves the youth squad you will lose visibility of his potential, so try not to promote players while their potential OVR range is too wide if you can help it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally a player will essentially force you to promote him. You’ll recieve an email telling you that he’s unsettled, and you face a choice between adding him to your main squad or losing him. If a player is still in my academy then he usually has decent potential (otherwise he’d have been dropped), so my approach is usually to give him a professional contract and then loan him out if he’s not quite good enough to play alongside the first team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;breaking-into-the-first-team&quot;&gt;Breaking into the first team&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the time finally comes, either through judgement or through coercion, make sure that your young players get some decent game time in the first team so they can reach their full potential. I normally treat them as though they have a few more OVR points than they do, filling my bench with youngsters and subbing them on whenever a match is looking stable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/fifa-22-youth-development_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cup matches, which are arguably less important and are more likely to be against lower-level opposition, should be a big opportunity for young players. Consider starting some young talent in the cup - particularly goalkeepers, who aren’t likely candidates to be subbed on during other games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when you try your best, circumstances (or just the sheer number of youth players you’re farming) don’t always allow for everyone to get the minutes they need on the pitch. If a player isn’t playing regularly then don’t be afraid to send them out on loan. The offers that come in always seem to be for loans with the option to buy and the other club will walk away if you try to negotiate, but don’t be put off by this bug - delegating the response to your director of football will allow you to renegotiate a standard loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow this pattern, exposing young players to first-team football via the bench, cup starts, and loans. You should see their OVR increase by a few points per season (you can check exactly how much on the Squad Hub screen). Eventually some will develop enough to earn starting places in your lineup, and maybe - if you’re lucky - in a few seasons’ time a new world superstar will drop out of the bottom end of your youth academy funnel.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">There are different ways to tackle FIFA 22’s Career Mode. Some players prefer to take the Paris Saint-Germain approach and build out a squad of the best players in the world, spending hundreds of millions to secure the top talent. In fact, you might even say that’s what EA seems to encourage. But some - myself included - prefer a slower-paced challenge, finding young players with potential and nurturing them through carefully-timed promotion to the senior squad and ample game time with the first team. There’s a lot more going on with this sort of approach, so I’ve put this article together to run through the basics that you need to know to get started. Refining your youth setup The first thing you’ll want to do is address the top of your youth academy funnel and hire a decent scout. Head to the youth staff page and assess your current options. The most important factors are their experience rating (as far as I can decipher, this reflects how likely they are to find players) and judgement (how accurate their assessments of players’ abilities are). If your current scouts are no good, you can always spend some of your transfer budget on a new one. When you’re satisfied with their skills, you need to send them to set up a scouting network. You can choose which country they’re searching in, how long they’re out there for, and select specific traits you want them to look for in a young player. My Career Mode game is focused on young English players, so I usually send my scout out on long-term assignments in England and leave him to it. If you have different priorities then you might want to mix things up with shorter searches in different countries and with different parameters.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/fifa-22-youth-development_2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/fifa-22-youth-development_2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Resident Evil HD Remaster (PS4) retrospective</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/06/resident-evil-hd-remaster-retrospective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Resident Evil HD Remaster (PS4) retrospective" /><published>2022-05-02T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/06/resident-evil-hd-remaster-retrospective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/05/06/resident-evil-hd-remaster-retrospective">&lt;p&gt;Everyone has a series or two that are widely regarded as the pinnacle of video games that they’ve never got around to playing. For me, &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; is one of them. The first game in the series, which now spans nine core titles and numerous spin-offs and remakes, was released on the PlayStation in 1996. I have a vague recollection of playing a snippet on an old demo disc, but other than that I’d somehow avoided playing it for 26 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even after I’d decided to pick up 2015’s &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil HD Remaster&lt;/em&gt; on PS4, I had my apprehensions. Certain games have a “you had to be there” quality to them - I bounced off the old &lt;em&gt;Pokemon&lt;/em&gt; games when I tried to play them in recent years, for example. Even with retouched graphics and controls, would the base game still stand up in 2022 for someone without the nostalgia Capcom were likely banking on with this release? It was time to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setting-the-scene&quot;&gt;Setting the scene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; dumps you straight into the thick of the action. You can choose to play as either Chris Redfield or Jill Valentine (I chose the latter, and later learnt they have unique perks), members of the elite S.T.A.R.S. team, who are investigating the disappearance of their sister squad amidst a growing spate of murders in Raccoon City. When they are attacked by a pack of demonic dogs they are chased to a mansion, where they seek refuge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game pleasingly coheres with the dramatic principle of unity of place, as you spend its entirety exploring the mansion, finding missing members of your team, and uncovering the dark secrets it holds regarding the T-Virus and the Umbrella Corporation. The set-up is simple and the twists are all flagged well in advance, but the execution is strong enough that it’s still gripping, and by the end of the game you’ll know the map like the back of your hand.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mansion is split into rooms, which function as cells much like the areas in earlier &lt;em&gt;Metal Gear Solid&lt;/em&gt; titles. The camera is static, changing between angles when the player character reaches the edge of the screen. This has the benefit of allowing for some beautifully detailed static backgrounds, but the revamped controls aren’t suited to it. When the camera changes, so does the direction you need to run, and you can end up spinning in circles if you don’t adjust quickly enough - frustrating at the best of times, but especially awful when you’re running from an enemy and it hinders your escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also something of a mixed bag when it comes to how the game &lt;em&gt;uses&lt;/em&gt; the camera. Sometimes it rewards close attention, showing a zombie around a 90-degree corner with a conveniently placed mirror to give you a heads up. Other times it’s not so kind, and a particularly annoying recurrence was areas that forced me to run directly into the camera, only for a zombie to be hidden right behind it ready to pounce before I had a chance to react.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-horror-themed-puzzle-box&quot;&gt;A horror-themed puzzle box&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; expecting survival horror, but quickly discovered that the bulk of the game was actually more puzzle-based. You spend your time exploring the mansion, memorising routes, and passing trials to win keys. You’ll be traversing the map time and again as you solve challenges and unlock new rooms, and discovering what’s behind a previously locked door is a treat - enemies are usually just an inconvenience along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The puzzles themselves are usually about deciding which objects go together in which order and knowing where to use them. They’re challenging enough to make you think, but follow a coherent enough course of logic that they’re not so difficult you’ll be stuck for ages wondering what to do. Some involve some basic memorisation or mental maths, and my notes for this article were interspersed with jotted-down codes, numbers, and colours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the puzzles and use of the map are cool, the inventory management system is not. You have limited slots and can only swap items out in storage boxes in safe rooms. This means you need to keep as much space open as possible for new items, and if you realise you need a previous item for a puzzle you’ll have to trudge back through the zombie-filled corridors for it. This makes trial and error expensive - especially with limited ammo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;facing-your-fears&quot;&gt;Facing your fears&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the puzzles are the stars, the enemies add the colour. Over the game’s 11-hour span you’ll encounter various types of zombies, dogs, snakes, plants, crows, bees, and more. They’re all quite intimidating, especially given the stakes the save system introduces, but entering a room to see a giant spider right above my head - seemingly rendered in more detail than anything else in the game - is certainly a moment that lingers in the memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The zombies themselves have fairly basic AI. They’ll move towards you at various speeds, then either grab or swipe at you, and mainly serve to keep you on your toes while you’re darting to and from puzzle points. They don’t generally move between rooms, but they do persist in rooms you leave them in, so you’ll be taking mental notes of which areas to stay well away from. On rare occasions a zombie will burst through a door or window into the room you’re in, and it happens so intermittently that it’s always a shock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shooting takes some getting used to. Your character has an auto lock-on, but sometimes they don’t face the way they’re aiming so lining your shot up can still be tricky. There’s some randomisation at play, meaning the same type of enemy can take different numbers of shots to kill, and zombies have such long death animations that it can be difficult to tell when they’re finished, making it easy to waste ammo in a game where it’s already sparse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll soon learn that it’s best to avoid fights with random zombies where possible. The bosses are memorable and intense enough to get the heart racing, ranging from an even bigger spider to gigantuan snakes. Jill’s health is relatively weak and even a regular enemy can normally kill you in a few hits, but the challenge tends to dissapate once you nail a run-and-gun technique - by modern standards, you’re mostly fighting the camera and controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ps1-era-quirks&quot;&gt;PS1-era quirks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed the additional details you can learn by interacting with items. These one-line notes can help to build suspense - for example, when a rope looks “recently cut” or firewood looks “fresh” and you &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; someone is close by - or can provide hints when examining puzzle-related objects. There are also a few diaries dotted around that tell some quite heartbreaking stories of the subjects and scientists contending with the T-Virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cool feature - especially for a game of this age - is the number of story branches and optional areas. I noticed after finishing &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; that my ending was assigned a number, and discovered online that as well as multiple endings there were also many scenes and items I hadn’t seen (I &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; there was a reason I kept finding shotgun shells…).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typewriters serve as the game’s save mechanism, and you as the player must find ink ribbon, which is consumed each time you save in a safe room. This adds a tactical element - you must plan not only for your next fight, but also the journey there - but it can make it costly to work out the slightly clunky controls early on when dying sets you back so far, and if you use too much ribbon too quickly then you can end up essentially being held hostage by the game, forced to play on until you find more or lose your progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only other gripe is that &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; can be quite fussy with the angle at which you approach items to interact with them. You must be very precise, or Jill just won’t pick objects up. In one particularly bad example this fussiness led me to believe I couldn’t collect the grenade launcher, and I fought a challenging boss fight without it before later realising my mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;holding-strong&quot;&gt;Holding strong&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve called out &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; for some of its residual jank through this article, but I don’t want to give the impression that I didn’t enjoy it. The story, the mechanics, and the general atmosphere together make it something special, and while the HD remaster has had quite a facelift, it’s amazing that the core of the game - still present in this version - holds up so well after 26 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern video games tend to hold your hand so much that gameplay becomes a case of a following a list of instructions on the HUD. &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/em&gt; was a refreshing departure into a time in video game history where the player was provided with very little guidance. It requires you to keep mental notes and act on your hunches, and is more rewarding as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throw in the detail in the notes and diaries, and all the background mathematics that randomise various elements of the environment, and you’ve got a game that still stands its ground in 2022. Even if, like me, you never played the 1996 version or the GameCube upgrade, I’d urge you to give &lt;em&gt;Resident Evil HD Remaster&lt;/em&gt; a go. If you can look past a few rough edges in the camera and combat, it’s a great refinement of a classic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="resident-evil" /><category term="horror" /><category term="survival" /><summary type="html">Everyone has a series or two that are widely regarded as the pinnacle of video games that they’ve never got around to playing. For me, Resident Evil is one of them. The first game in the series, which now spans nine core titles and numerous spin-offs and remakes, was released on the PlayStation in 1996. I have a vague recollection of playing a snippet on an old demo disc, but other than that I’d somehow avoided playing it for 26 years. Even after I’d decided to pick up 2015’s Resident Evil HD Remaster on PS4, I had my apprehensions. Certain games have a “you had to be there” quality to them - I bounced off the old Pokemon games when I tried to play them in recent years, for example. Even with retouched graphics and controls, would the base game still stand up in 2022 for someone without the nostalgia Capcom were likely banking on with this release? It was time to find out. Setting the scene Resident Evil dumps you straight into the thick of the action. You can choose to play as either Chris Redfield or Jill Valentine (I chose the latter, and later learnt they have unique perks), members of the elite S.T.A.R.S. team, who are investigating the disappearance of their sister squad amidst a growing spate of murders in Raccoon City. When they are attacked by a pack of demonic dogs they are chased to a mansion, where they seek refuge. The game pleasingly coheres with the dramatic principle of unity of place, as you spend its entirety exploring the mansion, finding missing members of your team, and uncovering the dark secrets it holds regarding the T-Virus and the Umbrella Corporation. The set-up is simple and the twists are all flagged well in advance, but the execution is strong enough that it’s still gripping, and by the end of the game you’ll know the map like the back of your hand.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/05/resident-evil-hd-remaster_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Buying MP3s is stupidly difficult</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/29/buying-mp3s-is-too-difficult" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buying MP3s is stupidly difficult" /><published>2022-04-23T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/29/buying-mp3s-is-too-difficult</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/29/buying-mp3s-is-too-difficult">&lt;p&gt;Many video game fans mourn what has happened to their hobby in recent years. With the announcement of each new game, from even the most acclaimed studios, a question lingers - have the developers followed the trend and stuffed it full of microtransactions? And all too often the answer is yes. How could it possibly get any worse, gamers ask? Well friends, I tried buying some music last week and I’ve seen how bad things could become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think it’s unreasonable to want to buy some MP3s. Yes, nearly every song in existence is available for free on Spotify, but what would I do if that service ever ceased to exist, or got locked behind a paywall? It makes sense to keep a trickle of your favourite songs coming in to your offline library so you can own the music, keep it, and listen to it on the Tube without paying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having relied too much on Spotify for years, I wasn’t up to speed with MP3 pricing and was expecting to get ripped off, but I was pleasantly surprised to find that most songs are a reasonable 99p, with a few slightly below that. That’s not too bad when you consider that as far back as the early 2000s you’d buy a CD album for £10 with an average of ten songs or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;amazon-music&quot;&gt;Amazon Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first stop was Amazon, because that was where I bought my digital music in the early 2010s, but I was shocked to find just how badly the customer experience had deteriorated since my last visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your first steps are to open the homepage, search for a song, and click it - so far, so good. But instead of treating songs like normal items for purchase, Amazon now redirects you to an Amazon Music page that &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; wants you to stream them instead. To buy a track, you have to find a what is basically a hidden menu item under Purchase Options &amp;gt; MP3 Music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/buying-mp3-downloads_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This takes you to another page plastered with Amazon Music stream buttons, but at least this time there are prices next to each song that you can use to purchase them. If you click one of these, you’ll be taken to a page that &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; like the Amazon basket, but it’s not. If you don’t click Buy there and then, it’s gone. That’s right - if you want to buy MP3s on Amazon in 2022, you have to purchase each song or album &lt;em&gt;individually&lt;/em&gt;. So if you have a list of 40 tracks to buy like I did, you’d have to go through the whole process separately for each one. I didn’t have time for that, so I moved on.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;itunes-store&quot;&gt;iTunes Store&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I Googled for alternatives, but there are basically no modern MP3 stores, so I went to the only other one I knew - the iTunes Store. For a company known for its slick user interfaces, Apple has really let itself down here. iTunes as a whole feels like a relic from the mid-2000s, and the store is weirdly unreliable for what is basically pages loading in a browser. I even had to restart the application a couple of times when it wouldn’t load anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/buying-mp3-downloads_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it does work, there is once again no basket. Ever the optimist, I decided to try adding the songs I wanted to my account’s wish list in the hope that I could review and purchase them all together later. But lo and behold, there’s no option to buy the whole list at once! If &lt;a href=&quot;https://discussions.apple.com/thread/5886224&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the Apple forums&lt;/a&gt; are to be believed, this &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; a feature but was removed because some users complained they were accidentally clicking the Buy All button. Sigh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With no other options, I persevered. At least all the individual buy buttons were lined up nicely with all the songs in my wish list. But buying the tracks only revealed &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; problems. You see, there’s no grouping when you buy songs from the iTunes Store - every track you buy triggers a separate transaction on your payment card and a separate confirmation email. Resigned to spamming myself, I got about halfway through my 40-song list before my bank started blocking the transactions and I had to switch cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/buying-mp3-downloads_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d think that the wealthiest company in the world would notice if its purchasing system was so convoluted that users were blocked from buying its products because the payments looked fraudulent, but apparently not. However, to give Apple credit where it’s due, downloading the songs to my iPhone was really smooth afterwards - much more so than it would have been if I’d bought the songs from Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;get-it-before-its-gone&quot;&gt;Get it before it’s gone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s sad that there’s no good option to buy and own digital music anymore, and that the stores that remain are so neglected by some of the biggest companies in the world. Amazon and Apple are clearly set on chasing Spotify and earning their money through subscriptions, but that model doesn’t suit everyone, and even if that is their strategy, is it really necessary to be so anti-consumer as to remove features that made it easier for customers to buy things and &lt;em&gt;give you more of their money&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s only a matter of time until these storefronts become so delapidated that they close down completely, so if you have any desire to build a digital music library then I’d suggest you move quickly to download your favourites before they’re gone. Past that? I don’t think it’s unreasonable to predict a rise in CD sales in the near future - buying a physical disk and ripping it could soon be your only option if you want to legally own MP3 music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let’s hope this isn’t the future of gaming. At the moment the digital options are there, but in you can still buy a boxed copy of your favourites and keep them on a shelf so you can still play them in years to come (&lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review&quot;&gt;in most cases, anyway&lt;/a&gt;). Having seen what’s happened in the music industry, it’s all too easy to imagine a future where subscription services rule and the possibility of true ownership is ripped away from us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html">Many video game fans mourn what has happened to their hobby in recent years. With the announcement of each new game, from even the most acclaimed studios, a question lingers - have the developers followed the trend and stuffed it full of microtransactions? And all too often the answer is yes. How could it possibly get any worse, gamers ask? Well friends, I tried buying some music last week and I’ve seen how bad things could become. I don’t think it’s unreasonable to want to buy some MP3s. Yes, nearly every song in existence is available for free on Spotify, but what would I do if that service ever ceased to exist, or got locked behind a paywall? It makes sense to keep a trickle of your favourite songs coming in to your offline library so you can own the music, keep it, and listen to it on the Tube without paying. Having relied too much on Spotify for years, I wasn’t up to speed with MP3 pricing and was expecting to get ripped off, but I was pleasantly surprised to find that most songs are a reasonable 99p, with a few slightly below that. That’s not too bad when you consider that as far back as the early 2000s you’d buy a CD album for £10 with an average of ten songs or so. Amazon Music My first stop was Amazon, because that was where I bought my digital music in the early 2010s, but I was shocked to find just how badly the customer experience had deteriorated since my last visit. Your first steps are to open the homepage, search for a song, and click it - so far, so good. But instead of treating songs like normal items for purchase, Amazon now redirects you to an Amazon Music page that really wants you to stream them instead. To buy a track, you have to find a what is basically a hidden menu item under Purchase Options &amp;gt; MP3 Music. This takes you to another page plastered with Amazon Music stream buttons, but at least this time there are prices next to each song that you can use to purchase them. If you click one of these, you’ll be taken to a page that looks like the Amazon basket, but it’s not. If you don’t click Buy there and then, it’s gone. That’s right - if you want to buy MP3s on Amazon in 2022, you have to purchase each song or album individually. So if you have a list of 40 tracks to buy like I did, you’d have to go through the whole process separately for each one. I didn’t have time for that, so I moved on.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/buying-mp3-downloads_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/buying-mp3-downloads_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">F1 22’s announcement video was a colossal waste of time</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/22/f1-22-announcement-colossal-waste-of-time" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="F1 22's announcement video was a colossal waste of time" /><published>2022-04-22T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-22T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/22/f1-2022-announcement-colossal-waste-of-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/22/f1-22-announcement-colossal-waste-of-time">&lt;p&gt;Racing game fans across Reddit and Twitter were excited this week after EA revealed that not only did they have the Imola Grand Prix to look forward to this weekend, but on Thursday they would also get a glimpse of the latest game in the Codemasters F1 series: the hotly anticipated &lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/f1-22-announcement_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the reveal turned out to be peak 2022 gaming and social media. After a day of countdowns, the official YouTube channel premiered &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K5RLRoRWUds&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;an announcement video&lt;/a&gt; that was just 30 seconds long, showed no gameplay, and contained only the following bland marketing phrases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• The future is here&lt;br /&gt;
• Next generation machines&lt;br /&gt;
• Racing redefined&lt;br /&gt;
• Rivalries renewed&lt;br /&gt;
• Enter the new era&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got a release date for the new game - 1st July 2022 - but the whole exercise was largely pointless. A tweet would have more than sufficed. The reaction was a mixture of disappointment, bemusement, and apprehension about what the lack of substance meant for the finished product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;beyond-the-video&quot;&gt;Beyond the video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the video was bereft of detail, we did get a little more information - and a few pretty screenshots - on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ea.com/en-gb/games/f1/f1-22&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the newly launched &lt;em&gt;F1 22&lt;/em&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;, so I thought I’d dive in and try to decipher what I could from the sales copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;New season, new rules: Take your seat for a new season as redesigned cars and overhauled rules redefine race day with the authentic 2022 lineup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means basically nothing. The latest iteration in an annual sports game series will include the latest cars and driver lineup? Colour me surprised.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Race day, redefined: Take control of your virtual F1® experience with immersive and broadcast options for Pit Stops, Formation Laps, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from one unnecessary comma and many unnecessary capital letters, what does this say? “Immersive” is the most abused word in gaming, but juxtaposed against “broadcast” maybe it means they’ve added TV-style cameras for formation laps and pit stops alongside the usual in-car angles? I wonder if the new pit stop format might take its cues from &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/01/gran-turismo-7-guide-race-strategy-pit-stops&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gran Turismo 7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;digging-into-the-detail&quot;&gt;Digging into the detail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait - there’s more! Hidden near the bottom of the website there’s a link to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ea.com/en-gb/games/f1/f1-22/news/f1-22-announce&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;an announcement page&lt;/a&gt;, which again provides just the &lt;em&gt;tiniest&lt;/em&gt; drop more detail. There’s slightly more text here, so I’ll just pull out the highlights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Take your seat for the new era of F1® with the sport’s stunning new cars and a new handling model that recreates the intense wheel-to-wheel racing that’s had us on the edge of our seats so far in the 2022 Formula 1® season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handling in the previous games was passable but not amazing, so a new model is welcome as long as it’s a solid improvement. That said, I’ll believe it when I see it because EA also says various parts of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/fifa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are being overhauled every year and many of them stay largely the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/f1-22-announcement_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Plus, test your talent amongst the iconic Florida palm trees around the 19 challenging corners of the vibrant new Miami International Autodrome, and go flat out as F1® Sprint comes to the game for the first time in F1® 22.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ll also get the newest circuit on the calendar, which isn’t surprising. As for the sprint races… They’re an addition that few fans want in real F1, but I suppose that’s not up to EA and Codemasters to decide. They could be entertaining in video game form, although I do wonder how they’ll work for players who drive even the full races on shorter settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;F1® 22 also includes VR compatibility on PC via Oculus Rift and HTC Vive to give you the ultimate immersive F1® experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be the big one for a lot of people, and I have no idea why they didn’t mention it in the announcement video. Fans have been waiting for &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt; to be able to play &lt;em&gt;F1&lt;/em&gt; in virtual reality, so Oculus Rift and HTC Vive support will have those with the right equipment very excited indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Get a taste of the glitz and glamor of Formula 1® in F1® Life, a new space for you to unlock and show off supercars, clothing, accessories, and more for the world to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know what F1 Life is exactly, but this description certainly makes it sound like it’s going to be completely irrelevant to the core gameplay. Those “supercars, clothing, accessories, and more” sound like the perfect opportunity to slip in more microtransactions, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My Team and Career Mode return in F1® 22 with fresh new features, along with two-player split screen, F2™, online multiplayer and all the features you know and love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose this is good to know, but there’s nothing new or unexpected here - someone was obviously trying to hit their word count. If any of this stuff was missing then there’d be a backlash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EA has promised more detail “in the coming weeks”, but that’s it for now. Given the feature list above, it seems the game is veering slightly further in the casual direction with F1 Life. For those who play the games for the actual racing, there’ll be a lot riding on that new handling model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="formula-1" /><category term="racing" /><summary type="html">Racing game fans across Reddit and Twitter were excited this week after EA revealed that not only did they have the Imola Grand Prix to look forward to this weekend, but on Thursday they would also get a glimpse of the latest game in the Codemasters F1 series: the hotly anticipated F1 22. Unfortunately, the reveal turned out to be peak 2022 gaming and social media. After a day of countdowns, the official YouTube channel premiered an announcement video that was just 30 seconds long, showed no gameplay, and contained only the following bland marketing phrases: • The future is here • Next generation machines • Racing redefined • Rivalries renewed • Enter the new era We got a release date for the new game - 1st July 2022 - but the whole exercise was largely pointless. A tweet would have more than sufficed. The reaction was a mixture of disappointment, bemusement, and apprehension about what the lack of substance meant for the finished product. Beyond the video While the video was bereft of detail, we did get a little more information - and a few pretty screenshots - on the newly launched F1 22 website, so I thought I’d dive in and try to decipher what I could from the sales copy. New season, new rules: Take your seat for a new season as redesigned cars and overhauled rules redefine race day with the authentic 2022 lineup. This means basically nothing. The latest iteration in an annual sports game series will include the latest cars and driver lineup? Colour me surprised.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/f1-22-announcement_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/f1-22-announcement_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FIFA 22 Career Mode: TSP United – escaping the lower leagues</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIFA 22 Career Mode&amp;#58; TSP United &amp;#8211; escaping the lower leagues" /><published>2022-04-15T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-15T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/15/fifa-22-career-mode-tsp-united-part-1">&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t bought a &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; game in years, but I couldn’t resist picking up &lt;em&gt;FIFA 22&lt;/em&gt; when I learnt that EA has finally given us the tools to emulate &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/16/pro-evolution-soccer-5-master-league&quot;&gt;the classic Master League experience&lt;/a&gt;, creating a brand new club and taking them from football’s bottom rung to continental glory. I’ve always enjoyed reading about people’s Career Mode journeys, so I thought I’d share how it’s going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-setup&quot;&gt;The setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually burn out on &lt;em&gt;FIFA&lt;/em&gt; Career Mode quite quickly. When you start a game with a big team like Chelsea, a few tactical additions to your squad are all you need to win it all, and from there it’s just a matter of bringing through young players to sustain the success and build your legacy. So this time around, I was determined to do something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I created my own club, TSP United - complete with a snazzy purple kit - and dumped them in League Two. When you create a club in Career Mode you begin with a randomly generated squad of unskilled players with which to ascend the ladder, and to make things even more challenging I decided that I would not spend a penny in transfer fees. Instead, my focus would be on bringing through youth players, with the odd free signing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202122---league-two&quot;&gt;2021/22 - League Two&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took some time to settle in before my first season gained momentum. I had a shaky start as I learnt the game and worried that I’d made things too difficult for myself, but eventually I found some rhythm and form, and by the end of the season TSP United won the league with a couple of games to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other highlights included an extended League Cup run that saw us reach the quarter finals, earning scrappy wins against Premier League heavyweights Wolves and Newcastle before taking a battering against Manchester United.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/fifa-22-career-mode_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This season was also all about learning my squad. &lt;strong&gt;Prince&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Johnson&lt;/strong&gt; established themselves as the first-choice strike partnership, with the former earning the League Two golden boot by the end of the year. I also started to put the feelers out for youth talent, with &lt;strong&gt;Greenwood&lt;/strong&gt;, a young left-back, making the most first-team appearances. The foundations were laid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best original player&lt;/strong&gt; - Prince, the goal machine&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - N/A (no signings made)&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Greenwood, our cup left-back&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;202223---league-one&quot;&gt;2022/23 - League One&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the start of the second season, my best players were &lt;em&gt;just about&lt;/em&gt; pushing the 70 Overall mark. I also made efforts to bolster the squad by signing free agents &lt;strong&gt;Acuna&lt;/strong&gt; (RB) and &lt;strong&gt;Pierre&lt;/strong&gt; (RW). The latter would prove invaluable, with more than 10 goals and 15 assists coming in from the right wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After another slow start, we went on an immense run of mid-season form and won the league with six games left to play, with &lt;strong&gt;Prince&lt;/strong&gt; rising to the challenge and continuing his scoring habit. Injuries to regulars &lt;strong&gt;Thornton&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Prior&lt;/strong&gt; meant that newly promoted youth prospects &lt;strong&gt;Green&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Groves&lt;/strong&gt; could enjoy extended runs in the first team to boost their development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/fifa-22-career-mode_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside all of this, TSP United also managed to win the Papa John’s Trophy in the most dramatic fashion possible. The highlight of the campaign was a thrilling 7-6 semi-final victory over Mansfield Town, before we went to Wembley to take on Port Vale. The final was best described as a demolition, with young &lt;strong&gt;Groves&lt;/strong&gt; playing to the occasion and scoring a hat trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;strong&gt;Best original player&lt;/strong&gt; - Prince, topping the league scorers chart again&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best signing&lt;/strong&gt; - Pierre, both scorer and creator&lt;br /&gt;
• &lt;strong&gt;Best youth breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt; - Groves, the centre midfield maestro&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;looking-forward&quot;&gt;Looking forward&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve reached the point where I’m comfortable with the game and comfortable with my squad, who seem much more capable and cohesive than they were two seasons ago. But at the same time I know there will be a point (maybe next season in the Championship?) where the opposition becomes too strong for my squad’s technical ability and things get a lot tougher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re on the right track, and hopefully we’ll be hitting the Premier League before too long. Until then, it’s a race against time for my young players - I hope they’ll be able to develop quickly enough to handle the big stage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="fifa" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">I hadn’t bought a FIFA game in years, but I couldn’t resist picking up FIFA 22 when I learnt that EA has finally given us the tools to emulate the classic Master League experience, creating a brand new club and taking them from football’s bottom rung to continental glory. I’ve always enjoyed reading about people’s Career Mode journeys, so I thought I’d share how it’s going. The setup I usually burn out on FIFA Career Mode quite quickly. When you start a game with a big team like Chelsea, a few tactical additions to your squad are all you need to win it all, and from there it’s just a matter of bringing through young players to sustain the success and build your legacy. So this time around, I was determined to do something different. This time I created my own club, TSP United - complete with a snazzy purple kit - and dumped them in League Two. When you create a club in Career Mode you begin with a randomly generated squad of unskilled players with which to ascend the ladder, and to make things even more challenging I decided that I would not spend a penny in transfer fees. Instead, my focus would be on bringing through youth players, with the odd free signing. 2021/22 - League Two It took some time to settle in before my first season gained momentum. I had a shaky start as I learnt the game and worried that I’d made things too difficult for myself, but eventually I found some rhythm and form, and by the end of the season TSP United won the league with a couple of games to go. Other highlights included an extended League Cup run that saw us reach the quarter finals, earning scrappy wins against Premier League heavyweights Wolves and Newcastle before taking a battering against Manchester United.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/fifa-22-career-mode_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Formula 1: Why now’s the time to choose a backup series</title><link href="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/08/formula-1-time-to-choose-backup-series" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Formula 1&amp;#58; Why now's the time to choose a backup series" /><published>2022-04-08T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-08T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/08/formula-1-time-to-choose-backup-series</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stratpack.blog//2022/04/08/formula-1-time-to-choose-backup-series">&lt;p&gt;The last decade or so has been a bad time to be a fan of many things. Your favourite film has had an unimaginative reboot because Hollywood had no new ideas, the latest entry in your favourite video game series is &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/03/25/gran-turismo-7-ps4-review&quot;&gt;a live service bursting with microtransactions&lt;/a&gt;, and if you’re particularly unlucky your football club is now being run for profit rather than silverware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even governing bodies haven’t been immune to the madness of chasing money at any cost. The last World Cup was held in Putin’s Russia and the next will be hosted by Qatar amidst &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/football/59253789&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;all sorts of human rights issues&lt;/a&gt;. And while UEFA are no saints in this regard (the 2019 Europa League final in Baku being just one example), fans were forced to take action against the Super League in an attempt to hold on to the lesser of two evils and maintain at least &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; level of fairness and sporting integrity in European club football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/formula-1-cc_0.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-brief-history&quot;&gt;A brief history&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at least we could still rely on Formula 1. While the sport’s previous ownership wasn’t exactly immune to the lures of a big cheque - they were the ones who signed up for races in places like Abu Dhabi and Bahrain, after all - Bernie Ecclestone and his team understood the sport’s history and tradition and its most loyal fans. In fact, you could argue that this was to a fault, as Formula 1 was slow to embrace new trends like social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberty Media’s 2016 takeover was met with some skepticism over whether the new American owners would embrace the spirit of Formula 1, but in the years that followed, most of the changes were positive. We got the halo to better protect drivers, plus an upgraded presentation package with better graphics, a heightened social media presence, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JBFPP_BG-qo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;an adrenaline-triggering intro and theme tune&lt;/a&gt; to add a bit of fanfare to race weekends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most questionable addition at this point was Netflix’s &lt;em&gt;Drive to Survive&lt;/em&gt; series, which promised a behind-the-scenes view of the sport but confused dedicated fans with dishonest editing, artificial drama, and a disorientating structure. Still, it helped to bring Formula 1 further into the mainstream, and additional followers could only be a good thing, right?&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-slippery-slope&quot;&gt;A slippery slope&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But large organisations never know where to stop, and since the COVID pandemic things have been pushed even further. The heart of Liberty’s strategy seems to be to secure as much money as possible, even if that means alliances with states with questionable human rights records. Saudi Arabia and Qatar have secured long deals when many believe they shouldn’t even have been considered as destinations for the pinnacle of motorsport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia has complications even beyond this. Despite the nation having a bottomless pit of money to spend on facilities, we somehow ended up with another bland (and barely finished) street circuit with blind corners and walls close on each side - the perils of which have been seen through many incidents, not least &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8yLNmb2-yrQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mick Schumacher’s massive qualifying crash this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberty are also keen to capitalise on the growing American fan base that &lt;em&gt;Drive to Survive&lt;/em&gt; has helped to cultivate. In 2022 we will see a Grand Prix in Miami, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/formula1/60932994&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Las Vegas recently joined the 2023 calendar&lt;/a&gt;. While it’s certainly a better curcuit than its 1980s counterpart in the Caesars Palace car park, it’s yet another street circuit - a bland rectangle when there are so many purpose-built race tracks in the world - even in America - going unused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this might be tolerable if there were any assurances that Formula 1’s heritage - and in particular Silverstone, Monaco, Spa-Francorchamps, Monza, Suzuka, and Interlagos - would be protected. But new CEO Stefano Domenicali has suggested that even the Belgian Grand Prix, which arguably takes place at the best circuit on the calendar, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.autosport.com/f1/news/f1-ready-to-drop-current-races-to-make-way-for-new-grands-prix/9134981/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;could be one of the first to face the axe&lt;/a&gt; to make room for all these new races on a crowded calendar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;contingency-plans&quot;&gt;Contingency plans&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not quite enough for me to abandon Formula 1 after so many decades - &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt; - but the warning signs are there. While the sport inevitably needed to be brought into the 21st century, everything points to Liberty Media trying to squeeze out every cent it can, no matter what the cost in terms of tradition and the enjoyment of long-standing fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what can we do? It doesn’t seem that Formula 1 itself is all that keen to listen to fans - Spa ranked as fans’ second-favourite circuit in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.formula1.com/en/latest/article.new-global-fan-survey-reveals-f1s-most-popular-team-and-driver.2evqTWEPsWYeBlw9vmSyBs.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;last year’s fan survey&lt;/a&gt; and yet it’s rumoured to be at risk of being discarded entirely. So the only option looks to be to hedge your bets and pick up some backup series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could be the feeder formulas - while F2 and F3 tour with F1, &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-4&quot;&gt;Formula 4&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/formula-ford&quot;&gt;Formula Ford&lt;/a&gt; are more grassroots and visit smaller regional circuits. Outside of open-wheel racing there are endurance series like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gt-world-challenge.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GT World Challenge&lt;/a&gt; and famous races like the Le Mans 24h and Bathurst 12h. And if you still fancy some action at even higher speeds, there’s always &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indycar.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IndyCar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you’ll need to hunt down TV coverage, but often these series are streamed for free online. It’ll also take some time to get used to the teams, drivers, and stories - but didn’t we all have to do that with Formula 1 at some point? My point is that it’s better to build up the knowledge now than to be completely lost later on, because at the moment it seems like it’s only a matter of time before Formula 1 becomes unrecognisable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/105731165@N07/26747780448&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Artes Max&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 2.0&lt;/a&gt;). Cropped.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>thestratpack</name></author><category term="formula-1" /><category term="formula-4" /><category term="formula-ford" /><category term="motorsport" /><summary type="html">The last decade or so has been a bad time to be a fan of many things. Your favourite film has had an unimaginative reboot because Hollywood had no new ideas, the latest entry in your favourite video game series is a live service bursting with microtransactions, and if you’re particularly unlucky your football club is now being run for profit rather than silverware. Even governing bodies haven’t been immune to the madness of chasing money at any cost. The last World Cup was held in Putin’s Russia and the next will be hosted by Qatar amidst all sorts of human rights issues. And while UEFA are no saints in this regard (the 2019 Europa League final in Baku being just one example), fans were forced to take action against the Super League in an attempt to hold on to the lesser of two evils and maintain at least some level of fairness and sporting integrity in European club football. A brief history But at least we could still rely on Formula 1. While the sport’s previous ownership wasn’t exactly immune to the lures of a big cheque - they were the ones who signed up for races in places like Abu Dhabi and Bahrain, after all - Bernie Ecclestone and his team understood the sport’s history and tradition and its most loyal fans. In fact, you could argue that this was to a fault, as Formula 1 was slow to embrace new trends like social media. Liberty Media’s 2016 takeover was met with some skepticism over whether the new American owners would embrace the spirit of Formula 1, but in the years that followed, most of the changes were positive. We got the halo to better protect drivers, plus an upgraded presentation package with better graphics, a heightened social media presence, and an adrenaline-triggering intro and theme tune to add a bit of fanfare to race weekends. The most questionable addition at this point was Netflix’s Drive to Survive series, which promised a behind-the-scenes view of the sport but confused dedicated fans with dishonest editing, artificial drama, and a disorientating structure. Still, it helped to bring Formula 1 further into the mainstream, and additional followers could only be a good thing, right?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/formula-1-cc_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stratpack.blog//wp-content/uploads/2022/04/formula-1-cc_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>